<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Rev. James Chalmers.— Glad at the prospect of seeing you; ¶ When Chalmers visited Melbourne, a public meeting presided over by the Governor was held on 14 June 1886, at which M moved a vote of ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1886/86-05-18a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>86.05.18a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>To the Rev. James Chalmers.— Glad at the prospect of seeing you; ¶ When Chalmers visited Melbourne, a public meeting presided over by the Governor was held on 14 June 1886, at which M moved a vote of ...</title>
               <date when="1886-05-18">1886-05-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1886/86-05-18a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Chalmers</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">To the Rev. James Chalmers.— Glad at the prospect of seeing you; ¶ When Chalmers visited Melbourne, a public meeting presided over by the Governor was held on 14 June 1886, at which M moved a vote of ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">86.05.18a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Chalmers</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Geographical Society's Expedition to New Guinea', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leader</seg>, 22 May 1886, p. 29. It is introduced by </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letters were received from Mr. Forbes from time to time announcing the successful progress of the expedition, and hopes were entertained that in the end a larger amount of information relative to New Guinea would be placed at the disposal of the society. These hopes, however, were dissipated by the receipt of the following telegrams from the Rev. Mr. Chalmers and Mr. H. O. Forbes, announcing the collapse of the expedition. … The following replies were sent on Tuesday by Baron Von Mueller:—</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to H. Forbes, 18 May 1866, in this edition as 86-05-18b.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">To the Rev. James Chalmers.— Glad at the prospect of seeing you;</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When Chalmers visited Melbourne, a public meeting presided over by the Governor was held on 14 June 1886, at which M moved a vote of appreciation of Chalmers's services </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>in not only carrying the blessings <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of Christianity to the savage populations of New <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Guinea but in advancing also the science of <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>geography by penetrating into the wildest recesses of that large island thus revealing to us simultaneously many new forms of the wondrous works <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>through which Almighty God speaks to us in living nature; and that this meeting further gratefully recognises the aid cheerfully rendered by Mr Chalmers and by his estimable colleague Mr Lawes, by which exploratory efforts were vasttly (</seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                           <hi rend="underline">sic</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="">) promoted in that great country with which, indeed Mr Chalmers's <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>name will ever be historically identified and where it will be cherished in the future by a flourishing community, and will be held in grateful remembrance by the native races. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>('Public welcome to the Rev. J. Chalmers', </seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>
                        <seg style="">, 15 June 1886, p. 7, col. g.)</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> sorry council Victorian branch meets to-morrow.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> (20 May 1886, p. 5) reported that at the special meeting of the Council of the Victorian Branch of the Geographical Society </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg style="">On the motion of Baron von Mueller it was resolved that Mr. Forbes be asked whether in the event of the Geographical Society subsidising him he is willing to make his expedition a geographical one solely—his efforts to be concentrated in ascending Mount Owen Stanley in the present cool months; that he be asked the minimum expenditure which the expedition would entail; and also, whether he will remain in Cooktown for 10 or 14 days while an effort is being made to see whether sufficient funds can be raised here and in the other colonies for such an expedition.</seg>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg style="">In the 'Under the Verandah' column in the </seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leader</seg>
                        <seg style="">, 29 May 1886, p. 26, 'Atticus' reported that at the meeting of the society 'last week', M had suggested seeking private funds to aid Forbes's explorations, and he </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>held out as an inducement to the wealthy that "the names of donors should be perpetuated in the nomenclature of rivers, mountains and other geographical features of the country which Mr. Forbes would examine." If this proposal is adopted we may look upon the exploration of New Guinea as already accomplished. Who would grudge a paltry £500 to have his name figure on the map of the world as godfather to a grand geographical feature? How far superior to an ordinary knighthood, or the privilege of writing C.M.G. after one's name, to have a cape a mountain or a river as a passport to fame? Of course there should be a tariff, say £500 for a main range or a principal river, £100 an isolated peak or a tributary, and £50 some geographical trifle that would only be known in the neighborhood. And what a magnificent oppportunity (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">sic</seg>) for advertisers. There is a fortune in the idea of a Hop Bitters Bay, a Cockle's Pill Land, or a Pears's Soap Lake; and I have not the slightest doubt that many enterprising sewing machine makers would be satisfied to bear the whole expense for the sake of having the geographical features named after their wares. The idea is excellent but for one thing. The Imperial Government has taken every precaution to prevent the British Papuans from being plundered by the white man. We cannot take their persons, their lands or their property, and yet the Baron coolly proposes to plunder them of their names. Who steals their purses steals trash; but he that filches from them their good names to minister to the vanity of a Victorian man of money robs them of that which will not enrich geographical knowledge, and will leave them poor indeed. Is there no nobler feeling the Baron can appeal to than that which actuates the British tourist when he carves his initials on the Pyramids? </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg style="">M had used a similar strategy to fund the explorations of Ernest Giles: see M to D Mackinnon, 7 January 1873, p. 3 (B75.04.07). </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg style="">See also M to the Royal Society of Queensland, 19 May 1886, and M to A. Macdonald, 29 May 1886.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Perhaps Forbes's expedition could be subsidised out of High Commissioner's vote.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
