<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The arrangements and all details in connection with Mr. Sayer's movements are under the immediate supervision of Baron von Mueller, the Victorian Government botanist. According to a letter received l...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1886/86-12-00g-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>86.12.00g</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>[The arrangements and all details in connection with Mr. Sayer's movements are under the immediate supervision of Baron von Mueller, the Victorian Government botanist. According to a letter received l...</title>
               <date when="1886-12">1886-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1886/86-12-00g-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Sayer</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[The arrangements and all details in connection with Mr. Sayer's movements are under the immediate supervision of Baron von Mueller, the Victorian Government botanist. According to a letter received l...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">86.12.00g</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Sayer</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from a report in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">South Australian weekly chronicle</seg>, 12 February 1887, reprinted from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cairns chronicle</seg>, on the successful ascent of Mt Bellenden Ker, Qld. (See Lavarack (2015) for accounts of the early exploration of the Bellenden Ker range, including the ascent by Sayer and Davidson in December 1886). M's letter was probably received by Sayer between 1 January 1887, when the party returned to Cairns after the ascent, and when, urged by M in a telegram [not found] they set out for a re-ascent after resting for about a week in Cairns (Lavarack 2015, p. 584). It is thus likely to have been written after Sayer and W.W. Froggatt managed to reach an elevation of c. 2,000 feet but were forced to turn back by bad weather and fatigue; the date of this effort is not precisely known. Davidson replaced Froggatt for attempts in December. The item is dated to December 1886 as the latest likely date of composition. </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[The arrangements and all details in connection with Mr. Sayer's movements are under the immediate supervision of Baron von Mueller, the Victorian Government botanist. According to a letter received last mail by Mr. Sayer, the baron is extremely satisfied with the work now being carried out. He writes to say that Mr Sayer and his companion deserve great credit for the perseverance and courage displayed under considerable danger and adversity. The baron also adds:— "As you have now a track and a valiant companion (after whom any new plant from the summit will be named), I trust you will not lose any opportunity to render us acquainted with the flora of the summit." Mr. Sayer and his companion may pride themselves upon having gained the commendation of Baron von Mueller, who is perhaps the most celebrated botanist of the present day. Mr. Sayer started recently from Cairns with the object of reascending the Bellenden Ker, and if possible obtaining fresh botanical treasures from the district which, to use Baron von Müeller's own words, is "the most interesting botanic region yet to be explored in Australia."] </seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
