<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne botanic Garden, ¶ 12/9/69. ¶  ¶ Since some time ago, dear Sir Redmond, I intended to have written to you fully on the requirements of the phytological branch of the industrial Museum, but my...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-09-12.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>VPRS 5486/PO/4, no. 13 official inward correspondence, VA 928 Melbourne Public Library, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>69.09.02</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne botanic Garden, ¶ 12/9/69. ¶  ¶ Since some time ago, dear Sir Redmond, I intended to have written to you fully on the requirements of the phytological branch of the industrial Museum, but my...</title>
               <date when="1869-09-12">1869-09-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-09-12.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Redmond Barry</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne botanic Garden, ¶ 12/9/69. ¶  ¶ Since some time ago, dear Sir Redmond, I intended to have written to you fully on the requirements of the phytological branch of the industrial Museum, but my...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">69.09.02</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Redmond Barry</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">VPRS 5486/PO/4, no. 13 official inward correspondence, VA 928 Melbourne Public Library, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof. p/cs by TD.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Melbourne botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">12/9/69.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">check date it might be 10 over 12 or 12 over 10.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since some time ago, dear Sir Redmond, I intended to have written to you fully on the requirements of the phytological branch of the industrial Museum, but my time has been increasingly occupied lately with the ordinary departmental duties, and besides the whole subject is so large, that it is not easily approached in all its bearings.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first difficulty which presents itself to my mind is the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">utter helplessness</hi>
               </seg>, in which I find myself in doing anything at the Exhibition Building. It is true you kindly arranged for the aid of the two attendents<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> there, who helped me one Sunday very readily. It is not the less true that you wish me to send in requisition for cases &amp;c. But you can readily feel, that it would be impossible for me to be always at the building to direct the work of the attendants, who themselves are not acquainted with the work to be carried out. And then again until some proper <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">safe</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">place</hi>
               </seg> for the accommodation of the vegetable articles is provided nothing can be measured [out] in the form of fittings, glass-cases, stages &amp;c</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In first instance I would suggest then, that the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">floors</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">roof</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">and windows</hi>
               </seg> in the annex are fully prepared. Then space [w]ould be safely available for the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">rougher</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">articles</hi>
               </seg>, such as timber, crude fibres, wood implements &amp;c &amp;c</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2, Grant of a limited sum, perhaps fifty pounds (£50) to be disbursed by me in engaging the assistance of a man occasionally, who is conversant with the woods, and who can secure from artisans &amp;c such additions as are obtainable in the city. This all cannot possibly be done by an ordinary employee at the exhibition building.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3, Grant of some means to cut the timber specimens at the Exhibition building into shape, to repolish them &amp;c, to have labels painted for them &amp;c. Altho' a Carpenter is employed, I believe, at the Exhibition-building &amp; public Library, I cannot but recommend that I may be entrusted with engaging a carpenter specially for this work. It will extend over some considerable time, and in the present state of the annex &amp; while so much fitting work is also [to]<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> be done in the main Exhibition building it is quite impossible for one carpenter to attend as a byework also to the requirements of the timber. I should think, that under rigorous economy for thirty pounds (£30) a good deal might be done to the wood-specimens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4, There are numerous glass vessels required for the reception of fibres, resins, gums, dyes, vegetable chemicals &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c. I see no possibility to obtain such glass without an immense loss of time under a tender- or requisition system. What I would respectfully suggest, is to place a small sum (from five to ten pounds) for direct purchases of such glass-vessels at my disposal</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5, I report respectfully, what I already suggested in my last note,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to R. Barry, 2 September 1869.</p>
               </note> that any empty glass-cases or other cases or glasses, suitable for the reception of drugs, fruitwares, and any other vegetable substances or casts, as may be <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">available</hi>
               </seg> already at the Exhibition building be placed at my disposal, to save expenditure. Such cases &amp;c could be temporarily used, and as gradually the collections increase, and as from time to time fund may be available, uniform accommodations could be provided for the exhibits.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6, If a collection of material medica is not already formed at the University, such collections [can] form a fitting part of the phytological series, and this portion of the articles might find best a place in the portion of the main exhibition building.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7, For the general collection of the vegetable substances the annex-building will not at all be to large, if we bear future requirements in mind especially as some space for lectures and demonstrations must be allowed. If this is conceded, the sooner the annex can be brought into a state of repair, the better.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>8, One of the small bye buildings should be allotted a work-shop and lumber room of the vegetable section of the exhibition, as carpenters work labeling, cleaning, preparing exhibits must of necessity be going continually on.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>9, During the season fruit casts &amp; models of vegetables &amp;c should at least to a small extent be prepared. For this and for microscopical vegetable preparation, of which latter I can obtain fine sets in Germany a small sum would be needed, perhaps thirty pounds for the first year.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>10, It would be desirable, partly for decoration, partly also for illustrations and instruction to secure pictures (not expensive) of landscapes illustrating special features of vegetation, further diagrams, shewing vegetable structures further, enlarged microscopic drawings, and also pictures of celebrated authors in material medica, phytography, vegetable anatomy, industrial applications of plants. That these must be obtained by direct purchase is evident. What sum would really be needed I cannot say finally, but a small beginning might be made in this.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>11, I have in my laboratory 20 framed samples of paper made here, also a large lot of specimens of paper &amp; past<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>paste?</p>
               </note> board made in Belgium, France &amp; Germany from wood shavings &amp;c (the foreign samples not framed) also a collection of vegetable acids, tars, resins, […], dye liquids &amp;c, which could at once go to the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">main</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">building</hi>
               </seg>, until the annex is put into secure repair and cleanliness, if cases and shelves can be provided or [found] for such be granted to me. However I beg to reserve for myself the right of dividing the quantity of these exhibits hereafter, as Mr Verdon will require a series of them in London at the Office building he occupies or perhaps at the Colonial Museum under the Colonial Society in London.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>12 The agricultural Collections at the board of Agriculture would form part of the general vegetable collection, and I have given notice to move, that they be transferred to the new industrial Museum.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>13. Provision will be needed for printed labels.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>14. It seems also that no proper <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ventilation</hi>
               </seg> is secured at the annex, without in hot windy weather dust blowing copiously into the building.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>15. I believe it is necessary that the floor laths in the annex should be pulled up and relaid, for the purpose of removing the accumulation of dirt under it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>16 For forming pyramids of wood &amp; placing the planks into [&amp;c]<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic – sentence ends here.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>These propositions, dear Sir Redmond, could have much been extended, but I have for the present said enough to show how a proper <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">well</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">working</hi>
               </seg> system of preparations could be commenced, but while I am most willing to Superintend the formation of the vegetable section of the new museum, I cannot refrain from remarking, that it would neither be just nor encouraging to me, if the final arrangements were such as to involve unnecessary loss of time by complicate arrangements, or if by want of some direct trust in my judgement and economy needless additional toil was burdened on me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I remain, dear Sir Redmond, your regardful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
