<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ I am considering to have Mr Forrest make an attempt during the cooler season of the year 1870 (from March to September) to penetrate with a light party from the sources of the Murchison River ¶  to...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-09-06b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>69.09.06b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ I am considering to have Mr Forrest make an attempt during the cooler season of the year 1870 (from March to September) to penetrate with a light party from the sources of the Murchison River ¶  to...</title>
               <date when="1869-09-06">1869-09-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-09-06b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ I am considering to have Mr Forrest make an attempt during the cooler season of the year 1870 (from March to September) to penetrate with a light party from the sources of the Murchison River ¶  to...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">69.09.06b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see B69.12.04. The text is introduced, 'Aus einem Schreiben des Dr. F. von Müller d. d. Melbourne 6. September 1869 erfahren wir Folgendes: ...' [From a letter of Dr F. von Mueller, dated Melbourne, 6 September 1869, we learn the following:...]. For a published version of this extract, see Voigt (1996), pp. 95-6.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich gehe nun mit dem Gedanken um, Mr. Forrest in kühler Jahreszeit (von März bis September) 1870 einen Versuch machen zu lassen, mit einer leichten Partie von den Quellen des Murchison-Flusses nach Carpentaria vorzudringen, und es sind die Negotiationen mit der Regierung West-Australiens deshalb bereits angeknüpft. Für eine schnelle Reise und eine sechsmonatliche Abwesenheit einer kleinen Schaar an Buschleben gewöhnter Reisender hoffe ich hier die bescheidenen Mittel zusammenzubringen. Ist die Jahreszeit und die Richtung der Reisenden eine günstige, so werden dieselben leicht die Carpentaria-Stationen erreichen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine leicht passirbare Linie von dem Murchison-Flusse bis Carpentaria würde unverzüglich dazu führen, dass die ganze Westküste von den Squattern von Queensland aus okkupiert würde. Ist das Land völlig unwirthbar, was man nach dem, was ich selbst am Termination Lake der Gregory'schen Expedition im Jahre 1856 gesehen, nicht annehmen darf, so kann sich Forrest vor der heissen Jahreszeit wieder nach den Niederlassungen West-Australiens zurückziehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach den Pflanzen, die mir vom Lake Barlee und östlich davon gesandt wurden, nehme ich an, dass eine Landstrecke, ganz ähnlich der in der Nachbarschaft vom Spencer-Golf in Süd-Australien, sich quer durch ganz Australien hinzieht und dass es nur der Auffindung von permanentem Wasser bedarf, um den ganzen Strich zu okkupiren.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch Abbrennung der Gebüsche, Aussaat perennirender Gräser und Weidekräuter und Senkung von Wassergruben und dann durch reguläre Beweidung lässt sich dieses Wüstenland wunderbar für Niederlassungen zugänglich und nutzbar machen. Übrigens ist das Land in der neu proponierten Reiserichtung jedenfalls viel reicher an Wasser und viel freier von Gestrüpp als der Strich, längs dessen Mr. Forrest hinziehen musste, um die Aussagen der Eingeborenen zu prüfen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Regierung West-Australiens, welche nicht reich ist, verdient hohe Anerkennung für die Bereitwilligkeit, mit welcher sie diese letzte Entdeckungsreise unternahm.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am considering to have Mr Forrest make an attempt during the cooler season of the year 1870 (from March to September) to penetrate with a light party from the sources of the Murchison River<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">WA.</p>
               </note> to the Gulf of Carpentaria, and negotiations about this have already been initiated with the Western Australian Government. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I hope to be able to bring together here the modest means for a fast journey and a six-months’ absence by a small group of travellers used to life in the bush. If the season and the direction of the travellers is favourable, they will be able to reach the Carpentaria stations easily.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An easily traversed route from the Murchison River to the Gulf of Carpentaria would rapidly lead to the occupation of the west coast by squatters coming from Queensland. If the land is completely inhospitable, which should not be expected from what I myself saw at Termination Lake<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Now Lake Gregory, WA.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> during Gregory's expedition in the year 1856,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> Forrest can draw back to the Western Australian settlements before the start of the hot season.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Judging by the plants sent to me from Lake Barlee and to the east from there,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">WA; see B70.10.01.</p>
               </note> I assume that a tract of land very similar to that at Spencer's Gulf in South Australia stretches right across Australia, and that the only thing required for the whole area to be occupied is the finding of permanent water.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By burning off the scrub, sowing perennial grasses and pasture herbs, and sinking bores, and then by regular pasturing, this desert land can be wonderfully opened up for settlement and become useful. By the way, the land in the newly proposed direction of travel is far richer in water and much freer of scrub than the stretch of land along which Mr Forrest had to travel to investigate the statements by the natives.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Forrest had gone to investigate the rumours by aborigines that Leichhardt and his party had perished further to the south in WA.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Government of Western Australia is not rich and deserves strong commendations for the readiness with which it undertook this last exploring expedition.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
