<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TO THE EDITOR OF THE ARGUS. ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ In  ¶ The Argus ¶  of this day complaints are not unjustly raised on account of the want of an extensive display of spring flowers in the Botanic gardens. Wit...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-09-27-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>69.09.27</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>TO THE EDITOR OF THE ARGUS. ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ In  ¶ The Argus ¶  of this day complaints are not unjustly raised on account of the want of an extensive display of spring flowers in the Botanic gardens. Wit...</title>
               <date when="1869-09-27">1869-09-27</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-09-27-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of the Argus</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">TO THE EDITOR OF THE ARGUS. ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ In  ¶ The Argus ¶  of this day complaints are not unjustly raised on account of the want of an extensive display of spring flowers in the Botanic gardens. Wit...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">69.09.27</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Editor of the Argus</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is from 'The botanic gardens', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 30 September 1869, p. 6 (B69.09.01).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> of 27 September 1869 (p. 5) published an article critical of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens. It began: 'It cannot be said that the Botanic gardens at the present time offer many attractions to the visitor. Either from want of means, or from an injudicious use of the funds which are available, the gardens have been suffered to fall into a condition which is certainy not creditable to a city of such pretensions as ours.'</p>
               </note>TO THE EDITOR OF THE ARGUS.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir, —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In <seg style="font-style: italic; ">The Argus</seg> of this day complaints are not unjustly raised on account of the want of an extensive display of spring flowers in the Botanic gardens. With equal justice, it is remarked that the ground is not free of weeds, and presents not that tidiness which, with more or less success, I endeavoured to give it during the former 13 years of my directorship. In common fairness you will, however, permit me to explain, what I repeatedly mentioned to your reporters during this year, that I must claim the indulgence and forbearance of the public, particularly at this season, when, for obvious reasons, the garden could not possibly get its proper attention. By common assent, it would have been unwise in the extreme to miss the only opportunity which ever occurred, through the unparalleled drought of last year, for removing by cart labour from the bottom of the lake the soil thus readily accessible for a flood dam. For this work, by which also the freshness and permanency of water in some parts of the lake is secured, the whole much-reduced public works fund was devoted which was left available after payment for the steam works recently established here. This fund, however, was not half sufficient; and as I applied repeatedly for special aid, and such aid could only be rendered by a special supplementary vote of Parliament, I had to complete the dam solely by garden labour. Thus, for several months, nine or ten, people had to be withdrawn from their ordinary garden occupation, and even now five men have yet to work till the middle of next month to complete the dam. I leave it to the fair judgment of the public whether it was wiser to spend the labour in a lasting work of improvement, which is to protect the garden against the devastations of flood such as has occurred in succession four times within a few years, or whether it would have been better to renew the miles of edging scorched by the drought of last season, or to cultivate annuals for the sake of their transient glory, or to attend most scrupulously to the clearing-up of the whole ground. However desirable all this may be, it could not be done simultaneously with the resources at my command. I beg you also to remember that no Yan Yean is — even on rainy days, or even at late night hours — any longer available here. Thus, during this almost rainless spring, great difficulty was already experienced to provide water for the avenues and shrubberies by the steam-engine, much garden labour by all this being withdrawn. Perhaps the generality of the citizens are also not aware that only comparatively a small share of the garden labour can anyhow be devoted to the embellishment of the ground, because the calls for plants from early in May till August, for the shade and ornamentation of church and school grounds, public reserves, and road sides and cemeteries, is almost incessant, although for fully a dozen of years I implored the public not to tax my department with this onerous duty after May. I might also add, that the wish for the maintenance of very many flower borders in a neat and gay appearance is easily expressed on paper, but with slender means is not to be accomplished easily over a very extensive area, especially when, I regret to say, utter disregard is shown to the rules, pilfering and destruction being of daily occurrence, not to mention the damage constantly done by the invasion of rabbits let loose by reckless neighbours. The calls, also, for flowers wanted for bazaars, tea meetings, and other public purposes is almost continuous; and, however, much the director may wish to aid these public or charitable objects, this aid makes a sad inroad on the garden labour, and on the display of flowers on the ground. Progressive work is also yet to be carried on, as shown this season by laying out the tea-ground, and by the formation of the walks and avenues on the Yarra towards the city bridge. This coming summer, again, the formation of the drives to the garden over the ridge and along the base of the hill will absorb very much labour. Repairs of the numerous buildings, painting of the wooden structures, tarring of iron fences, and similar work devolve also on the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">employés</seg> of the garden, as well as improving the originally excessively barren ground. In my opinion, it would be a wasteful expenditure if to ornamental culture alone the main resources of the garden were devoted, so long as in a young country prominent works of utility have to be carried out. It is needless to point out that the acquirement of new plants for the colony, as well as the introduction of forest trees and industrial plants in masses for our fields and ranges, must absorb some means, even if we do not consider the modest outlay which the museum, the laboratory, and the literary branch of the service incur. The nurseries have also to be stocked in the cool season, and this work, in anticipation of the necessities of the next year, has not yet been completed. As it is, I have struggled against impossibilities this year more than ever; and while I claim the consideration of the public under the unusual circumstances of difficulty in which I am placed, I feel sure that those who are unprejudiced will still be able to find some enjoyable spot, and many a pretty flower even now; will not be blind to the lasting improvements going on; will recognise and appreciate the increasing riches and utility of the establishment; and will give me the credit that, disinterestedly, I have left nothing undone, as far as it was within my means and my power to promote not only the present, but also the future interest of the department entrusted to my care. —</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I am, Sir, yours, &amp;c.,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">FERD. VON MUELLER, M.D.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>Melbourne Botanic gardens, Sept. 27.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
