<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melb. bot Garden ¶ 6/6/69. ¶  ¶ It affords me very much pleasure, dear Sir William, to be able to send you  ¶ all ¶  the plants, which you desire. I have taken them out of pots, and packed them horizo...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-06-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>A2938 Macarthur papers, vol. 42, pp. 376-91, Mitchell Library, State Library of New South Wales, Sydney.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>69.06.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melb. bot Garden ¶ 6/6/69. ¶  ¶ It affords me very much pleasure, dear Sir William, to be able to send you  ¶ all ¶  the plants, which you desire. I have taken them out of pots, and packed them horizo...</title>
               <date when="1869-06-06">1869-06-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-06-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Alsophila Robertsiana</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d9699953-4f23-4d82-84e1-341652677618">Alsophila australis</term>
               <term>Alsophila MArthuri</term>
               <term>Alsophila Rebeccae</term>
               <term>Alsophila Cooperi</term>
               <term>Alsophila excelsa</term>
               <term>Cinchona</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Macarthur</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melb. bot Garden ¶ 6/6/69. ¶  ¶ It affords me very much pleasure, dear Sir William, to be able to send you  ¶ all ¶  the plants, which you desire. I have taken them out of pots, and packed them horizo...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">69.06.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Macarthur</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">A2938 Macarthur papers, vol. 42, pp. 376-91, Mitchell Library, State Library of New South Wales, Sydney.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melb. bot Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">6/6/69.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It affords me very much pleasure, dear Sir William, to be able to send you <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> the plants, which you desire. I have taken them out of pots, and packed them horizontally. The case is forwarded simultaneously with this letter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e have borne a cold of 28° F. but only in a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">completely sheltered</hi>
               </seg> position in a brush shade. A less degree of cold will carry them off if combined with wind. The whole secret of <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name> culture consists in associating them with ferntrees in their natal places of the latter. We might weather the plants through a very hot summer in a sheltered spot and through a frosty winter, but their growth would not be prolific for bark culture. It is therefore only by having <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name> plantations in the fern tree gullies themselfes, that we can do good with them. Indeed it is the fern soil also, in which they delight, and I am here so unfortunately placed, that for raising the plants I have to fetch such soil 30 miles from the ranges or from Tasmania! As yet I have had no funds to form a separate <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name> establishment in our fern glens, where also Cork Oaks, Hickories, West Austr. Mahogony, N.SW. Red Cedar, Chinese &amp; Assam Tea and Coffee and several other plants are to be grown in quantity and for which purpose I have very many thousand plants ready, as, I think, I explained in my report, which I hope you received<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B69.07.03. M’s Annual Report, though dated 14 September 1868, was not tabled in Parliament until 8 July 1869. M evidently distributed copies before this.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I need scarcely say, how happy I shall be to get the rare <name key="Alsophila%20Cooperi">Alsophila Cooperi</name> from your vallies for my artificial fern tree gully here, which contains about 10 species of treeferns, but as far as I can see not this one. Hooker a few weeks before his death in the synopsis filicum reduced it to <name key="Alsophila%20excelsa">Alsophila excelsa</name> (from Norfolk-Island), but our lamented friend had probably imperfect material to judge! This may be an apt opportunity to state that about 2 years before his death Sir Will Hooker revised all my ferns, a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">large</hi>
               </seg> case full, sent to Kew on loan. He wrote <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">then</hi>
               </seg> on the cover of a huge package of Alsophilae (comprising what he subsequently distinguished as A. australis, A. M'Arthuri<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">A. macarthurii</seg>.</p>
               </note> &amp; A. excelsa (A. Rebeccae &amp; A Robertsiana then not being discovered) that either several species as but one existed, but that he could <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> make out their limits. When soon after the return of the original specimens from Kew my collector at Rockinghams Bay found A Rebecca &amp; A Robertsiana the occasion arose to revise the genus, as far as the Australian members are concerned &amp; I had certainly no knowledge of even the name, which one of the species bore (unpublished <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">as far as I know</hi>
               </seg>) in honor of yourself. My oldest specimens of a new one were Leichhardts (1842) &amp; I gladly gave to it Leichhardts name, which in the synopsis has rightly given way to yours. I presume that all the rare plants are almost annihilated at Illawarra. — How sad, that not a square mile of this floral paradise is sacredly preserved and reserved by Government. An other generation would wander through the remnant of that famed classic spot with veneration.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There must be many heath-plants also in that direction <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">new to locality</hi>
               </seg>. I wished much, it would fall to my lot to determine from collections of many local observers the southern limit of the many East Australian plants, which <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> advance into Gipps land.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Any notes of yours dear Sir William, on immigrated plants will with scrupulous care be utilized for the supplemental volume of the Austr. flora.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg> included notes on naturalized exotic plants in Australia.</p>
               </note> — of your exhibition I had never any special knowledge, altho' Mr Walter Hill of Brisbane referred incidentally to it, but this mere allusion passed amidst the turmoils of so much other work quite from my memory, and as I have never leisure to read political papers I became not reminded of the exhibition.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably the first Metropolitan Exhibition (forerunner of the annual Sydney Show) organised by the Agricultural Society of NSW, 4-6 May 1869. Macarthur was a leading figure in the Society.</p>
               </note> I merely mention this as an excuse, that I did not contribute, as this might be construed into apathy. Above all however I do not wish that this explanation should cause ill feelings in any quarter. I certainly do <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not remember</hi>
               </seg> having received any papers on the subject, and if I did so and forgot it, it must have been during my severe illness. The correspondence written by my own hand is about 3000 letters a year, and this again only a small <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">byework</hi>
               </seg> of late evening hours mostly; thus some oversight or forgetfulmess may occur. I was however an exhibitor at St Petersburg last month.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The drought has also here most sadly impeded our progress. With <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">no</hi>
               </seg> water supply on <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">400 </hi>
               </seg>acres except by steam pumps, it was a time of terror for many months, for our heat is not less than yours and our air on days of hot winds still drier, I believe. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In writing to Sir Edward, pray let me be kindly remembered and let me remain your very regardful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Pray let the cases be opened as early as possible, in order that the plants may not be too long imprisoned. Should any have suffered, I will replace them.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May I venture to offer you the enclosed little photogram<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Photogram not found.</p>
               </note> and solicit yours &amp; Sir Edwards for my book of portraits of celebrated men, who honored me with their friendship. The picture is an old one, as I have not sat in an atelier for several years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It seems that I overlooked any notice inviting contributions from the other colonies in the excellent journal of the Agricult. Soc.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of the Agricultural Society of New South Wales</seg>, publication of which began in 1868.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alsophila%20australis">Alsophila australis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alsophila%20Cooperi">Alsophila Cooperi</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alsophila%20excelsa">Alsophila excelsa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Alsophila M'Arthuri</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alsophila%20Rebeccae">Alsophila Rebeccae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alsophila%20Robertsiana">Alsophila Robertsiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
