<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 11/8/69. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ 1. In compliance with the request of the honorable the Chief Secretary I have secured a quantity of the seeds of Eucalyptus Globulus for the Government of M...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-08-11a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>U69/7994, unit 695, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>69.08.11a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 11/8/69. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ 1. In compliance with the request of the honorable the Chief Secretary I have secured a quantity of the seeds of Eucalyptus Globulus for the Government of M...</title>
               <date when="1869-08-11">1869-08-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-08-11a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eucalyptus Sideroxylon</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus citriodora</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus marginata</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Globulus</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Globosa</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Odgers</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 11/8/69. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ 1. In compliance with the request of the honorable the Chief Secretary I have secured a quantity of the seeds of Eucalyptus Globulus for the Government of M...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">69.08.11a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Odgers</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">U69/7994, unit 695, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to W. Odgers, 9 September 1869.</p>
               </note>Melbourne bot. Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">11/8/69.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1. In compliance with the request of the honorable the Chief Secretary I have secured a quantity of the seeds of <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globulus">Eucalyptus Globulus</name> for the Government of Madras.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 10 November 1868 W. S. Seton-Karr, Secretary to the Government of India, Simla wrote (letter no. 1974) to James McCulloch, Chief Secretary, Melbourne: 'It has been brought to the notice of the Viceroy and Governor General in Council that there are several localities in the provinces of Mysore and Coorg in Southern India, well adapted for the cultivation of the Eucalyptus and other useful timber trees which grow in Australia, and that the introduction of these trees might be very beneficial to the said provinces. Such being the case, His Excellency in Council is desirous of giving this experiment a fair trial, and he accordingly directs me to request that the Government of Melbourne will be so good as to favor this Government with a supply of seeds of five species of the Eucalyptus, viz: | E. Globulus — 30lbs weight | " Marginata — 30 do | " Sideroxylon — 20 do | " Globosa — 10 do | " Citridora — 10 do | I am further to request that the seeds may be carefully packed and sent through the Madras Government to the address of the Commissioner of Mysore, at Bangalore. | Any expense which may be incurred on this account will, of course, be defrayed by the Indian Government, at such place and in such manner as may be most convenient to the Government of Victoria; and any information which you could supply as to the planting of these seeds, would be very acceptable. It is intended to make the experiment of planting the seeds at an elevation of about 4000 feet, or more.' (R68/13237, unit 695, VPRS 3991, PROV). The Under Secretary, J. Moore, referred this letter to the Commissioner of Crown Lands on 28 December 1868, 'with a view to instructions being given to the Govt Botanist to procure a supply of the seeds required by the Indian Govt', and it was forwarded to M on 31 December.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 25 May 1869 the Acting Secretary to Government, Fort Saint George, India wrote to the Chief Secretary of Victoria, J. McCulloch: 'I am directed by His Excellency the Governor in Council to draw your attention to Mr. Secretary Hudleston's letter, dated 7th January, 1868, No. 41, asking for a supply of seeds of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globulus">Eucalyptus Globulus</name>
                     </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus Marginata</seg>, and to request that, with the permission of His Excellency the Governor of Victoria, you will do this Government the favor to have this application complied with as early as practicable, if no difficulty exists.' (T69/5610, unit 695, VPRS 3991, PROV). On 9 July 1869, the Under Secretary, W. Odgers, referred this letter to the Commissioner of Lands 'for a report from the Director of the Botanic Gardens'; Odgers noted that the Indian application was received on 12 February 1868 and forwarded to the Lands Department the next day. On 15 July the Assistant Commissioner of Crown Lands, C. Hodgkinson, replied: 'I beg respectfully to suggest that some action be taken relative to the minutes by Dr Von Mueller and myself dated 16th April and 6th April on attached con.; and with reference to which minutes, when submitted to him, the Honble The Commr of Lands &amp; Survey arrived at no decision'. (Neither Hudleston’s letter nor the minutes to which Hodgkinson referred are in the file.) McCulloch approved Hodgkinson's suggestion on 18 July, minuting: 'There need be no difficulty in this matter. Let Dr Von Mueller effect the purchase of such seeds as can be procured in Melbourne upon the most favorable terms he can. The a/cs can be paid from the Treasurer's Advance Vote pending application to the Governments of India and Madras respectively — When the seeds are ready for shipment furnish me with the particulars and I will write to India'.</p>
               </note> All that was at present obtainable in the Melbourne market was 12lb, and I was fortunate enough to secure it at 18/ pr lb. The account, amounting to £10.16. -, due to Mr Will. Adamson, Seeds merchant, 71 Collins Street west, is appended.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Account not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. The <name key="Eucalyptus%20marginata">Eucalyptus marginata</name> seeds, desired also by the Government of Madras, can only be gathered in West Australia, where alone that tree is indigenous. It might be worthy of the consideration of the honorable the Chief Secretary, whether the Madras Government should be advised to obtain the seeds thus mentioned rather direct from the West Australian Government.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. The seeds of <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globulus">Eucalyptus Globulus</name>, as above indicated, are forwarded herewith in a zink-lined case ready for transmission by mail-steamer, and I suppose that no further supply will be needed for Madras, until further order.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4. One of the letters (the first one) referring to this supply, sent by the Madras Government, I have not yet received back from the Lands Department.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. With reference to the larger order, to be executed for the Governor-General of India, I have the honor to suggest, that his Excellency may be informed of the following facts. That the price of Eucal. Globulus seeds ranges from 18/ - 25/ or even up to 30/ pr lb for well matured fresh and sifted seeds; that <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globulus">Eucalyptus Globulus</name> and E. Globosa<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. globosa </seg>
                     <seg style="">is not in APNI or IPNI (accessed 29 June 2020), but is used in some non-taxonomic texts, e.g. </seg>Mejstřík &amp; Cudlín (1983).<seg style=""> </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> are the same; that Euc. marginata occurs only in West Australia and Eucal. citriodora only in Queensland, and that the price of the seeds of these trees would be probably considerably higher than that of Euc. Globulus; that Euc. Sideroxylon is obtainable at our Goldfields, but no seed of it at this moment in the market</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6. I await therefore further instructions from the hon. the Chief Secretary in reference to this order, as probably the honorable Gentleman may desire to communicate again on this subject with the Secretary of the General Government of India at Simla, before action is taken in the purchase of all these seeds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7. If the hon. the Chief Secretary directs me to purchase the seeds of Euc. Globulus and Euc. Sideroxylon, I will endeavour to obtain them as early as possible, but it would be probably needful to send them in successive smaller lots.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your very obedient</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">J.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's mistake, it should be W.</p>
               </note> Odgers Esq &amp;c<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was requested to order seeds of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. globulus</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. sideroxylon</seg>; see W. Odgers to M, 3 September 1869.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Undersecretary to the Victorian Government</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20citriodora">Eucalyptus citriodora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globosa">Eucalyptus Globosa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globulus">Eucalyptus Globulus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20marginata">Eucalyptus marginata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Sideroxylon">Eucalyptus Sideroxylon</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
