<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>14/8/69. ¶  ¶ With this month's mail, esteemed Professor, I have appropriately thanked the Minister for Religious and Educational Affairs for the establishment of the first foundation and also on this...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-08-14d-proofed.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>69.08.14d</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>14/8/69. ¶  ¶ With this month's mail, esteemed Professor, I have appropriately thanked the Minister for Religious and Educational Affairs for the establishment of the first foundation and also on this...</title>
               <date when="1869-08-14">1869-08-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1869/69-08-14d-proofed.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Todea rivularis</term>
               <term>Todea Africana</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/26f088e5-c0e9-44d3-9684-57815342b778">Dicksonia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Progress note</term>
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">14/8/69. ¶  ¶ With this month's mail, esteemed Professor, I have appropriately thanked the Minister for Religious and Educational Affairs for the establishment of the first foundation and also on this...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="color: #c00000; font-weight: bold; ">I don’t understand the descripton of the missing pages: Are there 4 pages per folded sheet? If so, as there been confusion between sheet and page?</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="color: #ed7d31; font-weight: bold; ">
                  <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <seg style="color: #ed7d31; font-weight: bold; ">There is a missing photocopy of the reverse of the page that begins Ich hoffe dass Ihre Todea We have 3 sheets of photocopy when there should be 4. For some reason Doris didn’t realise that it was a photocopy missing rather than an incomplete letter. I’ll look through the odd strays and see if it’s there, but I’m not hopeful. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="color: #ed7d31; font-weight: bold; ">Looked through not there. Suggest writing to Stuttgart to ask for digital images of the complete letter.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">69.08.14d</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Ferdinand Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Krauss: 'Empf. d. 9. Oct. | R. 21 März 70' [Received 9 October 1869, answered 21 March 1870] (letter not found). Other annotations in three different hands: (1) (probably by Christoph Hegelmaier; see below) 'Danken von mir wegen Fragmenta phytographiae VI' [Thanks from me for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae </seg>VI]; (2) 'Wegen Alfred schreiben; | Woher sind die Säugethierbälge v. Aug. 69'. [Write concerning Alfred; from whence are the mammal skins of August 1869?] (see M to Krauss, 28 February 1869 (in this edition as 69-02-28a), and Sonder to Krauss, 31 July 1869 (in this edition as M69-07-31), regarding the consignment received in Stuttgart in August 1869); (3) 'Genauer Fundort des Goldklumpens, Säugethier 95' [Exact location of the gold nugget, mammal 95]. <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">The MS is incomplete, with at least two pages of text and the valediction missing.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>14/8/69</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit dieser Monatspost, verehrter Herr Professor, habe ich dem königl. Staatsminister für Kirchen- u Schulwesen gebührend für die Errichtung des ersten Stipendiums gedankt, und auch bei dieser Gelegenheit wieder meine Absicht kund gegeben ein 2tes folgen zu lassen. Dann habe ich auch versprochen, dem königl Naturalien-Museum fast ausschliesslich meine künftigen Sammlungen zuzuwenden, wie ich es bereits seit 2 Jahren gethan, u ich habe mich um so mehr dahin bereit erklärt, als hervorragende Männer des Wissens in dem königl Museum wirken.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Alle Ihre Winke sollen in Zukunft mehr beobachtet werden. Indessen da ich selbst jezt wenig im Felde bin (die grossen Departementsarbeiten lassen dies nicht zu) so muss ich mich oft mit minder gutem erkauftem oder durch Freunde gesammelten oder eingetauschtem Materiale begnügen. Es soll geschehen, was in meiner Macht steht. Herr Traill in Neuseeland bittet recht inständig um die Benennung der wenigen vordem gesandten Conchilien.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Heute</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> sind an das schöne Clipper Ship "Norfolk" eine grosse Kiste u ein Fass geschafft, die Hr Dr W. Sonder, unser guter Freund u Gönner gütig kostenfrei nach Stuttgart besorgen wird. Das für Sie vielleicht Wunderbarste ist ein Gypsguss der grossen Goldmasse, welche in dieser Colonie vor wenigen Monaten entdeckt wurde u zwar innerhalb weniger Zolle von der Erdoberfläche im Diluvium! Ich habe das Stück hier nicht vergolden lassen, da die Vergoldung nur auf der Reise leiden würde, aber ich bitte Sie, es </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dort</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> thun zu lassen, aber unter der Bedingung, dass Sie die Rechnung zur Zahlung an unsern Freund Sonder senden, da ich es stets als eine Ehrensache angesehen, die Sammlungen Ihnen kostenfrei überliefert zu sehen. Das königl Museum hat schon Ausgaben genug für die Aufstellung. In der Kiste ist noch ein 2ter Abguss, u ich habe durch eine hohe Prämie es vermocht 4 zu erlangen, der 3te ist an meinen edlen Freund Rich Owen gesandt für das Brit. </seg>Museum, den 4 schicke ich an Ad. <seg style="">Brogniart für das Pariser Museum, wo ich Ehrenmitglied der Administration bin. Die Form ist zerstört, u der Eigenthümer erlaubt nicht die Vervielfältigung der gesandten Exemplare. Ich habe es Herrn Dr Sonders Gutachten überlassen, ob er überhaupt die grosse Kiste in Hamburg öffnen wolle. Vielleicht verständigen Sie sich mit ihm darüber. Es sind zwar allerlei Dinge für Sonder u andere Freunde darin, indessen das Meiste ist für Sie, und das Umpacken möchte die Gypsgüsse gefährden. So möchte es leichter sein Sonder seinen Theil von Stuttgart nach Hamburg zu senden, als Ihren Theil von Hamburg nach Stuttgart. Wenn nur alles unbeschadet ankommt. Es ist doch eine weite Reise, diese lange oceanische Fahrt, u das Spediren in London führt doch auch leicht Zerbrechen herbei. Es ist übrigens alle Vorsicht beobachtet.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Kupferkiese, die ich vormals sandte, werden wenigstens geographische Interesse haben u es war doch eine grosse Reihe von Prachtstücken; in der That </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unser</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Museum hier hat nichts so Schönes.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun noch ein paar Worte über den Inhalt der Kiste u des grossen Fasses. Der 6te Band der Fragmenta ist für Sie u Prof Hegelmaier dabei. Sollte die Kiste ungeöffnet nach Stuttgart kommen, dann bitte ich Sie, die Versendung der betreffenden Bände an die Freunde Fenzl, Miquel u. sw. übernehmen u die Kostenrechnung Hr Dr Sonder senden zu wollen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin mit Ihnen ganz einverstanden, dass alle überzähligen Exemplare </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihrer Anstalt</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> zu Gute kommen sollten. Nur auf die Bitte des grossen von Martius wich ich davon ab u in Bezug auf die Kupfererze. Diese Ausnahmen werden nicht wieder vorkommen denn es liegt </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mir</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> selbst daran, das Material in Zukunft für Stuttgart ganz zusammen zu halten. Inzwischen wird Ihnen eine Sendung mit mehreren seltnen Marsupialien u allerlei Anderem (ich glaube es war pr Essex) zugekommen sein u mit mGreat Britain das letzte mal sandte ich Holzklötze wissenschaftlich benannt, die Sie wohl brauchen können theils um sie im Format Ihrer Sammlungen schneiden zu lassen, theils um von Prof. Nördlinger aus dem Überschuss anderes zu ertauschen. Sie</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="color: #c00000; ">Two pages</seg> of text missing. The first page of the second folded sheet commences ‘Nun noch ein paar Worte…’, and what follows here <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">sits beside it</seg> as the fourth page on the sheet. <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">The second and third pages are missing</seg>
                     <seg style="color: #0b2aff; font-weight: bold; background-color: #ffff00; ">.</seg>
                     <seg style="color: #0b2aff; font-weight: bold; "> </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich hoffe dass Ihre <name key="Todea%20Africana">Todea Africana</name> (od. T. rivularis) sich in der Wärme des Gewächshauses erholt hat. Sie werden aus Südafrika erinnern, dass dieser enorme Farnklotz gern geradezu </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> den Bächen steht. Wenn also die Wedel noch nicht hervorgeschossen sind, so stellen Sie nur die Todea in Wasser im Warmhaus. In St Petersburg habe ich auch eine Todea gehabt u es mag Sie interessiren, wenn ich sage, dass ich der </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Erste</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> war der diese grossen100 Jahr alten u 1000 lbs wiegende Stücke verpflanzte. Erst nachdem ich die Möglichkeit der weiten Verschiffung gezeigt erhielt Verschaffelt seine Prachtexemplare, u erst vor </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">2 Monat</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> hat Kew sein erstes grosses Todea Exemplar durch mich erhalten! Wenn man bedenkt, dass Vasco de Gama vor fast 400 Jahren das Kap der guten Hoffnung umschiffte, so ist es doch ein Triumph für mich, wenn, wie ich glaube, ich zuerst die grosse Todea Europa zugänglich machte. Prof Giglioli in Florenz, ein liebenswürdiger Gelehrter u sehr versprechender Zoologe mit dem Sie jedenfalls in Verbindung stehen möchten, schreibt mir, dass meine zahlreichen hohen Dicksonien, die von der Fregatte Magenta mitgenommen wurde, die grösste Pracht von Florenz gewesen seien im letzten Sommer.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The text ends at the bottom of the page; there is no valediction.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14/8/69.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With this month's mail, esteemed Professor, I have appropriately thanked the Minister for Religious and Educational Affairs for the establishment of the first foundation and also on this occasion have again reiterated my intention to follow up with a second foundation.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to L. von Golther, 14 August 1869.</p>
               </note> I have also promised to give my future collections almost exclusively to the Royal Natural History Museum, as I have already been doing for the past 2 years, and I have been prepared to do so all the more readily as eminent men of science work in the Royal Museum.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In future more attention shall be paid to all your hints. However, I personally am rarely out in the field now (the large departmental labours do not permit this), so that I must often be satisfied with less perfect material that has been purchased or collected by friends, or acquired through exchange. What is in my power will be done. Mr Traill<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Charles Traill. Traill’s collection of shells had been sent to Melbourne on 15 June 1868 (annotation by Gore on Charles Traill to R. B. Gore, 1 June 1868; MU 147, box 2 (1 June 1868), Museum of New Zealand Te Papa Tongarewa Archives, Wellington).</p>
               </note> in New Zealand earnestly begs to have the few previously-sent shells named.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Today</hi>
               </seg> a large case and a barrel have been taken aboard the beautiful clipper <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Norfolk</seg> that our good friend and patron Dr W. Sonder will kindly forward to Stuttgart free of charge. What is perhaps for you most wonderful is a plaster model of the large gold nugget that was discovered in this colony a few months ago, just a few inches below the surface in the diluvium.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">John Deeson and Richard Oates discovered the 'Welcome Stranger' gold nugget weighing 2,284 ounces near Dunolly, Vic, on 5 February 1869.</p>
               </note> I did not get the piece gilded here as the gilding would only suffer during the voyage, but I ask you to have it done <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">there</hi>
               </seg>, on condition however that you will send the expense account for this to our friend Sonder for payment, as I have always considered it a matter of honour to see to it that you should receive all consignments delivered to you free of charge. The Royal Museum has already enough expense with the exhibition. There is a second plaster cast in the case, and by paying a high premium I was able to obtain four of them; the third went to my noble friend Richard Owen for the British Museum and I am sending the fourth to Ad. Brogniart<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Brongniart.</p>
               </note> for the Paris Museum, where I am an honorary member of the administration.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Hooker, 11 August 1869 (in this edition as 69-08-11b) and M to R. Owen, 14 April 1869. M had been a 'correspondent' of the Muséum d’Histoire Naturelle since 15 July 1862. </p>
               </note> The mould has been destroyed and the owner does not permit copying of the specimens sent. I have left it to the discretion of Dr Sonder, whether he would want to open the large case at all in Hamburg. Perhaps you will consult about it with him. There are, it is true, various items for Sonder and other friends in it; however, most of it is for you and unpacking it might endanger the plaster casts. It might therefore be easier to send Sonder his portion from Stuttgart to Hamburg, than to send your part from Hamburg to Stuttgart. Just so long as everything arrives undamaged! It is, after all, a long voyage, this long trip across the oceans, and forwarding it from London often leads to breakages, too. By the way, every care has been taken.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The copper pryrites I sent earlier will at least be of geographical interest, and it certainly was a large series of magnificent pieces; indeed, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">our</hi>
               </seg> Museum has nothing so splendid.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now still a few words about the contents of the case and of the large barrel. The 6th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg> is in it for you and Prof. Hegelmaier. I beg you to see to the forwarding of the relevant volumes for my friends Fenzl, Miquel, etc., if the case goes to Stuttgart unopened, and to send the account for the expense to Dr Sonder.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I quite agree with you, that all superfluous specimens should be of benefit to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your institute</hi>
               </seg>. I diverged from this only on the request by the great Martius and concerning the copper ores.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On the copper ores, see M to F. Wöhler, 5 November 1868 (in this edition as 68-11-05a).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">These exceptions will not happen again, because <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">I myself</hi>
               </seg> am anxious in future to keep all the material together in Stuttgart. Meanwhile you will have received a consignment with several rare marsupials and various other things (I think it was per the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Essex</seg>),<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to F. Krauss, 28 February 1869 (in this edition as 69-02-28a).</p>
               </note> and last time I sent by the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg> timber blocks with their scientific identifications that you could probably use, partly <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to have them cut to the format of your collections, partly to exchange from the surplus other specimens with Professor Nördlinger. You [...]<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="color: #0b2aff; ">Two pages of text missing from photocopy</seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope that your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea africana</seg> (or <seg style="font-style: italic; ">T. rivularis</seg>) has recovered in the warmth of the glasshouse. You will remember from South Africa that these enormous fern clumps love to stand right <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
               </seg> the creeks. So if the fronds have not yet emerged, just stand your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea</seg> in water in the warm glasshouse. I also had a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea</seg> in St Petersburg, and you may be interested to learn that I was the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">first</hi>
               </seg> to transplant these large 100-year-old specimens weighing 1,000 lbs. Only after I had proved that it was possible to ship them such distances did Verschaffelt receive his magnificent specimens, and Kew received its first <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea</seg> specimen only <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">2 months</hi>
               </seg> ago through me!<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Hooker, 19 May 1869 (in this edition as 69-05-19a).</p>
               </note> When you consider that Vasco da Gama sailed around the Cape of Good Hope nearly 400 years ago, it really is a triumph for me when, as I believe, I am the first to introduce the large <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea</seg> into Europe. Professor Giglioli in Florence, an amiable scholar and very promising zoologist with whom you should certainly be in communication, writes to me<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> that my numerous tall <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>s, which were taken across by the frigate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Magenta</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Italian Navy frigate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Magenta</seg>, on a commercial and scientific voyage, was in Melbourne from 4 to 25 May 1867 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 6 May 1867, p. 5; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 27 May 1867, p. 5).</p>
               </note> were the greatest glory of Florence last summer.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, 'Segoe UI Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="color: #0b2aff; ">The text ends at the bottom of the page; there is no valediction.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea%20Africana">Todea Africana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea%20rivularis">Todea rivularis</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
