<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Copy ¶ (original delivered by me to Executors on 29/1/09) ¶ "Von Mueller" ¶ Arnold St. ¶ South Yarra...</title>
            <author>Charles Topp</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M1909-01-29-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>where?, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M1909.01.29</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles Topp</author>
               <title>Copy ¶ (original delivered by me to Executors on 29/1/09) ¶ "Von Mueller" ¶ Arnold St. ¶ South Yarra...</title>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M1909-01-29-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Hermann and Alexander Büttner</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Copy ¶ (original delivered by me to Executors on 29/1/09) ¶ "Von Mueller" ¶ Arnold St. ¶ South Yarra...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M1909.01.29</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Charles Topp to Hermann and Alexander Büttner</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">where?</seg>, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Transcribed 1.6.93.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Copy</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">(original delivered by me to Executors on 29/1/09)</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">"Von Mueller"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Arnold St.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">South Yarra</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">29/1/09.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Sirs,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reply to your letter of the 12th of January<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> asking for certain information in connection with the publication of the biography of the late Baron von Mueller and other matters, and requesting me to furnish replies to certain questions, I have the honor now to forward a statement which will be found, I think, to supply all the information asked for, and to contain answers to your questions.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I am,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dear Sirs,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>yours faithfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>(sigd) Chas A Topp.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1. Government kindly granted me the services of M Renner as Secretary, and is paying his usual Salary.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Renner has been so engaged for the last 6 months, and I recently obtained the permission of the Hon. the Chief Secretary to Mr Renner's continuing this work for 6 months during my absence from the state.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have asked that Mr. Renner may have the use of a good office, and I believe there will be no objection to granting this request, provided there is one available; but I am afraid that there will be a difficulty in finding a suitable room not in use<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">It would appear from the address line that Topp used that he and Renner had been using M's house as their workplace while they went through M's papers. However, Topp was about to go overseas for 12 months — <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Morea</seg>, on which he travelled with his family, cleared out of Melbourne on 2 February — and it appears that Topp thought that Potter's surviving family were fully occuping the house.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">2. I estimate that the preparation of the biography will occupy at least 2 years after my return from Europe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I can venture no opinion as to when the "posthumous writings" will be printed</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">3. I have not undertaken the publication of the posthumous writings &amp;c, and desire to point out that the Baron directs that the cost of certain reports be defrayed from his estate<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M's last will and testament (in this edition as 84-06-17).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In respect to the Biography a very large number of references to the Baron and his recent work have been searched and a selection made of those which seem to be of sufficient interest, to be carefully perused, in connection with the Baron's life. There still remains a great deal of this work to be done.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All books, journals magazines and pamphlets containing any original work by the Baron have been selected from his library and placed together for future reference.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All letters to and from the Baron have been collected from various receptacles (drawers, boxes, shelves &amp;c., these embrace a period of nearly 60 years and number many thousands. About one third of them has been classified - chronologically and under the name of the writer, — and extracts and précis of about 500 have been written.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It has been considered too early at present to take any steps with regard to publication of the Biography, but I have a letter of introduction to the "Clarendon Press" delegates at Oxford, and propose to discuss the question with them. I may remind you that I expressly mentioned that I could take no pecuniary responsibility in connection with the publication, and that my writing the life was contingent upon there being a reasonable prospect of some form of repute undertaking the publication at their own cost. Of course I cannot enter into negotiations with any firm of publishers until can give them a somewhat detailed description of the proposed work and possibly some specimen chapters. I must mention that apart from the cost of publication there are various preliminary expenses incidental to the preparation of the work, such as stationery, letter and parcel postage, possibly lighting, warming and cleaning of an office, and tramway and railway fares. These I cannot undertake to find; and my continuing to work as biographer must depend upon my receiving from the Executors the assurance that they will make available for these expenses a sum of not less than £100, to be advanced in amounts of £10 from time to time as may be required.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Topp's biography was never completed, presumably because of the Order in the proceedings between Alexander and Herman Büttner as plaintiffs and Clara Doughty as defendant in the Supreme Court of Victoria in 1909 (VPRS 267/P0007/ 1909/515, Civil case files, In the matter of the will of Ferdinand Jacob Heinrich von Mueller deceased, Public Record Office, Victoria).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>William Potter died on 28 April 1908 and in May 1908 the Büttners as surviving executors received from solicitors acting for M's nieces and nephews the advice that a writ seeking the administration of M's estate by the court was now to be served against them personally. They responded that they intended to take steps to wind up the estate. The Büttners were advised by Counsel on 26 March 1909 that they should immediately sell the real estate (which they advertised in April for sale by auction in May (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 10 April 1909, p. 2)) and seek a court order on the administration of the estate by means of an Originating Summons. Clara Doughty, M's niece, was the defendant. The Originating Summons was drafted in consultation with the solicitors acting for M's nieces and nephews, and it was decided that Clara Doughty was the most appropriate defendant. An affidavit of the executors' solicitor asserts that Potter had carried out all the administration for the executors. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The case was heard in chambers by Mr Justice a'Beckett on 9 August 1909. In their affidavit the Büttners stated that M's papers, specimens, correspondence and books filled several rooms and that 'in order to protect and classify them and to carry out [M's] desires in respect to them our co-executor William Potter went to reside in the testator's house and resided there until his death'. They understood that Potter had made enquiries and reported that Baroness Negri had died shortly after M, before the bequest of his unofficial correspondence, diplomas and manuscript journals could be sent to her in Italy. They believed that M had left his papers to her so that she would carry out a promise she had made to write his biography. They went on to say that to carry out M's wishes regarding the writing and publication of his biography 'the said William Potter who was a literary man commenced and at the time of his death had partly prepared such a biography having been assisted in that work by a gentleman [Gerhard Renner] skilled in the translation of foreign languages whose services were provided by the government for the purpose'. After Potter's death, the 'surviving executors arranged with Mr Charles Topp formerly Under-Secretary for Victoria and a gentleman acquainted with [M] to carry on the preparation of and edit said biography and the same is now being proceeded with'. All M's real estate had been sold and debts paid, 'the net balance of the estate being Nine hundred pounds representing secured unpaid purchase money of the real estate'. They concluded 'the executors are in doubt as to the true interpretation of the testator's will and as to their duties under it and desire the guidance of this honourable Court thereon'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As part of her response, Clara Doughty argued that the executors should be charged 'with an occupation rent in respect of the real estate ... wherein the executor William Potter resided and be surcharged with any of the testator's estate monies expended by them in the unauthorised preparation of a biography of the testator'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 23 August, the judge ruled among other things that it was the plaintiffs' duty to forward the items left to Baroness Negri 'or deal with them as directed by the person who under the law of her domicile became entitled to her personal property'; that the 'executors were not legally entitled ... to prepare at the cost of the estate any memoir or biographical notices such as they supposed that the testator desired the said Baroness to prepare'. He also ruled that the persons entitled to the proceeds were 'Mrs Wehl and after her death her heirs and those of the testator's sister Mrs George Doughty', and that the 'question of the liability of the executors in respect of breaches of trust, if any, cannot be determined in this proceeding'. He also held that several parts of M's will were inoperable in practice or under general law.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 9 September 1909, Clara Doughty waived any right to the full value of her mother's share of the estate and was content to take an equal share distributed to all thirteen of M's surviving nieces and nephews. On 17 September, the judge directed that 'the Plaintiffs distribute the estate in accordance with such consent'. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Approved costs of each party were to be charged to the estate; the plaintiffs' amounted to £43/7/11, and those of the defendant were £55/19/6.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Büttners sought to clarify the legal position in Italy concerning the estate of Baroness Negri. When after much delay the report that she had died on 16 July 1895 was received, Justice a'Beckett issued a Further Order on 2 November 1910. As she had predeceased M, he 'declared that the said bequest to the said Baroness Negri in the said will failed' and ordered 'that the plaintiffs deliver such private and unofficial correspondence diplomas and manuscript journals to or place the same at the disposal of Messieurs Abbott and Beckett... as the solicitors for the ...beneficiaries'. Additional costs to be charged to the estate were fixed at £5/5/0 for the Plaintiffs and £3/3/0 for the defendant.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As the Executors have expressed their willingness that I should retain any profits (if any) from the work which the publishers may agree to give, I for my part shall be quite willing to undertake to refund to the Executors any amounts paid me for my expenses out of such profits.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In regard to the Baron's posthumous writing and Scientific MS. the position is as follows. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is MS. for a supplement to the first volume of Bentham's "Flora Australiensis." As there are 7 volumes of the "Flora" I do not think this fragment, which would be now considerably out of date, of sufficient botanic value for publication.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There are copies of the last edition of "Select Plants" with marginal notes and additional slips evidently intended for insertion in a new edition (the tenth) The only profitable use would be to incorporate them, as intended by their author in a new edition of the work. As the Government possesses the copyright of "The Select Plants" I cannot recommend any publication of this MS. by the Executors but would suggest that the MS. be offered to the Government for use in connection with the next edition of "Select Plants" on condition that due acknowledgment be made of the use of the Baron's notes and proposed additions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In regard to the re-prints of articles in the metropolitan Journals on the botanic Gardens I regret to state that no traces have been found of the copies referred to in the Baron's will as "being ready" at his residence.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In regard to reprints of the Baron's botanic reports to Government during his term of office as Government Botanist and as Director of the botanic Gardens a volume has been found containing the reports and arranged in chronologic order so that there will be no difficulty in carrying out the direction in the will in regard to this matter. I have asked Mr Püttmann of the firm of McCarron Bird, printers, to be good enough to furnish me with an estimate of the probable cost of 500 copies of such a reprint, and he has kindly promised to forward me an estimate in the course of few days. In case I have left the state before the estimate is ready I have arranged that it is forwarded to the Executors<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In their affidavit the Büttners stated that they had '<seg style="">ascertained that the same will cost about £200', and Mr Justice a'Beckett ordered</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">owing to the lapse of time since the death of the testator the request contained in the said will to publish and distribute the departmental reports therein referred to cannot now be complied with so as to affect any object that the testator had in view and no part of that testator's estate is now to be expended in attempting to attain such object.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In regard to the Executors' proposed disposal of letters, private and otherwise &amp; of other writings not required in connection with the preparation for, and publication of the deceased Baron's posthumous writings, scientific MS., &amp;c, and of the biography I think the best course will be for Mr Renner, who will be engaged during the next 6 or more months in perusing these letters and writings, to hand over from time to time to the Executors such of these as he considers will not be required in connection with the matters mentioned I have full confidence in leaving to Mr Renner's discretion during my absence the selection of such writings as are valuable and needful and the rejection of those which will not be required</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I may now state that to the best of my knowledge Professor Ewart has now received all the books and pamphlets he is entitled to and that he is satisfied</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There may be a few books to be returned by him after he has checked those received, as not having been purchased by Government. The number of these, however, will be small.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In connection with the Baron's writings, which have already appeared in print and have been published I should mention that he has left, chronologically arranged, a large volume of printed slips of descriptions of new species of plants examined and classified by him since the publication of the last volume of the "Fragmenta Phytographiae Austral." nearly up to the time of his death. These appeared originally in a great variety of journals and magazines, some of which it would not be easy to obtain. The publication of these in one volume, would, I believe, be much appreciated by Botanists. It would form a companion volume to the eleven books of the "Fragmenta, although it would differ from them in that the description would be in English while those of the "Fragmenta" are in Latin. I think it probable that the Government would undertake this publication and they should be approached on the subject.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No such volume was published.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
