<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg 3 May 53 ¶ Esteemed Professor ¶  ¶ In the name of my friend Dr Ferd. Müller in Melbourne, Australia, I beg to send you a manuscript on the Flora of southwestern Schleswig for publication in th...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M53-05-03-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Archiv der Regensburgischen Botanischen Gesellschaft, Universitätsbibliothek, Regensburg.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M53.05.03</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg 3 May 53 ¶ Esteemed Professor ¶  ¶ In the name of my friend Dr Ferd. Müller in Melbourne, Australia, I beg to send you a manuscript on the Flora of southwestern Schleswig for publication in th...</title>
               <date when="1853-05-03">1853-05-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M53-05-03-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Polygoneae</term>
               <term>Proteaceae</term>
               <term>Thymeleae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Fürnrohr</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg 3 May 53 ¶ Esteemed Professor ¶  ¶ In the name of my friend Dr Ferd. Müller in Melbourne, Australia, I beg to send you a manuscript on the Flora of southwestern Schleswig for publication in th...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M53.05.03</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to August Fürnrohr</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Archiv der Regensburgischen Botanischen Gesellschaft, Universitätsbibliothek, Regensburg.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg d. 3 May 53</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Geehrter Herr Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Namen meines Freundes, Dr. Ferd. Müller in Melbourne in Australien, erlaube ich mir Ihnen ein Manuskript über die Flora des südwestlichen Schleswig zur Aufnahme in die Flora zu übersenden. Da über diese Gegend noch nichts veröffentlicht ist, und Müller eine Reihe von Jahren sehr emsig gesammelt und beobachtet hat, möchte die Aufzählung der Veröffentlichung werth sein.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zu gleicher Zeit sende ich hierbei ein Packet mit Pflanzen, gesammelt von Dr Müller und Herrn C. Stuart in Neuholland und auf Van Diemensland. Sie ersehen daraus, dass Müller auch an seinem jetzigen Aufenthaltsorte die Botanik nicht vergessen hat; ich kann <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>mit vollem Rechte hinzusetzen, dass er schon recht viel in Australien geleistet hat und noch sehr viel zu leisten verspricht. Ich erwarte bedeutende Sendungen von Müller, da er jetzt in Melbourne ansässig ist, wo er als Arz und Apotheker figurirt; ich werde Ihnen <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>auch für das Herbarium der bot. Gesellschaft später mehr Pflanzen mitzutheilen haben. Die ersten Jahre hielt Müller sich in Adelaide auf, als aber der Strom der Goldgräber sich nach Melburne wandete, schien es ihm vortheilhaft denselben zu folgen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Müller hat mehrere Male gegen mich geäussert, dass es ihm ausserordentlich lieb sein würde, wenn er und Stuart Mitglieder der Regensburger bot. Gesellschaften werden könnten. Ich denke Sie werden es mir nicht übel nehmen, wenn ich Ihnen dieses ohne viele Umschweife mittheile. Müller wird mit seinem regen Eifer sich der Ehre werth zeigen; und wenn alles, was Müller mir über Stuart mitgetheilt, wahr ist, woran ich nicht zweifle, so hat dieser Mann hinreichende Verdienste um der Botanik. Charles Stuart gegenwärtig auch in Melbourne lebend, grösstentheils aber auf Van Diemensland sich aufenhaltend, ist ursprünglich ein Gärtner. Er lebte längere Zeit ganz von Pflanzensammeln und treibt dieses auch noch, und immer, wenn er sich einige Pfund auf irgend eine Weise verdient hat; dann geht er in die Berge, bis Nahrungssorgen ihn wieder von seinen Pflanzen abrufen. Er hat lange für Gunn gesammelt, von diesem aber nur Undank und schlechten Lohn eingeerndtet, Gunn obgleich er nichts dabei gethan, ist mit dem Ruhme davon gegangen, von Stuart hat früher niemand etwas gehört. St. soll ein höchst bescheidenen Mensch sein, der sehr unterrichtet und für Australien vielleicht zu brav und ehrlich ist. Vielleicht könnte ihm das Diplom als Mitglied der Reg. bot. Gesellschaft eine Stelle einbringen, so dass seine Zukunft gesichert wäre; Sie wissen gewiss auch, wie viel in England und dessen Besitzungen auf eine solche Auszeichnung gegeben wird.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Halten Sie diese Herren für würdig, um unter die Mitglieder der botan. Gesellschaft aufgenommen zu werden, und ist der Herr Präsidenten damit einverstanden, so werde ich mich glücklich schätzen, den Herren die Diplomen zuzustellen. Geht es nicht an, so hat es auch nichts auf sich.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Müller möchte gerne von seinem Breviarium 12-15 Abdrücke erhalten; wenn es sein müss, wird er gerne dafür entrichten, welches durch mich geschehen kann, da ich von seinen Pflanzen verkaufen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin seit ungefähr 1½ Jahren von der Botanik viel abgegangen, erst seit Anfang dieses Jahres habe ich wieder mehr Zeit. Man hat mich in's Sanitätscollegium gewählt. Obgleich ich keine besondere Lust dazu verspürte, habe ich es doch nicht abschlagen können.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Neulich hatte ich zuerst den Besuch von Dr Münter aus Greifswald und darauf den von Prof. Meisner aus Basel, letzterer war mehrere Tage in Hamburg und durchsah die Sendundungen von Proteaceen, Polygoneen und Thymeleen, die bald für Decand's Prodromus gedruckt werden sollen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Herrn Dr Steetz habe ich Ihnen freundliche Grüsse zu bestellen, und in der Hoffnung, dass Sie sich wohl befinden, verbleibe ich</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hochachtungsvollen ergebenen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg 3 May 53</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Professor</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the name of my friend Dr Ferd. Müller in Melbourne, Australia, I beg to send you a manuscript on the Flora of southwestern Schleswig for publication in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B53.08.01.</p>
               </note> As nothing has been published yet about this region and Müller has observed and collected assiduously over a number of years, the enumeration might be worthy of publication.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the same time I enclose a parcel with plants collected by Dr Müller and Mr C. Stuart in New Holland and Van Diemen's Land. You will perceive from this that Müller has not forgotten botany even in his present place of residence. For good reason I can add that he has already accomplished much in Australia and promises to accomplish even more. I expect significant consignments from Müller because he is now resident in Melbourne, where he now operates as physician and pharmacist.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By the time Sonder wrote this letter, M had been appointed Victoria's Government Botanist.</p>
               </note> I shall also later have more plants to send you for the herbarium of the botanical society. Mülller stayed in Adelaide for the first years but when the stream of gold diggers turned to Melbourne, it seemed advantageous to him to follow.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Müller has remarked to me several times that he would be very glad, if he and Stuart could become members of the Regensburg Botanical Society. I think you would not take it amiss, if I say this to you bluntly. Müller will prove himself worthy of the honour by his zealous ardour; and If all that Müller has said to me about Stuart is true, which I do not doubt, this man has sufficient contributions to botany. Charles Stuart, at present living in Melbourne too but for the most part staying in Van Diemen's Land, was originally a gardener. He lived for a long time completely from plant collecting and still does this, and when he has earned some pounds in any way, he always goes into the mountains until worries about food call him away from his plants. He collected for Gunn for a long time but obtained only ingratitude and poor pay from him. Although he did nothing for it, Gunn has got the glory and no one previously has heard anything of Stuart. St. is said to be an extremely modest person, who is very educated and perhaps too upright and honest for Australia. Perhaps the diploma as member of the Reg. Bot. Society could get him a position, so that his future would be secured. You surely also know how much is given in England and its possessions for such a distinction.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If you regard these gentlemen as worthy to be admitted among the members of the Botan. Society and the President is in agreement with it, I shall count myself fortunate to deliver the diplomas to the gentlemen. If it is not possible, never mind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Müller would like to get 12–15 reprints of his Brevarium. He will willingly pay if he has to, which can happen through me because I am selling his plants.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I have very much gone off botany for about 1½ years and only since the beginning of this year have more time again. I've been elected to the health commission. Although I felt no particular desire for it, I really could not refuse it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Recently I first had a visit from Dr Münter from Greifswald and after that from Prof. Meisner from Basel. The latter was in Hamburg several days and looked through the consignments of <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>, <name key="Polygoneae">Polygoneae</name> and <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name> that are to be printed soon for Decand's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus.</seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meisner (1856), Meisner (1856a) and Meisner (1857a), respectively. He cited collections by both M and Stuart. See, for example, Meisner (1856a), p. 147.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have to deliver friendly greetings to you from Dr Steetz, and in the hope that you are well, I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">respectfully devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polygoneae">Polygoneae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
