<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg 25 January 1856. ¶ Highly esteemed Sir! ¶  ¶ I am very grateful for your letter of 13th of this month, and the news has pleased me very much that you have finished the working up of the Muelle...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M56-01-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Universiteitsbibliotheek, Hs 1873, Utrecht, Netherlands.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M56.01.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg 25 January 1856. ¶ Highly esteemed Sir! ¶  ¶ I am very grateful for your letter of 13th of this month, and the news has pleased me very much that you have finished the working up of the Muelle...</title>
               <date when="1856-01-25">1856-01-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M56-01-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Dawsonia superba</term>
               <term>Juncagineae</term>
               <term>Xerotideae</term>
               <term>Myrtaceae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Miquel</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg 25 January 1856. ¶ Highly esteemed Sir! ¶  ¶ I am very grateful for your letter of 13th of this month, and the news has pleased me very much that you have finished the working up of the Muelle...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M56.01.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Friedrich Miquel</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Universiteitsbibliotheek, Hs 1873, Utrecht, Netherlands.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg d. 25 Januar 1856.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter Herr!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin Ihnen recht dankbar für Ihren Brief vom 13. d. M., und recht sehr erfreut hat mich die Nachricht, dass Sie die Bearbeitung der Müller'schen Pflanzen beendigt haben. Was die Publication Ihrer Arbeit anbetrifft, so werden Sie in den letzten beiden Jahren mehrere Artikel der "Plantae Müllerianae" in der Linnaea gesehen haben. Ich hätte gerne gesehen, dass in derselben Zeitschrift auch Ihre Bearbeitung erscheine; Sie machen mich aber aufmerksam auf die baldige Herausgeben von Hooker's Flor. Tasm. und da bin ich doch zweifelhaft geworden, ob es nicht rathsam sei, das Mss so schnell als möglich zum Druck zu befördern. Schlechtendal hat seit October v. J. die Bearbeitung mehrerer kleinen Familien z. B. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <name key="Juncagineae">Juncagineae</name>, <name key="Xerotideae">Xerotideae</name> etc von mir in Händen, ausserdem habe ich ihm neulich die Bearbeitung der zweiten Sendung Müller'schen Laubmoose zugesandt; kömmt dieses erst an die Reihe, wenn die Berg'sche Arbeit über die Amerikanischer Myrtaceen vollendet ist, und nachher erst Ihr Mss über die Myrtaceen etc so könnte leicht noch ein halbes Jahr darüber vergehen, bevor Ihre Arbeit gedruckt ist. Desshalb will ich es ganz Ihrem Ermessen überlassen ob Sie das Mss direct an Schlechtendal übersenden, oder dort in den Schriften der Academie veröffentlichen wollen. In letzterem Falle muss ich aber am wenigstens 1 Dutz Separatabdrücke für Dr Müller bitten, ich für meine Person brauche nicht mehr als ein einziges Exemplar.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich mag es gar nicht wagen, Sie zu fragen, ob Sie Lust haben, fernerhin noch mehr von Müller's Pflanzen zu bearbeiten, Ihre Zeit wird durch die Flora des Ind. Archip. auf längere Dauer in Anspruch genommen sein: Von Ihnen erfolgreichen Bestrebungen habe ich häufig gelesen, die Cultur der Chinobäume auf Java ist überaus interessant und verspricht glänzende Resultate. Mit Freuden wird die botanische Welt Ihre Flora des Ind Archipels begrüssen, worüber bis jetzt die Literatur so zerstreut war. Welches Material müssen Sie dazu in den Museen Ihres Landes besitzen! Fenzl hat mir davon erzählt. Nur mit einem <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">vollständigen</hi>
               </seg> Materiale sollte jede bedeutende Arbeit angefangen werden, es ist der einzigste Weg, um der so überhand nehmenden Speciesmacherei Einhalt zu thun. J. Hooker's offene Erklärung, wenn sie vielleicht auch etwas zu weit geht, hat mich sehr erfreut.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin Ihnen ausserordentlich dankbar, dass Sie mich mit einem Päckchen javanischer Pflanzen erfreuen wollen. Ich habe nur von Zollinger eine Anzahl aus diesem herrlichen Lande erhalten, und desshalb nehme ich einen neue Beitrag mit Freuden an. Da Sie so freundlich sind, hinzuzufügen, dass in der Folge noch mehrere nachfolgen dürften, so ist es wohl nicht mehr als meine Pflicht Sie zu fragen, ob ich Ihnen nicht ein Aequivalent anderer exotischer Pflanzen anbieten darf. Aus Südafrika und Port Natal bin ich wohl gegenwärtig die Hauptquelle, da mein Haus, so zu sagen, voll davon ist; aber auch aus Neuholland habe ich noch mancherlei abzugeben, vielleicht wissen Sie es nicht, dass die Pflanzen von Dr Ferd. Müller nur allein in meinem Besitze sind und nicht verkauft sondern nur von mir verschenkt werden. Ich werde mich bestreben Ihren Wünschen in dieser Beziehung nachzukommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Erlauben Sie mir eine Anfrage. Sie haben einen berühmten Bryologen in Holland, von dem ich neulich in der Bibliothek ein Heft javanischer Laubmoose, wenn ich nicht […]<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Page torn.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> denken, bearbeitet, sah. Sollte es nicht möglich sein, von diesem Herrn (Dozy oder Molkenboer der eine ist wie ich in der Bonplandia las, gestorben) von seinen Doubletten zu erhalten? Ich interessire mich sehr für meine Moossammlung, und bin im Stande, ihm seltne und neu beschriebene Arten aus Neuholland, worunter <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Dawsonia%20superba">Dawsonia superba</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>, wovon Dr Müller mir schöne Exemplare sandte, dagegen zugeben. Fűr Ihren Herrn van den Bosch habe ich bereits Flechten und Filices, worum er mich bat, zusammengelegte. Bei Uebersendung dieser Pflanzen wollte ich mir erlauben, für Sie das neueste Heft der <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Flora universalis</hi>
               </seg>, wofür ich mich jetzt interessire und wozu ich die Pflanzen hergebe, beizulegen und Sie bitten, dieses so wie die Fortsetzung freundlichst anzunehmen; aber der Frost ist auch mir entgegengetreten, und das Packet muss bis zur Eröffnung der Schiffarth liegen bleiben. Ich danke Ihnen für die opuscula botanica, die Sie, wie Sie schreiben, der Kiste beigelegt haben. Ich bedaure, Ihnen augenblicklich nichts dagegen anbieten zukõnnen, da in den letzten Jahren meine Zeit theils von Geschäfte, theils von meinen amtlichen Geschäften, als Mitglied des Gesundheitrathes fast gänzlich in Anspruch genommen sind. In unserem freien Staate muss man nolens volens solche Aemte annehmen. Leider sind die Beziehungen, zu welchen die hiesigen Botanicker zu einander stehen, in Hamburg auch nicht die angenehmsten; mit dem, der eigentlich unser Leiter sein sollte, ist kein Umgehen, und so sind Dr Steetz und ich die einzigen, die zusammenhalten, und Spötteleien und Angriffe nicht achtend, der freundlichen Flora angenehme Stunden entnehmen. Wie angenehm war unser Zusammenleben in botanischen Kreise hier früher, und wie entmuthigend ist es jetzt. Doch bald hätte ich hierüber vergessen, Sie zu fragen, ob ich Ihnen für Ihren botanischen Garten eine nicht grosse aber interessante Anzahl neuholländischer Sämereien, welche mir im Herbste von Freund Müller gesandt werden, anbieten darf, und wenn überhaupt auf welchen Wege ich Ihnen dieselbe zuschicken darf</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich verbleibe</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>hochachtungsvoll ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg 25 January 1856.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Highly esteemed Sir!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am very grateful for your letter of 13th of this month, and the news has pleased me very much that you have finished the working up of the Mueller plants. In respect to the publication of your work, you will have seen in the last two years several articles of "Plantae Müllerianae" in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg>. I would like to have seen your work also published in the same periodical. However, you have drawn my attention to the early publication of Hooker's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora Tasmaniae</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. Hooker (1860), issued in fascicles from 1855.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and then I have become really doubtful whether it is not advisable to send the manuscript to press as soon as possible. Since October of last year, Schlechtendal has the working up of several small families, e. g. <name key="Juncagineae">Juncagineae</name>, <name key="Xerotideae">Xerotideae</name> etc by me in hand, in addition I have recently sent him the second consignment of Mueller mosses for working up; it is next in turn only when the Berg work on the American <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name> is completed and only after that your manuscript on the <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name> etc, so another half year could easily pass before your work is printed. Therefore I will leave it entirely to your judgement, whether you send the manuscript direct to Schlechtendal, or want to have it published there in the publications of the academy.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Miquel opted to publish in Holland; see Miquel (1856).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> In the latter case, however, I must ask you for at least one dozen separate prints for Dr Mueller. For myself I need no more than a single copy.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not like to venture to ask you whether you feel like working up still more of Mueller's plants in the future. Your time will be taken up by the flora of the Indian Archipelago<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. Indonesia. See Miquel (1855-9).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> for some time. I have frequently read of your successful endeavours, the cultivation of the China trees on Java is extremely interesting and promises marvellous results. The botanical world will greet your flora of the Indian Archipelago with pleasure, about which up to now the literature was so scattered. What material you must have for that in the museums of your country! Fenzl has told me of it. Every significant work should be begun only with <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">complete</hi>
               </seg> material, it is the only way to put a stop to the species-making that is becoming so rampant. J. Hooker's open declaration, even if it perhaps goes somewhat too far, has pleased me very much.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. Hooker (1853-5), vol. 1, pp. xii-xvii.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am extraordinarily grateful to you that you intend to please me with a small parcel of Javanese plants. I have received a number from this splendid country only from Zollinger and therefore I accept a new contribution with pleasure. As you are so kind to add that still more may follow sequentially, I suppose it is no more than my duty to ask you whether I may not offer you an equivalent of other exotic plants. At present I am probably the principle source from South Africa and Port Natal, because my house, so to speak, is full of them; but also from New Holland I have still many kinds to give away. Perhaps you do not know that the plants from Dr Mueller are in my possession alone and not to be sold but only to be given away by me. I will endeavour to fulfil your wishes in this regard.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Permit me a question. You have a celebrated bryologist in Holland, by whom I recently saw a paper in the library of Javanese mosses worked up, if I am not thinking [in error?].<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dozy &amp; Molkenboer (1855-70), vol. 1, fasc. 1-10?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Should it not be possible to get his duplicates from this gentleman (Dozy or Molkenboer, the one is dead as I read in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bonplandia</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Molkenboer died in 1854.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>)? I am very interested in my moss collection and I am in a position to give him in return rare and newly described species from New Holland, among which <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Dawsonia%20superba">Dawsonia superba</name>
               </seg>, of which Dr Mueller sent me beautiful specimens. I have already put together lichens and ferns for your Mr van den Bosch, which he requested of me. In sending these plants I intended to permit myself to include for you the latest part of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora universalis</seg>, in which I am now interested and to which I furnished the plants<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora universalis in colorirten Abbildungen</seg>
                     <seg style=""> was issued in parts from 1849. D. Dietrich (1849-55) is a new series, with which Sonder was presumably involved. Mueller had the 'last facsicles' (B65.10.01, p. 19), presumably Hefte 8 and 9 held by the Library at MEL.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and to ask you kindly to accept this as well as the continuation, but the frost has also anticipated me and the parcel must stand over until the opening of the navigation. I thank you for the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">opuscula botanica</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. small botanical works. Not identified.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> that you, as you write, have enclosed in the box. I regret not being able to offer you anything in return at present, because in recent years my time has been taken up almost completely partly by business and partly by my official duties as member of the sanitary council. In our Free State one must perforce accept such offices. Unfortunately the relationships to which the local botanists stand to one another in Hamburg are also not the most pleasant; there is no association with him who really should be our leader,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. G. C. Lehmann, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>director of the Hamburg Botanic Garden?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and so Dr Steetz and I are the only ones who stick together and, not paying heed to mocking and attacks, take pleasant hours for the friendly flora. How pleasant was our social life in botanical circles here previously, and how discouraging it is now. But I soon would have forgotten to ask you whether I may offer you a not large but interesting number of New Holland seeds for your botanical garden, which were sent to me in autumn by friend Mueller and if at all in what way I may send them to you.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your respectful devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dawsonia%20superba">Dawsonia superba</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Juncagineae">Juncagineae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xerotideae">Xerotideae</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
