<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>High Office of the Imperial Royal Chamberlain ¶  ¶ In the interest of the Imperial Royal Court’s  ¶  ¶ botanical cabinet as well as of the University’s botanical garden, the most humble undersigned pr...</title>
            <author>Eduard Fenzl</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M63-06-10-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>1863r, 58/3, 524 B Oberstkämmerersamt, Ordensarchiv, Abt. Haus-, Hof- und Staatsarchiv, Österreichisches Staatsarchiv, Vienna.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M63.06.10</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Eduard Fenzl</author>
               <title>High Office of the Imperial Royal Chamberlain ¶  ¶ In the interest of the Imperial Royal Court’s  ¶  ¶ botanical cabinet as well as of the University’s botanical garden, the most humble undersigned pr...</title>
               <date when="1863-06-10">1863-06-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M63-06-10-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Lord High Chamberlain's Office, Vienna</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">High Office of the Imperial Royal Chamberlain ¶  ¶ In the interest of the Imperial Royal Court’s  ¶  ¶ botanical cabinet as well as of the University’s botanical garden, the most humble undersigned pr...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M63.06.10</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Eduard Fenzl to the Lord High Chamberlain's Office, Vienna</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">1863r, 58/3, 524 B Oberstkämmerersamt, </seg>
               <seg style="">Ordensarchiv, Abt. Haus-, Hof- und Staatsarchiv, Österreichisches Staatsarchiv, Vienna.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hohes K. K. Oberstkämmerer-Amt</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Interesse des K. K. botanischen Hofkabinetes wie des G. b Universitäts Gartens und des zoologischen Museums erlaubt sich der gehorsamst Gefertigte ein Hohes Amt auf eine im englischen Colonial-Dienst stehende Persönlichkeit aufmerksam zu machen und einer besonderen Berücksichtigung und Auszeichnung wärmstens zu empfehlen. Es ist diess Herr Dr. Ferdinand Müller, Director des botanischen Gartens zu Melbourne in Australien, Vice-Praesident der dortigen Gesellschaft für Acclimatization, Reichsphytograph der Colonie Victoria und Professor an der Universität zu Melbourne &amp;c. &amp;c., ein Mann, der sich im Laufe von 10 Jahren die grössten Verdienste um die wissenschaftliche Kenntniss der Colonie Victoria und des innern von Neu Holland erworben hat und als Gelehrter wie als Staatsbeamter in hohem Ansehen bei dem dortigen Gouvernement wie in der gelehrten Welt steht.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Dr. Ferd. Müller steht mit mir seit einer Reihe von Jahren in Relation und hat unser Museum wie den Garten und die Bibliothek des ersteren fortwährend mit den interessantesten Sammlungen an Pflanzen, Sämereien und Druckwerken bereichert und weitere Zusendungen an naturhistorischen Schätzen zugesagt. Die Mitglieder der Novara-Expedition, namentlich Professor Dr. Hochstetter erfreuten sich nicht bloss seiner ausgiebigsten und freundlichsten Unterstützung, sondern erhielten durch ihn höchst werthvolle Geschenke an Pflanzen und zoologischen Gegenständen von bedeutendem Umfange. Seit der Zeit, als Sr. Excellenz Freyherr von Hügel und vor ihm der unglückliche Reisende Franz Sieber unsere Museen mit naturhistorischen Schätzen aus Neu Holland bereicherten, waren selbe fortwährend angewiesen sich derartige Objecte um schwere Summen durch Naturalien-Händler zu verschaffen, während sie ihnen jetzt in weit grösserer Menge und in ganz anderer Weise ohne Kosten durch die Liberalität Herrn Dr. Müllers Jahr für Jahr zufliessen. Ein Gewinn, den niemand höher als der Fachgelehrte und Vorstand eines nur mit den nothdürftigsten Geldmitteln ausgestatteten Museums seinem ganzen Umfang nach zu würdigen im Stande ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es darf daher nicht befremden, wenn der Gefertigte von seinem Standpunkte als Gelehrter sowohl wie als Administrator eines der bedeutendsten Museums auf dem Continente, nicht bloss persönlich sich zu lebhaftesten Dank für Herrn Dr. Müller verpflichtet fühlt, sondern noch auf alle und jede Weise sich bemüht sich diese Besugsquelle für die Folge offen zu erhalten. Leider glaubt derselbe aber nicht wirksamer entsprechen zu können, als wenn er es wagt an ein Hohes Amt die ergebenste Bitte zu stellen: Es geruhe Allerhöchsten Ortes den Antrag auf gnädigste Verleihung des Ritterkreuzes des Franz Josephs-Ordens an Herrn Dr. Ferd. Müller zu stellen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zu bemerken habe ich noch, dass Herr Dr. Müller laut brieflichen Mittheilungen an Herrn Dr. u, Graf Hochstetter auf eine Besuchsreise in sein Vaterland /: Hamburg :/ begriffen bereits in Triest angelangt sein dürfte und nächster Tage in Wien eintreffen wird. Nichts könnte ihm eine grössere und ehrenvollere Überraschung bereiten, als die Mittheilung der ihm allergnädigst zu Theil gewordenen Auszeichnung.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Dr Ed. Fenzl</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vorstand</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Wien den 10. Juni 1863.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">High Office of the Imperial Royal Chamberlain</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the interest of the Imperial Royal Court’s <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>botanical cabinet as well as of the University’s botanical garden, the most humble undersigned presumes to call the attention of the High Office to a person in the English colonial service and to recommend most warmly a particular consideration and award. It is Dr Ferdinand Mueller, Director of the Botanical Garden at Melbourne in Australia, Vice-President of the local Acclimatisation Society, Government Botanist of the Colony of Victoria and Professor at the University of Melbourne<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was never a university professor.</p>
               </note> &amp;c &amp;c, a man, who in the course of ten years has rendered the greatest service to the scientific knowledge of the Colony of Victoria and the interior of New Holland and both as scholar and civil servant stands in high esteem with the government there as well as in the learned world.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Mueller has been in correspondence with me for a number of years and has continually enriched our Museum as well as the Garden, and the Library of the former, with the most interesting collections of plants, seeds and printed works and further consignments of natural history treasures are promised. The members of the Novara expedition, especially Professor Dr Hochstetter, enjoyed not only his most ample and most friendly support, but also received through him highly valuable donations of plants and zoological objects in significant amount. Since the time when His Excellency Baron von Hügel and before him the unfortunate traveller Franz Sieber enriched our museums with natural history treasures from New Holland, these were continually dependent on procuring such objects through natural history dealers for large sums, whereas now they flow to them year after year in far greater quantity and in quite another manner without cost through the liberality of Dr Mueller. A gain that no-one higher than the specialist and board of a museum endowed with the the poorest of funds is in a position to value according to its whole extent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It may therefore not be surprising if the undersigned from his standpoint both as scholar and administrator of one of the most significant museums on the continent not only feels obliged personally with the warmest thanks to Dr Mueller, but also still endeavours in all and every way to keep open this source of supply for the future. Sadly, however, he believes himself unable to comply more effectively than by daring to put the most humble request to the High Office: That the Supreme Place may deign to propose the most gracious confering of the Knight’s Cross of the Franz Joseph Order on Dr Ferdinand Mueller.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Fenzl’s submission was successful; see T. Peithner von Lichtenfels to M, 17 July 1863.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have still to remark that according to correspondence to Dr and Count Hochstetter, Dr Mueller, travelling on a visit to his fatherland (Hamburg), may have already arrived in Trieste and next day will arrive in Vienna.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had been planning to visit Europe but at the last minute had decided not to go. Hamburg was not M’s fatherland but would have been a major port of call for him, en route to visit his relatives in neighbouring Schleswig-Holstein.</p>
               </note> Nothing could give him a greater and more honorable surprise than the information of the award most graciously bestowed on him.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dr Ed. Fenzl</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Chairman</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Vienna, 10 June 1863.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
