<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 6 August 1867. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ The case with the natural history objects ¶  was sent yesterday, freight paid, by rail, per address of the Royal Natural History Museum in Stuttgart. It ...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M67-08-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M67.08.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 6 August 1867. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ The case with the natural history objects ¶  was sent yesterday, freight paid, by rail, per address of the Royal Natural History Museum in Stuttgart. It ...</title>
               <date when="1867-08-06">1867-08-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M67-08-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Alsophila</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/26f088e5-c0e9-44d3-9684-57815342b778">Dicksonia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 6 August 1867. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ The case with the natural history objects ¶  was sent yesterday, freight paid, by rail, per address of the Royal Natural History Museum in Stuttgart. It ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M67.08.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotated by Krauss 'No 4 | R. d. 11. Sept.' [Replied 11 September]. Letter not found.</p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 6 Aug. 1867</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Herr Professor!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Kiste mit naturhist. Gegenständen ist gestern mit der Eisenbahn und frankirt abgegangen, unter der Addr. Königl. Naturalien Cabinet in St. Es sind circa 100 Gegenstände darin, meist Vogelbälge, dann ein Affenskelett, ein Kasten mit Schmetterlingen, 2 Kisten mit Käfern oder andern Insekten, einige Proben, [...] [Früchten] u 1 Päckchen Sämereien. Was die Zoologie anbetrifft, so werden Sie vielleicht darin nicht viel Ihnen Unbekanntes oder Seltenes finden, es sind dies ja alles noch Sendungen, die Ihnen ursprünglich nicht zugedacht waren, und was Ihnen lieb u werth sei, wusste Dr Müller nicht. Die Schmetterlinge, meint M., müssten einige neue enthalten, es sind nicht viele, aber sie sind aus dem Innern. M. hatte sie mir geschickt, um sie bestimmen u wenn neu, beschreiben zu lassen; das können Sie in Würtemberg ebenso gut, denn Herrich-Schäfer lebt in Ihrer Nähe, wenn Sie sonst keinen am Ort haben. Die Sämereien habe ich beigelegt, weil es meistens Sträucher oder Blattpflanzen sind, die wegen ihres Laubes als solche die Cultur verdienen möchten. Sie ersehen aber wieder hieraus, dass M. ungemein thätig u mittheilsam ist. Er schreibt mir in seinem letzten Briefe vom 12 Mai, dass er im Juni wieder eine Kiste mit Frischwasser u Landmuscheln senden wolle, über die Dr Cox gerade ein Buch schreibt, dann eine Sammlung correct benannter Crania von Vögeln. Seine Fische will er jetzt auch nicht mehr an Agassiz, Dumeril? u a<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">und andere.</p>
               </note> senden; er meint unter den Fischen müsste doch noch manches Neue auftauchen, er hat seinem Sammler an der Nordküste, Alcohol für diese Thiere, Saurier u.s.w. mitgegeben. Aus seinen Coleopteren hat sich Graf Castelnau seit Jahren das Beste ausgesucht, dieser Herr ist dort im Consulat. Die nächste Sendung wird ein Exemplar eines Argonauten bringen, den Dr Müller u a.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">und andere.</p>
               </note> Naturforscher in Melbourne für neu halten. Was er hierüber mittheilt, finden Sie auf beiliegendem Blatt. Ebenfalls sendet er mir eine Skizze des neuen Casuarius, die ich Ihnen auch beilege.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Müller's Brief ist ganz wie ich erwartet habe, er ist mit meiner Disposition ganz einverstanden. Ich musste ihm, was Sie billig finden werden, die Nachricht von der Absicht der auswärtigen Regierung, die ihm den Barontitel zusicherte, mittheilen, indess, wenn ihm dies auch sehr schmeichelhaft erschien, er meint doch er sei ein Deutscher u hätte seine Sachen lieber im lieben Vaterlande. Er will auch, wie er [geäussert], das Stipendium stiften u wünscht meine Meinung über einige Sp[ecialia] darin, er will, dass man ihn später auch achte, auch wenn er nicht mehr lebt. Seinen Ehrgeiz hat er allerdings, er wäre auch nichts geworden, wenn er den nicht hätte, er ist aber dankbar, wie es wenig gefunden wird. Sie fragten einmal nach seinen Titeln; das neue Titelblatt zum 5 Band der Fragmenta Phytograph. Australas. zählt sie Ihnen auf. Ich glaube, dass Sie ihm mit dem Orden der würt. Krone, mit dem der persönl. Adel verbunden ist, eine grosse Freude machen werden, u dass Sie dann ihn für immer gefesselt haben. Wahrscheinlich wird er in seinen Leistungen gegen Ludwig nicht zurückbleiben, u wenn Sie berücksichtigen, dass M. nicht mit Glücksgütern so gesegnet ist, verdient letzterer gewiss nicht weniger Anerkennung. So wie seine Stellung dort, durch Auszeichnugen des Auslandes immer mehr gewinnt, so<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">so <seg style="font-style: italic; ">interline</seg>. </p>
               </note> so wird er auch immer mehr leisten können. — Er schreibt wieder von den vielen Briefen von Keferstein, Wöhler, aus Berlin, Paris u.s.w., u der italienische Naturforscher, der mit der Fregatte Magenta dort ist hat eine ganze Anzahl schöne Sachen, auch eine Menge Stämme von <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name> u <name key="Alsophila">Alsophila</name> eingenommen. — Doch genug davon. Die Hauptsache ist, dass Sie nun wissen, wie Sie mit Dr Müller dran sind. Er hat mich vorläufig gebeten, Sie freundlichst von ihm zu grüssen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn Ihre Gesundheit angegriffen war, so haben Sie jedenfalls besser gethan in die Schweiz als nach Paris zu reisen, von woher alle Bekannte noch abgespannt u müde zurückgekehrt sind. Ich will hoffen, dass der Nutzen von Ihrer Reise ein lange anheltender sei</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit aufrichtigem Grusse</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 6 August 1867.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The case with the natural history objects<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Sonder to Krauss, 1 July 1867 (in this edition as M67-07-01).</p>
               </note> was sent yesterday, freight paid, by rail, per address of the Royal Natural History Museum in Stuttgart. It contains approximately 100 objects, mostly bird skins, a monkey skeleton,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The skeleton was of a Proboscis Monkey (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Nasalis larvatus</seg>) from Borneo; see W. Sonder to F. Krauss, undated fragment, probably early 1868 (in this edition as M68-00-00).</p>
               </note> a box with butterflies, two boxes with beetles and other insects, some samples, [...] [fruit], and a packet of seeds. As far as the zoological specimens are concerned, you will probably not find much that is unknown to you, or rare; but these are still all consignments that had not been intended for you originally, and Dr Mueller did not then know what you would like or what would be of value to you. The butterflies, Mueller thinks, should contain a few new ones; there are not many, but they come from the interior. Mueller sent them to me to identify, and if new, to have them described; you can do that just as well in Stuttgart, for Herrich-Schäfer<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">G. A. W. Herrich-Schäffer.</p>
               </note> lives near you if you have no-one in place there. I have enclosed the seeds as they are mostly of shrubs or foliage plants that are deserving of culture on account of their foliage alone. But you can see once again from this that Mueller is extremely active and communicative. In his last letter to me of 12 May<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Only a copy made by Sonder of an enclosure sent by M with this letter survives, together with a sketch of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Casuarius Johnsonii</seg> also enclosed by M with his letter; see M to W. Sonder, 13 May 1867.</p>
               </note> he writes, that he intends to send another case in June, containing freshwater and land shells—Dr Cox is writing a book on them at present<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Dr James Cox; see Cox (1868).</p>
               </note>—further a collection of correctly named skulls of birds. He will no longer send his fish to Agassiz, Dumeril? and others; he thinks quite a few new ones should turn up among the fish, he has given his collector on the north coast alcohol for these animals, lizards, etc. Count Castelnau has picked out the best specimens from his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Coleoptera</seg> for years, this gentleman is in the consulate there. The next consignment will bring a specimen of an <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argonauta</seg> that Dr Mueller and other naturalists in Melbourne think to be new. You will find on the enclosed sheet, what he has written about it. He also sent me a sketch of the new Cassowary, which I enclose as well.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to Sonder, 13 May 1867, and also B66.12.02.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mueller's letter is just as I had expected, he agrees fully with my propositions. I had to inform him—as you will agree—of the news from the foreign government that assured him of the title of Baron.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Denmark; see Sonder to Krauss, 16 March 1867 (in this edition as M67-03-16).</p>
               </note> However, though he was very flattered by this, he did think he was a German, and would rather see his materials in his dear fatherland. He also mentioned that he will endow the foundation and wants my opinion on the details for it; he wants still to be respected later on, even when he is no longer alive. He does have his ambitions, but then, without them, he would have achieved nothing; but he is so grateful, such as one rarely finds any more. You once asked after his titles, the new title page of the 5th volume of his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytograph. Australas.</seg> enumerates them. I believe that you will gladden his heart with the Order of the Crown of Württemberg and the personal nobility that comes with it, and that you will then have captured him for always. He will probably not be inferior to Ludwig,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Baron Karl von Ludwig, a dealer in natural history objects in Capetown, South Africa, who received the Crown Order for supplying the Natural History Museum in Stuttgart with large quantities of specimens, especially of the large African animals.</p>
               </note> and if you take into account that Mueller is not so blessed with fortune, the latter surely does not deserve less recognition. As his standing there increases more and more with decorations from abroad, he will be able to achieve ever more. He writes again of the many letters from Keferstein, Wöhler, from Berlin, Paris, etc.; and the Italian naturalist who is visiting there with the frigate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Magenta</seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">Enrico Giglioli, who travelled on the Italian Navy frigate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Magenta</seg>, in Melbourne from 4 to 25 May 1867.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>has taken on board a lot of beautiful things, also a lot of trunks of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Alsophila">Alsophila</name>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Both tree-ferns.</p>
               </note> But enough of this. The main thing is that you now know where you stand with Dr Mueller. Meanwhile he has asked me, to pass on to you his kind regards.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If your health was affected, you were certainly better off going to Switzerland rather than travelling to Paris, from where all acquaintances are returning worn out and tired.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The 1867 Exposition universelle was in full swing in Paris at this time.</p>
               </note> I shall hope that the benefit of your journey will be long-lasting.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With sincere regards</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alsophila">Alsophila</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
