<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Neuenwall ¶ Hamburg, 9 May 1867. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ Absent on business for some time, and after my return constantly kept busy, I was prevented from replying sooner to your friendly letter of 19 M...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M67-05-09-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M67.05.09</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Neuenwall ¶ Hamburg, 9 May 1867. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ Absent on business for some time, and after my return constantly kept busy, I was prevented from replying sooner to your friendly letter of 19 M...</title>
               <date when="1867-05-09">1867-05-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M67-05-09-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Neuenwall ¶ Hamburg, 9 May 1867. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ Absent on business for some time, and after my return constantly kept busy, I was prevented from replying sooner to your friendly letter of 19 M...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M67.05.09</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Krauss: 'No 2. | d. 13/18 geantw. | d 20. Juni wegen der Sammlung geschrieben.' [No 2. Replied 13/18. Written 20 June [1867] concerning the collections.]</p>
               </note>Neuenwall</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg d 9 Mai 1867</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Herr Professor</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Längere Zeit in Geschäften abwesend, und nach meiner Rückkehr beständig in Thätigkeit gehalten, bin ich verhindert gewesen, Ihren freundlichen Brief vom 19 März früher zu beantworten. Ich habe mit der letzten Post an Dr Müller geschrieben und ihm von unserer Correspondenz erzählt. Vor einigen Tagen traf auch wieder eine Kiste mit Kästchen voll australischer Orchideenknollen für verschiedene botanische Gärten an, die ich in der nächsten Zeit weiter zu befördern habe, die auch gewiss Interesse erregen werden, da man diese niedlichen Gewächse in Europäischen Gärten bisher nicht kannte. Ein Kasten voll australischer Schmetterlinge ist leider wegen schlechter Verpackung unbrauchbar geworden, zwei kleine Kisten mit Käfern sind aber schön erhalten u sind für Sie zurückgestellt. Sie fragen nach Dr Müller's Herkunft und Lebenslauf, worauf ich Ihnen genau antworten kann. Müller's Vater wohnte in Rostock, wo er eine kleine Anstellung erhalten hatte, nachdem er 1814 die Feldzüge mitgemacht. Nach seinem Tode kam Müller's Mutter mit den kleinen Kindern nach Tönning im Schleswig'schen, wo der Oncle sich derselben annahm u die Kinder erziehen liess. Unser Ferdinand, der schon von Kind an eine Vorliebe für Naturwissenschaft gezeigt, wurde Apotheker, ging, nachdem er seine Lehrzeit in Husum beendet, nach Kiel, studirte daselbst zuerst Pharmacie, dann Medicin, hauptsächlich aber Naturwissenschaften u siedelte vor 20 Jahren nach Südaustralien (Adelaide) über. Eigentlich wollte er mit seinen beiden von der Schwindsucht leidenden Schwestern nach Madeira gehen, ich überredete ihn aber zur Reise nach Australien, weil ein einjähriger Aufenthalt auf Madeira seine und seiner Schwestern Vermögen aufgezehrt haben würde, u weil auch Australien den Geschwistern so wie ihm selbst Gelegenheit geben würde, in dem wärmeren gesunden Klima zu bleiben. Ich bin also die Veranlassung, dass Müller nach Australien gekommen ist, die grösste Genugthuung habe ich durch diesen Rath aber darin gefunden, dass er u seine Schwestern vollkommen gesund wurden, Letztere verheiratheten sich bald u glücklich. Dem Bruder wollte es Anfangs leider gar nicht glücken, mit der ärztl. Praxis war es nichts, die Apothekerei musste wieder hervorgezogen werden wozu ihm von hier aus Arzneien geschickt wurden. Er sammelte eifrig u sandte Pflanzen etc, die ich versilberte, bis die Goldsucherei auch ihn ergriff u ihn nach Melbourne u weiter führte. Aber auch darin hatte er kein Glück, so dass er in Melbourne genöthigt war alle Anstrengungen zu machen um das Leben zu fristen. Einige Subsidien aus Europa hielten ihn aufrecht, bis der <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Zufall</hi>
               </seg> ihn mit dem damaligen Gouverneur Latrobe zusammenführte, der ihn botanisiren sah. Da sich der Gouv. selbst für Botanik interessirte, war bald die Bekanntschaft gemacht. Müller's eminentes Talent, das jedem einleuchtete, der ihn einmal gesehen u gesprochen, kam zur Geltung, er wurde ausgeschickt, entferntere Gegenden auf ihre Culturfähigkeit zu untersuchen, übernahm die Höhenbestimmungen der Berge u legte solche Berichte vor, die seine sofortige Anstellung als Government Botanist zu Folge hatten. Er machte bald darauf die grosse Expedition Gregory's von der Ostküste nach der Westküste Australiens mit, die 1½ Jahre [dauerte], kehrte dann aber in seine frühere Stellung in Melbourne zurück, wo er die Anlage des botanischen u zoologischen Gartens übernahm, für welche Institute er gegenwärtig Director ist u in welchem die Regierung ihm ein schönes Wohnhaus gebaut hat. Nachdem die Universität gegründet, ist ihm auch darin ein Platz als [Lehrer] eingeräumt. Wegen seiner ganz ungewöhnlichen Thätigkeit ist ihm auch von Seiten der sonst sehr neidischen Engländer Anerkennung zu Theil geworden; in Australien steht er aber an der Spitze aller gemeinnützigen Unternehmungen, er sinnt immer, wie er seinem neuen Vaterlande nützlich werden kann. So hat er zu der in den verflossenen Monaten stattgefundenen Industrieausstellung alle Erzeugnisse des Pflanzenreichs zusammengebracht u in seinem Laboratorium ätherische Öle u.s.w. aus den Myrtaceen, sowie sehr gutes Papier aus Gräsern u Baumrinden herstellen lassen. Obgleich in Zoologie wohlbewandert, ist seine Hauptthätigkeit doch am meisten der Botanik zugewendet gewesen, worin er für Australien viel geleistet hat u gegenwärtig mit Bentham zusammen den 3ten Band der Flora australiensis veröffentlicht hat. So wie ich nun diese Arbeiten vielleicht genauer kenne, als irgend jemand in Europa u sie demnach schätze, ebenso sehr schätze ich aber auch seine ungewöhnliche Freigebigkeit in Mittheilung von naturhistorischen Gegenständen zu wissenschaftlichen Zwecken. Ich will nicht wiederholen was ich Ihnen in meinem ersten Briefe über das Bestreben, solche Mittheilungen an einem Platze in Deutschland zu concentriren sagte. Uneigennützig in hohem Grade ist Dr Müller, unter uns gesagt aber doch nicht unempfindlich gegen Beweise von Anerkennung. Ich glaube, dass es ihn doch nicht wenig ehren würde, wenn Ihr König ihm seinen Kronorden zu verleihen sich veranlasst fühlen dürfte, weil das kleine damit verbundene Wörtchen etwas anderes ist als die blosse Decoration, so ehrend diese auch sonst ist. Ich habe in meinen letzten beiden Briefen schon darauf hingearbeitet, dass M. den ausser-deutschen Barontitel aufgiebt u zweifele ich nicht im Geringsten, dass er mit mir übereinstimmen werde. In den nächsten Tagen werde ich Ihnen ein Paket mit von Dr Müller herausgegebenen Drucksachen übersenden, die Sie vielleicht als Einleitung benützen können. Schreiben Sie uns dann, ob ich sogleich die Kisten mit Thieren etc absenden soll u wie sie addressirt werden müssen. Haben Sie einen Königl. Garten, wohin die beiden baumartigen Farren kommen können. Da ich dem hiesigen bot. Garten, der jetzt keinen Inspector hat, diese werthvollen Stämme nicht anvertrauen möchte, habe ich sie nach Herrenhausen an Wendland gesandt, der sie bis zu meiner Disposition aufgewahrt, wofür ich ihm ein drittes Ex. geschenkt habe. Die Stämme sind nach meiner Meinung über 100 Jahre alt. Die Wedel dieser Dicksonia antarctica sollen 12-14 Fuss lang werden. — Da Dr Müller jetzt kaum 40 Jahre alt ist, hat er noch Zeit genug, Ihr Museum zu versorgen, und wenn auch in Anzahll geringer als das productive Südafrika, so dürfte Neuholland Ihnen doch an Eigenthümlichkeiten vielleicht ebensoviel bieten. Gebe der Himmel, dass wir nun Frieden behalten, sonst wird die Wissenschaft für lange Zeit wieder einen Stoss erhalten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit der Bitte, meine verzögerte Antwort nicht übel zu nehmen, grüsst sie freundlichst</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Neuenwall</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder's address in Hamburg.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 9 May 1867.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Absent on business for some time, and after my return constantly kept busy, I was prevented from replying sooner to your friendly letter of 19 March.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> I have written to Dr Mueller with the last mail and told him of our correspondence. A few days ago another case arrived with little boxes filled with Australian orchid tubers for various botanic Gardens, which I shall have to forward in the coming days, and which are sure to excite interest, as these pretty plants have been unknown so far in European gardens. A box filled with Australian butterflies has sadly been rendered useless due to bad packing, but two small boxes with beetles are beautifully preserved and have been put aside for you. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You ask after Dr Mueller's provenance and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">curriculum vitae</seg>, and I can answer that for you in detail. Mueller's father lived in Rostock, where he had received a minor position, after he had taken part in the 1814 campaigns. After his death Mueller's mother came to Tönning in Schleswig with her little children, where the uncle<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ferdinand Mertens.</p>
               </note> took care of them and had the children educated. Our Ferdinand, who showed a predilection for natural history from early childhood, became an apothecary, then, after he had completed his apprenticeship in Husum, he went to Kiel, studied there at first pharmacy, then medicine, but predominantly the natural sciences, and 20 years ago he migrated to South Australia (Adelaide). Initially he had intended to go to Madeira with his two sisters, who were suffering from tuberculosis,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clara Müller is not known to have been suffering from tuberculosis, only Bertha.</p>
               </note> but I talked him into a voyage to Australia, because one year spent in Madeira would have eaten up his and his sisters' inheritance, and also because Australia would give him and his sisters the opportunity to remain in the warmer, healthy climate. So I am the cause, that Mueller came to Australia, and the greatest satisfaction from this advice I have found in this, that he and his sisters gained complete health.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha died of tuberculosis in 1861.</p>
               </note> The brother had no luck in the beginning, nothing came of the medical practice, he had to get back to pharmacy, for which medicines were sent to him from here. He collected assiduously and sent plants, which I turned into money, until he, too, was gripped by the gold fever, leading him to Melbourne and beyond. A few subsidies from Europe kept him going, until <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">pure chance</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had, however, carried with him from SA a letter of introduction to La Trobe; see F. Dutton to C. La Trobe, 11 August 1852 (in this edition as M52-08-11).</p>
               </note> brought him together with the then Governor La Trobe, who saw him botanizing. As the Governor himself was interested in botany, an acquaintance was soon established. Mueller's eminent talents, that were evident to anyone, who had just seen or spoken to him once, came to his aid, he was sent out to assess distant areas for their suitability for cultivation, then took over the triangulation to measure the heights of the mountains, and he presented such reports, that they brought him the immediate employment as Government botanist.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was appointed Government botanist first, then determined the altitude of several mountains while on field trips in the Victorian alps, and after that presented his reports.</p>
               </note> Soon afterwards he took part in Gregory's great expedition from the east coast to the west coast of Australia,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6. The expedition in fact went by sea to the Victoria River on the north coast of Australia before pushing south and then south-west into the interior of the continent without ever reaching the west coast. After returning to the base at the Victoria River, Gregory and a small party, including M, travelled eastwards and then south, reaching the east coast at Brisbane, while the rest of the expedition returned by sea to Sydney.</p>
               </note> which took a year and a half, but then he returned to his former position in Melbourne, where he accepted the establishment of the botanic and zoological Gardens and is at present Director of these institutes, where the Government built him a beautiful house. After the founding of the university he was also given a place there as lecturer.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was never a lecturer at the University.</p>
               </note> Because of his quite extraordinary industry he even received recognition from the otherwise very envious Englishmen; in Australia he is at the forefront of every philanthropic enterprise, he is always looking for new ways, in which to be of use to his new homeland. Thus he has brought together all the products of the vegetable kingdom for the industrial exhibition,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Intercolonial Exhibition of Australasia, Melbourne, 1866-7.</p>
               </note> that took place during the past few months, and has had essential oils etc. produced in his laboratory from the Myrtaceae, as well as very good paper from grasses and tree barks.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See B67.13.02.</p>
               </note> Although he is well-versed in zoology, his main activity has been mostly in the field of botany, where he has achieved much for Australia, and he has just published the 3rd volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg> together with Bentham. Now I know all these works of his probably better than anyone else in Europe, and appreciate them accordingly, but I also appreciate just as much his extraordinary liberality in the communication of natural history objects for scientific purposes. I do not want to repeat, what I told you in my first letter<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See W. Sonder to F. Krauss, 19 February 1867 (in this edition as M67-02-19).</p>
               </note> about my efforts, to concentrate such communications in one place in Germany. Dr Mueller is extremely altruistic, but in confidence between us, is not insensitive to demonstrations of recognition. I believe, that it would honour him considerably, if your King would feel himself inclined to bestow on him his Order of the Crown, as that little word connected with it<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The 'von' before Mueller.</p>
               </note> is something different than a mere decoration, as honouring as that might otherwise be. I have already worked towards it in my last two letters, that Mueller should forget about the non-German title of Baron, and I have not the least doubt, that he will agree with me. In the next few days I am going to send you a parcel with publications by Dr Mueller, which you might perhaps use as an introduction. And then write to us, whether I should dispatch the cases with animals etc. immediately, and how they should be addressed. Do you have any Royal Gardens, where the two tree-like ferns could go? As I do not want to entrust these valuable specimens to our botanic Gardens here, where there is no inspector now, I have sent them to Herrenhausen to Wendland, who has accommodated them until I make other arrangements for them, and in return I have given him a third specimen. In my opinion these trees are more than 100 years old. The fronds of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia antarctica</seg> are said to grow to 12-14 feet long. — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As Dr Mueller is now only just over 40 years old, he has enough time left, to provide for your Museum, and even though less in numbers than the productive South Africa, New Holland may perhaps have just as much to offer to you in unique specimens. May Heaven grant, that we maintain peace, otherwise science will once more receive a blow that will have long-lasting effects. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Begging, that you will not take offence at my delayed reply, I send my best regards.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
