<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the King ¶ Report of the Minister  ¶ of Church and Educational Affairs ¶ respecting gifts for the Natural History Cabinet ¶ Stuttgart, 13 December 1867....</title>
            <author>Ludwig von Golther</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M67-12-13-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Bestand E 16a Bü. 51, Hauptstaatsarchiv, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M67.12.13</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ludwig von Golther</author>
               <title>To the King ¶ Report of the Minister  ¶ of Church and Educational Affairs ¶ respecting gifts for the Natural History Cabinet ¶ Stuttgart, 13 December 1867....</title>
               <date when="1867-12-13">1867-12-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M67-12-13-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
               <term>Times</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>form text</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Karl I, King of Württemberg</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">To the King ¶ Report of the Minister  ¶ of Church and Educational Affairs ¶ respecting gifts for the Natural History Cabinet ¶ Stuttgart, 13 December 1867....</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M67.12.13</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Ludwig von Golther to Karl I, King of Württemberg</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Bestand E 16a Bü. 51, Hauptstaatsarchiv, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This copy is written by an amanuensis. A second draft copy in an unknown hand is also attached to this file (E 56 Bü. 28, Hauptstaatsarchiv Stuttgart).</p>
               </note>
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times; ">An den König</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times; ">Anbringen</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times; ">des Ministers</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times; ">des Kirchen- und Schul-Wesens</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Printed and decorated letterhead.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">betreffend</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Geschenke für das Naturalienkabinet</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Stuttgart den 13. Dez.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Dez. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">above</seg> September <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted</seg>.</p>
               </note> 1867.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nachdem schon im Jahr 1860 dem Naturalienkabinet dahier von Dr. Ferdinand Müller, Direktor des zoologischen und botanischen Gartens in Melbourne in Australien, eine Schenkung von Naturalien zugegangen, hat Oberstudienrath Krauss in neuerer Zeit durch den Botaniker Dr. Sonder in Hamburg, einem sehr intimen Freund <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">An unfamiliar symbol, M67-12-13_image01.jpg appears here and on several other occasions in this letter, each time immediately preceding a person's surname. It is most likely a stylized p, standing for praedictus, i.e. before-mentioned.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Müllers, erfahren, dass letzterer, welcher seither beinahe alle naturhistorische Museen Europas in freigiebigster Weise mit Schenkungen von Naturalien bedacht hatte, nunmehr beabsichtige, künftig <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg> seine Sendungen von Naturalien als Schenkung in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Einem</hi>
               </seg> deutschen Museum zu <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">konzentriren</hi>
               </seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Krauss ergriff diese Gelegenheit mit aller Energie und veranlasste sofort den Dr. Sonder, es bei Dr. Müller zu vermitteln, dass dieser seine Schenkungen dem <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hiesigen</hi>
               </seg> Naturalienkabinet zuwenden möchte. Die hierüber eingeleiteten Verhandlungen hatten den besten Erfolg, indem Dr. Sonder in seinem neuesten Briefe an Krauss die Zustimmung Müllers zu allen seinen Anträgen zu Gunsten der diesseitigen Anstalt meldete. Hienach ist, wie Krauss bemerkt, zu hoffen, dass das Naturalienkabinet, wie vor 30. Jahren durch die Freigebigkeit des Freiherrn von Ludwig die südafrikanische, so nun bald auch durch Dr. Ferdinand Müller die höchst eigenthümliche Fauna und Flora Neuhollands in hervorragender Reichhaltigkeit vertreten haben werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine weitere, sehr schätzbare Zusage Müllers, die nunmehr auch Württemberg zu gut käme, bezieht sich auf die Stiftung eines ansehnlichen Reisestipendiums für einen jungen Naturforscher zur Ausbildung in naturwissenschaftlichen Fächern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Noch ehe die zustimmende Antwort von Dr. Müller eingetroffen, schickte Dr. Sonder im Juni dieses Jahres alle bei ihm vorräthig liegenden Müllerschen Nauralien hieher, sodann im August dieses Jahrs diejenigen, welche in der Zwischenzeit aus Neuholland angekommen waren, und in den letzten Tagen kam hiezu eine dritte Schenkung.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Diese Sendungen enthielten theils Bücher, namentlich einige von Dr. Müller selbst verfasste naturwissenschaftliche Schriften, theils Waffen und Geräthschaften der Neuholländer, hauptsächlich aber Naturalien aller Art (Säugethiere, Vögel, Insekten, Conchylien, botanische und mineralogische Gegenstände und anderes mehr), darunter mehrere sehr wilkommene Objekte, die längst auf der diesseitigen Desideratenliste vermerkt waren. Die eingesendeten Bücher wurden sofort in die Bibliothek, die Waffen und Geräthe in die unter der Aufsicht des Oberstudienraths v. Stälin stehende Sammlungen abgegeben, die Naturalien dem Naturalienkabinet einverleibt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Gesamtwerth aller von Dr. Ferdinand Müller bis jetzt erhaltenen Schenkungen darf nach der Angabe des Oberstudienraths Krauss wohl auf 1200 f. angeschlagen werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn nun neben diesen bereits gemachten Schenkungen im Werth von wenigsten 1200 f. in Berücksichtigung zu nehmen ist, dass Dr. Müller, kaum 40. Jahre alt, den diesseitigen Instituten noch manchen Schatz von Sammlungsstücken zum Geschenk machen wird, und dass sein Anerbieten ein glänzendes genannt werden kann, so hat Krauss den Antrag stellen zu sollen geglaubt, dass Müller durch die Verleihung des Ritterkreuzes des Kronordens ausgezeichnet werden möchte, worin derselbe, nach Andeutungen des Dr. Sonder in Hamburg, wohl eine ihn sehr ehrende Auszeichnung erblicken würde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. Müller ist geboren in Rostock, erlernte in Husum die Pharmazie, studirte in Kiel Medizin und Naturwissenschaften und reiste vor 20 Jahren nach Australien, wo er zuerst bald als Arzt, bald als Apotheker sein Glück versuchte, später in Anerkennung seiner naturwissenschaftlichen Kenntnisse als Governements Botanist angestellt wurde, als solcher viele Reisen machte, und auch an einer grossen Expedition von der Ost- nach der Westküste Neuhollands Theil nahm. In Melbourne wurde er von der Regierung mit der Anlage des botanischen und zoologischen Gartens betraut und ihm daselbst nach Gründung der Universität eine Lehrstelle übertragen. Als Direktor des sehr ausgedehnten Gartens ist Müller ausserordentlich thätig, betheiligt sich ausserdem an allen gemeinnützigen Unternehmungen und hat sich in der litterarischen Welt durch Herausgabe vieler trefflichen Abhandlungen und Werke, welche er zum Theil schon der Königlichen Bibliothek zum Geschenk gemacht hat, einen so hochgeschätzten Namen erworben, dass ihn die meisten wissenschaftlichen Institute durch Aufnahme als Mitglied ehrten. Wie ihn die Wissenschaft hoch achtet, so wurde er von den Regierungen, deren naturhistorische Museen er bereicherte, mit ehrenvollen Auszeichnungen bedacht: er besitzt Orden von Dänemark, Frankreich, Österreich, Italien, Preussen, Mecklenburg, Sachsen-Gotha.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Einer Mittheilung des Dr. Sonder in Hamburg zufolge soll ihm eine ausserdeutsche Regierung neuerdings den <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Baron</hi>
               </seg>titel zugesichert haben, wenn er seine Naturaliensendungen und das beabsichtigte Stipendium <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ihr</hi>
               </seg> zuwende. Müller hat aber als Deutscher das Anerbieten abgelehnt und sich — wie bemerkt — entschlossen, alle seine Zuwendungen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hieher</hi>
               </seg> zu machen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass Dr. Müller sowohl für seine bisherigen Schenkungen, als auch für seinen Entschluss wegen künftiger Zusendungen, wodurch dem hiesigen Naturalienkabinet eine ausserordentlich reiche Quelle der interessantesten Bereicherungen eröffnet ist, eine Anerkennung verdiene, und dass hiefür die Verleihung des Ritterkreuzes des Kronordens als angemessen erscheint, werde ich nach dem Bisherigen nicht erst näher zu begründen haben. Im Weiteren würde ich aber nicht nur an den Dr. Sonder in Hamburg, welcher die bisherigen Sammlungen Müllers vermittelt und namentlich den von letzterem zu Gunsten der diesseitigen Sammlung gefassten Entschluss herbeigeführt hat, ein verbindliches Danksagungsschreiben richten, sondern auch für angezeigt halten, dass dem Oberstudienrath Krauss, dessen energischen und umsichtigen Bemühungen dieser ganze Erfolg zu verdanken ist, das Wohlgefallen und den Dank Euer Königlichen Majestät zu erkennen gegeben würde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dem Bisherigen zufolge erlaube ich mir den unterthänigsten Antrag:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Euer Königliche Majestät möchten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1., dem Dr. Müller, Direktor des botanischen und zoologischen Gartens in Melbourne (Australien) das Ritterkreuz Höchst Ihres Kronordens gnädigst verleihen und</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2., mich ermächtigen, dem Dr. Sonder in Hamburg für seine Vermittlung und dem Oberstudienrath Krauss hier für seine Bemühungen um Bereicherung des Königlichen Naturalienkabinets Höchst Ihr Wohlgefallen und Ihren gnädigsten Dank erkennen geben zu dürfen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ehrfurchtvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Golther</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To the King</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Report of the Minister </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">of Church and Educational Affairs</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">respecting gifts for the Natural History Cabinet</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgart, 13 December 1867.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After a donation of natural history objects from Dr Ferdinand Mueller, director of the zoological and botanical garden in Melbourne, Australia, came to hand to the Natural History Cabinet here as early as 1860, Oberstudienrath Krauss ascertained recently through the botanist Dr Sonder in Hamburg, a very close friend of Mueller, that the latter, who since then had provided nearly all the natural history museums of Europe most liberally with donations of natural history objects, henceforth intends to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">concentrate</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> his shipments of natural history objects in the future as a donation in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg> German museum.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Krauss grasped this opportunity with all energy and immediately induced Dr Sonder to intercede with Dr Mueller that the latter might allocate his donations to the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">local</hi>
               </seg> natural history cabinet. The negotiations initiated about this had the best success, as Dr Sonder in his latest letter to Krauss reported Mueller's assent to all his proposals in favour of our institution. Accordingly it is to be hoped, as Krauss remarks, that the natural history cabinet will now soon have the highly distinctive fauna and flora of New Holland also represented in exceeding richness through Dr Mueller, like the South African 30 years ago through the generousity of Baron von Ludwig.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ludwig had been created a Baron in response to his donation of South African material to the Stuttgart museum.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A further, very estimable commitment of Mueller, which will now also benefit Württemberg, has reference to the foundation of a sizeable travel grant for a young naturalist for training in natural history disciplines.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Even before the consenting answer of Dr Mueller arrived, Dr Sonder sent here all the Mueller natural history objects lying at hand with him in June of this year, then in August of this year those items that had arrived from New Holland in the meantime, and in the last few days a third donation came in addition to that.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>These donations contained partly books, particularly some of the natural history papers written by Mueller himself, partly weapons and implements of the New Hollanders, but mainly natural history objects of all kinds (mammals, birds, insects, shells, botanical and mineralogical objects and many other things), among them several very welcome objects that were long ago noted on our list of desiderata. The books sent were immediately added to the library, the weapons and implements delivered to the collections under the custody of Oberstudienrath von Stälin, the natural history objects incorporated into the natural history cabinet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The total value of all the donations received from Dr Ferdinand Mueller so far may be estimated according to the statement of Oberstudenrath Krauss probably at 1200 florins.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If it is now taken into consideration, together with these donations already made in value of at least 1200 florins, that Dr Mueller, scarcely 40 years old, will still make donations of many a treasure of collection items to our institutions, and that his offer can be called a splendid one, Krauss thought to put the proposition that Mueller might be honoured by the awarding of the Knight Cross of the Crown Order, in which he would probably perceive a decoration that honoured him very much according to the suggestions of Dr Sonder in Hamburg.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Mueller was born in Rostock, learned pharmacy in Husum, studied medicine and natural sciences in Kiel and 20 years ago travelled to Australia, where initially he tried his luck alternately as a physician and as pharmacist, later was appointed as Government Botanist in recognition of his knowledge of natural history. As such he made many journeys and also took part in a large expedition from the east to the west coast of New Holland.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The North Australian Exploring Expedition, at the end of which a party under Augustus Gregory and including M travelled overland from the Victoria River, on Australia's north coast, to Moreton Bay in Qld.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> In Melbourne he was entrusted by the government with the laying out of the botanical and zoological garden and after the foundation of the university was appointed to a teaching position there.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M never held a teaching position at the University of Melbourne but was examiner in Materia Medica for the University's medical degree.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> As director of the very extensive garden, Mueller is exraordinarily active, in addition participates in all social eneterprises and in the literary world has acquired such a much-valued name through the publicaton of many excellent papers and works, which he has already in part donated to the Royal Library, that the majority of scientific institutes have honoured him by admission as a member. As science regarded him highly, so he was endowed with noble awards by the governments whose museums he enriched. He posseses orders from Denmark, France, Austria, Italy, Prussia, Mecklenburg and Sachsen-Gotha.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>According to a communication of Dr Sonder in Hamburg, a non-German government<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Denmark; see W. Sonder to F. Krauss, 16 March 1867 (in this edition as M67-03-16), and notes thereto.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> recently is said to have assured him the title of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Baron</hi>
               </seg>, if he allocated his natural history consignments and the intended grant to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">them</hi>
               </seg>. Mueller, however, as a German declined the offer and, as remarked, decided to make all his contributions <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">here</hi>
               </seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That Dr Mueller both for his previous donations and for his decision regarding future consignments, whereby an extraordinarily rich source of the most interesting enrichments is opened to the the local natural history cabinet, deserves recognition and that for this purpose the confering of the Knight Cross of the Crown Order seems appropriate, I will just not have to justify in greater detail after what has come so far. Furthermore, however, I would not only address a gracious letter of thanks to Dr Sonder in Hamburg, who facilitated the previous collections of Dr Mueller and especially has brought about the decision of the latter expressed in favour of our collection, but also regard as indicated that the pleasure and the thanks of Your Royal Majesty should be given to recognise Oberstudienrath Krauss, to whose energetic and careful endeavours this entire success is due.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>According to the above I permit myself the most humble proposal:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your Royal Majesty might </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">graciously confer the Knight Cross of your Crown Order on Dr Mueller, director of the botanical and zoological garden in Melbourne (Australia) and</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">authorize me to give recognition to Dr Sonder in Hamburg for his facilitation and to give your pleasure and your gracious thanks to Oberstudienrath Kraus here for his endevours to enrich the Royal Natural History Cabinet.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The King promptly approved these recommendations; see Karl I, King of W</seg>ürttemberg, to L. von Golther, 20 December 1867 (in this edition as M67-12-20).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Golther</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
