<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ You probably had reason to expect a letter from me. At the time you had perhaps not seen Director Schmidt, to whom I wrote before Pentecost, otherwise you would have known that I had...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M68-07-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M68.07.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ You probably had reason to expect a letter from me. At the time you had perhaps not seen Director Schmidt, to whom I wrote before Pentecost, otherwise you would have known that I had...</title>
               <date when="1868-07-28">1868-07-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M68-07-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Macrozamia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ You probably had reason to expect a letter from me. At the time you had perhaps not seen Director Schmidt, to whom I wrote before Pentecost, otherwise you would have known that I had...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M68.07.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotated by Krauss 'R. d. 9. Juli | [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>] 19. Aug.' [Received 9 July, [replied] 19 Aug.]. Letter not found. Krauss's annotation must be in error, and should probably read 'R. d. 9. Aug.' [Received 9 August], since Sonder's letter was not written until 28 July.</p>
               </note>Hamburg 28 Juli 68</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Freund,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie hatten wohl Ursache auf einen Brief von mir zu warten, Herr Director Schmidt, dem ich vor Pfingsten schrieb, hat Sie damals vielleicht nicht gesehen, sonst würden Sie gewusst haben, dass ich verreist war. Ich hatte zweierlei Gründe, meinen Vorsatz aufzuschieben, erstens sitze ich bis über die Ohren in einer Arbeit, die mich fast krank gemacht hat, weil ich die Nächte dabei zu Hülfe nehmen musste. Es ward mir neulich von Seiten des Senates der Auftrag, nachdem es beschlossen ist, dass am 1. Juli die Preuss. Pharmacopoa bei uns gesetzlich eingeführt werden soll, bis zu diesem Zeitpunkt einen Nachtrag dazu, der die in Hamburg gebräuchlichen Arzneimittel enthält auszuarbeiten, ausserdem die Apothekertaxe in das mit dem 1. Juli hier ebenfalls in Gebrauch kommende Grammengewicht umzuändern. Der Auftrag wurde mir erst im Februar u so können Sie berechnen, wie viele Zeit mir für aussergeschäftliche Dinge übrig blieb.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hierzu gesellte sich nun der zweite Grund meines Schweigens, der mir trübe Stunden verursacht hat u der war folgender: der Brief mit dem Wechsel von Dr Müller traf gegen Ende April hier richtig ein; ich übergab ihn sofort einem verwandten Kaufmanne zum eincassiren, und denken Sie sich meinen Schrecken den zweiten Tag darauf erhalte ich die Nachricht, dass der Wechsel verloren gegangen sei. Es musste sofort an die Bank in London telegraphirt werden; glücklicher Weise war der Wechsel erst nach 1 Monat Sicht zahlbar u da ich für den ganzen Werth sogleich Bürgschaft stellen liess, kam die Nachricht zurück, dass der Wechsel nur auf die Secunda oder auf meine [Ordre] ausgezahlt werden solle. Die Secunda ist gekommen u darauf auch aus London die Nachricht, dass bei Verfall der Betrag an mich remittirt werde. Im Laufe des nächsten Monats hoffe ich in den Besitz des Geldes zu gelangen, u werde dasselbe dann nach Stuttgart senden. Ich denke es werden wohl 2000 Thaler voll werden, u diese Summe dachte ich Ihnen zu übermitteln, höre aber nun, dass Sie verreisen wollen, u bitte deshalb mich wissen zu lassen, an wen ich nun addressiren soll. Mein Neffe wird mir dann schon Anleitung geben, ob ich den Betrag in einem Wechsel oder in Papiergeld übersende.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Denken Sie sich, dass sich die Prima neulich wieder angefunden hat. Mein Neffe, dem ich den Wechsel auf seinem Landgute übergab, hat ihn in der Eile seiner Abfahrt nach der Stadt auf seinem Tische liegen lassen u erst gegen Abend auf dem Comptoir vermisst. Unterdess hat eins seiner neu eingetretenen Hausmädchen das Papier für ein Bild der Kinder gehalten, zerrissen u in den Papierkorb geworfen! Ende gut alles gut!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was die Stipendium-Angelegenheit betrifft, so dachte ich, Müller würde ausführlich an Sie darüber geschrieben haben. Mir hat er, wie Sie wissen, seinen Plan längst mitgetheilt aber auch nicht ausführlicher als Ihnen, das Uebrige uns beiden überlassend. Ich habe noch nicht daran gedacht, etwas niederzuschreiben, habe aufrichtig gesagt, auch keine Zeit dazu gehabt. Nachdem Müller seine Idee klar ausgesprochen, könnten Sie vielleicht passender dem Ministerium, das doch die Hauptverfügung über das Stipendium haben muss, bei dem Speciellen zu Hülfe kommen, besser als es mir, dem Ausländer zukömmt. — Das zweite Stipendium, oder eine zweite Geldsumme wird Müller zur Verfügung stellen wie er mir schreibt, wenn die dortigen Verhältnisse sich nur einigermassen günstiger stellen als es augenblicklich der Fall ist, er kann nicht zu seinem Geld kommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich werde in meinem nächsten Brief an Ihre Desiderate erinnern. Wahrscheinlich ist die längere Abwesenheit Müller's, dann der Besuch des Prinzen in Australien Schuld daran, dass er Ihre Wünsche nicht hat erfüllen können. Sie erhalten in der nächsten Woche eine bedeutende Kiste, die schon in meinem Hause steht, nur das ich die Pakete für Berlin, Wien, München u.s.w. zu entnehmen, den Rest aber Ihnen zuzustellen hatte. Ich werde heute oder morgen wohl die Geschichte in Ordnung bringen können u dann die Kiste auf der Bahn senden. Ich bin freilich noch immer im Zweifel, ob ich Ihnen alle die Vogelbälge schicken soll, da Sie einen Theil derselben schon einige Male erhielten; so kömmt es mir vor, obgleich ich sie nicht kenne. Ich dachte, man könnte sie an kleine Museen geben, die noch nichts von Australien besitzen, indess dazu habe ich das Recht nicht. Ein junges Krokodill aus Nordaustralien so wie ein drolliges rattenartiges Thier werden Ihnen Spass machen u vielleicht auch die Insekten u sonstiges Ungeziefer in Spiritus. Die Schädel der Eingeborenen sind aus den Grampians; mit den übrigen Knochen lässt sich vielleicht ein wildes Menschenkind künstlich herstellen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In seinem letzten Briefe schreibt Müller, dass er beschäftigt sei, eine neue Kiste zu packen, worin ein Fass mit Fischen u.s.w.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Herrn Director Schmidt habe ich keinen Brief erhalten, es freut mich durch Sie zu erfahren, dass er die <name key="Macrozamia">Macrozamia</name> empfangen hat. Diesen Stamm hat man hier allgemein bewundert, ein hiesiger Krösus wollte ihn durchaus nicht fahren lassen, da auf dem Continent kein zweiter existirt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Wiederersetzung der Fracht, wovon Sie erwähnen, ist nicht von mir, sondern von Herrn Direct. Schmidt selbst in Anregung gebracht, der in seinem vorigen Briefe auf Rückzahlung bestand. Ich habe ihm geschrieben, dass ich nicht wüsste, wie ich mich dabei zu verhalten habe, mir ist es gleich, wer die Unkosten zurückerstattet, habe ich 300 Thaler für Dr Müller ausgelegt, kann es mir auch auf einige Thaler mehr nicht ankommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich verdenke es Ihnen nicht, dass Sie wieder auf einige Wochen nach der Schweiz gehen, da Sie stets so guten Erfolg davon haben. Ich kann mich leider nicht auf mehrere Wochen frei machen, obgleich es bei mir auch Bedürfnis wäre. Kann ich eine kurze Zeit in ein Seebad gehen, so ist das wohl alles, was ich für dies Jahr zu erreichen im Stande bin, meiner Frau ist es auch nöthig, dass sie nach den letztjährigen Anstrengungen eine Kräftigung u Erholung erhalte. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoffentlich erhalte ich vor Ihrer Abreise noch eine Nachricht.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mir freundl. Gruss</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You probably had reason to expect a letter from me. At the time you had perhaps not seen Director Schmidt, to whom I wrote before Pentecost, otherwise you would have known that I had gone away. I had two different reasons to delay my intention. First, I am over my ears in work that has almost made me ill because I have to use the nights. Recently the Senate, after deciding that on 1 July the Prussian Pharmacopoeia will be officially introduced for us, gave me the task to work out a supplement to it that contains the medicaments in use in Hamburg up to this time. In addition to altering the pharmacy tax in which the gram weight likewise comes into use here on 1 July. The commission came to me only in February and so you can estimate how much time remained over for me for things other than business.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Joined with it now the second reason for my silence, which has caused me troubled hours, as follows. The letter with the draft from Dr Mueller arrived safely here towards the end of April. I immediately handed it over to a related businessman to cash and you can imagine my horror the second day after that when I received the news that the draft had got lost. The bank in London had to be telegraphed immediately. Fortunately the draft was only payable after one month's sight and because I immediately stood surety for the whole value, the news came back that the draft is only to be payable on the duplicate or on my order. The duplicate has arrived and also after that the news from London that the amount will be remitted to me on expiry. In the course of the next month I hope to be in possession of the money and will then send it to Stuttgart. I think it will probably amount to fully 2000 Thaler and I thought to transmit this sum to you, but now hear that you intend to go away and therefore request you to let me know to whom I should now address it. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>My nephew will then give me guidance whether I should send the amount in a draft or in paper money. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Can you imagine that the original has recently turned up again? My nephew, to whom I handed over the draft on his country property, left it on his table in the hurry of his departure for the city and only towards evening missed it at the office. Meanwhile one of his newly appointed housemaids, thinking the paper a children's picture, tore it up and threw it in the waste paper basket! All's well that ends well!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Concerning the affairs of the scholarship, I thought Mueller would have written to you in detail about it. As you know, he informed me of his plan long ago, but also not in detail as with you, leaving the rest up to us both. I have not yet thought to write anything down, have said honestly that I have had no time for it. Once Mueller expresses his idea clearly, you could perhaps more conveniently get the Ministry, which surely must have the principal disposal of the scholarship, to help better than me, an outsider. Mueller will put the second scholarship, or a second sum of money, for disposal, as he writes to me, once conditions there are only to some extent more favourable than is the case at present when he cannot get to his money.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In my next letter I will remind [him] of your desiderata. Probably Mueller's long absence<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M was ill and away from his office for several months during the second half of 1867.</p>
               </note> and then the visit of the Prince to Australia<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Queen Victoria’s second son, Prince Alfred, Duke of Edinburgh, visited Melbourne in November-December 1867.</p>
               </note> is to blame for his not being able to fulfil your wishes. In the next week you will receive an important crate, which is already in my house. I just have to take out the packets for Berlin, Vienna, Munich and so on, but I have to deliver the remainder to you. I will probably be able to sort out the business today or tomorrow and then send the crate on the train. Admittedly I am still in doubt whether I am to send you all the bird skins, because - so it would seem to me although I am not certain - you received part of them a few times already. I thought they could be given to small museums that still have nothing from Australia; however, I do not have the right to do this. A young crocodile from North Australia as well as a droll animal like a rat will give you some enjoyment, and perhaps also the insects and other vermin in spirit. The skulls of the Aborigines are from the Grampians.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> Perhaps a wild man can be made artificially with the remaining bones. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In his last letter Mueller wrote that he is occupied in packing a new crate in which there is cask with fishes and so on.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have not received a letter from Director Schmidt<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The director of the Stuttgart Museum was E. von Schmidlin.</p>
               </note>; it pleases me to learn through you that he has received the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Macrozamia">Macrozamia</name>
               </seg>. The trunk was generally admired here. A local Croesus<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Not identified.</p>
               </note> by no means wanted to allow it to travel, because a second does not exist on the Continent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The reimbursement of the freight that you mention was not suggested by me but by Director Schmidt himself, who urged repayment in his previous letter. I have written to him that I do not know how I have to go about it. It is all the same to me who refunds the expenses. I have paid out 300 Thalers for Dr Mueller. A few Thalers more also does not matter to me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not blame you that you will go to Switzerland again for some weeks, because you have always had a good outcome from it. Unfortunately I cannot make myself free for several weeks, although it would also be a desideratum for me. If I can go for a short time to a sea bath, that is probably all that I am in a position to achieve for this year. It is also necessary for my wife that she gets some invigoration and relaxation after the efforts of the last year.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope I shall receive some news before your departure.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With kind greeting</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Macrozamia">Macrozamia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
