<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg 6 Febr [18]69 ¶ Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ You certainly have looked out for a letter from me for some time already, which should have been in your hands long ago if it weren't for a severe cold chaini...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M69-02-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M69.02.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg 6 Febr [18]69 ¶ Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ You certainly have looked out for a letter from me for some time already, which should have been in your hands long ago if it weren't for a severe cold chaini...</title>
               <date when="1869-02-06">1869-02-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M69-02-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Balantium antarcticum</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/9c9ecf70-9027-490a-b26e-add18d163bf7">Dicksonia antarctica</term>
               <term>Macrozamia preissi</term>
               <term>Todea rivularis</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg 6 Febr [18]69 ¶ Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ You certainly have looked out for a letter from me for some time already, which should have been in your hands long ago if it weren't for a severe cold chaini...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M69.02.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand Krauss</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotated by Krauss 'geantw. d. 20 Fbr. 69 | wegen Todea [...]' [answered 20 February 1869, [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>] concerning <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea</seg>]. Letter not found.</p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 6 Febr 69</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Freund,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gewiss haben Sie schon lange nach einem Briefe von mir ausgesehen, der, ohne eine heftige Erkältung, die mich 14 Tage ans Zimmer fesselte, längst in Ihren Händen gewesen wäre. Die in den ersten Wochen des Januar in meinen Besitz gelangende grosse Kiste aus Australien musste unangerührt in meinem Keller stehen, bis ich am vergangenen Sonntag endlich von meinem Arzt die Erlaubnis erhielt, die Auspackung oder vielmehr Umpackung vorzunehmen. Nachdem ich nun die zahlreichen Pakete mit Sämereien für die botanischen Gärten und Drucksachen abgenommen, habe ich es für zweckmässig erachtet, Ihnen Ihren Antheil in zwei Kisten zu übermitteln. Die eine enthält eine Menge schöner Mineralien, ausser einigen andern hauptsächlich eine grosse Anzahl Kupfererze aus den neuen Gruben der Halbinsel York in Nordaustralien. Die Sammlung ist ebenso interessant als selten, es wird wohl noch kein Museum etwas davon besitzen. Mit den Doubletten werden Sie mehrere Museen bereichern können. Dann sind in derselben Kiste ein Kasten mit Fischhäuten, wovon ich nichts verstanden habe, ausserdem mehrere Pakete mit Seespongien u einer Anzahl Bücher u Drucksachen. Die zweite Kiste enthält ein grosses Bündel mit Vogelbälgen. Ob dieses Bündel, in braun Packpapier gewickelt aus Neuseeland ist? Das werden Sie bald aus dem Inhalt erkennen. Ich schliesse es daraus, dass Dr Mueller mir vor einiger Zeit schrieb, er erwarte eine Anzahl Vogelbälge aus Neuseeland. — Die übrigen loose beigepackten Vogelbälge sind aber aus Südaustralien, sie sehen besser aus als die früheren u mögen etwas Ihnen Erwünschtes enthalten. Der übrige Theil der Kiste ist mit Drucksachen u ein oder zwei kleinen Kisten mit Conchylien so wie mit einigen Schädeln erfüllt. Die Menschenschädel sind von einem jetzt völlig ausgestorbenen Stamme vom Richmondriver. — Prof. Keferstein wollte gerne einen davon haben, er mag sich aber an Sie wenden. Der Tiger oder Jaguarschädel aus Ostindien schein sehr schön zu sein. Welchem Thier der andere Schädel angehört, vermag ich nicht zu sagen. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun habe ich noch einige Hefte mit Australischen Ansichten (den Schluss derselben) von Eugene Guerard, wovon Sie schon einige erhielten, nebst einigen Photographien und eine ganze Anzahl Hefte des ornithologischen Werkes von Diggles, die ich mit der Post nachschicken werde, da sie nicht in die Kiste passten. Das eine Textblatt des ornitholog. Werkes hat einen kleinen Einriss, den es wahrscheinlich beim Öffnen der Kiste in England, wo man oft ganz liederlich mit den Sachen umgeht, erhalten; von Bedeutung ist es aber nicht. — Ich denke diese werthvolle Sendung wird Ihnen Freude machen, welches unserm Freunde in Australien sehr angenehm sein wird. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Einliegend finden Sie eine Liste von Fischen, die wahrscheinlich auf die voriges mal erhaltenen Fische sich bezieht. — Das ausgestopfte Crocodil welches Sie erhielten — ein junges Thier — war aus Nordaustralien — im Süden kommen sie nicht vor. — Wenn das Skelett des Ihnen im vergangenen Jahre gesandten Australiers mangelhaft war, so hoffe ich, wird das nun erfolgende besser sein. Ich habe keine zu dem ersteren fehlenden Knochen, ich freue mich immer wenn ich diese Art Sachen aus dem Hause los bin. — Die Macrozamia aus </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Westaustralien</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> heisst Macr. Preissii Miquel. Die <name key="Todea%20rivularis">Todea rivularis</name> sowie Dicksonia oder jetzt <name key="Balantium%20antarcticum">Balantium antarcticum</name> sind aus der Provinz Victoria. Ich bin sehr gespannt ob die Todea angekommen ist, es ist ein sehr werthvolles Stück. Wenn Ihrem Hofgärtner, dem ich Palmensamen besorgen werde, sehr daran liegt noch einen grossen Stamm von Dickson (Balant) antarctica zu erhalten, so will ich ihm einen besorgen. Ich habe einige zurückbehalten die ich bei einem hiesigen Gärtner eingesetzt habe, die ich aber zu der hier im Herbst stattfindenden grossen Ausstellung behalten möchte; nachher soll ich sie doch weiterschicken.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich mache unsern Freund immer auf Ihre speciellen Wünsche aufmerksam, er ist aber nicht immer Herr der Sache. Es lassen sich dort keine bestimmten Gegenstände kaufen, es giebt dort keine Händler für naturhistorische Gegenstände. Müller kauft sie wenn ein Reisender oder Binnenländer etwas nach Melbourne bringt, oder er bestellt sie u muss dann doch nehmen, was man ihm sendete. In den letzten Jahren sind keine Expeditionen gewesen, so wie die stattfinden, giebt es auch immer etwas Neues u Seltenes. Schütten Sie Ihr Herz nur gegen Müller aus, Sie können ihn Alles besser fragen als ich! Sie können seinen Vorzügen u seinen Leistungen doch dabei Gerechtigkeit widerfahren lassen. — Wenn er so verschiedene Sachen in Spiritus geschickt hat, die nicht hineingehören, so müssen Sie bedenken, dass es in den subtropischen Gegenden u bei den Reisen in unwirthbare Länder oft nicht anders möglich ist, die Gegenstände zu conserviren. So ist es der Fall mit den Sachen die Dallachi bei Port Denison u Rockinghamsbay gesammelt hat. Der Mann sammelt fast nur für Dr Müller u ist kein Sachkenner, aber unendlich thätig inmitten der unendlichen Beschwerden u Mühseligkeiten. — Ich denke Sie sollen trotz mancher Mängel doch mit der Zeit das grösste australische Museum auf dem Kontinent erhalten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wissen sie nicht, ob auch an Dr Müller über den Eingang des Geldes eine Anzeige gemacht ist? Ich habe ihm natürlich angezeigt, dass ich eine Quittung von den Kassen erhalten habe. Da Sie ihm, wie Sie äusserten, selbst geschrieben haben, so haben Sie auch wohl einige Worte darüber einfliessen lassen. — Die Bestimmungen des Stipendiums werden Ihnen wohl viele Mühe gemacht haben. — Als Sie im vorigen Herbst in Berlin waren, hätten Sie in 7 Stunden nach Hamburg kommen können, das Sie gegen früher sehr verändert gefunden haben würden!</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Paragraph unrelated to M not included here.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vor einiger Zeit besuchte mich der jetzt in Dresden wohnende Dr Eulenstein, um Diatomaceen zu sehen. Er war sehr liebenswürdig! Er ging von hier über Copenhagen nach Lund u kehrte dann wieder hierher zurück. Er wollte gerne wissen, wie Dr Müller dazu käme, soviel nach Stuttgart zu schicken, worauf ich natürlich keine Antwort wusste.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die beiden Kisten sind gestern frankirt und pr Eisenbahn abgegangen. Hoffentlich kommen sie früh genug an, dass Sie mir bis zum 24 Februar eine einfache Anzeige davon machen können, um in meinem Brief nach Australien deren erwähnen zu können.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Mir bestem Gruss</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg 6 Febr [18]69</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You certainly have looked out for a letter from me for some time already, which should have been in your hands long ago if it weren't for a severe cold chaining me to my room for 14 days. The large crate from Australia that arrived into my possession in the first week of January had to remain untouched in my cellar, until last Sunday I finally received permission from my physician to carry out the unpacking or rather repacking. After I took out the numerous packets with seeds for the botanical gardens and printed matter, I have deemed it advisable to send you your share in two crates. One contains a large number of beautiful minerals, besides some others mainly a large number of copper ores from the new mines of York Peninsula in North Australia.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder has mistaken the locality, which is Yorke Peninsula in South Australia., not Cape York Peninsula, Qld.</p>
               </note> You will be able to enrich several museums with the duplicates. The collection is just as interesting as rare. Probably no museum will yet have any of them.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had previously sent a collection of Australian minerals to Berlin; see M to F. Wöhler, 28 June 1867.</p>
               </note> Then in the same crate a box with fish skins, of which I understand nothing, besides several packets with sea sponges and a number of books and printed matter. The second crate contains a large bundle with bird skins. I wonder if this bundle wrapped in brown packing paper is from New Zealand? That you will soon ascertain from the contents. I conclude from what Dr Mueller wrote to me some time ago that he expected a number of bird skins from New Zealand. — The remaining loosely enclosed bird skins are, however, from South Australia. They look better than the previous ones and may contain something desired by you. The remaining part of the crate is filled with printed matter and one or two small boxes with shells as well as some skulls. The human skulls are from a now completely extinct tribe from the Richmond River.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">NSW.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> — Professor Keferstein would like to have one of them, but he may turn to you. The tiger or jaguar skull from the East Indies seems to be very beautiful. I am not able to say to what animal the other skull belongs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now I still have some parts with Australian views (the conclusion of them) by Eugene Guerard,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Guerard (1866-8).</p>
               </note> of which you already have received some, together with some photographs and a whole number of parts of the ornithological work of Diggles,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Diggles (1866-70).</p>
               </note> which I will forward by post, because they are not suitable for the crate. One of the text pages of the ornithological work has a small tear, which it probably received in opening the box in England where they often handle things sloppily, but it is no of significance. — I think this valuable consignment will bring you pleasure, which will be very agreeable to our friend in Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Enclosed you will find a list of fishes that probably refers to the fishes received last time. — The stuffed crocodile that you received — a young animal — was from North Australia — they don't occur in the south. — If the skeleton of the Australian sent to you last year was unsatisfactory, I hope the one now following will be better. I do not have anything from the first one lacking bones. I am always glad when this kind of item is out of the house. — The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Macrozamia</seg> from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Western Australia</hi>
               </seg> is called <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Macr. preissi</seg> Miquel. The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Todea%20rivularis">Todea rivularis</name>
               </seg> as well as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia</seg> or now <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Balantium%20antarcticum">Balantium antarcticum</name>
               </seg> are from the province of Victoria. I am very anxious whether the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea</seg> has arrived. It is a very valuable item. If your court gardener, for whom I will procure palm seeds, is still very anxious to get a large trunk of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia (Balantium) antarctica</seg>, I will procure one for him. I have kept some back, which I have placed with a local gardener, but which I would like to keep for the great exhibition to take place here in autumn. Afterwards I shall send them on.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I always draw our friend's attention to your special requests, but he is not always master of the situation. Particular items cannot be purchased there. There are no dealers there in natural history objects. Mueller purchases them when a traveler or an inlander brings something to Melbourne, or he orders them and then must really take what is sent to him. In the last few years there have been no expeditions, as soon as they take place there is always something new or rare. Just pour out you heart to Mueller, you can ask him for everything better than I! You can at the same time do justice to his merits and his achievements. — When he has sent such different things in spirit that do not belong in it, you must consider that in the subtropical regions and with travellers in inhospitable countries it is often not otherwise possible to preserve the objects. Such is the case with the things that Dallachi<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">John Dallachy.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> has collected at Port Denison and Rockingham Bay.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Qld.</p>
               </note> The man collects almost only for Dr Mueller and is no expert, but interminably active in the midst of endless troubles and hardships — In spite of many a shortcoming I think you shall with time get the largest Australian Museum on the Continent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Do you not know whether a report has been made to Dr Mueller about the receipt of the money? Of course I have notified him that I have received a receipt from the Treasury. Since you have yourself written to him, as you said, you have probably mentioned some words about it in passing. — The regulations of the scholarship will probably have given you much trouble. — When you were in Berlin last autumn, you could have come to Hamburg in seven hours, which you would have found changed very much compared with formerly!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[…]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Some time ago, Dr Eulenstein, who now lives in Dresden, visited me to see diatoms. He was very amiable! He went from here to Lund via Copenhagen and then returned here. He wanted to know how Dr Mueller came to send so much to Stuttgart, for which of course I had no answer.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Both the crates were prepaid yesterday and go off by train. It is to be hoped they come early enough for you to make a simple report to me by 24 February in order to be able to mention them in my letter to Australia.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With best greetings</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Balantium%20antarcticum">Balantium antarcticum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicksonia%20antarctica">Dicksonia antarctica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Macrozamia%20preissi">Macrozamia preissi</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea%20rivularis">Todea rivularis</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
