<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 9 June [18]71 ¶ Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ Director von Schmidt ¶  has just written to me that you want to have an answer to your last letter. For eight days I have carried around the same thought, bu...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M71-06-09-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M71.06.09</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 9 June [18]71 ¶ Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ Director von Schmidt ¶  has just written to me that you want to have an answer to your last letter. For eight days I have carried around the same thought, bu...</title>
               <date when="1871-06-09">1871-06-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M71-06-09-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/26f088e5-c0e9-44d3-9684-57815342b778">Dicksonia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 9 June [18]71 ¶ Dear Friend, ¶  ¶ Director von Schmidt ¶  has just written to me that you want to have an answer to your last letter. For eight days I have carried around the same thought, bu...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M71.06.09</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand von Krauss</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg d. 9 Juni 71</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Freund</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Director v Schmidt schreibt mir so eben, dass Sie eine Antwort auf Ihren letzten Brief zu haben wünschten. Seit acht Tagen trage ich mich mit demselben Gedanken herum, es ging aber einmal nicht vor heute vor. Dass ich Sie nicht vergessen wird Ihnen meine Sendung bestehend von 2 Kisten u 1 Fass, die in der vorigen Woche an Sie per Bahn u frachtfrei abgegangen sind, bewiesen haben. Wenn Sie nach der Ursache meines späten Schreibens fragen so können Sie nichts für mich [...] darin finden, sobald ich Ihnen sage, dass im Kreise meiner Familie sowie zahlreicher Verwandten u Freunde vor einigen Tagen meine Frau u ich unsere silberne Hochzeit gefeiert haben. Trotz allerlei Einrichtungen u Vorbereitungen die dazu nöthig waren habe ich doch noch Musse gefunden in den freien Stunden die Verpackung der gerade angekommenen australischen Sendung vorzunehmen, damit wenigstens von meiner Seite kein Fehler gemacht werde. Ich habe die Sachen so gut gepackt als irgend möglich, alles eigenhändig, u ich hoffe, dass das Ganze in gutem Zustande ankommen wird. Möge auch recht viel Ihnen Erwünschtes dabei sein. Die Moa Knochen hätten einige meiner hiesigen Bekannten gerne gesehen, ich habe es indess nicht gewagt, sie aus den Händen zu geben. — Von den grossen grünen Schmetterling waren meistens die Leiber abgefallen, ich habe diese in eine besondere Schachtel gelegt, die Sie schon finden werden. Was die Hölzer u Proteaceenfrüchte anbetrifft, so werden Sie darüber von unserm Freunde Nachricht haben. Die grosse Holzsammlung steht Ihnen ja noch bevor, angekommen ist sie noch nicht in London, hoffentlich bleibt sie aber nicht lange mehr aus, u mit den jetzt übersendeten Gegenständen nebst den an Herrn v Schmidt beförderten beiden lebenden Dicksonien, die ihres Gleichen nicht in Europa haben, wird doch wohl ein Eclat für unsern Freund erreicht. Seinen Brief sende ich hiermit zurück. Ich denke, Sie haben darin die Bestätigung dessen gefunden, was ich Ihnen schon mündlich in Stuttgart äusserte. Es ist mir lieb, dass M Ihnen dies nun selbst geschrieben hat. Nicht seiner selbst willen ersehnt M. die Würde, er hat so viele Ehrenbezeugungen erhalten, dass er nach meiner Meinung vollkommen gesättigt sein dürfte, aber für das zweite </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ich</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> fehlt immer noch das den Schluss bildende. Ich habe M in meinem vorletzten u letzten Briefe von Ihren Aeusserungen gegen mich in Kenntnis gesetzt, sowie er diese beiden Briefe erhalten hat, wird er die Geldsumme unverzüglich übersenden. Er bemerkt in seinem letzten Brief vom 18 März, dass er auch Ihnen die Mittheilung gemacht, das 2te Stipendium werde er mit der am 16 Juli abgehenden Post senden, früher könne er nicht, da erst bis dahin das Kapital gekündigt sei. Wenn er nun nach Lesung meiner Briefe vielleicht die Herbeischaffung der Geldsumme hat beschleunigen können, so haben wir die Ankunft derselben schon früher zu erwarten. Senden wird er es, darüber können Sie ruhig sein u bitte ich Sie keine für die Sache nöthigen Schritte zurückzuhalten. Ich habe Ihnen in der ersten Zeit schon mitgetheilt, dass man von anderer Seite, die wie ich höre, mir jetzt nichts weniger als freundlich gesinnt ist, Anerbietungen gemacht hatte, die M. Wünsche realisirt hätten, doch mein Streben ging immer dahin, einem </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Deutschen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Museum u zwar einem solchen wo die Schätze gewürdigt werden, den Vorzug zu geben. Dass Portugal Ihnen keinen Nachtheil bringt, dafür will ich schon sorgen, die Verbindung ist durch mich eingeleitet, der Director des botan. Gartens, dem Dr M. einige botan. Gegenstände geschickt, ist ein persönlicher Bekannter von mir, ich habe nicht geglaubt, dass dieser letztere so viel Ansehn bei seiner Regierung habe, um die Auszeichnung für Dr M. zu erwirken. — Nun, wenn der Baron da ist, werden, denke ich, die Zusendungen an Ihr Museum nicht geringer werden, vielleicht wichtigere Beiträge liefern.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wieviel Geld unser Freund für die Geschenke ausgiebt, mögen Sie daraus entnehmen, dass ich in den letzten 2 Jahren für Fracht u sonstige Auslagen 300 Thaler baar ausgelegt habe. — Ich bitte Sie, in der Sache, vielleicht mit Herrn Dir. Schmidt vorzugehen, das Geld </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wird ankommen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">. Mein zu Anfang Februar nicht angelangter Brief ist am 9/3 mit dem folgenden zugleich eingetroffen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich hätte bald vergessen zu bemerken, dass die schönen Zeichnungen der Miss Atkinson, jetzt Mistrs Calvert nicht mitgekommen sind, weil die Kisten schon gefüllt waren, sie werden das nächste Male mitfolgen. Sie mögen diese hübschen Bilder verwenden wie Sie es für gut finden, hier war keine passende Verwendung dafür, u verkommen sollen sie doch nicht.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Einlage wird früh genug in Ihre Hände gelangen, so dass Sie mit der Austral Post schreiben können, ich schreibe wie gewöhnlich. — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoffentlich haben Sie kein Zahnweh u Rheumatismus mehr bei dem jetzt eingetretenen schönen Wetter. Alt wollen wir noch nicht sein, damit können wir noch etwas warten.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Freundl. Gruss von </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihrem ergebenen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Entschuldigen Sie die Tintenklexe.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Tintenkleckse.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 9 June [18]71</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Director von Schmidt<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Eduard von Schmidlin, Director of the Royal Gardens in Stuttgart.</p>
               </note> has just written to me that you want to have an answer to your last letter. For eight days I have carried around the same thought, but it didn't happen before today. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>My consignment, consisting of two crates and one barrel, which was sent off to you last week by railway and freight-free, will have proved that I have not forgotten you.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Krauss prepared some notes (Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart) for a letter of thanks sent to M on 10 July 1871 for this consignment, which reached Krauss on 26 June 1871. The notes are headed 'Sendung v. F. v. Müller d. 26. Juni 1871 (1 grosse u. 1 kleine Kiste u. 1 Fass) [Consignment from F. von Mueller, 26 June 1871 (1 large and 1 small case and 1 barrel)]' and enumerate various items received. The material listed includes items mentioned in different letters from M, for example M to F. von Krauss, 13 July 1870 (in this edition as 70-07-13c) and M to F. von Krauss, 25 August 1870. The notes mention several damaged specimens, for example an Australian bustard without feet, and moa bones, and raise questions about the origins of some specimens, details of which had been specifically given in letters from M that would, however, have arrived well before the crates. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Krauss's letter of thanks has not been found.</p>
               </note> If you ask about the cause of my late writing, you can find nothing for me […], as soon as I tell you that my wife and I celebrated our silver wedding some days ago in the circle of my family as well as numerous relatives and friends. In spite of all kinds of arrangements and preparations that were necessary for this, I have still found leisure in free hours to engage in the packing of the Australian consignment that just arrived, so that at least no error will be made on my part. I have packed the items as well as anybody could, all single-handedly, and I hope that the lot will arrive in good condition. May very much of what you desire be in it. Some of my local acquaintances would have gladly seen the moa bones, but I have not dared to let them out of my hands. — The bodies of most of the large green butterflies have fallen off. I have put them in a special box, which you will find. Concerning the woods and proteacean fruits, you will receive information about them from our friend. The large wood collection for you<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">See M to F.von Krauss, 9 February 1871.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> is still coming, not having yet arrived in London. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>However, it is to be hoped it will not loiter long and that with the items sent now, together with the two living <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>s sent to Mr von Schmidt, which do not have their equal in Europe, will indeed achieve splendour for our friend. I send back his letter herewith.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> I think you will have found the confirmation in it of what I already said to you verbally in Stuttgart. I am glad that M has now written this himself to you. M does not long for the honour on his own account. He has received so many tokens of honour that in my opinion he ought to be completely satisfied, but for the second <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">I</hi>
               </seg> still lack that forming the conclusion. In my last letter and the one before, I have informed M of your remarks to me. As soon as he receives both these letters, he will send the money promptly. He mentioned in his last letter of 18 March<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> that he has also informed you that he will send the second scholarship with the mail departing on 16 July.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to F. von Krauss, 16 June 1871; a letter sent simultaneously by M to Sonder has not been found.</p>
               </note> He could not do it sooner, because the capital is only recalled then. If, after reading my letters, he can now perhaps speed up the getting of the money, we can expect its arrival earlier. He will send it, you can be assured about that. I ask you not to hold back any steps necessary for the matter. I have already informed you from the first that from the other side, as I heard it, people now disposed in no less friendly a manner towards me had made offers that would have realised M's desires, but my aim was always to give preference to a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">German</hi>
               </seg> museum and indeed to one where the treasures would be valued. I will see to it that Portugal does not disadvantage you. The connection is managed through me. The director of the botanic garden, to whom Dr M sent some botanical specimens,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Adolpho Möller, director of the botanic garden at Coimbra?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> is a personal acquaintance of mine. I did not believe that the latter had enough authority with his government to obtain the decoration for Dr M.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was made a Commander of the Order of St Jago by the King of Portugal in November 1870; cf. M to F. von Krauss, 9 February 1871.</p>
               </note> — Now if the Baron comes about, I believe the consignments to your museum will not be less, perhaps will yield more important contributions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How much money our friend has outlaid for the donations, you may deduce from the fact that I have paid out 300 Thalers cash in the last two years for freight and other expenses. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I ask you in the matter perhaps to proceed with Dr Schmidt, the money <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">will arrive</hi>
               </seg>. My letter that had not arrived at the beginning of February arrived on 9/3 at the same time as the following one.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would nearly have forgotten to mention that the beautiful drawings of Miss Atkinson, now Mrs Calvert, have not come because the boxes were already filled. They will follow next time. You may use these pretty pictures as you see fit. There was no suitable use for them here and they should not get lost.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The enclosure will arrive early enough in your hands, so that you can write by the Austral post. I shall write as usual.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is to be hoped you have no more toothache and rheumatism with the fine weather just setting in. We don't want to be old yet, we can wait a bit for that.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Friendly greetings from</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your humble</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Excuse the scribble</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
