<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne 20.3.73 ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ Having been instructed by you "to report generally of the present state of the Botanical Garden and to make suggestions for rendering it in future more subservient for th...</title>
            <author>Alexander Wallis</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M73-03-20-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>K73/5085, unit 750, VPRS 44 inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M73.03.20</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Alexander Wallis</author>
               <title>Melbourne 20.3.73 ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ Having been instructed by you "to report generally of the present state of the Botanical Garden and to make suggestions for rendering it in future more subservient for th...</title>
               <date when="1873-03-20">1873-03-20</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M73-03-20-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plantnames</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Casey</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne 20.3.73 ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ Having been instructed by you "to report generally of the present state of the Botanical Garden and to make suggestions for rendering it in future more subservient for th...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M73.03.20</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Alexander Wallis to James Casey</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">K73/5085, unit 750, VPRS 44 inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; "/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Casey: 'obtain for me a copy of the paper prepared by Mr C. Hodgkinson which I submitted to Parlt and attatch to this. I will then get both printed. I want also a report from "Curator" with copy of approved design attatched of Public Gards to be printed at same<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>time. J.J.C. 24.3.73'.</p>
               </note>Melbourne 20.3.73</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Having been instructed by you "to report generally of the present state of the Botanical Garden and to make suggestions for rendering it in future more subservient for the purpose of affording practical and scientific information for the instruction of those desirous of obtaining information in plants useful to the country and novel industries", I have the honor to submit the following as the result of my inquiries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1. What is now known as the Botanical Garden, it would appear, originally formed a part of the Reserve for new Govt House, the whole reserve, that is the Botanical Garden together with the adjacent grounds of the Govt House Domain, having been selected and specially set apart for that purpose by Mr Superintendent La Trobe. So far as I have been able to gather, it was originally intended to lay out the entire Reserve, excepting such portion as might be required for the private grounds of Govt House, as an ornamental park and public pleasure garden. The north-eastern portion was the first to be changed from its native state; and the greater portion of what is now the Botanical Garden was laid out by the former curator — Mr Dallachy, and by his predecessor — Mr Arthur. The last named gentleman, it would appear, acting as general foreman under Mr Ghinn, fixed the position of the river walk which extends from the gate near the engine-house to the bridge at Anderson-street, the walks on the east and west banks of the lagoon, and the walks on the southern slope of the same as far up as the wooden summer-house (which was erected some years since by the ladies of South Yarra as a place for holding Horticultural exhibitions), whilst the former laid out the remaining walks south of the lagoon to the position of the present fence, and the walks west of the aviary. The "natural system" which is situated immediately opposite the Director's house, is the work of Baron Dr v. Mueller. The portion of the garden laid out by Mr Arthur was planted for the most part by Mr Dallachy, whilst the Grevillea, Ficus macrophylla and other avenues in the neighbourhood of the large conservatory, the collection of trees, principally conifers, to the south and east of the same, the collection of oaks and fruit trees between the Director's and gardener Schneider's house, the Pinus Halepensis avenue, and the orchard which it is proposed to annex to the private grounds of new Govt House, have been planted under the direction of Baron Dr v.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Mueller. The trees throughout the entire garden, with the exception of those planted by Mr Dallachy and an occasional specimen amongst the others,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are either hidebound and stunted, or otherwise exhibit signs of premature decay. For example, the bark of the Ficus macrophyllas growing near the Palm House, owing, I believe, to the injudicious removal of the lower branches and the exposure of the trunk to the direct rays of the sun, is shrivelled and cracked, which circumstance is fast killing the trees. Again, in the mixed avenue of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Gleditschias<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and Cupressus Goveniana, situated also near the Palm House, there is scarcely one of the cypresses but<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>shows<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>distinct signs of decay, whilst the Gleditschias, though planted about 14 years, are only a few feet in height and so obviously hidebound and stunted that I question whether they will ever make much more growth. The decay of these last named trees, i attribute partly to the ground not having been properly prepared in the first instance partly to the manner in which the trees were propagated and the plants cared for during their early growth. The same is true of the maples near Gardener Coller's house, and of trees in other parts of the garden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. The Geographical Distribution. This system of classification, which was adopted for the first time a few months since, occupies the borders of the two central parallel walks on the slope south of the lagoon. The ground is divided into four sections each of which represents one quarter of the globe, while the north and south borders of each division contain respectively plants from the corresponding areas. the borders, which are only 10 feet wide, appear to have undergone no preparation in anticipation of the above mentioned distribution being made. The multiplication of geraniums and other common flowering plants is unchanged, whilst we have in addition a number of forest trees and large growing shrubs crowded together and planted, not unfrequently, in positions where it is impossible for them to grow. This is rendered only too obvious when we witness oaks and other timber trees planted under the shade of large shrubs, and placed only 3 to 4 ft apart.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>It is self evident that when the trees thus planted have made from two to three or four years' growth this system of planting will prove unsatisfactory.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would, therefore, recommend that this crowding together of forest trees in narrow garden borders be discontinued, and that in future all specimen forest trees be planted in the arboretum and other portions of the Govt House Domain to be specially set aside for the purpose.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">crossed through.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. The Industrial Division. This is situated on the precipitous slope west of the lagoon, and comprises pasture grasses and culinary plants, as well as the olive, the castor oil, and other vegetable products of commercial importance. The grasses are planted in rows and apparently little pain is taken to keep the species distinct, whereas the olive, the castor oil and other plants are each present in too great number; moreover, the site is unsuitable, for owing to the steepness of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>position and the manner in which the ground is laid out and planted, it is almost impossible to make a careful examination of the specimens for the purpose of study. I would recommend that the industrial division be removed to the portions of the ground indicted in another part of this report, and that the present site be turfed and planted with flowering and other ornamental shrubs. I would beg further to suggest that this division be divided in future into two parts, the one to comprise our native grasses and those exotic species known to be useful or likely to prove valuable pasture grasses in this country, together with<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the hop, flax, colza, hemp, and such like herbaceous vegetable products of commercial importance, the other to contain industrial plants of greater stature, that is those which attain the proportions of a shrub or a tree. The former, I would recommend, should be planted in the piece of land (at present occupied principally by fruit trees &amp; oaks) which<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>lies<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>between the Director's and gardener Schneider's House. The ground should be laid out in small beds intercepted by narrow gravel paths. Each bed should contain a distinct plant with a label attached giving its trivial and botanical name, natural order, and habitat, together with a few brief remarks of its commercial uses &amp; value, or if a grass, a statement as to its grazing and feeding capabilities and the season of the year in which it makes its principal growth. The latter I would recommend, should be planted in the piece of vacant ground south-east of the Palm House. The soil certainly, in this portion of the garden, is not of the best description, but, by trenching and a judicious application of fertilising agents, it might speedily be rendered available. The adoption of a system of classification such as the above would, I believe, tend greatly to increase the utility of the garden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4 The Conservatories. Of these there are three. The Palm House, the small conservatory, and the Victoria House; and in the same category may be included the forcing-pits, or propagating-houses. The Palm house contains besides palms a number of ferns &amp; other plants, which are displayed, for the most part, upon stages, or arranged on the floor of the building. In grouping the plants, it has evidently been the aim of the Director to place together those of one family or species rather than to arrange them for the purpose of producing a pleasing effect; moreover, there is in this house a number of ferns &amp; other plants which if placed out of doors would thrive far better. The heating apparatus is not of good construction. The boiler represents more that of a locomotive than a tubular or saddle boiler as used for heating, and consequently a somewhat large quantity of coal — 12 to 14 tons — is consumed annually. The house itself is completely rotten, and I question whether it would be prudent to expend much money in alterations or repairs. The stages are too high and require to be lowered; for, as placed at present,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the plants cannot be seen to advantage.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The ferns, &amp;c under the stages should be removed elsewhere, for these suffer not only from the water which constantly drips from the plants standing above, but also from want of light. The window rollers also require to be taken away, for besides being useless they take up a considerable space.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">crossed through.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The small conservatory is in better repair, and the arrangement of the stages, &amp;c. is an improvement on<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that in the Palm House. The Victoria House is<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is unworthy of its occupant. The house is<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>both small and ill-constructed. It consists only of a square tank with a narrow space in front, affording accommodation only for one visitor at a time with the gardener in charge; and, owing to there being but a single door, which if frequently opened would so reduce the temperature of the interior of the building as to injure the health of the Victoria, the public are excluded. A more suitable structure for such a plant would be a circular or octagonal house, having a round tank in the centre, a passage around the entire house, staging for orchids and other tropical plants along the side walls, and fitted with double doors. A house of this description might form part of an ornamental aggregate of conservatories and hot houses, and thus afford the public every facility of inspecting the Victoria regia and the singular forms of the orchidaceous plants contained therein, without fear of injurious consequences. In conclusion, i would recommend that no more money than is requisite to execute slight repairs from time to time be expended on the conservatories; for, as ample provision has been made for conservatory accommodation in the plans for laying out the grounds of the Govt House Domain, it will be better to expend money in erecting new houses than to be at any great expense repairing the old ones in the Botanical Garden. Of propagating pits, there are two sets. The one is under the care of gardener Coller, whilst the other abuts onto the Victoria House and is heated by the same stove. The former is thoroughly out of repair, but the latter is still in moderately good condition. The quantity of coal consumed is 5 to 6 tons in the one, and 7 to 8 tons in the other; but the last named amount includes the coal required for heating the Victoria House. Thus, the average quantity of coal used annually for heating conservatories in the Botanical Garden is twenty-six tons.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. The Nurseries. In these large quantities of forest trees, flowering shrubs, and other ornamental plants have been raised from year to year for distribution to the various Public Parks and Recreation Reserves throughout the colony, as well as for despatch to gardens &amp;c in other countries;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and there is, moreover, at the present time, a considerable stock of nursery plants on hand. The system adopted in the Botanical Garden of raising forest trees — viz, propagating the seed in small boxes and then transferring each plant to a three inch pot — is, I think, hardly satisfactory, and I question whether trees so raised, except in extraordinary instances, will ever attain their natural development. But<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>aside from the question of the propriety of raising forest trees upon the abovementioned principle, must be considered the cost of each tree so raised. This, when we consider the time expended in the propagation, potting, and subsequent fostering of the plants together with the outlay for pots, cannot be estimated at less than from two to three pence for each tree, whereas the cost of rearing ordinary forest trees should in no case exceed a small fraction of a penny. I would, therefore, recommend that the rearing of forest and ornamental trees in the Botanical Garden, except for use in the establishment or for the purpose of exchange with like institutions, be discontinued, and that in future all work of this nature be conducted in a cheap, yet efficient manner at the State Nursery, Mt Macedon.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>under the supervision of Mr Ferguson.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">crossed through</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">; i.e., William Ferguson.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Again, I would recommend, now that some 6 acres of ground in the State Nursery have been prepared for the reception of plants during the ensuing autumn, that the young trees, &amp;c, at present in the nurseries of the Botanical Garden, be transferred to the State Nursery that they may be planted there in the open ground for the space of one year and allowed to get well rooted previously to being permanently planted out or distributed. And, further, I would recommend that the seeds of forest trees, &amp;c, which from time to time may be received by the Director of the Botanical Garden, be transferred to the State Nursery, and that they be there grown and reared upon the inexpensive system adopted in the forest nurseries on the continent of Europe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6. The Museum. This building, which is constructed of blue stone relieved by brick, is situated on the high ground near to the Observatory and distant some 200 yds from the Director's Office. It contains an extensive collection of dried plants indigenous to all parts of the globe, most of which are stowed away in the cupboards or cases which line the walls of the entire building. However, extensive as the collection is, it appears to possess but few attractions for the public, for few people ever enter the building unless accompanied by the Director. Indeed, it may be said that the Museum is visited, except for mere curiosity, by none but the Director and his employeés. This being the case, it is certainly folly to have the museum so far removed from the office, for much time and labour must necessarily be lost in obtaining specimens therefrom, and in returning the same to their respective places, as these from time to time may be required by the Director.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>in the pursuance of his literary and scientific studies.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">crossed through.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Since, then, it is proposed to expend money on additions to the museum, and since the building and the plants contained therein are virtually used only by the Director, I am of opinion that it would be the better course to remove it at once to a more convenient site, and would recommend that the existing building, which is anything but ornamental and much interferes<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>with the improvement about to be effected in the Govt House domain, be pulled down, and that a new museum be erected on the piece of ground immediately south of the Director's residence, at present occupied by shrubs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7. The Laboratory. The work of this branch of the Botanical Garden consists chiefly in preparing fibres, fatty and essential oils, tannin, tar products, vegetable alkaloids, and the like from indigenous and exotic plants grown in the garden. Specimens so prepared have been presented to various scientific and industrial institutions, others have been despatched<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for exhibition at Vienna, while<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>others, again, have been retained for the use of the Department. The work of preparing these several substances does not occupy the whole time of the laboratory operator. In addition to the above he looks through and makes extracts from the English and other journals which come to the Botanical Garden. Since, then, the work executed in the Botanical laboratory appears to be in a great measure a repetition of the same, and since it does not engage the whole time of one operator, it would be better, I think, to have connected with the Department of Agriculture a chemist of recognised ability, who has made the chemistry of Agriculture his chief study. Such a man would be free to do whatever was required of him, that is he would be<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>at the disposal of the Department to make analysis of soils, manures, and agricultural products, while a fair proportion of his time would be devoted to doing such work as the Director of the Botanical Garden might require.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>8. The Zoological Division. This comprises two monkeys, two emus, one native companion, one kangaroo, one kangaroo rat, two swans, a collection of birds in the avaries, and a number of wild fowl.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The cages in which the monkeys &amp;c, are confined, are both circumscribed and unsightly, whereas the avaries, aside from being situated in a gully and the only gully in the Garden available for fern-trees and such like vegetation, are so overgrown with creepers and overshadowed by trees that the birds live in almost perpetual darkness.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">crossed through.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>A Zoological division can scarcely be considered a necessary adjunct to the Botanical Garden. it contributes only in a minor degree towards its attractiveness; and what little it affords in this way is more than counterbalanced by the litter<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>of straw and paper<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">crossed through.</seg>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.1666in; text-indent: -0.1666in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>addition to the crossing though of the passages indicated, numerous smaller editorial changes have been marked on Wallis's text in a hand different from his, probably in preparation for the printing of the document as foreshadowed by Casey.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>However, no printed submission to Parliament has been found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and general untidiness which its presence occasions. It would be better, I think to keep the departments distinct, and not to detract from the beauties or usefulness of one by unnecessary introductions from another, and for this reason I would recommend that the animals in the Botanical Garden be made over to the care of the Acclimatisation Society, which is exclusively devoted to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Zoology, and that the natural beauties of the present site of the avaries be taken advantage of for the formation of a ferntree gully.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>9. The Lagoon is much overgrown with weeds and requires cleaning out. This, I would recommend,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>should be done in conjunction with the chain of lagoons within the grounds of the Govt House Domain.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>10. The site of the Botanical Garden, when first reserved, having formed a part of the Reserve for new Govt House, and it having been originally intended to make the grounds ornamental rather than scientific, I am of opinion the course primarily proposed should still be adhered to. And this, I may remark, might be done without detracting in the least degree from the general usefulness of the garden. For example, the portions to be devoted strictly to ornamental gardening might be made horticultural in their character, whereas those to be set apart for industrial purposes might, by a tasteful distribution of the various plants, be rendered attractive as well as instructive. The Director's time, however, is already so much engaged with foreign correspondence and pursuance of his scientific and literary studies, as to render him unable to exercise such supervision over the practical management of the out-door work as its importance demands; moreover, I am of opinion that this is work which should not be required of one possessing the special qualifications of Baron Dr v. Mueller. I would, therefore, recommend that the Director be relieved in future of what may be termed the drudgery of his office and that he be free to devote his whole time and attention to scientific and literary pursuits, and to the collating and classification of the dried plants contained in the museum. Baron Dr v. Mueller, I think, should be able to accomplish the whole of this work with the aid of an assistant. The entire control of the practical management of the gardens should, in my opinion, be entrusted to a gardener of recognised ability, who would also perform the duties of Curator of the Govt House Domain.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>11. In having herein recommended the removal of the museum to a more convenient site, the transfer of the nursery plants and the work of raising forest trees in future to the State Nursery, Mt Macedon, the transfer of the Zoological division to the gardens of the Acclimatisation Society, &amp;c, it will be evident that much more labour will be available for general garden work than heretofore. And, in conclusion, I may add that I consider £1000 per annum which will provide for eight gardeners sufficient for wages alone in the Botanical Garden, that is exclusive of the salary of Director's assistant, and the awards to the boys of the Industrial school.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your most obedient Servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. R. Wallis</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Secretary for Agriculture</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">The Honble the Commissioner of Lands &amp; Survey, Minister of Agriculture, &amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Cupressus Goveniana</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Ficus macrophylla</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Gleditschia</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Grevillea</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Pinus Halepensis</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Victoria regia</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
