<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grand-ducal Ministry of State. ¶ Karlsruhe, 30 September 1879. ¶ No 5011. Concerning conferring of an Order. ¶ To His Royal Highness the Grand Duke (to the Grand-ducal Privy Cabinet), we have the hono...</title>
            <author>Ludwig Turban</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M79-09-30-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>General-Landesarchiv, Karlsruhe, 60/1266.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M79.09.30</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ludwig Turban</author>
               <title>Grand-ducal Ministry of State. ¶ Karlsruhe, 30 September 1879. ¶ No 5011. Concerning conferring of an Order. ¶ To His Royal Highness the Grand Duke (to the Grand-ducal Privy Cabinet), we have the hono...</title>
               <date when="1879-09-30">1879-09-30</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M79-09-30-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich I, Grand Duke of Baden</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Grand-ducal Ministry of State. ¶ Karlsruhe, 30 September 1879. ¶ No 5011. Concerning conferring of an Order. ¶ To His Royal Highness the Grand Duke (to the Grand-ducal Privy Cabinet), we have the hono...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M79.09.30</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Ludwig Turban to Friedrich I, Grand Duke of Baden</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">General-Landesarchiv, Karlsruhe, 60/1266.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>In pencil on back of letter:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="">1. Verleihung des Ritterkreuzes I Klasse mit Eichenlaub an Baron Ferdinand von Müller. </seg>[Conferring of the Knight Cross 1 Class with Oakleaves on Baron Ferdinand Mueller.]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="">2 Hiervon lassen S.K.H. der Gr den Gr Stministerium auf seinen Vortrag &amp;c unter dem Anfügen in Kenntniss setzen, dass Hr Müller nach […] seiner[?] […] Auftrag durch die Intendanz der Hof Domänen an ihn gerichteten Schrift bedenken seiner Schenkung der Gr Hof Gartendirektion, ausdrücklich den Wunsch ausgesprochen habe, dass ihm durch die gnade SKH ein grossh. Orden möchte verliehen werden, und somit es keinen Zweifel unterliegen dürfte, dass Hr Müller die ihm zugedachte Auszeichnung annehmen werde. SKH haben desshalb von weiteren Erhebungen […] <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[…] zu nehmen zu der Ordenverleihung […] auszusprechen geruht. Die Insignien u Statuten des Ordens sowie die Verleihungsurkunde […] Person[?] </seg>[…] uns zur geneigt. Zustellung an den D[…] […] […] zu überreichen </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[His Royal Highness the Grand Duke informs the Grand-ducal Minister of State hereof on his report &amp;c under the adjoining, that Herr Mueller […] letter by the board of management of the Court Domains directed to him his gift to the Grand-ducal Court Garden Office has explicitly expressed the desire that a Grand-ducal Order might be conferred on him by the grace of His Royal Highness, and therefore there may be no doubt that Herr Mueller will accept the distinction intended for him. Therefore His Royal Highness has […]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The insignia and statutes of the order as well as the document of conferring […] to hand over the deliver to the […]</p>
               </note>Grossherzogliches Staats-Ministerium.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Karlsruhe den 30ten September 1879.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Nr 5011 Ordensverleihung betr.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">An Seiner Königlichen Hoheit dem Grossherzog</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">(zum Grossherzoglichen Geheimen Cabinet) beehren wir uns in Befolgung der mit Rescript aus Geheimen Cabinet vom 19 d. M No 1870 erhaltenen Höchsten Weisung unterthänigst vorzutragen:</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Baron Ferdinand von Müller hatte schon früher der polytechnischen Schule dahier eine höchst werthvolle Collection pflanzlicher Produkte, namentlich Hölzer aus Ostindian, Australien, Java, ferner medizinisch und technisch verwerthbarer Rinden, Fasern und Harze zum Geschenk gemacht. Wir sind in Folge dessen auf Veranlassung des Grossh. Ministeriums des Innern in der Lage gewesen, über die persönliche Stellung des Genannten und über die Verhältnisse, welche bei der Begründung eines unterthänigsten Antrags auf gnädigste Verleihung einer Ordensauszeichnung in Betracht kommen können, im verflossenen Jahre Erkundigungen einzuziehen, welche sich namentlich auch darauf erstreckten, ob derselbe englischer Staatsangehöriger und ob ihm als solchen die Annahme fremdherrlicher Orden gestattet sei.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Kaiserliche Botschaft in London hat auf unsere Anfrage mit Schreiben vom 1ten Mai v. J. erwidert, dass Herr von Müller am 14 September 1857 unter dem Namen Ferdinand James Henry Müller in der Colonie Victoria als englischer Unterthan naturalisirt sei und gegenwärtig die Stelle als Botaniker für die genannte Colonie bekleide.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das englische Gesetz stehe an und für sich der Annahme fremder Orden Seitens der englischen Staatsangehörigen nicht entgegen, nun dürfen fremde Decorationen in Gegenwart Ihrer Majestät der Königin nicht ohne vorgängig eingeholte Ermächtigung angelegt werden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch eine Bemerkung der Botschaft veranlasst, haben wir weitere Erkundigungen in Berlin eingezogen. In Folge derselben ist der Grossh. Gesandtschaft in Berlin vom Auswärtigen Amt des Deutschen Reichs mit Schreiben vom 12 Mai v. J. die Mittheilung gemacht worden, dass im Jahre 1876 die Verleihung des rothen Adlerordens dritter Klasse an Dr von Müller aus Anlass der Uebersendung einer Sammlung sehr werthvoller Pflanzen an Seine Majestät den Deutschen Kaiser und König vom Preussen beantragt worden war. Da indess nach den in England geltenden Bestimmungen den britischen Staatsangehörigen die Annahme fremdherrlicher Orden ohne besondere Erlaubniss Ihrer Majestät der Königin nicht gestattet sei, und diese Erlaubniss nur denjenigen ertheilt werde, welchen Ordensauszeichnungen für Verdienste vor dem Feinde in der Armee oder auf der Flote oder für hervorragende Leistungen im Dieste eines fremden Souverains verliehen worden, so habe von der beabsichtigten Decorirung des Dr von Müller Abstand genommen werden müssen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wir haben dem Ministerium des Innern darauf unsere Ansicht s. Zt dahin ausgesprochen, dass die Uebung bezüglich der Gestattung der Annahme fremdherrlicher Orden in England eine strengere zu sein scheine, als die von der Botschaft erwähnten ausdrücklichen gesetzlichen Beschränkungen erfordern würden, und dass es sich aus zu empfehlen scheine, sich in dem fraglichen Falle dem in Preussen beobachteten Verhalten anzuschliessen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn nun auch regelmässig an englische Unterthanen fremde Orden nur aus den oben bezeichneten Anlässen verliehen zu werden pflegen, so weist doch auch die Badische Ordensliste einzelne Ausnahmen auf. Namentlich ist im Jahre 1875 der Vorstand des Kensington Museums in London, Sir Philipp Cunliffe Owen mit dem Commandeurkreuz II Klasse des Zähringer Löwenordens decorirt worden; im Jahre 1871 erhielt der vormalige Consul Simson und im Jahre 1872 der Buchhändler Trübner in London das Ritterkreuz I Klasse desselben Ordens; doch steht nicht fast, ob die beiden Letzteren englische Staatsangehorige sind.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wir gelangen hiernach zu dem Ergebniss, dass, wenn auch die Verleihung fremder Orden an engliche Staatsangehörige nur in verhältnissmässig seltenen Fällen stattfindet, und mit Rücksicht auf diese Uebung und auch auf gewisse hergebrachte Beschränkungen in der Ertheilung der Erlaubniss zur Annahme solcher Orden von der Verleihung abgesehen wird, der letzteren gleichwohl in den englischen Gesetzen ein Hinderniss nicht entgegensteht. Immerhin scheinen uns aber die angedeuteten Verhältnisse eine gewisse Vorsicht zu empfehlen und gestatten wir uns der gnädigten Erwägung Euren Königlchen Hoheit ehrerbietigst zu unterbreiten, ob nicht vor dem Vollzug <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>der in Aussicht genommenen Verleihung uns die Höchste Ermächtigung und Weisung gnädigst ertheilt werden wolle, durch das Kaiserliche Consulat in Melbourne in vertraulicher und geeigneter Weise und unter Verlautbarung der Allerhöchsten Intention, Verlässigung darüber zu beschaffen, ob etwa bei Dr von Müller selbst mit Rücksicht auf die bestehenden Verhältnisse Bedenken gegen die Annahme eines fremden Ordens bestehen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Falle der gnädigsten Verleihung eines Ordens an Dr von Müller glauben wir nach dem vorliegenden Ergebnisse der gemachten Erhebungen das Ritterkreuz I Klasse des Ordens vom Zähringer Löwen, als den Verhältnissen entsprechend, ehrerbietigst bezeichnen zu dürfen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Turban</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Grand-ducal Ministry of State.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Karlsruhe, 30 September 1879.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">No 5011. Concerning conferring of an Order.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To His Royal Highness the Grand Duke (to the Grand-ducal Privy Cabinet), we have the honour in compliance with the most high instruction received with the decree from the privy cabinet of 19th of this month, No 1870,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See A. von Unger-Sternberg to L. Turban, 19 September 1879 (in this edition as M79-09-19).</p>
               </note> most humbly to report:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Baron Ferdinand von Mueller had previously already made a present to the polytechnical school here of a highly valuable collection of plant products, especially woods from the East Indies, Australia and Java, besides medicinal and technically useful barks, fibers and resins. Consequently on the instigation of the Grand-ducal Ministry of the Interior we have been in the position to make inquiries in the last year about the personal position of the said person and the circumstances that could come into consideration with the establishment of a most humble proposal on the most gracious conferring of an award of an Order, that especially also extended to whether he was a British subject and whether as such the acceptance of foreign orders was permitted.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On our inquiry the Imperial Embassy in London has replied by letter of 1 May last year that Mr von Mueller was naturalized as a British subject on 14 September 1857 in the Colony of Victoria under the name Ferdinand James Henry Mueller and at present holds the position of Botanist for the said colony.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The English law in itself is not against the acceptance of foreign orders on the part of British subjects. Now foreign decorations may not be donned in the presence of Her Majesty the Queen without previously obtained authority.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Induced by a remark of the Embassy, we have made further inquiries in Berlin. Consequently the Grand-ducal Legation in Berlin has been informed by the Foreign Office of the German Empire by letter of 12 May last year that in the year 1876 the conferring of the Order of the Red Eagle, third class, on Dr von Mueller had been proposed on the occasion of the sending of a collection of very valuable plants to His Majesty the German Emperor and King of Prussia. As in the meantime according to the regulations valid in England, the acceptance of foreign orders by British subjects without the particular permission of Her Majesty the Queen is not permitted, and this permission is only given to those to whom awards of orders have been conferred for service before the enemy in the army or navy or for outstanding achievements in the service of a foreign sovereign, so the intended decoration of Dr von Mueller must have been dispensed with.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We have expressed to the Ministry of the Interior our opinion on this in due time, that the practice regarding the authorization of the acceptance of foreign orders in England seems to be stricter than demanded by the expressly legal restrictions mentioned by the Embassy and that it seems to us to recommend, in the present case, following the example observed in Prussia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now even if foreign orders were to be generally conferred on British subjects only from the causes indicated above, the Baden order list does show individual exceptions as well. Thus in the year 1875, the chairman of the Kensington Museum in London, Sir Philipp Cunliffe Owen, was decorated with the Commander Cross II Class of the Order of the Zähringen Lion; in the year 1871 the former Consul Simson and in the year 1872 the <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>bookseller Trübner in London the Knight Cross I Class of the same Order, but it is not certain that both the latter are British subjects.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Accordingly we come to the conclusion that even if the conferring of foreign orders on British subjects only takes place in relatively rare cases and with consideration on this practice and also on certain customary restrictions in the granting of permission for acceptance of such orders is disregarded from the conferring, none the less there is no obstacle to the latter in the English laws. At any rate the indicated conditions seem to us, however, to recommend a certain prudence and we take the liberty of submitting most respectfully for your Royal Highness's gracious consideration, whether or not before the execution of the contemplated conferring the highest authority and instruction should be graciously given by the Imperial consulate in Melbourne in confidential and suitable manner and under divulging of the supreme intention, to procure reliable [information] about <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>whether any doubts about the acceptance of a foreign order exist with Dr von Mueller himself, given the existing conditions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the case of the gracious conferring of an order on Dr von Mueller, we believe according to the above conclusions, of the fitting ennoblements, the Knight's Cross I Class of the Order of the Zähringen Lion would be most respectfully indicated as answering to the circumstances.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Turban.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Turban was Minister of State. </seg>
                     <seg style="">Letter marked: Karlsruhe den 7tn Oktober 1879.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Verleihung des Z.L. O. mit Eichenlaub an den Hrn Baron von Müller in Melbourne [Conferring of the Zähringen Lion Order with Oakleaves on Baron von Mueller in Melbourne].</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Nachricht Gr. Staatsministerium auf obigen Vortrag unter Anschluss der Ordensinsignien Statuten u. Verleihungsukunde zur Vermittelung der Zustellung und mit dem Anfügen, dass etc. etc [Information Grand-ducal Ministry of State on the above report with connection of the Order insignia, Statutes and conferring document through an agent of conveyance and with the addition that &amp;c &amp;c].</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">(Siehe die Akten-Verleihung des Z.L.O. 1879 OR No 188 und umstehenden Bleistift.) </seg>[(See the conferring file of the Zähringen Lion Order 1879 Or no 188 and pencil draft[?] on the other side.)]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Zu den Ordensacten einen Auszug gebracht O.R. No. 188. </seg>[Extract brought to the Order file O.R. No 188.]</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
