<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>From the temple of art ¶  I went to the secluded dwelling of the scholars, to the seat of science, to our renowned compatriot Baron Dr Ferdinand von Mueller. I found my old highly regarded friend, who...</title>
            <author>Friedrich Basedow</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M87-06-15-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M87.06.15</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Friedrich Basedow</author>
               <title>From the temple of art ¶  I went to the secluded dwelling of the scholars, to the seat of science, to our renowned compatriot Baron Dr Ferdinand von Mueller. I found my old highly regarded friend, who...</title>
               <date when="1887-06-15">1887-06-15</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M87-06-15-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Australische Zeitung</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">From the temple of art ¶  I went to the secluded dwelling of the scholars, to the seat of science, to our renowned compatriot Baron Dr Ferdinand von Mueller. I found my old highly regarded friend, who...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M87.06.15</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Friedrich Basedow to the Australische Zeitung</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">Extract from a report by Friedrich Basedow on his visit to Melbourne, published in </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 15 June 1887, p. 9.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Aus dem Kunsttempel zog es mich in die Klause der Gelehrten, zum Sitz der Wissenschaft, zu unserm berühmten Landsmann Baron Dr. Ferdinand von Müller. Ich fand meinen alten hochgeschätzten Freund, den ich seit 15 Jahren nicht gesehen, wenig verändert, in eifriger Thätigkeit und voller Begeisterung für die Wissenschaft und dabei liebenswürdig wie immer. Eine fesselnde Unterhaltung kam, nach einer herzlichen Begrüssung, sofort in Fluss und wollte, als ich mich endlich trennen musste, nur schwer abreissen. Das dem hochverdienten Manne, der in seiner Wissenschaft (Botanik) als Stern erster Größe glänzt, von der victorianischen Regierung zugefügte himmelschreiende Unrecht nagt immer noch wie ein Wurm an seinem Herzen und es ist rührend, seine Klagen darüber anzuhören, wie man ihn in seinem Streben gestört, der Wissenschaft geschadet und ihm den Rest seines thatenreichen Lebens so gänzlich verbittert hat, dass er sich nimmer darüber hinwegsetzen kann. Der Botanische Garten, seine eigenste Schöpfung, war ihm wie ein Lieblingskind an das Herz gewachsen; was Wunder, dass das gewaltsame ungerechte Losreissen von demselben ihm das Herz brach, ihn völlig niederbeugte und knickte! Wahrlich, die Urheber dieses Frevels haben an dem guten Baron und an der Wissenschaft schwer gesündigt; Ersteres mag ihnen verzeihen, der der letzteren zugefügte Schaden hat keine Sühne! — Im Laufe unseres Gespräches kam die Rede u. A. auch auf die immer noch lückenhafte Erforschung unseres Erdtheils, ein Thema, das der Baron mit grosser Wärme aufnahm, so dass ich mich veranlasst sah, ihn um eine kurze schriftliche Darlegung seiner Ansichten darüber zu ersuchen. Die Antwort auf diese Bitte ist bereits in der "Austral. Ztg." vom 25. Mai im Druck erschienen. Ich verabschiedete mich von dem hochgeehrten Freunde mit dem aufrichtigen Wunsche, dass es ihm vergönnt sein möge, seine rastlose Thätigkeit für die Wissenschaft, der er sich völlig hingegeben, noch recht lange in ungeschwächter Gesundheit und Kraft fortsetzen zu können!</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">From the temple of art<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The National Gallery of Victoria?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I went to the secluded dwelling of the scholars, to the seat of science, to our renowned compatriot Baron Dr Ferdinand von Mueller. I found my old highly regarded friend, whom I had not seen for 15 years, little altered, in fervent work and full of enthusiasm for science and in addition amiable as always. After a hearty greeting an engaging conversation started and was only with difficulty broken when finally I had to part company. The shameful wrong inflicted by the Victorian government on the highly deserving man,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M’s removal from his position as Director of the Melbourne Botanic Garden.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> who in his science (botany) shone like a star of the first magnitude, still eats into his heart like a worm and it is touching to listen to his complaints about it, how they have prevented him in his endeavours, damaged science and have so completely embittered the remainder of his active life that he can never disregard it. The Botanical Garden, his most particular creation, was his heart’s delight like a favourite child. What wonder that the high-handed, unjust separation from it broke his heart, completely humiliated and broke him? Truly the originators of this malice have severely sinned against the good Baron and science. The former might forgive them, the damage inflicted on the latter has no atonement! – Among other things in the course of our conversation the subject of the still incomplete exploration of our part of the world came up, a theme that the Baron took up with great warmth so that I was induced to request of him a short written statement of his views about it. The answer to this request has already appeared in print in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg> of 25 May.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>See M to F. Basedow, 11 May 1887 (in this edition as 87-05-11c).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I took leave of my highly esteemed friend with the sincere wish that he might be permitted to be able to continue his indefatigable activity for science, to which he has sacrificed himself completely for a very long time, yet in unimpaired health and strength</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
