<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Note on the works of Baron Ferdinand Müller ¶  ¶ Baron Ferdinand von Müller will count among the most industrious savants of this century. Having arrived in Australia young, he devoted all his efforts...</title>
            <author>Charles Naudin</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/selected/M95-06-24-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Archives de l'Académie des Sciences, Paris.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M95.06.24</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles Naudin</author>
               <title>Note on the works of Baron Ferdinand Müller ¶  ¶ Baron Ferdinand von Müller will count among the most industrious savants of this century. Having arrived in Australia young, he devoted all his efforts...</title>
               <date when="1895-06-24">1895-06-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/selected/M95-06-24-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Chenopodium nitrariaceum</term>
               <term>Atriplex halimoides</term>
               <term>Salsolaceae</term>
               <term>Myoporineae</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus</term>
               <term>Acacia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Académie des Sciences, Paris</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Note on the works of Baron Ferdinand Müller ¶  ¶ Baron Ferdinand von Müller will count among the most industrious savants of this century. Having arrived in Australia young, he devoted all his efforts...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M95.06.24</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Charles Naudin to the Académie des Sciences, Paris</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Archives de l'Académie des Sciences, Paris.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The file has a title page: 'Rapport sur les travaux de M. le baron Ferdinand Müller par M. Ch. Naudin (Seance du 24 juin 1895)' [Report on the works of Baron Ferdinand Müller by Mr Ch. Naudin (Meeting of 24 June 1895)].</p>
               </note>Notice sur les travaux de M. le B[ar]on Ferdinand Müller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Le B[ar]on Ferdinand von Müller comptera parmi les savants les plus laborieux de ce siècle. Arrivé jeune en Australie, il consacra toutes ses forces à l'étude des plantes de ce continent, où dejà quelques botanistes l'avaient précédé, mais auxquels la difficulté de pénétrer dans l'intérieur et le danger des explorations n'avaient guère permis de s'aventurer loin des côtes. Grâce à l'immigration croissante des européens, au recul des populations indigènes et à la fondation de colonies dont le développement a été rapide, grâce aussi à la bienveillance et aux encouragements des autorités locales, les recherches des explorateurs ont été graduellement facilitées et Fd Müller a su mettre à profit ces avantages pour pénétrer beaucoup plus loin que ses devanciers dans l'intérieur du pays. Sans arriver tout à fait à son extrémité septentrionale, il l'a scruté, avec un soin meticuleuse dans toute sa longueur de l'Est à l'Ouest, depuis le Queensland et la N[ouv]elle Galles du Sud jusqu'à la colonie de Perth, dans le sud-occidental du continent. On imagine sans peine que, dans une si vaste étendue de pays, et si peu explorée jusqu'alors, Fd Müller a dû faire de larges récoltes de plantes, la plûpart peu ou point connues, qu'il s'est empressé de partager avec les musées de l'Europe, fournissant par là aux monographes d'innappréciables ressources. Mais, tout en récoltant des plantes pour les herbiers, notre botaniste préparait déjà, par des observations faites sur place, les travaux de botanique systématique qu'il devait publier quelques années après.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sa situation personnelle n'a du reste pas tardé à se consolider. Le Gouvernement anglais, en en faisant son botaniste attitré, le chargeait en même temps de la direction du Jardin botanique de Melbourne, la grande et florissante capitale de la Colonie de Victoria. C'est dans ce repos relatif qu'il a publié les travaux qui devaient lui faire prendre rang parmi les botanistes les plus en vue. Ils sont trop nombreux et trop divers pour que nous puissions les rappeler tous; il nous suffira de citer, entre les années 1860 et 1862, les deux volumes intitulés <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Plants of the Colony of Victoria</hi>
               </seg>, accompagnés d'un troisième volume de figures; en 1882 le <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Systematic Census of Australian Plants</hi>
               </seg>, recensement général de toutes les plantes d'Australie connues à cette date, présenté sous forme dichotomique, avec des compliments géographiques et chronologiques; de 1885 à 1888 une véritable flore de la Colonie de Victoria, en deux volumes, avec une carte botanique du pays, sous le titre de <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Key of the system of Victorian Plants</hi>
               </seg>. Peu avant cette dernière publication, l'auteur avait été chargé par le Gouvernement d'aller inspecter la nouvelle colonie de Perth et d'en faire connaître les ressources forestières et l'état du commerce des bois. Le résultat de cette exploration a fait la matière d'un grand volume in-folio, contenant, outre une minutieuse description des principaux arbres du pays, une série de planches très bien exécutées qui les représentent. La lecture en est instructive sous plus d'une rapport.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>La flore australienne est si particulière, et si nettement différente de celle des autres régions de la terre par la prédominance de certains types d'organisation, que l'idée devait naturellement venir à Fd Müller d'entreprendre la monographie des groupes de plantes les plus caractéristiques du continent australien. C'était un travail considérable et que le nombre des espèces dans chaque genre, leur variabilité suivant les lieux d'origine et l'indécision de leurs limites rendaient particulièrement difficile. Plus d'un botaniste en aurait été découragé, mais Fd Müller n'a pas reculé devant cette tâche; il l'a vaillamment entreprise et a réussi à la mener à bien en nous donnant quatre grandes monographies accompagnées de figures lithographiques de toutes les espèces décrites: les Salsolacées australiennes, au nombre de 90; les Myoporinées, plus nombreuses encore; les <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>s et genres voisins, en 13 fascicules contenant chacun la description et la figure de douze espèces; enfin, de 1879 à 1884, sous le titre d'<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Eucalyptographia</hi>
               </seg>, une oeuvre magistrale, comprenant la description très détaillée de cent espèces d'<name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>. Ce travail, très soigné, est peut-être le plus important de Fd. Müller, qui pressentait depuis long-temps le rôle que les <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> devaient un jour remplir dans la sylviculture de touts les pays à climat tempéré-chaud de la terre.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Je passe sous silence une multitude de notes détachées et d'observations de tout genre communiquées par notre auteur aux sociétés savantes, pour rappeler un des traits les plus caractéristiques de sa vie de botaniste explorateur, et qui le distingue de la plûpart de ceux qui l'ont précédé. Plus qu'aucun autre il a compris que la Science ne doit pas se borner à des théories plus ou moins philosophiques, et qu'elle n'est complète qu'à condition de fournir des applications pratiques qui contribuent à la richesse publique comme au bien-être des particuliers. A ce point de vue, le rôle essentiel de la botanique est la diffusion, dans le monde entier, des plantes qui peuvent avoir une utilité quelconque, suivant les lieux, les climats, les besoins et les goûts de la société civilisée, surtout en ce qui concerne l'agriculture et le jardinage. Sous l'empire de cette idée Fd. Müller s'est appliqué d'abord à introduire les plantes de l'agriculture européenne en Australie, puis celles de l'Australie en Europe, visant surtout celles qui devaient trouver d'utiles emploies chez nous, ou fournir aux botanistes des types nouveaux d'organisation. Depuis plus de 30 ans il nous inonde, peut-on dire, de plantes australiennes, les unes pour les serres du nord, les autres pour les climats plus doux du midi méditerranéen en France et dans le nord de l'Afrique. On n'oubliera jamais que c'est à lui que la Provence, l'Algérie et la Corse sont redevables de ces superbes <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>, arbres précieux pour l'assainessement des localités insalubres, non moins précieux comme arbres de reboisement, par la rapidité avec laquelle ils produisent des bois d'oeuvre et du combustible. C'est par ses soins que la Villa Thuret, pour n'en pas citer d'autres, possède aujourd'hui plus de Quatre-vingts espèces de ces arbres, qui, déjà en grand nombre, produisent des graines, qu'on expédie jusque dans nos colonies d'Amérique. Faut-il ajouter que nous devons encore à Fd Müller une quantité d'<name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>s, les uns de simple ornament, les autres plus utiles comme arbrisseaux ou arbres tannifères par leurs écorces, ou fourragers par leur feuillage, sans compter que quelques uns produisent une gomme presque ou tout à fait identique à celle du Sénégal? Même dans la famille des Salsolacées Fd Müller a trouvé des plantes d'une haute valeur (<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Atriplex%20halimoides">Atriplex halimoides</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Chenopodium%20nitrariaceum">Chenopodium nitrariaceum</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg> &amp;c) qui feront un jour la fond de l'agriculture des terrains salants, et qui commencent à être appréciées en Algérie.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Fd Müller, anobli par le Gouvernement anglais qui lui a conféré le titre de Baron, est membre de toutes les Académies scientifiques et sociétés savantes de l'Europe et de l'Amérique, un seul honneur lui manque, celui d'être associé à notre Académie des Sciences.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Fin!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ch. Naudin</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Finis coronat opus.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Note on the works of Baron Ferdinand Müller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Baron Ferdinand von Müller will count among the most industrious savants of this century. Having arrived in Australia young, he devoted all his efforts to studying the plants of this continent, where some botanists had preceded him but whom the difficulty of penetrating the interior and the danger of exploring had scarcely allowed to venture far from the coast. Thanks to the increasing immigration of Europeans, the retreat of the indigenous populations and the foundation of colonies the development of which has been rapid, thanks also to the benevolence and encouragement of the local authorities, the researches of the explorers have been gradually facilitated and Ferdinand Müller knew how to profit from these advantages in order to penetrate much further than his predecessors into the interior of the country. Without quite reaching its northern extremity,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Naudin was evidently unaware of M's travels on the north coast of Australia as a member of the North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> he has scrutinized with meticulous care its entire length from East to West, from Queensland and New South Wales to the colony of Perth, in the south-west of the continent. One imagines without difficulty that in such a vast extent of country, so little explored until then, Ferdinand Müller must have made large collections of plants, the majority little or not at all known, that he has hastened to share with the museums of Europe, thereby furnishing inestimable resources for monographs. But, even as he collected plants for herbaria, our botanist was already preparing, through observations made on the spot, the works of systematic botany that he was to publish some years later.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Moreover, his personal situation did not take long to consolidate. The English Government, while making him its accredited botanist, at the same time charged him with directing the Botanic Garden of Melbourne, the great and flourishing capital of the Colony of Victoria.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was not appointed Director of the Melbourne Botanic Garden until several years after he was appointed Victoria's Government Botanist.</p>
               </note> It is in this relative peace and quiet that he has published the works that have brought him to rank among the most prominent botanists. They are too numerous and too varied to be able to mention them all; it will suffice to cite, between the years 1860 and 1862, the two volumes entitled <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Plants of the Colony of Victoria</seg>, accompanied by a third volume of illustrations;<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B62.03.03, B63.13.06 (which, however, was never published although the first five sheets (40 pages) were printed and a set sent to George Bentham) and B65.13.04.</p>
               </note> in 1882 the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Systematic Census of Australian Plants</seg>, a general inventory of all the plants of Australia known at that date, set out in dichotomous form with geographical and chronological annotations;<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B82.13.16, which is not, however, set out in dichotomous form. Naudin has here evidently confused M's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Census</seg> with his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Key to the sytem of Victorian plants</seg> (B88.13.03), which is set out dichotomously.</p>
               </note> from 1885 to 1888 a real flora of the Colony of Victoria, in two volumes with a botanical map of the country, under the title <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Key of the system of Victorian Plants</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B86.13.01, B88.13.03.</p>
               </note> Shortly before this last publication, the author was appointed by the Government to go and inspect the new colony of Perth<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. WA.</p>
               </note> and to make known its forestry resources and the state of the timber trade. The result of this exploration became the subject of a large folio volume<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.13.10.</p>
               </note> containing, in addition to a minute description of the principal trees of the country, a series of very well executed plates that represent them. Reading it is instructive from more than one connection.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Australian flora is so specific, and so clearly different from that of other regions of the Earth through the predominance of certain types of organization, that the idea must have come naturally to Ferdinand Müller to undertake monographic studies of the most characteristic groups of plants of the Australian continent. This was a considerable labour that the number of species in each genus, their variability according to place of origin and the uncertainty of their limits rendered particularly difficult. More than one botanist would have been discouraged, but Ferdinand Müller did not shrink from the task; he undertook it valiantly and succeeded in bringing it off well in giving us four large monographs accompanied by lithographic figures of the species described: the Australian <name key="Salsolaceae">Salsolaceae</name>, 90 of them;<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B89.13.04, B90.13.14, B91.13.24.</p>
               </note> the <name key="Myoporineae">Myoporineae</name>, more numerous still;<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B86.13.21.</p>
               </note> the <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name> and neighbouring genera, in 13 fascicles each containing the description and illustration of a dozen species;<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B87.13.04, B88.13.01.</p>
               </note> finally from 1879 to 1884, under the title <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptographia</seg>, a magisterial work comprising the very detailed description of a hundred species of <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.13.11, B80.13.14, B82.13.17, B83.13.07, B84.13.19.</p>
               </note> This work, very carefully done, is perhaps the most important of Ferdinand Müller, who sensed long ago the role the Eucalypts might one day play in the sylviculture of every country in the world with a warm-temperate climate.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I pass silently over a multitude of separate notes and observations of all kinds communicated by our author to learned societies to recall one of the most characteristic features of his life as botanist-explorer, one that distinguishes him from the majority of those who have preceded him. More than any other he has understood that Science ought not to confine itself to more or less philosophical theories, and that it is complete only in so far as it furnishes practical applications that contribute to both public wealth and the well-being of individuals. From this point of view, botany's essential role is the diffusion, throughout the whole world, of plants that have any kind of utility, according to the places, the climates, the needs and tastes of civilized society — above all in relation to agriculture and gardening. Under the impress of this idea Ferdinand Müller applied himself first to introduce European agricultural plants to Australia, then those of Australia to Europe, aiming above all at those that might find useful employment with us or furnish botanists with new types of organization. For more that 30 years he has inundated us, may it be said, with Australian plants, some for the greenhouses of the north, others for the gentler climates of the Mediterranean south of France and north Africa. It will never be forgotten that it is to him that Provence, Algeria and Corsica owe those superb Eucalypts, precious trees for the cleaning up of unhealthy localities, no less precious as reafforesting trees on account of the speed with which they produce working and fuel timbers. It is thanks to him that the Villa Thuret, not to cite others, today possesses over eighty species of these trees, which already produce seeds in great number that are sent to our American colonies. Need one add that we likewise owe to Ferdinand Müller a great many <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>s, some simply ornamental, others more useful as shrubs or trees in tanning through their bark or as forage through their foliage, without taking into account that some produce a gum almost or quite identical to that of Senegal? Even in the family of <name key="Salsolaceae">Salsolaceae</name> Ferdinand Müller has found plants of high value (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Atriplex%20halimoides">Atriplex halimoides</name>, <name key="Chenopodium%20nitrariaceum">Chenopodium nitrariaceum</name>
               </seg> &amp;c) that will one day provide a basis for agriculture of marshy terrains, and that are beginning to be appreciated by Algeria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand Müller, ennobled by the English Government which has conferred the title of Baron on him,<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In fact the title had been conferred on M by the King of Württemberg. M's knighthood (KCMG) was his highest award from the British government.</p>
               </note> is a member of all the scientific Academies and learned societies of Europe and America. One honour only is wanting, that of being associated with our Academy of Sciences.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M was elected a Corresponding Member of the Académie des Sciences, Paris, on 1 July 1895.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The end!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ch. Naudin</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Finis coronat opus.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Traditional Latin proverb: 'The end crowns the work'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Salsolaceae">Salsolaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myoporineae">Myoporineae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Atriplex%20halimoides">Atriplex halimoides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Chenopodium%20nitrariaceum">Chenopodium nitrariaceum</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
