<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ In answer to your question I would like to remark that certainly the alpine species of  ¶ Eucalyptus ¶  would endure the climate of middle Europe, but even then the growth of these species ( ¶ E. a...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-05-00b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>79.05.00b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ In answer to your question I would like to remark that certainly the alpine species of  ¶ Eucalyptus ¶  would endure the climate of middle Europe, but even then the growth of these species ( ¶ E. a...</title>
               <date when="1879-05">1879-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-05-00b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d08558df-d0eb-4ddc-abcb-44770ebeb477">Eucalyptus gomphocephala</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/f6c2d8e7-9d03-4677-b4c8-1caee39964c7">Eucalyptus pauciflora</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus coccifera</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus vernicosa</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus urnigera</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/cb4d0878-9d4d-44b1-a806-a2ea02b61c2d">Eucalyptus alpina</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Gunnii</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Verein zur Beförderung des Gartenbaues in den Königlichen Preussischen Staaten</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ In answer to your question I would like to remark that certainly the alpine species of  ¶ Eucalyptus ¶  would endure the climate of middle Europe, but even then the growth of these species ( ¶ E. a...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">79.05.00b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To the Verein zur Beförderung des Gartenbaues in den Königlichen Preussischen Staaten</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Ueber Eucalyptus für kältere Gegenden und über die Weiden Australiens' [On Eucalyptus for colder regions and on the Australian willows], <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Monatsschrift des Vereines zur Beförderung des Gartenbaues in den Königlichen Preussischen Staaten und der Gesellschaft der Gartenfreunde Berlins</seg>, vol. 22 (1879), pp. 335-7 (B79.07.04). The letter is dated to May 1879 as the latest likely date that it could have been written, to have been included in the July issue of the journal. It is introduced by </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unser verehrtes korrespondirendes Mitglied, Herr Baron Ferd v. Müller in Melbourne, antwortet auf die im Aufträge des Vereins gestellte Anfrage, ob es nicht Eucalyptus für kältere Gegenden gebe (siehe Monatsschrift 1879 S. 52) mit gewohnter Bereitwilligkeit Folgendes:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[Our respected corresponding member, Baron Ferdinand von Mueller in Melbourne, answers with usual readiness the inquiry put in the name of the society, whether there are not <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus</seg> for colder regions (see Monatsschrift 1879, p. 52) as follows:]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The query to which M is responding is from a report of the meeting of the society on 18 December 1878. It was part of the discussion of a report by Ludwig Wittmack on the use of Eucalyptus in hospitals in Greifswald, comments on the species with the best oil and the growth rate of E. amygdalina around Lake Maggiore in Italy: </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Dr. Bolle empfahl, bei unseren korrespondirenden Mitgliedern Baron Ferd. v. Müller in Melbourne und Rich. Schomburgk in Adelaide anzufragen, welche Eucalyptus-Arten für kälteres Klima geeignet wären, und dann bei uns Versuche damit zu machen. Im Marly-Garten bei Potsdam hat ein vergessener E. globulosus den allerdings milden Winter von 1875-76 ohne Schaden ausgehalten.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[Dr Bolle recommended asking our corresponding members Baron Ferdinand von Mueller in Melbourne and Richard Schomburgk in Adelaide what species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus</seg> were suited for colder climates and then making trials with them here. In the Marly Garden near Potsdam a forgotten <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. globulus</seg> had endured the admittedly mild winter of 1875-6 without damage.]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M had been elected a corresponding member of the society on 26 November 1876. </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Beantwortung Ihrer Frage möchte ich bemerken, dass allerdings die alpinen Arten von Eucalyptus vielleicht das Klima MittelEuropas ertragen würden; aber selbst dann würde der Wuchs dieser Spezies (E. alpina Ldl., E. urnigera H. F., E. vernicosa H. F., E. Gunnii H. F., E. pauciflora Sieb., E. coccifera H. F.) wohl zu langsam sein, um bedeutende hygienische Einflüsse auszuüben. Ich sende Ihnen jedoch einstweilen etwas Samen von E. alpina, so dass Sie selbst Versuche über die Widerstandsfähigkeit dieser Art gegen Kälte anstellen können. Erlauben Sie mir, die Samen von E. gomphocephala hinzuzufügen, da dieser schöne west-australische Baum noch nirgends eingeführt ist, selbst noch nicht am Mittelmeer. Ich schulde dem Verein zur Beförderung des Gartenbaues dort auch noch meinen besten Dank für die wiederholten Zusendungen der wichtigen Abhandlungen Ihrer schönen Gesellschaft. Gelegentlich würde ich bereitwillig einen kurzen Beitrag für diese Schriften liefern. Um auf Ihren Zweck zurück zu kommen, Miasmen und Contagien durch Baurapflanzungen zu unterdrücken, möchte ich in Ihrer Zone das massenhafte Anpflanzen aller Art Coniferen, namentlich derjenigen Arten, welche in sumpfigem Boden gedeihen, ganz be- sonders empfehlen. Wie bei den Eucalyptus - Arten das Kajeput ähnliche Oel sowohl Ozon als Doppeloxyd von Wasserstoff entwikkelt, ebenso geschieht dies durch die flüchtig-öligen Terpentin-Exhalationen der Coniferen, und damit ist eins der mächtigsten Mittel gewonnen, um Krankheitsstoffe in der Sumpfluft oder in ungesunden Stadtgegenden zu zersetzen.*)<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The footnote here is ' Leider gedeihen in Städten unsere Coniferen nur so schlecht; der einzige Baum, der gut fortkommt, der Taxus, enthält keine Harze. D. R.' [Unfortunately our conifers grow only very badly in our cities. The single tree that thrives, the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Taxus</seg>, contains no resin.] ‘D. R.’ has not been identified. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The editor, Ludwig Wittmack, has inserted the following text before the next paragraph:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auf eine weitere Anfrage, ob die so gepriesenen anstralischen Weidegründe denn wirklich Weiden in unserem Sinne seien, da doch schon die blossen Namen der betreffenden Gräser mehr einen horstweisen als einen geschlossenen rasenartigen W’uchs voraussetzen lassen, bemerkt Herr Baron Ferd v. Müller wie folgt:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.472in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[On a further question whether the praised Australian pasture grounds are really pastures in our sense, because the mere names of the grasses in question allow one to suppose more a thicket than a compact turf-like growth, Baron Ferdinand von Mueller remarks as follows:]. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bezüglich der australischen Weideländereien wäre auf Ihre Anfrage zu bemerken, dass wir hier nur ausnahmsweise den dichten Grasrasen einheimisch besitzen, welcher so manchen schönen Teppich über Mittel- und Nord-Europa hinzieht. Erst in unseren Alpen, mit erhöhter Feuchtigkeit und erniedrigter Temperatur, kommt ein dichter Graswuchs häufiger vor. So nähren unsere Grasländereien, die nur selten Wiesen genannt werden könnten, auch nur eine viel geringere Anzahl Rinder oder Schafe, als in Europa auf Strecken gleicher Ausdehnung gedeihen; daher schreiten die Heerdenbesitzer auch hier nach und nach zum Anbau europäischer Gräser, um — nachdem sie ihr Weideland käuflich erstanden — eine grössere Anzahl Weidethiere darauf nähren zu können. In meinem Buche "select plants", das eine Uebersetzung in’s Deutsche verdiente, habe ich alle diejenigen Gräser angegeben, die für Kulturen im Wiesenbau hier anwendbar sind, nachdem ich viele derselben zuerst in Australien einführte und mit denselben im botanischen Garten zu Melbourne experimenlirte. Wie Sie treffend bemerken, sind viele der australischen Gräser recht hart und trocken, aber gerade dadurch ist es ermöglicht, dass sie der Dürre und dem Sirokko widerstehen.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The article concludes with 'Der Redakteur d. Z. ist sehr erfreut, seine Vermuthungen über den Charakter der australischen Weiden, die er in seinem Bericht über die Pariser Welt- Ausstellung*) aussprach, hierdurch bestätigt zu finden.' <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[The editor of the journal is very pleased to find his suppositions about the character of the Australian pastures that he expressed in his report on the Paris World Exhibition hereby confirmed.] A footnote cites ‘Wittmack, Die Nutzpflanzen aller Zonen auf der Pariser Welt - Ausstellung. Berlin, 1879. S. 92’. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In answer to your question I would like to remark that certainly the alpine species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus</seg> would endure the climate of middle Europe, but even then the growth of these species (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. alpine</seg> Ldl., <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. urnigera</seg> H.F.,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hooker f., i.e. Joseph Hooker.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. vernicosa</seg> H.F., <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. gunnii</seg> H.F., <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. paucifolia</seg> Sieb., <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. coccifera</seg> H.F.) would probably be too slow to exert significant hygienic influences. Meanwhile, however, I am sending you some seeds of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. alpine</seg> so that you can make trials yourself about the capacity of resistance of this species against the cold. Allow me to enclose the seeds of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. gomphocephala</seg>, because this beautiful West Australian tree has not yet been introduced anywhere, not even yet on the Mediterranean. I also owe the Verein zur Beförderung des Gartenbaues there my best thanks for the repeated consignments of the important papers of your fine society. Now and then I would be willing to produce a short contribution for these memoirs. To come back to your object of suppressing miasma and contagion through plantations of trees, I would like to recommend quite particularly the mass planting in your climatic zone of all species of conifers, especially those species that thrive in swampy ground. As with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus</seg> species the kajeput-like oil develops as both ozone and double oxide of hydrogen, likewise this occurs through the volatile oily turpentine exhalations of the conifers and thereby one of the most powerful means is obtained to decompose contagious matter in the swamp air or in unhealthy regions of cities.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reference to the Australian pasture lands it should be remarked on your question that here only exceptionally do we have the thick grassy turf of home, which extends so many a beautiful carpet over middle and north Europe. A thicker growth of grass occurs more abundantly only in the Alps with raised humidity and lower temperature. Thus our grassy lands, which only rarely can be called pasture, only feed a much smaller number of cattle or sheep than thrive in Europe on tracts of equal extent, therefore the stock owners even here are progressively resorting to the cultivation of European grasses, in order to be able to feed a larger number of grazing animals on it after they purchase their pasture land. In my book <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select Plants</seg>, which merits a translation into German,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B76.12.04; a German edition was prepared by Edmund Goeze (B83.13.06). </p>
               </note> I have mentioned all the grasses that are adaptable for cultivation in pastures here after having introduced many of them for the first time into Australia and having experimented with them in the botanical garden at Melbourne. As you pertinently remark, many of the Australian grasses are very hard and dry, but just by this it is rendered possible that they withstand the drought and hot winds. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20alpina">Eucalyptus alpina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20coccifera">Eucalyptus coccifera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20gomphocephala">Eucalyptus gomphocephala</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Gunnii">Eucalyptus Gunnii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20pauciflora">Eucalyptus pauciflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20urnigera">Eucalyptus urnigera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20vernicosa">Eucalyptus vernicosa</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
