<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hermannsburg Mission Station on the Finke, ¶ Finke River, NT. ¶  ¶ 21.4.79. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron! ¶  ¶ Your Honour will excuse that I was so long in sending the ¶  ¶ plants. It could not be helped ...</title>
            <author>Hermann Kempe</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-04-21-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M69, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>79.04.21</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Hermann Kempe</author>
               <title>Hermannsburg Mission Station on the Finke, ¶ Finke River, NT. ¶  ¶ 21.4.79. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron! ¶  ¶ Your Honour will excuse that I was so long in sending the ¶  ¶ plants. It could not be helped ...</title>
               <date when="1879-04-21">1879-04-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-04-21-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plantnames</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hermannsburg Mission Station on the Finke, ¶ Finke River, NT. ¶  ¶ 21.4.79. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron! ¶  ¶ Your Honour will excuse that I was so long in sending the ¶  ¶ plants. It could not be helped ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">79.04.21</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Hermann Kempe</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M69, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; "/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS found with a specimen of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Livistona mariae</seg>
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(MEL 726922).<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>MS annotation by M: 'Beantw. 16/6/79' [Answered 16 June 1879]. Letter not found.</p>
               </note>M. St. Hermannsburg am Finke d. 21.4.79.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter Herr Baron!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ew. Hochwohlgeb. werden entschuldigen, dass ich mit Zuschickung der Pflanzen habe so lange auf mich warten lassen. Es war mir nicht wohl anders möglich, denn voriges Jahr, als ich Ihren werthen Brief erhielt, blieb der sehnlich erwünschte Regen<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hier</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>aus u. damit auch die Blüthe so mancher Gräser u. Pflanzen, die ich Ihnen gern zugeschichkt hätte. Ich hoffe aber, dass es nun auch noch Zeit ist, u. Sie noch einigen Gebrauch davon machen können. Nur Eins ist, was ich dabei befürchte, dass nehmlich bei dem mangelhaften Postwesen allhier die Packete ziehmlich beschädigt sein werden, wenn dieselben in Ihre Hände kommen. Ich übersende Ihnen hiermit vier Packete.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Packet No 1. enthält ein Blatt u. Samen der von den E. Giles entdeckten Palman in dem von ihm genannten glen of palms. Von dem Blatt habe ich den Stiel u. die Spitzen der Lappen abgeschnitten, um das Packet kleiner zu machen. Die Länge des Stiel mag 5 Fuss betragen u. der Durchmesser des Blattes selbst ungefähr ebenfalls 5 Fuss, so dass die ganze Länge des Blattes 9-10 Fuss ist. Blüthen zu bekommen, war mir nicht möglich, ich kann Ihnen aber sagen, dass die Blüthe die Gestalt einer Weintraube hat, nur sehr gross, etwas 8-10 Fuss lang u. unten 2-3 Zoll dick, ebenso ist die Farbe der Blüthe, wie beim Wein, eine weisslich-grüne. So haben auch die Früchte, wenn reif, das Ansehen einer riesig grossen Weintraube. Das Mark des Stammes oben an der Krone ist zu geneissen, u. schmeckt ähnlich, wie die Cokusnuss. Auch habe ich ein Stück Holz mit beigelegt, aus der Mitte des Stammes gehauen. Die Höhe der ältesten dieser Bäume mag 70 Fuss betragen u. es stehen die meisten derselben nicht in dem sogenannten glen of palms, sondern an einem kleinen Creek, welcher in den Finke fliesst. Nach der Beschreibung, wie ich sie in der Naturgesch. v. H. Rebau vor mir habe, gleicht sie am meisten der in Ostindien heimischen Schirmpalme, Corypha umbraculifera.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In dem Paket No. 2 befindet sich ein Blatt u. etwas Samen von der in dem Thal der Ellery's Creek wachsenden Palmen. Ungefähr zwei Fuss habe ich von dem Stiele des Blattes abgeschnitten. Es thut mir leid, Ihnen keinen ganzen Samenzapfen schicken zu können, ich konnte<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>keinen finden. Diese Art wächst nicht hoch, sondern es liegen die alten Blätter auf der Erde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Paket No. 3 enthält eine Sammlung aller hier wachsenden Gräser, wenigstens konnte ich nicht mehrere finden, endlich</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In dem Paket No. 4 befinden sich allerlei Pflanzen u. Sträucher, theils mit, theils ohne Samen, wie ich sie finden konnte. Ich glaube nur nicht, dass da viel Neues dazwischen sein wird, auch sind es längst nicht alle hier wachsenden Arten, denn wollte ich von allen Arten eine Probe senden, möchten wohl gegen zehn solcher Pakete werden. Falls Sie es aber wünschen, bin ich gern bereit, Ihnen mehr davon zuzuschicken. Von Bezahlung dafür kann selbstverständlich bei mir nicht die Rede sein, es soll mich nur freuen, wenn Sie, hochgeehrter Herr Baron, von meiner geringen Mühe einigen Gebrauch machen könnten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nur Eins möchte ich mir erbitten, wenn nehmlich das von Ihnen beabsichtigte Werke erschienen, mir dasselbe zuzuschicken u. zwar an G. Schmidt, Palmenthal, Tanunda P. O. , S. Austr. Derselbe würde dann umgehend Ihnen den Betrag zuschicken. In der Hoffnung, dass Sie mein Schreiben nicht ungütig aufnehmen werden, schliesse ich, und wünsche Ihnen in allem Ihren Vornehmen Gottes reichen Segen, und dass es Alles gereichen möge zu Seines grossen Namens Ehre. Denn darauf kommt doch schliesslich Alles an, dass wir in allem unsern Thun nicht unsre, sondern Gottes Ehre zu fördern suchen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">In Hochachtung Ew. Hochwohlgeb.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>unterthäniger</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. H. Kempe</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Missionar.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hermannsburg Mission Station on the Finke,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finke River, NT.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>21.4.79.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Highly esteemed Baron!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your Honour will excuse that I was so long in sending the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>plants. It could not be helped<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>because last year, when I received your esteemed letter,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the badly wanted rain failed to come<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">here</hi>
               </seg>, and with that the flowering of so many grasses and plants that I would have been pleased to send you. I hope, however, that I am still in time, so you can make some use of them. There is only<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>one thing that worries me: that<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>with the poor postal facilities here, the parcels will be rather damaged by the time they reach you. I am posting four parcels to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Parcel No. 1 contains a leaf and seed of the palms discovered by E. Giles in the Glen of Palms,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>NT.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>so named by him. I have cut the petiole and the tips of the lobes from<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the leaf to make the parcel smaller. The length of the petiole may be about 5 feet, and the diameter of the leaf itself about another 5 feet, so that the total length of the leaf is about 9-10 feet. I was unable to obtain flowers, but I can tell you that the flower has the shape of a bunch of grapes, only much larger, about 8-10 feet long and 2-3 inches wide at the base, just as the colour of the flower is like that of the wine, a whitish-green. The fruit, too, have the appearance of a gigantic bunch of grapes when ripe. The pith of the trunk high up in the crown is edible and tastes similar to coconut. I have enclosed a piece of wood as well, cut from the middle of the trunk. The oldest of these trees would be 70 feet high, and most of them do not grow in the so-called Glen of Palms but along a small creek that flows into the Finke.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Presumably Palm Creek.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>According to the description in the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Natural History</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>by H. Rebau<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Rebau published a number of works that could be covered by the short title<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Natureschichte</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>given by<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Kempe, and the source Kempe used has not been identified.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that I have in front of me,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>it resembles most closely the East-Indian umbrella palm<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Corypha umbraculifera.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Parcel No. 2 contains a leaf and some seed from palms growing in the valley of Ellery's Creek.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ellery Creek, NT.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>MS annotation by M: 'Zamia'.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have cut about two feet off the leaf stalk. I am sorry I cannot send you a complete seed cone, I could not find one. This species does not grow very high, but the old leaves lie on the ground.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Parcel No. 3 contains a collection of all the grasses growing here, at least I could not find any others. And finally</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Parcel No. 4 contains all kinds of plants and shrubs, partly with and partly without seed, as I could find them. I doubt if there is anything much that is new amongst them, and these are not all the species growing here by any means, for if I were to send a sample of every species they would probably fill about ten such parcels. If, however, you wish it I should be pleased to send you more. Of course there can be no question of remuneration. I should be only too happy if you, Honoured Baron, could make some use of my small efforts.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is only one thing I should like to ask of you: if the book you intended writing has been published, would you send me a copy care of G. Schmidt,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn7" n="8">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Book not positively<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>identified; error for Carl Schmidt?</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Palmenthal, Tanunda P.O., S. Austr. He would forward the amount owing to you immediately. I conclude in the hope that you will not receive my letter ungraciously, and I wish you God's richest blessings on all your undertakings and that everything may be to the honour of His great name. For in the end that is what really matters: that in all we do we seek to promote not our own, but God's glory.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">In deepest respect<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your honour's humble</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. H. Kempe</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Missionary</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Corypha umbraculifera</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
