<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>12/1/79 ¶  ¶ Firstly, noble friend, I have to thank you for the attention that you devote to my collections and for the honour that has been done to me by yourself and your collaborators, by conferrin...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-01-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>79.01.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>12/1/79 ¶  ¶ Firstly, noble friend, I have to thank you for the attention that you devote to my collections and for the honour that has been done to me by yourself and your collaborators, by conferrin...</title>
               <date when="1879-01-12">1879-01-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-01-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">12/1/79 ¶  ¶ Firstly, noble friend, I have to thank you for the attention that you devote to my collections and for the honour that has been done to me by yourself and your collaborators, by conferrin...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">79.01.12</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Ferdinand von Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotations by Krauss: 'Fragen, ob wir nicht den von der Regierung herausgegebenen Prodom. of the Zoology of the Colonie u. den von McCoy publicirten Megascolides australis neu Wurm v. Fuss Lange bekommen können.'; 'bitte um Cereopsis Nov Holl. u. Dromaius Nov. Holl. Balg u. Skelet u. Anseranas melanoleuca Dingo Balg'; 'die Meerschlange ist Hydrophis asper Grey'. [Ask whether we can get the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus of the Zoology of the Colony</seg> published by the Government and the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Megascolides australis</seg> published by McCoy new worm of foot length; ask for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cereopsis novaehollandiae</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dromaius</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">novaehollandiae</seg>, skin and skeleton and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Anseranas melanoleuca</seg>. Dingo skin. The sea snake is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hydrophis asper Grey</seg>].</p>
               </note>12/1/79</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zunächst, edler Freund, habe ich Ihnen zu danken für die Aufmerksamkeit, welche Sie meinen Sammlungen zuwenden, und für die Ehre, welche mir durch Sie und Ihre Collaboratoren angethan ist, indem Sie meinen Namen auf mehrere der neuen Museum-Objecte übertrugen für specifische Benennung. Wenn im Fortgang Ihrer Correspondenz Sie den andern Herren, denen ich auch in dieser Hinsicht verpflichtet bin, meinen Dank erstatten wollen, so soll es mich recht freuen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass wieder ein Theil der Exemplare ankam in beschädetem Zustand, ist recht zu bedauern; diesmal ist die Erklärung leicht. Ein Theil der Fische, namentlich die vom K. George's Sound, kam in einer Mischung von einigen pro centen Carbol-Säure mit Wasser an. Ich hatte diese Aufbewahrungs Weise in meinem Laboratorium erprobt, u. solche den Sammlern empfohlen, denen kein Alcohol zur Hand war. Hätte ich die zoologischen Gegenstände nun einfach in dieser Flüssigkeit gelassen, so wäre alles gut abgegangen, aber ich trug meinem Gehülfen auf, die Sachen in Weingeist zu versetzen, u. übersah ihm speciell zu bemerken, dass der Alcohol wenigstens einmal erneuert werden müsse.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun fürchte ich, dass die nächste bei Ihnen eintreffende Sendung aus demselben Grunde bei Ihnen in schadhaftem Zustand eintreffen wird. — Ich habe nach dem Empfang Ihrer letzten gütigen Zuschrift Schritte getroffen, die von Ihnen speciell gewünschten Gegenstände herbeizuschaffen. Aber "Geld und gute Worte" thun es nicht allein; man muss Geduld haben. Selbst der einst so häufige Dingo ist in der Nähe der Niederlassungen überall durch Strychin vertilgt, weil das Thier so viele Schaafe erwürgt. Den Käfer, welcher so gemüthlich mit den Ameisen zusammen lebt, habe ich schon erlangt, freilich nur 1 Exemplar, welches mit <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dieser</hi>
               </seg> Post an Sie abgehen wird. Es werden enorme Preise für diese Käfer geboten; sie sind aber nicht erlangbar. Ich erhielt ihn von einem meiner früheren Gärtner, Mr. French, dem ich auch einige andere Gegenstände verdankte; es wäre mir lieb, wenn von den nun kommenden Arachniden eine neue Art nach ihm genannt werden könne.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seien Sie versichert, dass ich das Interesse Ihrer prächtigen u. reichen Anstalt hier immer wahren werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe den Pastor Dr. Bromby besucht und ihm mitgetheilt, wie gütig Sie und Ihre Frau Gemahlin sich seiner Tochter gegenüber benommen haben. Nach dem Wenigen, welches ich von Fräulein Bromby gesehen, ist sie eine ebenso begabte als gutmüthige junge Dame.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit der grössten Zuneigung bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Strengen Sie sich, edler Mann, um <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">meinet</hi>
               </seg>willen nicht über Ihre Kräfte an, u. lassen Sie mich hoffen, dass Sie nach Ihrer Erholungs Reise ganz erstarkt sind. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> müssen sich ja Ihrer <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Familie</hi>
               </seg> wegen schonen, um selbiger bis in den späten Lebensabend zu Seite stehen zu können; bei <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mir</hi>
               </seg> ist es ja gleichgültig, wenn ich dahin scheide, denn mein Haus ist ja verödet geblieben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Port Darwin ist einer der Häfen im äussersten Nord Westen Australiens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>McCoys Decaden liegen für Sie bereit, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">complete</hi>
               </seg>. Ist nicht der Pausiden Käfer der letzte, den Linné beschrieb?<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotations by Krauss: 'Phymatopterus Hopei Westwood'; 'die Pausiden sind unter <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">trockenen</hi>
                     </seg> Düngerfladen, alten Holzp[äcken?], unter Steinen im dortigen Frühjahr Herbst u. Winter zu suchen. Fliegen nachts nach dem Licht an weissen Tüchern.' [the Pausidae are to be sought under <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">dry</hi>
                     </seg> cow dung, old wood bundles, under stones in the spring, autumn and winter there. Flies at night to the light on a white sheet.]; 'das überschickte ist (Pausus) Phymatopterus Hopei Westw.' [that sent is (Pausus) [i.e. Paussus] Phymatopterus hopei Westw.]; 'Bitte um Tausch-Einleitg. mit den Trans. a. Proc. Roy. Soc. of Victoria Melbourne (1878 d. XIII Vol. erschien)' [Ask for exchange with the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions and Proceedings of Royal Society of Victoria</seg> Melbourne (the 13th volume appeared in 1878)].<seg style="color: #0000ff; font-weight: bold; "> </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">12/1/79</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Firstly, noble friend, I have to thank you for the attention that you devote to my collections and for the honour that has been done to me by yourself and your collaborators, by conferring my name upon several of the new museum objects for specific naming. If in the continuation of your correspondence you will express my thanks to the other gentlemen to whom I am also obliged in this respect, I shall be very pleased.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That a part of the specimens arrived again in damaged condition is to be regretted very much; this time the explanation is simple. A part of the fishes, especially those from King Georges Sound,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">WA.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> arrived in a mixture of some percent carbolic acid with water. I had tried this preservative in my laboratory and recommended it to the collectors for whom no alcohol was to hand. If I had now simply left the zoological objects in this fluid, all would have gone off well, but I instructed my assistant to put the things into spirit of wine and overlooked specially remarking to him that the alcohol must be changed at least once.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now I fear that the next consignment arriving at your place will arrive in spoilt condition for the same reason. After the receipt of your last kind letter, I have taken steps to procure the objects especially requested by you. But "money and good words" will not do it alone, one must have patience. Even the once so common Dingo is exterminated in the vicinity of settlements everywhere by strychnine, because the animal slaughtered so many sheep. I have already acquired the beetle that lives so comfortably together with the ants, admittedly only 1 specimen that will go off to you with <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">this</hi>
               </seg> mail. An enormous price was offered for this beetle; but they are no longer obtainable. I got it from one of my former gardeners, Mr French, to whom I am also indebted for some other objects; it would please me if a new species from the spiders now coming could be named after him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Be assured that I shall always watch over the interest here of your splendid and rich institution.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have visited the pastor, Dr Bromby, and informed him how kindly you and your wife have acted towards his daughter. From the little that I have seen of Miss Bromby, she is just as talented a young lady as she is good-natured.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With the greatest affection I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Do not exert yourself, noble man, beyond your strength on <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my account</hi>
               </seg>, and let me hope that you will be completely strengthened after your recreational trip. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">You</hi>
               </seg> must certainly take care of yourself on account of your <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">family</hi>
               </seg>, to be able to stand at their side in the late evening of life. In <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
               </seg> case it is all the same if I depart this world, because my house has remained desolate.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Port Darwin is one of the harbours in the extreme North West of Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>McCoy's Decades lie already for you <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">complete</hi>
               </seg>. Is the paused beetle not the last that Linné described.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
