<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christmas ¶ 1879 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ Your so kindly meant letter, dear fellowcountryman, has only made me even sadder in my troubled and depressed mood, and you must permit me to put before  ¶ you ¶ , the ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-12-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, folder 211, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>79.12.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Christmas ¶ 1879 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ Your so kindly meant letter, dear fellowcountryman, has only made me even sadder in my troubled and depressed mood, and you must permit me to put before  ¶ you ¶ , the ...</title>
               <date when="1879-12-25">1879-12-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1879/79-12-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius von Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Christmas ¶ 1879 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ Your so kindly meant letter, dear fellowcountryman, has only made me even sadder in my troubled and depressed mood, and you must permit me to put before  ¶ you ¶ , the ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">79.12.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius von Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, folder 211, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Privat</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">1879</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr so freundlich gemeintes Schreiben, theurer Herr Landsmann, hat mich in meiner trüben u. niedergeschlagenen Stimmung nur noch trauriger gemacht, u Sie müssen mir erlauben, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihnen</hi>
               </seg>, dem wissenschaftlichen Freunde, nun noch einmal brieflich vorzulegen, was ich mündlich auseinandersetzte, wie ich Sie und Ihre gütige Gemahlin hier zu treffen das Glück hatte, denn selbst <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> haben sich in Bezug auf meine jetzige Stellung gänzlich missleiten lassen. Mag es mir denn gestattet sein noch einmal und ohne Übertreibung zu wiederholen, dass ich social, finanziell u häuslich fast ganz <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ruinirt</hi>
               </seg> bin, und <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">literarisch</hi>
               </seg> nicht mehr halb das zu leisten vermag, seit man mir den Garten (das einzige welches ich im Leben hatte) so grausam nahm! Wer ist es denn gewesen, Bester, der Sie so gänzlich missleitete? Es muss doch jemand gewesen sein, der dabei interessirt ist, mich niederzuhalten und den Fortschritt meiner Forschungen zu hemmen! Meine Rohmaterialien u meine Beobachtungs Materialien sind <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hauptsächlich</hi>
               </seg> im Garten u. unter den lebenden Pflanzen! Was sollte Hooker denn machen, wäre es Ayrton gelungen ihn aus Kew zu stossen? Das Bot. Magaz. müsste doch gleich eingehen u er könnte nicht mehr die glorreichen Rapporte liefern deren wir gerade jetzt den letzten vor uns haben. Wie sollte <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">er</hi>
               </seg> ausserhalb Kew seiner Stellung als Regierungsbotaniker gerecht werden? in England. Wie sollte er seinen Untersuchungen selbst im Herbarium practischen Werth geben? Nein! Besser ich muss mich Ihnen gegenüber frei aussprechen, denn sonst <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">arbeiteten</hi>
               </seg> Sie meinen Feinden ja erst in die Hände, u <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">das</hi>
               </seg> können Sie doch nicht wollen. Der Platz eines Regierungs Botanikers ist <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">im</hi>
               </seg> botanisch Garten u nicht ausserhalb desselben. Er braucht, namentlich für die Industrien neuer Colonien, seine <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">lebenden</hi>
               </seg> Pflanzen viel mehr wie die getrocknet<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">getrockneten?</p>
               </note> Herbarien. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Im</hi>
               </seg> Garten sind die mir nöthigen Betriebs-<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Gelder</hi>
               </seg>, der von mir zugelernte <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Stab</hi>
               </seg>, die nöthigen Gebäude. Der Eindringling, der mit der Hülfe seines Vetters (des damaligen Ministers) mich spät im Leben in unverdientes Unglück stürzte, hat sogar mein Laboratorium niederreissen lassen damit ich doch ja nicht darin fortarbeiten solle und meine in Jahren zusammengebrachten Apparate des Laboratoriums sind mir auch entzogen. Ich habe daher <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nichts</hi>
               </seg> in der Philadelphia Ausstellung gehabt, nichts in der letzten Pariser, nichts in Wien, nichts in Sydney u werde auch nun in Melbourne nichts haben! Wie kann ich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ohne</hi>
               </seg> ein Departement etwas dem Lande nützendes herstellen? als etwa eine Sammlung trockner Pflanzen, die von fast gar keinem Belang wäre! O Gott! wie haben sich die Zeiten für mich unglücklich geändert. Als ganz junger Mann war ich bereits Commissionär für die erste Pariser Ausstellung, wohin ich unter Anderm das Eucalyptus-Öl sandte, dass jetzt <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">tonnenweise</hi>
               </seg> ausgeführt wird. Seit ich aus meiner Schöpfung getrieben u an die Strasse geworfen wurde, bin ich selbstverständlich aus allen Commissionen ausgeschlossen, u ein ganz ungebildeter Gärtner, der einfach den Sydney <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Zier</hi>
               </seg> Garten nachahmt (weil er nie etwas anderes im Leben sah) ist der <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">College</hi>
               </seg> von Hooker (<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht ich</hi>
               </seg>), und dieser unwürdige Mensch kann sich mit <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">meinen</hi>
               </seg> Schätzen nicht nur täglich vor dem Publicum brüsten mit der Hülfe der von mir jahrelang eingeschulten Gehülfen aus <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">meinen</hi>
               </seg> seit 25 Jahren gezogenen Pflanzen Sachen für die Ausstellungen senden, wie Sie in Sydney wahrgenommen haben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Soviel Ehrgefühl u professioneller Stolz sind mir noch geblieben, dass ich Melbourne während der Monate der Ausstellung verlassen werde, denn als <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">abgesetzter Gartendirector</hi>
               </seg> möchte ich mich doch den grossen Gelehrten aus andern Ländern nicht präsentiren u zum Lachstock werden! Nein! <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Das</hi>
               </seg> kann ich nicht, zumal da man mir absichtlich alle Culturmittel verweigert, damit ich ja nicht in Concurrenz mit dem Sydney nurseryman trete. Freilich hat mir das jetztige Ministerium, das mir nicht unfreundlich gesinnt ist, zehn (sage 10) Acker angeboten von den 2000 Acker Park u Gartenland des Landsdepartements um Melbourne. Da ich aber nach der Rate von 30 Ackern jährlich pflanzte u man mir fast gar keine Betriebsmittel geben würde, so habe ich dies abgelehnt!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was möchte wohl <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihr</hi>
               </seg> Gefühl sein, edler Freund, wenn der Vetter eines dortigen Ministers Ihnen Ihr Museum plötzlich nähme u unter solchen empörenden Beleidigungen, dass Sie es <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nie</hi>
               </seg> wieder betreten könnten; wenn ein solcher Eindringling mit Ihrem Stab fortarbeitete ohne selbst Kenntnisse mitzubringen, u Sie Ihrer Amts Wohnung entzogen würden, u kümmerlich aus dem <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Salair</hi>
               </seg> u einigen kleinen Mitteln Ihre Stellung in der wissenschaftlichen Welt aufrecht zu erhalten wäre!, während <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihre</hi>
               </seg> früheren Mittel für das Museum aus Nepotismus ver 3- oder 4-facht würden!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin gänzlich verarmt, kann nicht einmal einen Sammler mehr halten, u so ist selbst von den "<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">fragmenten</hi>
               </seg>" seit fast 2 Jahren nichts mehr mehr erschienen. Hooker kann dies selbstverständlich nur <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">lieb</hi>
               </seg> sein, denn er wünschte es <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg>, dass jemand an Pflanzen in brittischen Colonien unabhängig arbeitete. Der Eucalyptus-Atlas, das einzige meiner letztjährigen Thätigkeit, beruht hauptsächlich auf die Beobachtungen früherer Jahre, u selbst dafür ich<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">ist?</p>
               </note> mir meine reiche Sammlung von etwa 60 Arten Euc. entzogen, die ich im Garten cultivirte, u die nun grossentheils gewöhnlichem Rasen, wie Sie solche auf jedem "Bowling Green u Cricket Ground" sehen Platz gemacht haben!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist in der ganzen neuern Geschichte der Wissenschaft kein ähnlicher Fall, dass ein Mann in meiner Stellung <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unverschuldet</hi>
               </seg> in den Staub getreten wurde. Aber ich bin Deutscher! Meine Correspondenz u die literarischen Arbeiten, soweit solche kürzlich noch fortgesetzt werden können, verrichte ich in einer kleinen "Cottage", die ich durch eine Baugesellschaft gekauft, u woran ich noch jahrelang zu zahlen habe! Wittstein wurde <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">schon im Garten</hi>
               </seg> übersetzt, u es kostete mir die Ersparnisse zweier Jahre, den Druck zu bestreiten. Selbstverständlich ist fast nichts vom Werke verkaufbar gewesen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach Sydney bin ich nicht gewillt zu gehen. Was nützt es mir, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ohne Garten</hi>
               </seg> mich da zu zeigen? Etwaige neue Erfahrungen könnte ich ja doch practisch nicht verwerthen, u es würde für mich nur <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">peinlich</hi>
               </seg> sein, mich aus allem practischen Mitwirken ausgestossen zu sehen. Verzeihen Sie, dass ich so freimüthig spreche, aber wenn selbst Sie, der <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wissenschaftliche Landsmann</hi>
               </seg>, die Worte meiner Feinde aufnehmen freilich unbewusst, so ist um so weniger an den Aufbau eines ehrenhaften Departements nicht länger zu denken, u ich habe doch noch immer "gehofft gegen Hoffnung". — <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Im</hi>
               </seg> Garten hätte ich selbst <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">literarisch</hi>
               </seg> doppelt soviel leisten können, u. jetzt muss es grossentheils auf Kosten derjenigen Privatmittel geschehen, aus welchen ich so gern einen häuslichen Heerd u Familien Glück begründet hätte, aber selbst <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">das</hi>
               </seg> gönnt man mir hier nicht. Bei mir, Freund, ist es nicht Gefühlssache bloss, sondern <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ruin!</hi>
               </seg> u Sie haben sich täuschen lassen, wenn Sie jetzt schreiben "ich hätte meine ehrenvolle Stellung <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg> verloren!"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So werden wir uns wohl im Leben nie wiedersehen. Genehmigen Sie u Ihre Gemahlin die Anerkennung Ihrer Güte vieler früherer Jahre, u. mag das neue Jahr Ihnen u Ihrer schönen Familie recht viel Freude bringen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets Ihr Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Austausche von Samen u Pflanzen für selbst Industrie Culturen kann ich auch nicht mehr unterhalten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Im</hi>
               </seg> Garten hatte ich selbst durch den Stab in Correspondenzen u literarischen Arbeiten Vorhülfe welche ich seither entbehren musste.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auf Ihre hoffnungsvollen Söhne müssen Sie recht stolz sein!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass Ihre liebe Gemahlin ganz wiedererstarkte, muss Sie recht beglücken. Dr Martin ist nun auch schon dahingeschieden! u seine Witwe beinahe unversorgt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Christmas</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">1879</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Private</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your so kindly meant letter, dear fellowcountryman, has only made me even sadder in my troubled and depressed mood, and you must permit me to put before <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>, the scientific friend, again in a letter what I explained verbally, when I had the good fortune to meet you and your good wife here, since even <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> have let yourself be completely misled in respect to my present position.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May I then be permitted to repeat once again and without exaggeration, that I am almost completely <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ruined</hi>
               </seg> socially, financially and domestically, and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from a literary aspect</hi>
               </seg> no longer able to produce half as much since they took the garden from me so cruelly (the only thing which I had in life). Who has it been then, best of friends, who has misled you so completely? It must have been someone who is interested in keeping me down and retarding the progress of my research!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My raw materials and my observation materials are <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mainly</hi>
               </seg> in the garden and among the living plants! What would Hooker have done, if Ayrton had succeeded in pushing him out of Kew?<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See MacLeod (1974).</p>
               </note> The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Botanical Magazine</seg> would have had to cease immediately and he could no longer have produced the glorious reports, the last of which we just now have before us. How should <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">he</hi>
               </seg>, outside Kew, have justified his position as Government Botanist in England? How should he have given his investigations practical value even in the herbarium? No! Better I must express myself towards you freely, lest you <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">worked</hi>
               </seg> in fact really into the hands of my enemies and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">that</hi>
               </seg> you do not want. The place of a government botanist is <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
               </seg> the botanical garden and not outside it. He needs, especially for the industries of new colonies, his <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">living</hi>
               </seg> plants much more than the dry herbarium. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">In</hi>
               </seg> the garden are the operational funds necessary for me, the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">staff</hi>
               </seg> trained by me, the necessary buildings. The intruder,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">William Guilfoyle.</p>
               </note> who with the help of his cousin (the minister of the time<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. J. Casey.</p>
               </note>) overthrew me late in life into undeserved misfortune, has even had my laboratory torn down, so that I certainly shall not continue to work in it and my laboratory apparatus brought together over the years is also taken from me! Therefore I have had <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>
               </seg> in the Philadelphia Exhibition, nothing in the last Paris, nothing in Vienna, nothing in Sydney and will also now have nothing in Melbourne!<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Centennial Exposition, Philadelphia, 1876; Exposition Universelle, Paris, 1878; Weltausstellung [International Exhibition], Vienna, 1873; International Exhibition, Sydney, 1879-80; International Exhibition, Melbourne, 1880-1. </p>
               </note> How can I <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">without</hi>
               </seg> a department produce anything useful for the country? than perhaps a collection of dried plants, which would be of almost no importance at all! O God! how the times have changed unhappily for me. When quite a young man I was already Commissioner for the first Paris Exhibition,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Exposition Universelle, Paris, 1855.</p>
               </note> to which I among others sent eucalyptus oil, that now is exported <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">by the barrel</hi>
               </seg>. Since I was driven out of my creation and thrown on the street, I am of course excluded from all commissions and a quite uneducated gardener, who simply copies the Sydney <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">flower</hi>
               </seg> garden (because he never saw anything else in his life) is the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">colleague</hi>
               </seg> of Hooker (<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not I</hi>
               </seg>), and this unworthy person can not only daily give himself airs before the public with <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
               </seg> treasures, with the help of the assistants schooled for years by me, he can send things for the exhibitions from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
               </seg> plants raised for 25 years, as you have noticed in Sydney.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So much of my sense of honour and professional pride still remain that I will leave Melbourne during the months of the Exhibition, since as <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">deposed garden director</hi>
               </seg> I would certainly not like to be presented to the great scholars from other countries and be a laughing stock! No! <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">That</hi>
               </seg> I cannot, especially since they deliberately refused me all means of cultivation, so that I cannot enter into competition with the Sydney nurseryman. Admittedly the present ministry, which is not unfriendly disposed to me, has offered me ten (I say 10) acres of the 2000 acre park and garden land of the Lands Department around Melbourne, but because I planted annually at the rate of 30 acres and they would give me almost no means of production at all, I have declined this!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What would <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> feelings be, noble friend, if the cousin of a minister there suddenly took your museum from you and under such outrageous insults, that you could <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">never</hi>
               </seg> again set foot in it; if such an intruder continued working with your staff without bringing knowledge with him, and you were deprived of your official dwelling, and were to support your position in the scientific world wretchedly from the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">salary</hi>
               </seg> and some small means!, whereas <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> former means for the museum were trebled or quadrupled from nepotism!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am completely reduced to poverty, cannot even keep a collector any longer, and so even the "<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Fragmenta</hi>
               </seg>" has not appeared for almost 2 years. This can of course only <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">please</hi>
               </seg> Hooker, since he did <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> wish that anyone worked independently on plants in British colonies. The <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Eucalyptus</hi>
               </seg> Atlas, the only activity of my last years, is based mainly on the observations of earlier years, and even for that I am deprived of my rich collection of about 60 species of euc. that I cultivated in the garden, and that now for the most part have made way for common lawn, such as you see on every bowling green and cricket ground.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is no similar case in the whole recent history of science, that a man in my position was <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">undeservedly</hi>
               </seg> trodden into the dust. But I am a German! My correspondence and literary work, as far as such can still briefly be continued, I will carry out in a small "cottage", that I purchased through a building society, and for which I still have to pay for years! Wittstein was translated <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">already in the garden</hi>
               </seg> and it cost me the savings of two years to pay for the printing.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Wittstein (1878), i.e. B78.06.09.</p>
               </note> Of course almost nothing from the work has been saleable.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not intend to go to Sydney.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Haast and his wife visited the International Exhibition, Sydney, in September 1879, returning to NZ in November.</p>
               </note> What good is it for me to show myself there <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">without the garden</hi>
               </seg>? I certainly could not make practical use of possible new experiences, and it would only be <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">embarrassing</hi>
               </seg> for me, to see myself removed from all practical collaboration. Excuse me that I speak so frankly, but if even you, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">the scientific countryman</hi>
               </seg>, take up the words of my enemies, admittedly unknowingly, then it is so much less to think any longer of the building of an honourable department, and I have certainly still "hoped against hope". <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">In</hi>
               </seg> the garden I would have been able to accomplish even double as much <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from a literary aspect</hi>
               </seg>, and now it must happen for the most part at the expense of that private means from which I would so gladly have founded a household and family happiness, but even <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">that</hi>
               </seg> they begrudged me here. In my case, friend, it is not merely a matter of feeling, but <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ruin</hi>
               </seg>! and you have let yourself be deceived, when you now write "I would <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> have lost my honourable position!"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So we will probably never see one another again in life. May you and your wife accept the acknowledgement of your kindness of many previous years, and may the new year bring you and your splendid family very much joy.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I can also no longer undertake exchange of seeds and plants for even industrial cultivation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">In</hi>
               </seg> the garden I even had preliminary help by the staff in correspondence and literary work which since then I have had to do without.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You must be very proud of your promising sons!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You must be very pleased that your dear wife has grown quite strong again. Dr Martin<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Probably Lawrence Joseph Martin, MD (Melbourne), LRCS (Edinburgh), whose death at Cannes, France, on 19 January 1879 was noted in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australian medical journal</seg>, April 1879, p. 204.</p>
               </note> has now departed this world too! and his widow nearly unprovided for.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
