<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>INSTRUCTIONS FURNISHED TO SCIENTIFIC OBSERVERS ATTACHED TO THE VICTORIAN EXPLORING EXPEDITION — SURVEYOR, ASTRONOMER, METEOROLOGIST, GEOLOGIST, MINERALOGIST, ZOOLOGIST, AND BOTANIST. ¶ INSTRUCTIONS FO...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1860/60-09-03-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>60.09.03</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>INSTRUCTIONS FURNISHED TO SCIENTIFIC OBSERVERS ATTACHED TO THE VICTORIAN EXPLORING EXPEDITION — SURVEYOR, ASTRONOMER, METEOROLOGIST, GEOLOGIST, MINERALOGIST, ZOOLOGIST, AND BOTANIST. ¶ INSTRUCTIONS FO...</title>
               <date when="1860-09-03">1860-09-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1860/60-09-03-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Pandanus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>tab alignment</term>
               <term>even tabulation</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Robert O'Hara Burke</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">INSTRUCTIONS FURNISHED TO SCIENTIFIC OBSERVERS ATTACHED TO THE VICTORIAN EXPLORING EXPEDITION — SURVEYOR, ASTRONOMER, METEOROLOGIST, GEOLOGIST, MINERALOGIST, ZOOLOGIST, AND BOTANIST. ¶ INSTRUCTIONS FO...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">60.09.03</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Robert O'Hara Burke</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The text given here is from B61.14.02. For MS drafts of these instructions see MS 13071 Royal Society of Victoria Exploration Committee records, box 2082/3(b) &amp; box 2088B/5, La Trobe Australian Manuscripts Collection, State Library of Victoria, Melbourne. Minor editorial changes were made to the draft for publication. The draft copy is signed by the Honorary Secretary of the Exploration Committee, J. Macadam. The date is taken from the MS draft of the instructions.</p>
               </note>INSTRUCTIONS FURNISHED TO SCIENTIFIC OBSERVERS ATTACHED TO THE VICTORIAN EXPLORING EXPEDITION — SURVEYOR, ASTRONOMER, METEOROLOGIST, GEOLOGIST, MINERALOGIST, ZOOLOGIST, AND BOTANIST.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">INSTRUCTIONS FOR THE SURVEYOR, ASTRONOMICAL AND METEOROLOGICAL OBSERVER</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Every opportunity should be taken to ascertain the geographical position of the party, referring it to some well marked point, as offered by an easily recognizable mountain, the junction of rivers, creeks, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">2. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This should be done by astronomical observations, as well as by dead reckoning.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The dead reckoning always to commence with the last good, reliable astronomical observations made.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">3. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For determining the Latitude, the different methods to be chosen depend entirely upon circumstances, and it is only mentioned here that observations on sun, moon, and stars will have to be used.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">4. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The determination of the Longitude should be effected by lunar distances; if with stars, eastern and western distances should invariably be taken when possible, and the longitude should be derived from both sets. These observations, as well as those on latitude, should always be reduced immediately after the observations, or at least as soon after as possible. The longitude should further be ascertained whenever an opportunity occurs by occultation of stars, by eclipses of the sun, moon, and Jupiter's satellites. There is no necessity, however, for reducing these observations while on the journey, as it would be impossible to devote that amount of care to this work without interfering with the more essential work, and which would be desirable; and the original observations should, as early as possible, be clearly copied with ink, in a book, with every fact necessary for the subsequent reduction.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">5. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All astronomical phenomena of particular interest should be observed, if the means at the disposal of the astronomer do admit of such observation, and if these should not interfere with the general progress of the Expedition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">6. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The variations of the Compass must be observed as often as circumstances permit.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">7. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Observations on the Zodiacal Light may be made with great facility and advantage for science. The limits of the phenomenon should be traced upon a good map of stars, and afterwards taken from it and noted in a note-book.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">8. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A good look out should be kept for Meteors; the declination and right ascension of the beginning and end of their courses, with exact time and accompanying circumstances, should be noted. Particular attention should be paid to meteors near the Zodiac.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">9. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Whenever a permanent camp is to be erected, a systematic registration on meteorology should at once be carried on. The hours of registration are to be as numerous as possible. The hours 6 a.m., 9 a.m., 3 p.m., and 9 p.m. being obligatory. The registrations should extend over the following elements:—</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pressure of air, observed with the mercurial barometer, and, in case of an accident happening to the instrument, then with the best aneroid in the camp. The aneroids should be compared with the mercurial barometer whenever they are to be taken out for taking measurements of heights, or for conducting meteorological observations in a branch expedition. They ought to be compared again as soon as they are returned to the main camp.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The aneroids to be observed in a horizontal position.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the case of measurements of heights, Lamont's hypsometrical tables should be used.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Temperature of air and evaporation are to be observed with Munich hygrometer, in the large portable meteorological stand.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Direction and force of wind, by the astronomical meridian, and by Beaufort's notations.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Amount and form of clouds, and direction of the upper current.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Duration and intensity of rain, dew, hail, &amp;c.; solar radiation and terrestrial radiation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An exact register should be kept on all remarkable phenomena in meteorology, as whirlwinds, storms, thunderstorms, mirage, refraction, twinkling of stars, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">10. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>While travelling, the aneroids and the small hygrometer should be easily accessible, so that without any delay the observations can be made at the hours above mentioned, such observations to be used afterwards for computing the height of the ground passed over.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The temperature of rivers, creeks, lakes, and wells should be observed on the surface, and with the help of the sounding thermometer on the bottom. Should gases arise from the depth, they should be caught in small glasses prepared for the purpose, in order to have them analysed afterwards.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">11. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Particular attention should be paid to the direction of the flights of birds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">12. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Magnetical observations, in addition to the determination of the variation of the compass, should be carried out whenever an opportunity offers, though without interfering with the main object of the Expedition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">13. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The work connected with the topographical survey requires hardly any further remarks, but that everything should be done as minutely and accurately as possible, and that all more strictly called scientific observations should be subordinate to the mapping of the country.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">GEOLOGICAL, MINERALOGICAL, AND NATURAL HISTORY OBSERVER.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">GEOLOGY.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Diary to be kept regularly, and all observations made during the day to be entered before the next day, and as soon as possible after the camp is pitched for the night, and the necessary duties connected with camping, attention to stock, &amp;c., are completed. This to be, in all cases, determined by the Leader.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>General Heads of Diary —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1. Distance and course travelled.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. Number, character, distance apart, and general trend or fall of all watercourses or drainage channels crossed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. Quality of water, if any, in such courses or channels. To ascertain the nature of the salts in saline or other mineral waters, a certain quantity might be evaporated, and the deposited matter collected for chemical examination.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4. Mode of occurrence of water: springs, lakes, pools, or running streams, with average depth of ditto.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. Indications relative to probable permanence or otherwise of ditto, also of periodical floods.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6. Geological, physical, and mineral character of the banks and beds of streams, lakes, &amp;c., and also of the intervening and adjacent country. If composed of tertiary deposits of mud, clay, sand, or gravel, note nature of such, whether stratified or irregular accumulations, also mineral character, stating the nature and relative proportions of the materials, whether limestone, sandstone, quartz rock, quartz, or other rock fragments, sedimentary or igneous, or much waterworn. If composed of removed rocks, state probable geological age of such; if stratified and undoubtedly in situ, average direction and angle of dip (noted thus: D. N. 10° E. 15°), also probable thickness and relative geological position of different formations (conformable or otherwise) of igneous rocks, whether intrusive or contemporaneous.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7. Indications or presence of organic remains to be carefully sought for and noted, also of mineral veins, coal seams, lignite beds, &amp;c.; date and locality of such researches, with the time so occupied to be stated.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">MINERALOGY AND FOSSILS.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>8. Specimens: rock, minerals, and fossils. All specimens to be numbered consecutively, and entered with a corresponding number in a book kept for that purpose, with the locality and date of collection, and a short description of each. The numbers also to be entered in the diary, on the day of collection (thus: June 15, 1860, specimens 1 to 20, stating whether rock, mineral, or fossil).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>9. As geological specimens are difficult to transport, owing to their weighty character, it is desirable that only such as are new or doubtful should be collected, and these should be as small as possible for the purpose of examination and recognition; also that whenever an accurate description, or sketch, or both can be made to answer, they should be resorted to in preference to adding unnecessarily to the bulk and weight of the collection.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In all cases the gross weight of the specimens that can be taken, must be subject to the approval and control of the leader.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>10. Rock specimens should in all cases be abandoned in favor of either minerals, fossils, or recent natural history specimens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>11. All specimens that it may be found necessary or deemed expedient to abandon, should be marked off in the catalogue, and the date and cause for their being so abandoned stated.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If fossil or recent natural history, sketches of them should, if possible, be retained.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">MAPS.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>12. A tracing of the route, as laid down by the Surveyor, should be furnished daily, if possible, to the geological and other scientific officers, to enable them to mark the approximate position of their observations. To effect this rapidly, the daily observations in the journal should be numbered, and a corresponding number placed on the map at the point where the observation was made, or to which it refers.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Boundaries of different rocks or geological formations crossed on the line of route, should be marked on the map.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">SKETCHES.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>13. The observations, whenever practicable, should be copiously illustrated by sketches, with the number of the specimen or observation in the journal to which they refer attached.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A sketch of each camp and its environs should, if possible, be make before quitting it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sketches of all remarkable geological sections are desirable, also outline views of mountain ranges, remarkable hills, and other physical features on either side of the line of route; also of all objects of natural history and natives (aborigines).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>14. All views should be numbered and dated with the time of day, the position whence they were taken marked on the map, and the compass bearing, and estimated distance given of the extreme points embraced in each.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">ZOOLOGY.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Zoologist, in addition to all general observations which he may be able to make on all classes of animals that may occur to him, illustrated by sketches, is particularly required to ascertain, when possible, the fishes, shells, or articulata occurring in any stagnant or running waters met with, as these are of the highest interest in connection with questions of the geographical distribution of animals.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No duplicate specimens that might encumber the party need be collected. Of fossil animals, if any should be noted, it would be very desirable to secure characteristic specimens. The larger fishes may be skinned, by the removal of one-half of the fish, leaving the fins of the mid-line perfect; if then washed with solution of corrosive sublimate in spirit, the specimen can be packed flat between papers without injury.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The soft Annelida and small Crustacea, as well as the soft parts of Mollusca, should be inclosed in vessels of spirits, the specimens separated by portions of linen cloth to prevent their being injured by shaking. Paper labels, written with black lead pencil, will remain uninjured with specimens so packed. As a general rule, every specimen collected should receive one of a consecutive series of numbers (irrespective of the natural series of the objects), by which it should be indicated in the journal of the day, in which all particulars observed about it or illustrative sketches should appear.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In case a specimen of actually or doubtfully the same species be obtained for the second or third time, at some subsequent dates from its first entry in the journal, there is no objection to its receiving a new number in connection with any additional observations which may be made, in cases where loss of time would result from endeavouring to ascertain the first number applied to the series.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of Mammalia, the nocturnal ones, as bats, and the small murine forms, are the most interesting, and should receive particular attention.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No opportunity should be lost to obtain through the officer in charge of depôts, or through reconnoitering parties, additional specimens of rocks, fossils, minerals, and natural history.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It will be of vast importance to ascertain, as extensively as possible, what relation the vegetation bears to its geological formation.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">BOTANICAL OBSERVER.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">For the purpose of elucidating to the fullest extent the phytology of any part of Australia to be explored by the Victorian expedition, it is recommended that the Botanist attached to the caravan should keep a diary, in which the principal botanical features of the country should be noted, and into which any plant, either remarkable or observed for the first time, should be introduced under the same number or designation by which it is distinguished in the herbarium.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To the specimens which will be collected, and which should be pressed into paper always immediately, and dried as speedily as circumstances will permit, a label should be fixed, containing a note of the day of collecting, the habitat of the plant, the soil of the locality, the color and perhaps odour of the flower, the nature of the bark and of the wood of any arboreous species, the size of the plants, and any other characteristics which cannot be derived from the examination of the dried specimens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>These, when dried, it will be desirable should be well secured against pressure and moisture, and the thus formed collections should be forwarded to the Secretary of the Exploration Committee, always at the very earliest opportunity afforded for transmission.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To such selections of botanical specimens might be added any well matured seeds collected on the journey, which should either be numbered corresponding to the specimens of the herbarium, or be accompanied by leaves, flowers, and seed-vessels, for the purpose of recognizing the species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Samples of gums, resins, barks, and any other vegetable substances, likely to be of technical, or economical, or medicinal use, should be gathered and labelled in such a manner as to facilitate specific determination.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No opportunity should be lost to obtain through the officer in charge of depôts, or through reconnoitering parties, additional specimens of plants and seeds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Particular attention is directed to the necessity of closely examining the Pandani and Palms which are likely to be met with within the tropics; and since it will be difficult to procure the large fruits of the former, and since the determination of the species greatly depends on the habit of the plants, it would be of great advantage to have, through the artist of the expedition, sketches of the outlines of these rare trees secured, and the flowers and fruits fully delineated.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It will be of vast importance to ascertain, as extensively as possible, what relation the vegetation of the country bears to its geological formation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of any plants suspected to have been deleterious to either horses or dromedaries, such a quantity should be dried as will suffice for chemical analysis, and any experiments to be instituted thereafter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of plants which may prove of utility for food or otherwise, or which are drawn into use by the natives, more particularly, information is sought.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">GENERAL INSTRUCTIONS FOR SCIENTIFIC OBSERVERS.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Scientific observations or work that would cause hindrance, or otherwise interfere with the progress or necessary work of the expedition, never to be undertaken if contrary to the instructions of the Leader.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All specimens, journals, sketches, maps, or other documents, to be exclusively the property of the Royal Society, on behalf of the Government of Victoria; and on no pretence whatever are either specimens or copies of the said documents to be given away, or forwarded privately to any person, or even officially, except through the Leader, although it is intended that each observer should, on publication of the results of the expedition, receive the credit due to him for his observations.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All scientific, or other documents, journals, &amp;c., relating to the expedition, to be at all times accessible to the Leader.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M, F. McCoy, G. Neumayer and A. Selwyn were elected at a meeting of the Exploration Committee on 10 August 1860 to a subcommittee to draw up letters of instruction for the scientific staff of the Burke &amp; Wills expedition. Presumably M, who was not present at the meeting on 10 August, was particularly responsible for the Botanist's section because at an Exploration Committee meeting of 16 August it was agreed that letters be written to M and Neumayer requesting them to forward letters of instruction relating to their departments as soon as possible (MS 13071 Royal Society of Victoria Exploration Committee records, box 2088B/1, La Trobe Australian Manuscripts Collection, State Library of Victoria, Melbourne).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pandanus">Pandanus</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
