<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir—  ¶  ¶ Having but recently returned from the south-eastern frontiers of Gipps Land, ¶  it was not until this day that my attention was directed to a letter, published in The Herald on 29th Sept., ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1860/60-10-19-proofed.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>60.10.19</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Sir—  ¶  ¶ Having but recently returned from the south-eastern frontiers of Gipps Land, ¶  it was not until this day that my attention was directed to a letter, published in The Herald on 29th Sept., ...</title>
               <date when="1860-10-19">1860-10-19</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1860/60-10-19-proofed.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of the Herald</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sir—  ¶  ¶ Having but recently returned from the south-eastern frontiers of Gipps Land, ¶  it was not until this day that my attention was directed to a letter, published in The Herald on 29th Sept., ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">60.10.19</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Editor of the Herald</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg> (Melbourne), 20 October 1860, p. 5 (B60.10.02). <seg style="">The</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; "> South Australian register</seg> (25 October 1860, p. 3), in republishing M's letter, wrote: 'Dr. Mueller, it will be seen, even without knowing the particulars of Mr. Stuart's journey, has taken up the cudgels in his defence.' </p>
               </note>Sir— </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Having but recently returned from the south-eastern frontiers of Gipps Land,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> it was not until this day that my attention was directed to a letter, published in The Herald on 29th Sept.,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg> (Melbourne), 29 September 1860, p. 5, under the heading ‘Mr. Stuart’s Exploration’, carried a letter signed ‘R. D.’ that argued that it would have been ‘a physical impossibility’ for Stuart to have reached a position as far north as he claimed, and then to have returned to the settled districts, in the time available. The letter also disparaged the small size of Stuart’s party, insinuating that such a small group could not possibly have achieved what was claimed.</p>
               </note> to which a strong feeling for justice prompts me to offer a few remarks in reply.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Although I am not aware of the exact time when Mr. Stuart actually commenced the harassing task, so gloriously achieved, of crossing the continent, I am under the impression, that he awaited on Chambers's Creek<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>SA.</p>
               </note> the commencement of the cool season, as the most favourable for traversing the interior. If Mr. Stuart struck out on his noble path in the beginning of April, he would have had sufficient time available to reach the position which he assigns to the most northern point gained in his exploration, and thence to return to the outskirt settlements of South Australia, travelling at the ratio in which Mr. Gregory performed his journey from the lower Victoria River to Moreton Bay.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. during the final stage of the North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> We are well aware that Mr. Stuart must have expended considerable time in his repeated attempts to connect his survey with that of Mt Gregory towards Central Australia.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'The expedition had actually penetrated a hundred miles further north … than Gregory, in his North Australian Expedition, to the south, effecting for all practical purposes the crossing of the Continent' (Threadgill [1922], p. 53). For Stuart's diary see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Adelaide</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">observer</seg>, 15 December 1860, pp 3S-4S.</p>
               </note> Yet it must also not be forgotten, when comparing the relative lengths of Mr. Gregory's and Mr. Stuart's tracks, that the former gentleman's journey involved also many delays in fruitless endeavours to adopt with safety a less circuitous course than that excellent leader was able to take. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nor ought we, in estimating the possible celerity of travelling in the interior, be unmindful that the smallest party, if favoured by circumstances, is likely to make the most rapid progress— indeed, the safety of the party often depends on such rapid strides as to render the collecting of the scattered tribes of the nomades impossible around them.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That a strong party is not absolutely necessary for traversing the Australian interior,—to however much danger a few isolated travellers may be exposed— is fully demonstrated by facts which I scarcely need here record. Captain Sturt had but a solitary companion <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">alon</seg>e the main lines of his last journey. Eyre toiled for hundreds of miles alone, <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">reconnoitreing</seg> the barren solitudes at Lake Torrens,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>SA.</p>
               </note> in advance of his party, and rounded finally the Great Bight, accompanied by but one native. Mr. Augustus Gregory performed his most difficult journeys even amongst hordes of hostile natives but very few companions, and but three out of his party were his followers to Termination Lake.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now Lake Gregory, WA, the furthest point inland reached during the North Australian Exploring Expedition.</p>
               </note> The graphic account of some of the incidents given lately of Mr Stuart's journey, accord well with what we experienced in Northern Australia. The signal columns of smoke, which call the black warriors together against what they always consider invaders, arose frequently around us when traversing the country around the Gulf of Carpentaria, and it was within 200 miles of the spot where Mr. Stuart encountered the fiery attacks of the natives, that Mr. Gregory's party narrowly escaped destruction by a nightly attack of the natives.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the early morning of 5 September 1856, during the North Australian Exploring Expedition, Gregory’s party was attacked by a band of Aborigines while crossing the Leichhardt River near the Gulf of Carpentaria.</p>
               </note> The very fact that a traveller has been able to retrace his steps over a wide tract of unexplored country, is sufficient evidence that his positions must have been carefully ascertained, and that his charts must have been constructed with a considerable amount of exactness, landmarks being but too often wanting for guidance, and the lives of the travellers too frequently depending on solitary waterholes. Mr. J. Macdouall Stuart's well-known name as an experienced surveyor is, moreover, a further guarantee of the exactness of the charts, with which he will enrich Australian geography. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is a source of deep regret, that whilst every true friend of progress of Australian discovery, hailed Mr. Stuart's triumphant return with feelings of unmingled delight, that he and the generous man, who largely if not entirely was actuated by a rare cosmopolitan disinterestedness in fostering this noble enterprise, should have disturbed the pure joy of their successes. Mr. James Chambers, of Adelaide, has set our patricians a rare example. Now in gratitude to the prolific gifts of youthful Australia, a tribute should be paid on her altar. Although the late enterprises of Stuart have involved the expenditure of thousands, yet the magnanimity of their promoter is by no means exhausted, and Mr. Stuart will again rely, to a great extent, on his former private support, well seconded by the South Australian Government.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The SA government voted £2,500 to provide an escort for Stuart on his next journey, still supported by James Chambers, who effectively vetoed the appointment of a scientific officer (Threadgold [1922], pp. 53-60).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Whilst to John Macdouall Stuart the palm of merit is due, of having virtually crossed the continent from north to south, inasmuch as even now the enterprise of the squatters would enable them to bring their herds on a short route from Lake Torrens to the fertile pastures of Amheim's Land, whenever that fine tract of Australia becomes colonized, the main goal of geographical discoveries lies now in the western part of the continent. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thence we see Major Warburton with his slender party, bend now courageously his path. Thence, to a wide field for decennial exertions we trust the Victorian expedition<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Burke and Wills expedition, then in the field.</p>
               </note> will strike out for glorious achievements, adopting Columbus's call — ' To the westward.' </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain, Mr. Editor, most regardfully yours, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanical and Zoological Garden, 19th October, 1860. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
