<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>2/5/76 ¶  ¶ For a long time, dear friend, it was my intention to write to you and if it did not happen, it was not lack of recollection of you and all your long-standing kindness, but rather the reaso...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1876/76-05-02-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Bolander correspondence, University and Jepson Herbaria Archives, University of California, Berkeley, California.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>76.05.02</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>2/5/76 ¶  ¶ For a long time, dear friend, it was my intention to write to you and if it did not happen, it was not lack of recollection of you and all your long-standing kindness, but rather the reaso...</title>
               <date when="1876-05-02">1876-05-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1876/76-05-02-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Henry Bolander</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">2/5/76 ¶  ¶ For a long time, dear friend, it was my intention to write to you and if it did not happen, it was not lack of recollection of you and all your long-standing kindness, but rather the reaso...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">76.05.02</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Henry Bolander</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Bolander correspondence, University and Jepson Herbaria Archives, University of California, Berkeley, California.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">2/5/76</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit langer Zeit, theuerer Freund, war es meine Absicht Ihnen zu schreiben, und wenn es nicht geschah, so war es nicht Mangel an Rückerinnerung an Sie und alle Ihre vieljährige Güte; sondern vielmehr der Grund meines Schweigens lag in den für mein Departement seit den letzten drei Jahren elenden Verhältnissen. Der Beamte hier ist ein Spielball politischer Verhältnisse, und bei einer fast militärischen Disciplin gegen Übergriffe aller Art, die nicht einmal den Soldaten treffen, gänzlich machtlos und wird den Freunden und Anhängen der Leute die zu Zeiten Macht haben aufgeopfert. Doch sei es genug; bei Ihnen ist es ja wenig besser.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So wie die Sachen hier standen war es nutzlos an weiteren Austausch zu denken, zumal nachdem ich ein ganzes Vermögen dem Departement aufgeopfert hatte u mein Haus verödet blieb. Jetzt habe ich einen verständigeren und gerechteren Minister, so dass neue Hoffnungen mir aufleuchten, u ich den Muth erlange, die Correspondenzen wieder aufzunehmen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit dieser Monats-Post sende ich Ihnen Samen einiger <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">west</hi>
               </seg> Austr. Eucalypten, die bei Ihnen wahrscheinlich noch nicht gezogen sind, auch einige Druckschriften.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Freund Philippi schreibt mir,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> dass er so gütig gewesen sei, wieder eine Anzahl Museum Pflanzen an mich abzusenden, und dass er für die Weiterbeförderung Ihre gütige Hülfe angerufen habe. Nehmen Sie im Voraus meinen Dank hin, für die davon entstehenden Mühen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bis jetzt scheint aber die Sendung nicht angekommen zu sein. Es ist gut, stets <seg>-</seg> wie Sie es gethan <seg>-</seg> einen Folgezettel von dem Agenten oder dem Schiffer zu erlangen. Dadurch, dass der eherwürdige Miers dies vor einigen Jahren versaumte, und ebenso Hance es neulich unterliess, sind deren beträchtliche Sendungen mich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">spurlos</hi>
               </seg> verloren gegangen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nützt es, dass ich Ihnen getrocknete Pflanzen sende, oder haben Sie kein allgemeines Herb. In meinem Museum is die Vegetation Californiens bisher nur sehr dürftig vertreten. Indess Sie haben genug <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>sonst zu thun, und ich will Sie nicht plagen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sämereien Ihrer schönen Bäume und Zierpflanzen hätte ich eben gar sehr gern, und ich bin auch in der Lage etwas Gutes zurückzusenden. Haben Sie zu den Herrlichkeiten Mexicos vordringen können?! Ich wäre so sehr gern unterrichtet über den speciellen Nutzen der verschiedenen Eichen und andere werthvollen Bäume der <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">kühleren</hi>
               </seg> Gegenden Mexicos, was sich wohl durch einige intelligente Landsleute dort erlangen liesse, dan solche etwaige Notizen mit getrockneten Pflanzen begleiten könnten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Noch eins, Bester, u dann will ich schliessen. Liessen sich meine 4 Abhandlungen über Industrie Pflanzen in den 4 Bänden unserer Accl. Gesellschaft nicht dort in Buchform neu geordnet drucken lassen. Ich verlange kein honorar. Da diese Notizen in ihrer Art einzig dastehen und für Californien u die südl Staaten den […] […] ebenso nützlich als hier sind, so sollte sich doch wohl ein Verlager dort finden.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Oberst Warren würde darum rathen können</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 0in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich konnte die vier Bände nochmals senden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">2/5/76</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a long time, dear friend, it was my intention to write to you and if it did not happen, it was not lack of recollection of you and all your long-standing kindness, but rather the reason for my silence lay in the wretched conditions for my department for almost the last three years. The public servant here is a plaything of political circumstances and completely powerless against undue interference of all kinds with an almost militaristic discipline that not even soldiers are subject to, and is sacrificed to friends and supporters of people who have power at the time. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>But let that be enough, I am sure it is little better with you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As things stand here, it was useless to think of further exchange, especially after I had sacrificed my whole fortune to the department and my house remained desolate. Now I have a more reasonable and more just minister, so that new hopes revive me and I acquire courage to come back to correspondence again.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By this month's post I am sending you seeds of some <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">west</hi>
               </seg> Australian eucalypts that are probably not yet grown at your place, also some publications.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Friend Philippi writes to me that he, so kindly, has sent me a number of museum plants again and that he has called on your kind assistance for the further dispatch.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. Philippi was based in Chile and evidently sent things to M via California, there being no direct postal route across the south Pacific.</p>
               </note> Accept my thanks in advance for the trouble arising from this.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So far, however, the consignment seems not to have arrived. It is good, always <seg>-</seg> as you have done <seg>-</seg> to obtain a docket from the agents or the shipper. Thanks to the worthy Miers neglecting this some years ago and also Hance neglecting it recently, their important consignments to me are lost without trace.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Is it useful if I send you dried plants, or do you not have a general herbarium. In my museum the vegetation of California is only very poorly represented so far. However, you have enough to do otherwise and I do not want to trouble you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But I would like seeds of your beautiful trees and ornamental plants very much, and I am also in the position to send something good in return. Have you been able to advance on the splendors of Mexico?! I would so very gladly be informed about the special uses of the various oaks and other valuable trees of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">cooler</hi>
               </seg> regions of Mexico, that could probably be obtained through some intelligent farmer there while such eventual notes could be accompanied by dried plants.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>One thing more, my dear sir, and then I will close. Could my four monographs on industrial plants in the four volumes of our Acclimatisation Society not be published there in book form newly arranged.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Four essays by M were republished in E. Cooper (1876); see B76.07.04, B76.07.05, B76.07.06 and B76.07.07.</p>
               </note> I expect no honorarium. As these notes in their form stand alone and are just as useful for California and the southern states as here, then they should probably find a publisher.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Colonel Warren would be able to advise about it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I could send the four volumes again.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
