<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, ¶ 7. May 1883. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Undersecretary. ¶ Sir...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1883/83-05-07-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Z83/4641, unit 1407, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>83.05.07</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, ¶ 7. May 1883. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Undersecretary. ¶ Sir...</title>
               <date when="1883-05-07">1883-05-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1883/83-05-07-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteSymbol</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plantnames</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Thomas Wilson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, ¶ 7. May 1883. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Undersecretary. ¶ Sir...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">83.05.07</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Thomas Wilson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Z83/4641, unit 1407, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">7. May 1883.</p>
            <p rend="letter" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">T. R. Wilson Esqr</p>
            <p rend="letter" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">Undersecretary.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reply to your letter N. 1689<seg rend="FootnoteSymbol" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">See T. Wilson to M, 28 April 1883. James Thomson, Secretary to the Victorian Commission for the Calcutta International Exhibition, 1883-84, wrote to the Chief Secretary, G. Berry, on 28 April 1883: 'I have the honour by direction of the president, Joseph Bosisto, Esqr M.P. to state that a special effort is being made to ensure a thorough representation of the indigenous products of Victoria at the forthcoming international Exhibition at Calcutta, and the Commission will be glad to receive the assistance of the Government Botanist in the matter. It is proposed to form collections of seeds, dried plants, &amp;c and at the close of the Exhibition to present them to various public institutions in India, with the view of obtaining analogous collections in exchange. The high scientific attainments and world-wide reputation of Baron von Muëller would combine to greatly enhance the value of any such collection which might be forwarded from the colony, and the Commission trusts therefore that you will be so good as to invite his co-operation in the direction indicated.' The Under Secretary, T. Wilson, immediately referred this letter to M with a covering letter. M to T. Wilson 11 May 1883 (in this edition as 83-05-11a) returned the file referring to the letter above (Y83/4315, unit 1407, VPRS 3991/P, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>PROV).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I beg to inform the honorable the Chief Secretary, that I shall in accordance with his wish endeavour to bring together as many industrial articles, as may be within my reach departmentally or otherwise for the Calcutta Exhibition.<seg rend="FootnoteSymbol" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">International Exhibition, Calcutta, 1883-4.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>In an establishment like that, administrated by me, vegetable resources would claim my attention. Thus woodspecimens in a presentable form, Tan-material, Gums, Resin, fibres and other products and educts of plants would be got together, so far<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">as they really</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">represent articles or material for trade</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">and</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">export</hi>
               </seg>. Thus I would not advise, that indiscriminately seed-collections are made up for the Exhibition, as only a very small percentage of such seeds would represent mercantile goods. The same remark applies to fibres, of which only such would be chosen by me, as could be got for practical purposes in large quantity cheaply, and as would readily yield to manufactural processes at rope-work, in paper-mills, on looms &amp;c. Large numbers of samples might be prepared, if no restrictions are adopted, but such indiscriminate exhibits would be misleading to a great extent. I find it my duty, to point this out, as I should not aim at quantity, but<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">quality</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on occasions like this, and as it would be unwise to form collections, when only<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">selections</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>requisite. These are the principles, which guided me since I was a Commissioner and Exhibitor in 1854-1855 at the first Paris Exhibition.<seg rend="FootnoteSymbol" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">Exposition Universelle, Paris, 1855.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would propose to exhibit also a large Todea-fern at Calcutta, as no species of that genus occurs in India; but it will not likely be possible to obtain such exceptionally gigantic specimens, as were sent to the Amsterdam international and the Petersburg Horticultural Exhibition.<seg rend="FootnoteSymbol" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">Internationale Koloniale en Uitvoerhandel Tentoonstelling, Amsterdam, 1883; International Horticultural Exhibition, St Petersburg, 1883. See M to Messrs Watson &amp; Scull, 28 February 1883.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>A collection of dried plants could also be sent, or rather a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">selection</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of such, as would represent our best indigenous fodder-herbs, most nutritious grasses and leading technologic plants.</p>
            <p rend="letter" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As I have no longer any laboratory or apparatus, not the labor of a carpenter and other former auxiliaries available, it may be worthy of the consideration of the hon. the Chief Secretary, whether my vote, which is the smallest of all departmental establishments, could have added to it a modest item for the Calcutta Exhibition specially, the means at my disposal during the present finance year having proved quite insufficient, to carry effectually on the ordinary service along with the heavy extracalls on the departmental fund for the Amsterdam Exhibition.<seg rend="FootnoteSymbol" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">On 9 May Wilson returned the file to M 'with the request that he will be good enough to state what he estimates the outlay will be of sending a collection to the Calcutta Exhibition.' M replied 'I would respectfully suggest, that £140 be extra provided on the new estimates for special preparation of articles illustrative of Victorian vegetable resources for the Calcutta exhibition through the Gov. Botanists establishment. If my original complete Department was still available for me, I would not venture to ask for any subsidy at all' (M to T. Wilson 11 May 1883 (in this edition as <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>83-05-11a)).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be, Sir, your obedient</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.<seg rend="FootnoteSymbol" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">Wilson sent the file to the Chairman of the Commission along with a report from W. Guilfoyle, Curator of the Botanic Gardens, on 17 May and the Secretary, J. Thomson, returned it on 23 May with no indication of what action, if any, was proposed. However, estimates of 'miscellaneous' expenditure in the Chief Secretary's department for 1884 included £5,500 for 'expenses in connexion with the exhibition to be held at Calcutta' (<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Estimates of the revenue and expenditure for the year ending 30th June,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>1884, Victoria, Parliamentary paper no. B 2, p. 16). Expenditure of the grant was the responsibility of the Commissioners for the exhibition; their financial summary (Calcutta International Exhibition Commissioners (1884), p. 8) includes £509/7/7 for 'defraying cost of forming collections of indigenous products, mineral and geological specimens'.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Todea</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
