<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>18/6/83 ¶  ¶ You have honoured me very much, noble Friend, by translating my lecture about the vegetation of Australia in comparison to that of other countries into German and having it published in y...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1883/83-06-18-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>83.06.18</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>18/6/83 ¶  ¶ You have honoured me very much, noble Friend, by translating my lecture about the vegetation of Australia in comparison to that of other countries into German and having it published in y...</title>
               <date when="1883-06-18">1883-06-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1883/83-06-18-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ernst Behm</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">18/6/83 ¶  ¶ You have honoured me very much, noble Friend, by translating my lecture about the vegetation of Australia in comparison to that of other countries into German and having it published in y...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">83.06.18</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Ernst Behm</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">18/6/83.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben mich sehr geehrt, edler Freund, indem Sie meinen Vortrag über die Vegetation Australiens im Vergleich zu derjenigen anderer Länder ins Deutsche übersetzten und in Ihren berühmten "Mittheilungen" erscheinen lassen. Für diese Aufmerksamkeit und die damit verbundene Mühe bin ich Ihnen dankbar verpflichtet, auch dem ausgezeichneten Herrn Professor Drude für seine gütige Empfehlung bei dieser Gelegenheit. Diese literarische Arbeit wurde etwas überstürzt, da ich zur Zeit mit dem Termin mich übereilt fand, weil gerade damals neben gewöhnlichen Amtspflichten die Ausarbeitung <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>des "Census" der Pflanzen-Arten Australiens auf mir lastete. So wollte ich eigentlich auch über manche andere physiographische Beziehungen sprechen, und namentlich auch auf die Momente eingehen, welche neben der Wirkung des Golfstromes die ausserordentliche Verschiedenheit des Climas von West-Europa und Nordost-Amerika bedingen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit heutiger Post sende ich an Sie ein Exemplar ab eines kürzlich erschienen Werkes des (seitdem verstorbenen früheren Lands Ministers von Neu Süd Wallis) Hon. B. Wilson über die Lord Howe's Insel. Der Bericht mit den Photogrammen giebt Ihnen eine gute Idee von diesem riesigen Doppelfelsen isoliert im stillen Ocean. Hätte ich gewusst, dass dieses Buch erscheinen würde, so hätte ich ein Kapitel dafür liefern können über die dortige grossentheils endemische holzige Vegetation. Übrigens gab ich bereits im 9ten Bande der Fragm. phytogr. Austr. p.76-78 eine Herzählung der Lord Howe's Insel Pflanzen, welche sich dann (1875) auf 82 Vasculares belief, zu denen seither 5 Filices hinzukamen. In Sydney hat sich Anfangs dieses Monats eine geographische Gesellschaft für Ganz-Australien gebildet, und mir wurde unerwartet die Präsidentur angetragen. Aber in demselben Monat wurden mir auch 2 andere Präsidentursitze wichtiger Vereine anderer Tendenz in Victoria angeboten. Wie hoch ich diese Beweise der Aufmerksamkeit und des Vertrauens auch anschlage, fand ich mich doch veranlasst diese Ehrenämter abzulehnen, da mir neben meinen officiellen und literarischen Pflichten und einigem Aufwand von Zeit für Religion und Medicin nicht Musse genug bleibt, um thatsächlich die Interessen namentlich einer grossen geographischen Gesellschaft zu wahren. Wem jetzt der Vorsitz zufallen wird, weiss ich noch nicht; indessen habe ich der Sydney-Committee gerathen, Filiala in allen andern australischen Colonien zu errichten, und für jede Zweiganstalt einen Vicepräsidenten zu wählen, was auch angenommen wurde. Eine Organisation, wie diese neue, kann durch selbständige Mittel die Erforschung des noch nachbleibenden unbereisten Theiles Australiens beschleunigen, und eine der ersten Bestrebungen sollte sein, das Geschick Leichhardt's und seiner Begleiter aufzudecken.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit Ehrerbietung </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Unsere Colonien werden jetzt in den Welt Postverein treten, was unsere Verbindungen auch mit Deutschland vereinfachen wird.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The text that follows, which is in M's hand, is on a separate sheet that follows in the sequence in the file at this point, that may have been sent separately. A press cutting has been pasted on to the sheet, while M's text begins below this and continues over the sheet. The press cutting, which reads as follows, is headed 'The "Mueller River" of M'Kinlay'; the source, 'Queenslander March 10 1883', has been added in a hand other than M's:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.8264in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>SIR, — As an acknowledgment of the valuable services rendered by Baron F. von Mueller to the colonies, it would be a graceful act on the part of the Queensland Government if they restored to the maps the original name given by M'Kinlay to what is known as the Lower Diamantina. The Diamantina proper is that part of the river above the junction of the Western River. From the Western River downwards to the junction of the Herbert or Georgina was named the "Mueller" by the discoverer. When employed by the Ladies' Committee of Victoria to search for traces of Leichhardt, I had the fortune to meet with some of M'Kinlay's marked trees; these, when referred to his narrative, point to the fact that between the localities referred to the stream was named the Mueller. Surely it is not too late to amend the error, and by substituting "Mueller" for so much of the river (from junction of Western River to junction of Georgina), carry out M'Kinlay's intention to do honour to a gentleman of such high attainments. — I am, sir,</p>
                  <p rend="valediction"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">CHAS. W. DE BURGH BIRCH</p>
                  <p rend="letter"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.4929in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zelling, Aramac, 26th February</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Die Besitznahme Neu Guineas würde für Civilisation und Geographie eine grosse Errungenschaft sein, u. vielleicht könnte Grossbritannien den holländischen Theil der grossen Papuan Insel käuflich erwerben. Auch auf die Neu Hebriden und die Loyality Inseln hat man hier die Aufmerksamkeit gelenkt um Gewinn derselben für die englische Krone; alle diese Barbaren-Staaten u. namentlich auch alle in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Central-Afrika</hi>
               </seg>, wo durch Vogel, Beurmann, Heuglin, Barth, Nachtigall, Schweinfurth, Rolfs u. andere <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">deutsche</hi>
               </seg> Gelehrte, das deutsche Reich auf Territorial Erwerb das höchste Anrecht hat, sollten unter die Hoheit Europäischer Regierungen kommen, je eher um so besser für das Wohl der ganzen Welt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">18/6/83</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have honoured me very much, noble Friend, by translating my lecture about the vegetation of Australia in comparison to that of other countries into German and having it published in your celebrated <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.06.02, a translation of B82.13.07.</p>
               </note> I am grateful to you for this attention and the trouble coupled with it, also to the excellent Professor Drude for his kind recommendation on this occasion. This literary work was somewhat rushed because I found myself pressed at the time with the deadline, as just then the preparation of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Census</seg> of plant species of Australia<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.03.04.</p>
               </note> together with normal official duties weighed heavily on me. So I intended actually to speak also about some other physiographic relationships, and especially also to go into the factors that cause the extraordinary difference of the climate of Western Europe and north-east America together with the effect of the Gulf Stream.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By today's mail I am sending you a copy of a recently published work of the Honourable B. Wilson (since then deceased former Minister of Lands of New South Wales) about Lord Howe's Island.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Bowie Wilson (1882).</p>
               </note> The report with photographs gives you a good idea of the huge double rock isolated in the Pacific Ocean. Had I known that this book would be published, I would have been able to produce a chapter for it about the local for the most part endemic woody vegetation. By the way, I already gave an enumeration of the plants of Lord Howe's Island in the 9th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae </seg>p. 76-78,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B75.06.02.</p>
               </note> that then (1875) ran to 82 Vasculares, to which five ferns have since been added. In Sydney a geographical society for the whole of Australia was formed at the beginning of this month, and unexpectedly the presidency was offered to me. However, in the same month two other presidential seats of important societies of other purposes in Victoria were also offered to me. However highly I estimate these proofs of attention and of trust, yet I was induced to decline these honorary positions since insufficient leisure remains for me, beside my official and literary duties and some expenditure of time for religion and medicine, to really look after the interests especially of a large geographical society. I do not yet know to whom the presidency will now fall; meanwhile I have advised the Sydney committee to establish branches in all other Australian colonies, and for each branch to elect a vice-president, which was also adopted.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M became a Vice-President of the Society and President of its Victorian Branch when this was created.</p>
               </note> An organization like this new one can expedite the exploration of the still remaining untravelled parts of Australia by independent means, and one of the first endeavours should be to discover the fate of Leichhardt and his companions.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With respect</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Our colonies will now enter the International Postal Union, which will simplify our communications with Germany too.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The taking possession of New Guinea would be a great achievement for civilization and geography, and perhaps Great Britain could purchase the Dutch part of the large island of Papua. Attention is also directed here to the New Hebrides and the Loyalty Islands, to acquire them for the English crown; all these barbarous states and especially also all in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Central Africa</hi>
               </seg>, where the German Reich has the highest entitlement to territorial acquisition through Vogel, Beurmann, Heuglin, Barth, Nachtigall, Schweinfurth, Rolfs and other <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">German</hi>
               </seg> savants, should come under the sovereignty of European governments, the sooner the better for the wellbeing of the whole world.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
