<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>5/11/83 ¶  ¶ Your kindly letter, noble Baron, has reached me with the mail before last ¶  and I answer it today only briefly because I have been almost bound to my sick bed since about two months ago....</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1883/83-11-05d-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Archiv, Karl-Franzens Universität Graz.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>83.11.05d</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>5/11/83 ¶  ¶ Your kindly letter, noble Baron, has reached me with the mail before last ¶  and I answer it today only briefly because I have been almost bound to my sick bed since about two months ago....</title>
               <date when="1883-11-05">1883-11-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1883/83-11-05d-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Phymatocaryon</term>
               <term>Elaeocarpus</term>
               <term>Sapindaceae</term>
               <term>Nephalium</term>
               <term>Santalum</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Constantin von Ettingshausen</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">5/11/83 ¶  ¶ Your kindly letter, noble Baron, has reached me with the mail before last ¶  and I answer it today only briefly because I have been almost bound to my sick bed since about two months ago....</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">83.11.05d</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Constantin von Ettingshausen</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Archiv, Karl-Franzens Universität Graz.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">5/11/83</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr gütiges Schreiben, edler Herr Baron, hat mich mit vorletzter Post erreicht, und beantworte ich selbiges auch heute nur in der Kürze, da ich fast an mein Krankenlager gefesselt bin, seit etwa 2 Monaten leide ich nämlich an einem heftigen Bronchial-Catarrh u da bereits etwas Emphysem eingetreten ist, u ich von meinen früh verstorbenen Eltern eine Anlage zur Pulmonar Phthisis angeerbt habe, ist mein Zustand immerhin bedenklich.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Indessen hier tritt ja gerade der Sommer ein, so mag ich mich doch vielleicht noch wieder erholen. Wenn ich also diesmal mich nicht sehr weitläufig ergehe in meiner Correspondenz, so werden Sie es unter den Umständen freundlichst verzeihen</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zunächst erstatte ich Ihnen meinen tief gefühlten Dank, dafür dass Sie von den Tasmanischen Pflanzen-Fossilien gerade das jenige einzige ausgewählt haben, welches von Früchten begleitet war, um es mir zu widmen, eine Aufmerksamkeit, für welche ich mich ausserordentlich hoch geehrt fühle. Vielleicht bietet sich mir bald die Gelegenheit, diese Gute in ähnlicher Weise zu erwiedern</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre schöne und umsichtige Bearbeitung der australischen Blatt-Fossilien wird zum mehr extensiven Sammeln und Beobachten solcher Pflanzen-Reste anfeuern, damit auch von hier aus mehr Materialien zum Verständniss der Entwicklungs-Geschichte der Vegetation der Gesammtwelt geliefert werden mögen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Vorkommen von Erlenwäldern in Australien während der Pliocenzeit ist, als von Ihnen nachgewiesen, von hohem Interesse, u damit ist ja ein ganz besonderer Verknüpfungs-Faden für zusammenhängende Untersuchungen gewonnen. Wenn ich wohler fühle, sollte die Vorsehung mir Wiederherstellung meiner Gesundheit zuermessen, werde ich gern mit Ihnen für die Erkundung unserer Miocen- u Pliocen-Flora von hier aus zusammen wirken.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit letzter Post sandte ich Ihnen ein Exemplar der 2tn Decade meiner "veg. fossils of the auriferous drifts" in diesem Hefte sind nicht nur die früheren Notizen, wie solche zerstreut erschienen, wiederholt, sondern noch manche Bemerkungen hinzugefügt, welche sich beim Erlang weiterer Materialien nach u nach aufdrängten. Falls Sie die erste Decade nicht besitzen, kann ich Ihnen von solcher noch 1 Ex. ablassen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Ihre </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Herrn Baron von</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ettingshausen &amp;c</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Die Kgl. Gesellschaft forderte mich auf, für deren Schlusssitzung von 1883 (eben jetzt) eine Abhandlung zu liefern. Da nun Ihre Definitionen der Blattreste des Travartin von dort locales Interesse haben, so habe ich bei dieser Gelegenheit dieselben besprechen, u auch darauf hingedeutet, dass die Gesellschaft sich Ihnen erkenntlich zeigen möge.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Phymatocaryon">Phymatocaryon</name> rechne ich zu den Sapindaceen; es giebt <name key="Nephalium">Nephalium</name> Arten mit ähnlich rauhem Pericarp, u die Valvation ist stets deutlich vorhanden, während bei <name key="Elaeocarpus">Elaeocarpus</name> u <name key="Santalum">Santalum</name> das Putamen nicht aufspringt. Indessen bin ich vermuthlich bei der ersten Behandlung von <name key="Phymatocaryon">Phymatocaryon</name> durch ein Exemplar irre geleitet, das Theile eines vermeintlichen Exocarps trug; letzterer ist aber wohl nur ein Trug-gebilde gewesen, indem sich eine Erdschicht um die Frucht erhärtete u dann rundlich abrieb im Detritus. Ein solches freilich leicht vergangliches Exocarp habe ich bei den vielen nachher erlangten Früchten nie wieder wahrgenommen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unter den Früchten von Sheppey nahe London finden sich ähnlicher Sapindaceen Gebilde.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">5/11/83</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your kindly letter, noble Baron, has reached me with the mail before last<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> and I answer it today only briefly because I have been almost bound to my sick bed since about two months ago. You see I suffer from a severe bronchial catarrh and because some emphysema has already set in and I have inherited a predisposition to pulmonary phthisis from my prematurely deceased parents, my condition is always serious.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>However, here summer has just come, so perhaps I may still recover again. Thus if this time I do not hold forth in my correspondence very copiously, you will most kindly excuse it under the circumstances.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Firstly I express my deep-felt thanks that you have chosen from the Tasmanian fossil plants, just that single one which was accompanied by fruits to dedicate it to me,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Ettingshausen described </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Alnus muelleri</seg>
                     <seg style=""> in Ettingshausen (1883), pp. 1</seg>
                     <seg style="">14-6, plate 1, figs 15-17.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> an attention for which I feel extraordinarily highly honoured. Perhaps the opportunity will soon offer itself to me to return this kindness in similar manner.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your splendid and prudent treatment of the Australian leaf fossils will encourage more extensive collecting and observing of such plant remains, so that more material from here may also be supplied for the understanding of the history of development of the vegetation of the whole world.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The occurrence of alder forests in Australia during Pliocene time is, as shown by you, of high interest and because of that a quite special linking thread for connected investigations is certainly gained. When I feel better, should Providence grant me the restoration of my health, I shall gladly work with you for the investigation of our Miocene and Pliocene floras from here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With the last mail, I sent you a copy of the second Decade of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Vegetable fossils of the auriferous drifts</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.13.04.</p>
               </note> In this part are not only the earlier notes repeated, as such appeared dispersed, but several more observations are added that obtruded now and then with the acquisition of further material. If you do not have the first Decade,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B74.13.07.</p>
               </note> I can still let you have a copy of it.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Baron von Ettingshausen &amp;c</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Royal Society<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Of Tasmania.</p>
               </note> asked me to deliver a paper for their closing session of 1883 (just now). Since now your definitions of the leaf remains of the travertine from there have local interest, I have with this opportunity discussed them and also pointed out that the Society might show its appreciation of you.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B85.13.27. M's paper was not, in fact, read to the Society until the first meeting of its next session, on 8 April 1884. There is no record in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Proceedings</seg> of any meeting in November or December 1883. M's paper was a summary of Ettingshausen's monograph in which leaf remains from travertine outcropping at the mouth of Tasmania's Derwent River were studied.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I class <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Phymatocaryon">Phymatocaryon</name>
               </seg> in the <name key="Sapindaceae">Sapindaceae</name>; there are species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Nephalium">Nephalium</name>
               </seg> with similar rough pericarp, and the valvation always clearly exists, whilst in the case of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Elaeocarpus">Elaeocarpus</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Santalum">Santalum</name>
               </seg> the putamen do not burst open. However, I am probably misled in the first treatment of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Phymatocaryon">Phymatocaryon</name>
               </seg> by a specimen that bore part of a probable exocarp, but the latter has probably been only a phantom form, in that the sediment hardened around the fruit and then roundly abraded in the detritus. I have never again noticed such an admittedly easily perishable exocarp in the many fruits obtained afterwards.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Among the fruits from Sheppey near London are similar <name key="Sapindaceae">Sapindaceae</name> forms.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Elaeocarpus">Elaeocarpus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Nephalium">Nephalium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Phymatocaryon">Phymatocaryon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Santalum">Santalum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sapindaceae">Sapindaceae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
