<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Baron Von Mueller has just received a communication from Mr C. Hartmann to the effect that he and Mr George Hunter have reached the summit of the dividing range, near Mount Obree, which would be abou...</title>
            <author>Carl Hartmann</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1887/87-08-00b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>87.08.00b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl Hartmann</author>
               <title>[Baron Von Mueller has just received a communication from Mr C. Hartmann to the effect that he and Mr George Hunter have reached the summit of the dividing range, near Mount Obree, which would be abou...</title>
               <date when="1887-08">1887-08</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1887/87-08-00b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>Internet link</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[Baron Von Mueller has just received a communication from Mr C. Hartmann to the effect that he and Mr George Hunter have reached the summit of the dividing range, near Mount Obree, which would be abou...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">87.08.00b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Carl Hartmann</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Exploration in New Guinea', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg> (Melbourne), 17 August 1887, p. 3. The letter is dated to August on the basis that it had just been received; it must have been sent after mid-July when Hartmann and Hunter are reported to have 'just come in', to Port Moresby, see J. Douglas to M, 16 July 1887 (in this edition as 87-07-16b). The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg>, p. 2, has a brief comment and describes this text as a precis.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[Baron Von Mueller has just received a communication from Mr C. Hartmann to the effect that he and Mr George Hunter have reached the summit of the dividing range, near Mount Obree, which would be about half way between Port Moresby on the South coast, and Dyke Acland's Bay on the North coast of British New Guinea. The season proved exceptionally wet, so that these bold travellers had a far more difficult task than under ordinary circumstances would have been the case. They intend to resume their expedition with a view of getting quite across the Peninsula, by which means then an overland communication would be established between important harbors, north and south.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Soon after they returned, George Hunter accompanied Walter Cuthbertson on an ascent of Mr Obree; see W. Lawes to M, 21 September 1887. (However, also see J. H. P. Murray (1912), p. 273, for doubt that they reached the summit.)</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> A large fine valley opened from the summit of the range, east by north to Acland's, or perhaps Collingwood's Bay, with a long spur towards the main range to the left. The soil below the deposit of humus was found to be of stiff reddish, or yellowish clay. The rocks are deeply broken and flinty. There is a paradise of palms and ferns, one palm with long leaves which are crimson in a young state.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Hartmann speaks also of bamboos, masas,</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>musas?</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> aroids, pandanus, orchids, dracaenas, begonias and other treasures of horticultural wealth, which he will render accessible to Australian gardens. From Rigo, where Mr Hunter is Government Resident, the three days' route to Port Moresby was done on horses. From Rigo to Dr. Clarkson's last camp took three days also; and thence two days were required to gain the summit of the range. The highest elevation reached by Messrs Hunter and Hartmann is not given.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a near-contemporary map, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Map of part of southeast New Guinea embracing its northern and southern waters, </seg>
                        <ref target="https://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/papers/govpub/VPARL1890No21Map.pdf"
                             rend="Internet%20link"
                             style="color: #0000ff; ">
                           <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0000ff; ">https://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/papers/govpub/VPARL1890No21Map.pdf</seg>
                        </ref>, (accessed 16 February 2018.)</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>They started, with 27 natives, to carry burdens and to cut the track. At every village they passed more natives joined, the number,</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">when Dr Clarkson's last camp was reached, having increased to 183, and finally they mustered over 300, sufficient to intimidate some hostile tribes. Two or three pigs were bought every evening to aid in feeding the large human train. The main range is the Saromogoro,</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seremagoro?</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> which the tribes near wish to guard as the abode of the souls of their departed friends; but they abandoned their superstitions, and finally acted even as guides, though they had summoned by messages all their neighbors to destroy the party. To Mr Hunter's knowledge of the natives near him and their attachment to him the success was due, supported by Mr Hartmann's fearlesness and humorous sociability, though at one time, over one hundred armed warriors opposed the progress of the party.]</seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
