<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 11 May 1887. ¶  ¶ Requested by you, highly esteemed Mr Basedow, during your kind visit ¶  to express my opinions on the necessity of further research explorations in Australia, I would firs...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1887/87-05-11c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>87.05.11c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 11 May 1887. ¶  ¶ Requested by you, highly esteemed Mr Basedow, during your kind visit ¶  to express my opinions on the necessity of further research explorations in Australia, I would firs...</title>
               <date when="1887-05-11">1887-05-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1887/87-05-11c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Panicum spectabile</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Basedow</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 11 May 1887. ¶  ¶ Requested by you, highly esteemed Mr Basedow, during your kind visit ¶  to express my opinions on the necessity of further research explorations in Australia, I would firs...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">87.05.11c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Friedrich Basedow</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 25 May 1887, p. 4 (B87.05.06).</p>
               </note>Melbourne, 11. Mai 1887.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Aufgefordert von Ihnen, hochgeehrter Herr Basedow, während Ihres gütigen Besuches, meine Ansichten über die Nothwendigkeit weiterer Forschungsreisen in Australien auszusprechen, möchte ich zunächst darauf hinweisen, dass das Unbekanntsein ausgedehnter Regionen Australiens gerade so zu betrachten ist, als wenn ein Kapitalist sein Vermögen zinslos unbenutzt lässt oder nicht einmal den Betrag seines Eigenthums kennt. Wenn dies unter allen Umständen sehr zu bedauern wäre, so ist dies um so mehr zu beklagen, wenn zu Zeiten finanzieller Bedrückung grosses Landeigenthum dieser Kolonien uneinträglich oder sogar ungekannt und daher ein bedeutender und beständiger Ertrag der Revenue entzogen bleibt. In dieser Hinsicht ist für unseren Welttheil noch am meisten, für Süd-Australien und für West-Australien zu leisten. — Aber auch in den Colonial Territorien mit viel geringerer Ausdehnung, so in Neu-Süd- Wales, Victoria und Tasmanien, bleibt noch viel zu thun, selbst für den ersten Aufschluss von deren Areal-Eigenthum. Werden doch eben jetzt erst die ersten Pfade durch den Urwald im östlichsten Gippsland gehauen, und finden nun erst nach 50jährigem Bestehen die ersten Heerden dort ihre Ausnahme, nachdem schon vor einem drittel Jahrhundert ich mich dieser Region nahte, Gegenden mit dem herrlichsten Klima der Welt, freilich damals nahe um den Wilden zu erliegen. In einer ähnlichen Weise ist durch ein volles Jahrhundert mancher Landstrich in Neu-Süd-Wales unbenutzt geblieben, und die Revenuen, welche solche Regionen liefern werden, find daher sammt den Zinsen der Kron-Revenue entgangen. In der That werden auf meine eigenen Anregung jetzt Vorbereitungen getroffen, um den Mount Seaview am Hastings River, nicht gar fern von Niederlassungen, zu ersteigen, wohin der ausgezeichnete Dr. Beckler sich schon vor 30 Jahren wandte, aber unter Mitteln so gering, als von meiner Anstalt erlangbar, um als damals hoffnungsloses Project ausgegeben zu werden; so steht denn noch heute jener Berg (als wahrscheinlich überschätzt) in runder Zahl als 6000 Fuss hoch auf der Karte und von seinem etwaigen Mineral-Reichthum und anderen Naturschätzen, welche jedenfalls zum Gouvernements-Einkommen der Kolonie beitragen würden, wissen wir bisher nichts! So auch wurde Mount Bellendenker, in Nord-Australien, den schon Flinders 1802 benannte, erst in diesem Jahr erstiegen, und zwar ganz unabhängig, ohne vorherigeS Wissen von der Absicht, durch Mr. Sayer unter meinen Auspicien von der nördlichen Seite des Gebirges, und von Mr. Palmerston von den südlichen Abhängen aus, wodurch einerseits wichtige Resultate für die Pflanzenkunde gewonnen, andererseits reiche und ausgedehnte Goldfelder aufgeschlossen wurden. Wenn solche Explorationen bedeutende Geldmittel erforderten, so würde man sich weniger wundern über diese bisherigen Abschliessungen, aber das einfache Eröffnen von Pfaden ist ja mit ganz geringen Mitteln gethan, und die Ausgabe wird ja örtlich verwandt, und daher der Kolonie nicht entzogen. Wenn ich nicht irre, find die vier Züge, von welchen ich rede, alle durch Privatmittel beschafft oder durch solche zu vollenden. Diese Betrachtungen bringen mich nun zu einer Frage, ob es denn gar nicht möglich wäre, am besten noch in dieser günstigen Jahreszeit, die Erforschung von Süd-Auftraliens Territorium nordwestwärts vom Lake Amadeus und südwärts von Musgrave's und Tomkinson's Range zu vollenden? Jeder Wasserplatz, der gefunden würde, wäre ja von unberechnungsbarem Werthe, ganz abgesehen von späteren artesischen Bohrungen. Dass diese unbekannten Landstrecken nur Wüsteneien sein werden, ist nicht denkbar; jedenfalls giebt es dort manche Oasen, und was man jetzt Wüste nennt, wird gar bald in Triften umgestaltet werden, zumal wenn das wunderbare Coapim-Gras (ich meine das echte <name key="Panicum%20spectabile">Panicum spectabile</name>, nicht das seit 2000 Jahren bekannte Holippo-Gras</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Typesetter's mistake for </seg>
                     <seg style="">Haleppo-Gras?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">) selbst die Sandhügel mit seinen weitgestreckten Wurzeln überzogen haben wird, wie durch meine Vertheilungen dieser höchst werthvollen Pflanze es bereits in Riverina der Fall ist. — Es ist mit dem tiefsten Bedauern, meine Fürsprache, dass Mr. Ernest Giles diese Territorial-Forschungen übertragen würden, bisher fehlgeschlagen zu finden, so dass also noch immer für die Revenue Ihrer Kolonie weite Landstrecken gänzlich unverwerthet bleiben, einfach weil sie noch unbekannt sind! Ich weiss, edler Freund, dass Sie selbst die Vollendung der geographischen Forschungen in Süd-Australien stets befürworteten; vielleicht werden Sie es von Neuem thun, da ja durch zufällige Verhältnisse Mr. Giles gerade jetzt frei ist, um neue Forschungszüge zu übernehmen, und da auch der ebenfalls um Süd-Australiens Geographie so verdiente Gefährte von Giles, nämlich Mr. Tietkens, gewiss gern wieder ins Explorationsfeld ziehen würde. Wirklich grosse Ausgaben sind ja nicht damit verknüpft, wenn man die sicher erspriesslichen Erfolge in Betracht zieht, und ferner die bleibende Bereicherung, welche durch jede neue Expedition für die Kolonie erfolgt! Es kann ja eine leichte Partie sein, die auszieht, um die Ausgabe aufs Geringste zu reduciren. Schliesslich kann ich nicht umhin, die Ansicht auszusprechen, dass diejenigen Kolonien, welche von den Forschungsreisenden die grössten Vortheile haben, sich auch dieser in der Geschichte Australiens hochstehenden Männer annehmen! Wie hochsinnig wäre es, wenn man ihnen eine bescheidene Stellung gäbe für die Verwaltung der Kronländereien in eben denjenigen Districte, welche durch sie bekannt wurden, und wo diese Ehrenmänner dann für die erste Occupation und für das nachherige Erblühen durch Jahre weiter wirken könnten. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Ehrerbietig </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>der Ihre </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. v. Mueller.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 11 May 1887.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Requested by you, highly esteemed Mr Basedow, during your kind visit<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See Basedow's report on his visit to Melbourne (in this edition as M87-06-15).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> to express my opinions on the necessity of further research explorations in Australia, I would firstly like to point out that the ignorance of extensive regions of Australia is to be regarded just as if a capitalist left his fortune unused without interest or not even knew the amount of his property. If this among all other circumstances were to be much regretted, then this is all the more to be lamented, when at times of financial depression the large country property of these colonies remains unprofitable or even unknown and therefore a significant and constant return remains removed from the revenue. In this respect there is something to be achieved for our part of the world yet mostly for South Australia and for Western Australia. – But even in the colonial territories with much smaller expanse such as in New South Wales, Victoria and Tasmania, much still remains to be done, even for the first opening of their areal property. Indeed only just now are the first tracks being cut through the virgin forest in east Gippsland and the first herds are met with there now only after 50 years' existence, after I approached this region as long ago as a third of a century.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M first visited east Gippsland, Vic, in 1854.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Regions with the most magnificent climate in the world, admittedly at the time nearly left to the savages. In a similar fashion through a full century many a tract of land in New South Wales remains unused, and the revenues that such regions will produce are therefore missed together with the interest of the crown revenue. In fact on my own suggestion, preparations are being made now to climb Mount Seaview on the Hastings River,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to E. Ramsay, 30 March 1887 (in this edition as 87-03-30b).</p>
               </note> not very far from settlements where the excellent Dr Beckler travelled as long ago as 30 years, but with means as small as were available from my institute as to be given up as a hopeless project at the time. So still today that mountain (as probably overestimated) stands in round numbers as 6000 feet high on the map and of its possible mineral riches and other natural treasures, which in any case would contribute to the government income of the colony, till now we know nothing! So too Mount Bellendenker<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mt Bellenden Ker, Qld.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> in north Australia, which Flinders named as long ago as 1802, was climbed only this year and indeed quite independently without previous knowledge of the intention by Mr Sayer under my auspices from the northern side of the mountain and by Mr Palmerston from the southern slopes, whereby on the one hand important results for botany were gained, and on the other hand rich and extensive gold fields were opened.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to W. Sayer, December 1886 (in this edition as 86-12-00g), and Lavarack (2015).</p>
               </note> If such explorations require significant financial resources, then one would be less surprised about this previous locking up, but the simple opening of tracks is after all done with quite modest means and the expenditure is after all employed locally and therefore the colony is not deprived. If I am not mistaken, the four expeditions of which I speak were all brought about by private means or completed by such. These considerations bring me now to a question whether it would not be at all possible, at best still in this favourable season, to complete the exploration of South Australia's territory northwestwards from Lake Amadeus<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>NT.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and southwards from Musgrave's and Tomkinson's Range.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Both SA.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Each watering place that was found would after all be of incalculable value, quite apart from later artesian bores. That these unknown tracts would be just desert is not conceivable. In any case there are many oases there and what one now calls desert will quite soon be transformed to grazing ground, especially when the wonderful coapim grass (I mean the real <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Panicum%20spectabile">Panicum spectabile</name>
               </seg>, not the Holippo<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Typesetter's mistake for </seg>
                     <seg style="">Haleppo?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> grass known for 2000 years) will have spread over even the sand hills with its widely extended roots, as is the case already in the Riverina through my distributions of this highly valuable plant. – It is with the deepest regret to find that my recommendation that Mr Ernest Giles be entrusted with these territorial explorations came to nothing up to now, so that wide stretches still remain completely valueless for the revenue of your colony, simply because they are still unknown! I know, noble friend, that you always supported the completion of geographical explorations in South Australia. Perhaps you will do it again, because through fortuitous circumstances Mr Giles is just now free to undertake new expeditions and because also the companion of Giles, that is Mr Tietkens, who likewise rendered service to the geography of South Australia, would certainly gladly take to the field of exploration again.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Giles mounted no new expeditions in central Australia, but Tietkens led an expedition north-west from Alice Springs in 1889 during which he fixed the western limits of Lake Amadeus.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Really large expenditures are certainly not attended with it, if one considers the certain profitable outcomes and, further, the lasting enrichment that ensues for the colony from every new expedition! It can even be a light party that sets out to reduce the expenditure to the lowest. Finally I cannot refrain from expressing the opinion that those colonies that gain the greatest advantages from the explorers should also take care of these men of high standing in the history of Australia! How magnanimous would it be if a modest position were given to them for the administration of the crown lands in just those districts that were made known by them, and where these honourable men could work afterwards through the years for the first occupation and subsequent blossoming.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Panicum%20spectabile">Panicum spectabile</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
