<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>16/12/87 ¶  ¶ Your letter, ¶  dear Doctor, awakens memories especially of those days, when life with its hopes lay still largely before me, when I began to explore with youthful enthusiasm the wonders...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1887/87-12-16-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Cb 66, Nachlass Rudolf Fischer-Benzon, Schleswig-Holsteinische Landesbibliothek, Kiel.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>87.12.16</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>16/12/87 ¶  ¶ Your letter, ¶  dear Doctor, awakens memories especially of those days, when life with its hopes lay still largely before me, when I began to explore with youthful enthusiasm the wonders...</title>
               <date when="1887-12-16">1887-12-16</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1887/87-12-16-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Gentiana Pneumonanthoides</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/82f9d0be-fa94-44b0-837d-b5372427e4f3">Potamogeton pectinatus</term>
               <term>Hieracium virescens</term>
               <term>Trifolium spadiceum</term>
               <term>Epipogium Gmelinii</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/043ded87-f278-4c2b-802e-e1e404c6e874">Araliaceae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
               <term>Thymeleae</term>
               <term>Viniferae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/2ed7e3fa-8568-4c33-85fa-02fba53fe739">Rosaceae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Rudolf von Fischer-Benzon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">16/12/87 ¶  ¶ Your letter, ¶  dear Doctor, awakens memories especially of those days, when life with its hopes lay still largely before me, when I began to explore with youthful enthusiasm the wonders...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">87.12.16</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Rudolf von Fischer-Benzon</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Cb 66, Nachlass Rudolf Fischer-Benzon, Schleswig-Holsteinische Landesbibliothek, Kiel.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">16/12/87</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre Zuschrift, geehrter Herr Doctor, ruft in meiner Erinnerung wieder jene Zeit besonders wach, in welcher das Leben mit seinen Hoffnungen mir meist noch vorlag, und in der ich mit jugendlicher Begeisterung die Wunderwerke der Pflanzenwelt, soweit solche in freier Natur und in Garten-Culturen sich mir darboten, zu erforschen begann. Jene Jahre gehören zu den herrlichsten meines Daseins! Gern entspreche ich Ihrem Wunsch, für den schönen Zweck, welchem Sie und Herr Dr Prahl sich widmen, u. zu dem meine ersten Arbeiten im Felde der Wissenschaften auch vielleicht etwas beitragen, einige Notizen über meinen Lebenslauf zu liefern; u wenn ich schreibe vielleicht zu umfangsreich in dieser Hinsicht, so können Sie ja das, welches Ihnen als Zweck entsprechend ercheinen mag, auswählen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Verwaist trat ich als Eleve in das pharmaceutische Geschäft des Herrn A. B. Becker in Husum Ostern 1840 ein, im Alter von noch nicht ganz 15 Jahren, nachdem ich meinen ersten Unterricht am Gymnasium in Rostock, meiner Vaterstadt erlangt, und nach dem Tode meines Vaters, der dort erster Zoll-Controlleur war und als Freiwilliger 1813 mit bei Seestedt focht, mit meiner Mutter und drei Schwestern zu den Grosseltern in Tönning zog, wo ich die höhere Schule von 1836-1840 besuchte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">In dem Becker'schen Hause hatte zum Anfange des Jahrhundert auch Prof. Forchhammer, der scandinavische Geologe, seine erste Bildung für die Naturwissenschaften erhalten, u. ich hatte das Glück, diesem edlen Manne in der Naturforscher-Versammlung zu Kiel in 1846 zu begegnen, bei welcher für mich höchst anregenden Gelegenheit ich auch Oersted, Dalton, Schleiden, Roeper, Steenstrup, Kunze, Waitz, Rammelsberg, Volger u viele andere hervorleuchtende Männer der Wissenschaft persönlich kennen lernte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>Wie 1842 Hr. A B. Becker starb, ging die Apotheke als Erbschaft an dessen Neffen, Hr E. G. Becker, einen besonders tüchtigen Chemiker über; und hier will ich es wieder spät im Leben anerkennen, dass beide sich des verwaisten Knabens mit fast väterlicher Zuneigung annahmen. Ja, mit der Witwe des vor einigen Jahren in Berlin dahingeschiedenen Hr E. G. Becker bin ich noch jetzt in brieflichem Verkehr.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In 1845 bezog ich die Universität zu Kiel, wo unter den noch Lebenden Prof. Himly u Dr. Mein, meine Lehrer waren, denen ich meinen ehrerbietigen Gruss übersenden möchte! durch Sie theils um das pharmac Staats Examen zu bestehen, theils u. besonders um mich den Natur-Wissenschaften zu widmen, da meine Ausflüge in die Pflanzen-Fluren schon damals einen innigen Wunsch erregt hatten, in andern Welttheilen selbständig zu forschen, zu welchem Begehr ich besonders noch durch das Lesen von Humboldt's Reisen in die Äquinoctial-Gegenden der neuen Welt noch weiter angeregt wurde, u für welchen Zweck ich auch mich damals schon etwas der Medicin zuwandte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nachdem ich 1847 promovirte als Doctor der Phil. wanderte ich aus, trotz zweier für den Jüngling schon glänzenden Anerbietungen in Schleswig-Holstein, denn bei meiner ererbten Disposition zur Pulmonar-Phthisis fühlte ich, dass ich den nächsten Winter in Nord- oder Mittel-Europa nicht überleben würde; u da auch meine älteste Schwester an jenem Leiden erkrankt war, u diesem später als Opfer verfiel, wanderte ich nach Süd-Australien aus, wohin der Zug der deutschen Emigranten sich damals besonders wandte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Ende 1847 bis Mitte 1852 bereiste ich das Territorium von Südaustralien bis zur Grenze von Victoria, u bis nahe zum Lake Torrens auf eigne Kosten, zu einer Zeit wo es kaum eine Brücke oder Landstrasse gab, u. jede Tour zu Fuss oder auf dem Reit-Pferd durchgeführt werden musste, die Rast-Stätten fast immer unter freiem Himmel u wie noch jeder Reisende in der Gefahr stand, den Feindseligkeiten der Eingebornen zu erliegen. Diese Untersuchungs Reisen erstreckte sich damals schon lineal über 4000 engl. Meilen. Im Jahr 1852 nahm ich einen Ruf vom Gouverneur Latrobe an, die in Melbourne entstandene Stelle eines Regierungs Botanikers zu übernehmen, während für die des Regierungs Geologen Mr Selwyn, (jetzt Director des Museums in Canada) berufen wurde. Ich bereiste phytologisch die meisten Theile des Landes (Victoria) von 1852 - Mitte 1855, einschliesslich dreijähriger Sommer-Reisen in den damals <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">pfadlosen</hi>
               </seg> austral. Alpen, bestimmte gleichzeitig die Position vieler der Alpenhöhen u unternahm auch hypsometrische Beobachtungen. Auf Urlaub von Mitte 1855 - Mitte 1857 begleitete ich als Naturforscher Mr A. C. Gregory in der Expedition, die vom Herzog von Newcastle als damaligen Staats Minister der Colonien für die Erforschung des tropischen Australiens ausgesandt wurde, war einer der vier Entdecker der grossen Weide-Region, jetzt Kimberley-District genannt, u war auch einer derer, die durch die ganze Zeit im Felde waren, 17 Monate lang von allem Verkehr mit der civilisirten Welt absolut ausgeschlossen, und wiederholt in Collision mit den Eingebornen, durch Monate mit meinen Gefährten von örtlich getrocknetem Pferde-Fleisch unserer armen Packtiere lebend.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der enorme Aufschwung der austral Colonien während der glänzendsten Gold-Zeit machte die schnelle Entwicklung der ruralen Interessen auch zur Notwendigkeit. So übernahm ich 1857 unter dem Gouverneur Sir H Barkly das Directorat des kürzlich begonnenen botanischen Gartens von Melbourne, u knüpfte Horticultur-Verbindungen mit vielen Plätzen in der civilisirten Welt an. Ich baute die ersten Gewächshäuser dann gleich in Australien, zog die Victoria regia u schuf die damals grösste Sammlung lebender Garten Pflanzen in diesem Theil der Welt, u begründete 1857 das bot Museum, es aber auf getrocknete Pflanzen beschränkend, jetzt ziemlich ½ Million Bögen umfassend. Da für die Erfordernisse der schon damals grossen Stadt ein technol. Museum auch für Pflanzen-Producte neben der öffentl. Bibliothek errichtet wurde, da der bot Garten in ziemlicher Entfernung von Melbourne liegt. In 1873 zog ich mich von der Garten-Directur zurück, da ich der Anforderung, die Mittel einer solchen Anstalt in einer jungen Colonie hauptsächlich für Rasenculturen, Blumenbeete und anderer unproductiven Schau nicht opfern wollte. Durch einige Jahre war ich auch Director des zoolog. Gartens, bis solcher nach der entgegen gesetzten Seite der Stadt verlegt wurde, weil es bei mir an Raum gebrach für Weide der Nutztiere, wie Dromedare, Angoraziegen, Llamas, Alpacas, verschiedene Hirsche u Rehe &amp;c. Der Einführung der Sperlinge u Kaninchen aber widersetzte ich mich; behielt aber im Garten das Aviarium, und im Garten-See, wo ich die Inselchen u die Geiser-Fontaine (80' hoch) schuf, manche der Wasser-Vögel</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">pp. 13-16 missing from MS.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zwar werden Sie wohl nur in ganz kurzen Zügen ein Lebensbild von mir entwerfen wollen; da ich aber nicht weiss, nach welcher Richtung hin Sie meine Lebens Ereignisse schildern möchten, habe ich den 11ten Band der fragm. gesandt, aus dessen Titel-Blatt Sie meinen Status bis zum Jahre 1881 ersehen können. Seitdem ist das Werk nicht fosgesetzt,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">fortgesetzt?</p>
               </note> da andere Arbeiten dringender wurden während der mir karg zugemessenen täglichen Studien-Stunden in einer jungen Colonie, wo <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">angewandte</hi>
               </seg> Wissenschaft Alles gilt! Vielleicht nützt es Ihnen aber doch zu wissen, dass zu meinen Würden in letzteren Jahren die eines Grosskreuz des Christus-Orden von Portugal hinzugekommen ist Bei Gelegenheit des 50 jähr. Jubiläums der Königin von England.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bei … England. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is a marginal insertion by M.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> u die eines Commenthurs des Philip's Ordens von Hessen auch bei derselben grossen Feier, u die eines Ritters des Oldenburg Verdienstordens. Dann bin ich Präsident der geograph Gesellschaft von Vict seit den 3 Jahren der Existenz dieses Vereins, der einen Zweig der Royal geogr. Soc of Austr bildet; auch habe ich die Ehre Patron des Vict. Field-Naturalists Club zu sein u. Vice Präs. der grossen Melbourne Liedertafel; Giles McIntyre u Andere waren geographisch zuerst meine Emissäre. Seit 1881 bin ich auch noch als Ehrenmitglied in manche wissenschaftliche Vereine gewählt; in London (Ehrenm. Roy. Hort Soc), Brescia, Gent (Ehrenm. der agric u hortic Gesellschaft), Boston, Edinburgh (geolog Ges.) Danzig, London (geol. Gesellsch. u auch Society of arts), Brüssel, Bordeaux, Brisbane, Launceston, Dresden (Isis), Gotenburg, New York (chemische Gesellschaft) Melbourne (ordentl Mitglied der Brit medical Association, da meine Studien durch viele Jahre hier auch eine medicinische Wendung nahmen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In einem Clima der Orangen-Zone halten selbstverständlich die Pflanzen der Mittel-Europäischen Kalthäuser im Freien aus, so dass es für viele der Palmen, Bambusaceen u anderer scenischer Pflanzen hier keines Schutzes bedarf, u so ist es entsprechend mit den Nutzthieren.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um aber nicht prolyx zu sein, muss ich mich kürzer fassen, zumal da ich als einer der Commissäre auch mit Extraarbeiten neben den immer grossen Departements Arbeiten gerade jetzt sehr bedrängt bin; aber dies führt zu der Bemerkung, dass ich mit dem späteren Kanzler von England Childers und den jetzigen Generälen Sir Andr. Clarke u Sir Charles Pasley einer der 12 hiesigen Commissäre schon für die Pariser Welt Ausstellung von 1855 war. (Zur Zeit der ersten, durch den <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">grossen Prinzen</hi>
               </seg> hervorgerufenen war ich weit im Innere abwesend).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe zu Fuss oder zu Pferde etwa 28000 engl. Meilen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Beobachtungs</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Linien</hi>
               </seg>, die auch für die Geographie und andere Zweige des Wissens bedeutungsvoll waren, zurückgelegt, habe 40 Bände unabhängiger Original Werke geschrieben, abgesehen von meinem Theil an der Bearbeitung in Benthams Flora Austr., für welche ich in 70 grossen Kisten etwa 70000 getrocknete Pflanzen-Exemplar <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">fast ganz</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">durchgearbeitet</hi>
               </seg> lieh, etwa ⅔ des ganzen Materials bildend!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich war der Erste, welcher ein grosses Werk botanisch schrieb in diesem Welttheil, war der erste Australier, von dessen Werken eins in die deutsche Sprache durch Hr Dr Goeze und in die französ. durch M. le Dr Naudin de l'institut überging; — der erste Australier, von dem ein Band wissenschaftlichen u ruralen Inhalts in 7 Ausgaben in engl Sprache erschien (Select plants for industrial culture and naturalisation), selbst eine Edition für die Vereins Staaten v. N. Am. u eine für britisch Indien; war der Erste der extensiv Lithogrammata naturhistorisch in Australien lieferte, etwa 600 Platten von Pflanzen, fast stets mit Analysen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">von</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">der Knospe</hi>
               </seg> bis zum <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Embryo</hi>
               </seg>. Ich war einer der <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">drei</hi>
               </seg> Ersten in Australien, welchen von der Königin von England so gnädig der Orden von St. Michael u St. George verliehen wurde, wie dieser aus dem Mittelalter herrührende Orden, der auf die Länder des Mittelmeers beschränkt war, auch auf die britischen Colonien ausgedehnt wurde. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bitte Sie aber, geehrter Herr, irgend etwas diese Notizen in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dritter</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht erster</hi>
               </seg> Person zu geben, schon deshalb, weil mein Gefühl stets <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">gegen</hi>
               </seg> Biographien <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Lebender</hi>
               </seg> gewesen ist, u ich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hier</hi>
               </seg> wiederholt rund das Schreiben von biograph. Notizen auf mich selbst bezüglich ablehnte, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihnen</hi>
               </seg> aber doch bereit entgegen kommen wollte. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Und nun zu Schleswig Holstein! Es ist nicht bloss der Süd westlichste Theil, den ich kenne; ich ging auch nach Grafenstein, durchwanderte auch die schöne Landschaft Angeln, der das mächtige England als Anglia seinen Namen verdankt, kam auf meinen Zügen bis Heiligenhaven,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Heligenhafen?</p>
               </note> sammelte bei Altona, Wandsbeck, besuchte Föhr u Sylt, u fand auf letzterer Insel manche merkwürdige Pflanze, darunter die <name key="Gentiana%20Pneumonanthoides">Gentiana Pneumonanthoides</name> in einer Strandform nur etwa 1 Zoll hoch, welche ich 1846 an Fürnrohr, Sonder u Andere Correspondenten sandte, mit letzterem in innigem Freundschaftsverkehr stehend bis zum Ende seiner Tage, so dass sein <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">letzter</hi>
               </seg> Brief, wie auch der letzte von Lindley an mich gerichtet war.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meine Correspondenz nach den Departements Eintragungen hier erforderten während des letzten Drittel des Jahrhunderts etwa 100,000 Briefe aus meiner eignen Hand!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> besonders wohl zu wissen wünschen ist der Umstand, dass auch Dr Ecklon's Pflanzen vom Herzogthum Schleswig nach dem Tode des auch mir befreundeten Dr Steetz von meiner Anstalt erworben wurden, so dass ich Ihnen über zweifelhafte Notizen seinerseits authentisch Auskunft geben kann. Ich selbst fand Epipogium Gmelini in einem Buchen-Walde zwischen Kiel u. Heiligenhafen wieder auf, — sammelte <name key="Trifolium%20spadiceum">Trifolium spadiceum</name> reichlich auf feuchten Wiesen bei Ihrer Stadt, auch <name key="Hieracium%20virescens">Hieracium virescens</name> in einem Gehölz dort, u <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">gab</hi>
               </seg> davon ein Ex. an Sonder, der es nicht selbst fand.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mein plötzliches durch schwere Krankheit veranlasstes Auswandern, verhinderte mich diejenigen seltnen Pflanzen Schleswig-Holsteins zu veröffentlichen, welche nicht in das Gebiet des Breviariums gehören, u nachdem ich in die Forschungen eines <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">winterlosen</hi>
               </seg> Continents, fast von der Grösse Europas, gezogen wurde, blieb mir nicht Zeit, auf das in der Jugendzeit-Gesammelte zurück zu kommen. Ja, meine Reise-Journale seit 1847 liegen noch unveröffentlicht.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auch blieb einiges selbst von Husum als unerledigt zurück, da ja auch andere Wissenschaften mich in Anspruch nahmen; — so glaube ich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">zuerst</hi>
               </seg> als eine selbstständige Art ein Potamogeton erkannt zu haben, welches rigider ist als der normale Zustand von P. pectinatus u in brachischen Gräben ganz nahe bei den Häusern am Haven<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hafen.</p>
               </note> Husum vorkommt; es ist besonders dadurch auch merkwürdig, dass es scheu ist, Früchte zu bilden, nach welchen ich vergebens spät im Herbst suchte, selbst bis die Gräben vereisten. Wenn ich mich nicht täusche ist seitdem dieselbe Art aus Schweden beschrieben. Rücksicht zu Prof Nolte, mit dem ich seit 1841 correspondirte, hielt mich ab diese Art unabhängig von dem <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">damalig</hi>
               </seg> besten Potamogeton-Kenner der Welt vor die Öffentlichkeit zu bringen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Und schliesslich, wir armen mangelhaften Menschen, sollen auch immer der göttlichen Macht u Huld gedenken, u. so füge ich als am Wichtigsten vor Allem hinzu, dass ich Patron des Vereins christlicher junger Männer in einer der grössten schottisch. Kirchen Melbournes bin, u dort gelegentlich freie Vorträge gebe, u nie eine Gelgenheit versäume zum Anhalt an die Kirchen zu ermahnen, den erhebenden Gebeten u Predigten zu lauschen u in die Hymnen mit einzustimmen! Wie viele Thränen würden nicht fliessen, wieviele Qualen der Reue vermieden, wenn <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Jeder</hi>
               </seg> sich ans Kirchenleben eng anschlösse.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">Das Breviarium war bereits 1845 vollendet, aber durch meine Auswanderung verzögerte sich bis 1853 die Veröffentlichung.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mein Einfluss auf die Geographie Australiens (u jetzt auch auf Neu Guinea) ist so bedeutungsvoll erachtet, dass im Geogr. Congress zu Venedig eine der fünf Dank-Voten für Promotoren der Geographie mir zufiel.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Etwa ein Dutzend Werke in mehreren Wissensch. sind mir dedicirt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Für die technol. Industrie u für die Pflanzen-Chemie habe ich hier in einem eigenen Laborator auch manches Neue geschafft.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Manches aus der Fauna Australiens ist zuerst durch mich bekannt geworden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine grosse Höhe in Spitzbergen, ein grosser Cataract in Brasilien, ein Berg in Neu Guinea, ein Hauptfluss in Australien, ein Gletscher in Neu Seeland führen meinen Namen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> Culturen in allen anderen Theilen der Erde wurden meist von mir hervorgerufen u die franz Regierung [...]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible word.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> mich darüber schon vor fast 30 Jahren. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In meinen Key to the syst of Vict pl habe ich die Thymel. zu den Rosaceen u vor Planchon die Vinif. zu den Araliaceen gestellt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Baronisirt wurde ich durch die grosse Huld Sr Maj. des Königs von Württemberg bei der Feier S. M. silbern Hochzeit mit der Schwester der verst Czarin.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie u Hr. Dr Prahl werden meine Vereinfachung des Juss-D.C. System aus dem Census kennen lernen </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es freuet mich ausserordentlich, dass Sie u Hr Dr Prahl die Flora Schl Holst. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">erschöpfend</hi>
               </seg> bearbeiten wollen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">16/12/87</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your letter,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> dear Doctor, awakens memories especially of those days, when life with its hopes lay still largely before me, when I began to explore with youthful enthusiasm the wonders of the plant world as far as they presented themselves to me in open nature and in garden culture. Those years belong to the most wonderful times of my life! I am happy to respond to your wish to furnish you with a few notes about my life for the splendid purpose to which you and Dr Prahl are devoting yourselves,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The work to which M refers was published under the general title <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Kritische Flora der Provinz Schleswig-Holstein</seg>, edited by P. Prahl. It comprises Prahl (1888), Prahl (1890) which includes treatments of groups of families by each of E. H. L. Krauss and R. Fischer-Benzon in addition to Prahl himself, and Fischer-Benzon (1890), a history of floristic research in Schleswig-Holstein, with biographical and bibliographical notes on those who had worked on the subject. M's entry is on p. 39. See also M to R. von Fischer-Benzon, 15 July 1890.</p>
               </note> and to which my first labours in the field of science may perhaps contribute a little as well. If I write perhaps too voluminously about it, you are free to select whatever seems suitable for your purpose.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Orphaned, I entered the pharmaceutical business of Mr A. B. Becker in Husum as a pupil at Easter 1840, at not quite 15 years of age. I had received my first education at the classical grammar school in Rostock, my home town, and after the death of my father, who was First Customs Controller there and in 1813 had fought as a volunteer near Seestedt,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. at the battle of Sehestedt, in Schleswig-Holstein, during the Napoleonic wars.</p>
               </note> I moved with my mother and three sisters to my grandparents' in Tönning, where I attended the secondary school from 1836-1840.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the beginning of the century Professor Forchhammer, the Scandinavian geologist, had also received his first education in natural history in Becker's house. I had the good fortune of meeting this noble man during the meeting of natural scientists held in Kiel in 1846.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lists of members and participants at the 1846 meeting of the Deutscher Naturforscher und Aertze are in Michaelis &amp; Scherk (1847), pp. 285-92.</p>
               </note> On this for me most stimulating occasion I also made the personal acquaintance of Oerstedt, Dalton,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">d'Alton?</p>
               </note> Schleiden, Roeper, Steenstrup, Kunze, Waitz, Rammelsberg, Volger, and many other prominent men of science.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When Mr A. B. Becker died in 1842 the pharmacy went as an inheritance to his nephew Mr E. G. Becker, a particularly able chemist;<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">It has not been possible to determine the date of Albert Becker's death. Notwithstanding M's statement here, it would seem that he was still alive in March 1843 (see A. Schütt to M, 10 March 1843), but he had almost certainly died by October 1844 when the privilege for the pharmacy was transferred to his nephew (Klatt (1988)). We are grateful for Dr Klatt's efforts to establish the date of death more precisely.</p>
               </note> and here I want to acknowledge late in life that both cared for the orphaned boy with almost fatherly affection. Yes, I still correspond today with the widow of Mr E. G. Becker, who died a few years ago in Berlin.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In 1845 I went up to the University of Kiel — where from among my teachers Prof. Himly and Dr Mein are still living, and I would like to pass on to them my respectful regards through you — partly to pass the pharmaceutical state examination, partly and particularly to devote myself to the natural sciences, as my excursions into the open fields of plants had already then aroused the fervent wish to explore independently in other parts of the world. This desire was further stimulated by my reading of Humboldt's travels<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">It is unlikely that M would have had access to one of the various issues of the full multi-volume set of Humboldt's account of his travels in South America, for example Humboldt (1805-34). Most likely he read one of the many abbreviated editions published in German.</p>
               </note> in the equinoctial areas of the New World and for this purpose I applied myself a little to medicine already even then.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After I had graduated with a Doctorate in Philosophy in 1847 I emigrated, even though I had received two splendid offers for a young man in Schleswig-Holstein. With my inherited disposition to pulmonary phthisis I felt that I would not survive the next winter in northern or central Europe. As my eldest sister<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha Müller.</p>
               </note> had also become ill with this disease and later fell victim to it, I emigrated to South Australia, where the stream of German emigrants then mainly flowed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>From the end of 1847 to mid-1852 I travelled at my own expense in the territory of South Australia, as far as the border with Victoria and to near Lake Torrens, at a time when there was hardly a bridge or a road, and each journey had to be made on foot or on horseback, camping places nearly always under the open sky, and when every traveller was in danger of falling victim to the hostile natives. These exploration journeys already covered a distance of more than 4000 linear miles. In 1852 I accepted the appointment from Governor Latrobe to fill the position of Government Botanist, then created in Melbourne, while Mr Selwyn (now Director of the Museum in Canada<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Selwyn was the Director of Geological Survey of Canada.</p>
               </note>) was appointed Government Geologist. I explored phytologically most parts of the country (Victoria) from 1852 to mid-1855, including summer journeys for three years to the then <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">pathless</hi>
               </seg> Australian Alps, at the same time determined the position of many alpine summits, while also conducting hypsometric observations. On leave from mid-1855 to mid-1857 I accompanied as naturalist Mr A. C. Gregory's expedition,<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> sent out by the Duke of Newcastle as the then State Minister for the Colonies to explore tropical Australia, was one of the four discoverers of the vast pasture regions now called the Kimberley District, and was also one of those who remained in the field through the whole time, completely cut off from all contact with the civilised world for 17 months, repeatedly in collision with the natives, living with my companions for months on the locally dried meat of our poor packhorses.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The enormous boom of the Australian colonies during the peak of the gold-rush made the rapid development of rural interests a necessity. Thus I accepted in 1857 under Governor Sir H. Barkly the directorship of the recently-created Botanic Gardens of Melbourne, and established horticultural contacts with many places in the civilised world. I soon built the first glasshouses in Australia, raised the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Victoria regia</seg>, and created the then largest collection of living garden plants in this part of the world. In 1857 I founded the botanical Museum, restricting it to dried plants, which now comprise about half a million sheets, the reason [for the restriction] being that for the needs of the already large city a technological museum also for vegetable products was built adjoining the public library, as the Botanic Garden is a fair distance from Melbourne. In 1873 I resigned from the Directorship of the Garden, as I did not want to sacrifice the means of such an institute in a young colony largely for the cultivation of lawns and flowerbeds and other such unproductive show.<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M is stretching the truth here concerning the circumstances of his leaving the Botanic Garden; see C. Hodgkinson to M, 31 May 1873, and subsequent correspondence. See also Cohn &amp; Maroske (1996).</p>
               </note> For some years I was also Director of the Zoological Garden, until this was moved to the opposite side of the town, because I was lacking the space for pastures for the useful animals such as dromedaries, angora goats, llamas, alpacas, various stags and deer, &amp;c. But I was strongly opposed to the introduction of sparrows and rabbits. I did, however, retain an aviary in the Garden, and in the Gardens Lake, where I created the islets and the geyser fountain 180 feet high, many of the water birds</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Four pages of text missing in the MS.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will probably want only a very short biographical sketch from me, drawn in very broad strokes; but as I do not know from which point of view you might want to recount the events of my life, I have sent the 11th volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>. From its title page you can see my status up to the year 1881. Since then the work has not been continued,<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M did publish a first fascicle of vol.12, pp. 1-26, in December 1882 (B 82.12.03), but the volume was not completed and remained without a title page.</p>
               </note> as other work became more urgent during the meagre study hours given to me in a young colony, where <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">applied</hi>
               </seg> science is everything! But perhaps it will help you to know, that the Grand Cross of the Christus Order of Portugal has been added in recent years on the occasion of the golden anniversary of the Queen of England<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Queen Victoria succeeded to the British throne 20 June 1837 and was crowned on 28 June.</p>
               </note> and that of a Commander of the Philipp's Order of Hesse<note xml:id="ftn21" type="footnote" n="21">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was appointed to the Order of Philipp the Magnanimous, Hesse, on 21 June 1887. For an analysis of the reasons for the bestowal of honours mentioned in this letter, see Lucas (2013a), especially p. 21.</p>
               </note> also during the same great celebration, and that of a Knight of the Oldenburg Order of Merit.<note xml:id="ftn22" type="footnote" n="22">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was appointed to the Oldenburg House and Service Order on 17 January 1887.</p>
               </note> Furthermore, I have been President of the Geographical Society of Victoria for the 3 years since its inception which forms a branch of the Royal Geographical Society of Australasia. I also have the honour to be patron of the Field Naturalists Club of Victoria and Vice-President of the large German Liedertafel. Giles, McIntyre and others were first my geographical emissaries. Since 1881 I have been elected to many scientific societies as an honorary member: in London (hon. member of the Royal Horticultural Society), in Brescia, Ghent (hon. member of the Agricultural and Horticultural Society), Boston, Edinburgh (Geological Society) Danzig, London (Geological Society and also Society of Arts), Brussels, Bordeaux, Brisbane, Launceston, Dresden (Isis), Gothenburg, New York (Chemical Society), Melbourne (ordinary member of the British Medical Association, as my studies here over many years also took a medical direction).<note xml:id="ftn23" type="footnote" n="23">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See the file 'Honours, awards and memberships' in this edition.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In a climate comparable to the orange-zone the plants of the central European cold-houses grow, of course, in the open, so that many of the palms, Bambusaceae and other scenic plants do not require any protection, and it is the same with the useful animals.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But in order not to be too prolix, I must cut it shorter, especially seeing that, as one of the Commissioners,<note xml:id="ftn24" type="footnote" n="24">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">For the Centennial International Exhibition, Melbourne, 1888.</p>
               </note> I am pressed with extra-work just now, apart from the always large workload of the Department. That leads me to remark that I was one of the 12 local commisioners for the Paris International Exhibition of 1855, together with the later Chancellor of England Childers and the present Generals Sir Andrew Clarke and Sir Charles Pasley. (At the time of the first Exhibition, constituted by the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">great Prince,</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn25" type="footnote" n="25">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The 1851 Exhibition in London, promoted by Prince Albert.</p>
               </note> I was absent far away in the interior.)</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have covered on foot or on horseback about 28,000 English miles, making observations, which were also of value to geography and other branches of science. I have written 40 volumes of independent original works, apart from my share in the work of Bentham's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn26" type="footnote" n="26">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78).</p>
               </note> for which I lent about 70,000 dried plant specimens in 70 large cases, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">almost completely worked out</hi>
               </seg>, which comprised about ⅔ of the whole material! </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I was the first to write a large botanical work in this continent, — was the first Australian who had one of his works published in the German language through Dr Goeze and in French by M. Dr Naudin of the Institut;<note xml:id="ftn27" type="footnote" n="27">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. the Institut de France. See B83.13.06 and B87.14.06.</p>
               </note> — the first Australian who had a work with scientific and rural contents published in 7 editions in the English language (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select extra-tropical plants, readily eligible for industrial culture and naturalisation), </seg>with an edition even for the United States of America and for British India.<note xml:id="ftn28" type="footnote" n="28">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B84.13.22 and B80.13.07.</p>
               </note> I was the first to produce extensive natural history lithographs in Australia, about 600 plates of plants, nearly always with analytical drawings <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from the bud</hi>
               </seg> to the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">embryo</hi>
               </seg>. I was one of the first <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">three</hi>
               </seg> in Australia, who was so graciously appointed to the Order of St Michael and St George from the Queen of England,<note xml:id="ftn29" type="footnote" n="29">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Royal Warrant, 24 April 1869.</p>
               </note> when this medieval order, previously restricted to Mediterranean countries, was also extended to the British colonies. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But I ask you, dear Sir, to publish anything from these notes in the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">third, not the the first</hi>
               </seg> person, if only because my feelings have always been <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">opposed</hi>
               </seg> to biographies of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">living</hi>
               </seg>, and because I have refused repeatedly the writing of biographical sketches of me out of hand <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">here</hi>
               </seg>; but I did want to oblige <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And now to Schleswig-Holstein! I know not only the south-western part; I also went to Grafenstein, wandered through the lovely countryside of Angeln, from which mighty England derives its name, went as far as Heiligenhafen during my excursions, collected near Altona, Wandsbeck, visited Föhr and Sylt, and found many a strange plant on the latter island, among them <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Gentiana%20Pneumonanthoides">Gentiana Pneumonanthoides</name>
               </seg>in a coastal form only about 1 inch high, which I sent to Fürnrohr, Sonder and other correspondents in 1846. With the latter I remained in contact as a close friend to the end of his days, so that his <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">last</hi>
               </seg> letter was written to me, as was Lindley's.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My correspondence according to the Department's registers here required about 100,000 letters written in my own hand during the last third of the century! </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> are probably particularly interested to hear is the fact that Dr Ecklon's plants from the Duchy of Schleswig were purchased by this institute after the death of my friend Dr Steetz, so that I am in a position to give you authentic information on any doubtful notes by him. I myself rediscovered <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Epipogium Gmelini</seg> in a beech forest between Kiel and Heiligenhafen, collected <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Trifolium%20spadiceum">Trifolium spadiceum</name>
               </seg> plentifully on damp meadows near your town, also <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hieracium%20virescens">Hieracium virescens</name>
               </seg> in a wood there, and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">gave</hi>
               </seg> a specimen of it to Sonder, who did not find it himself.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My sudden emigration due to a severe illness prevented me from publishing those rare plants, which did not fall within the area covered by the 'Breviary',<note xml:id="ftn30" type="footnote" n="30">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B53.08.01, B53.08.02.</p>
               </note> and once I was drawn into the exploration of a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">winterless</hi>
               </seg> continent almost the size of Europe I lacked the time to return to what I had collected during my youth. Yes, my travel journals since 1847 are still lying here, unpublished.<note xml:id="ftn31" type="footnote" n="31">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's journals disappeared, along with most of his files of correspondence, early in the twentieth century.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Even a few things from Husum remained unfinished, as other branches of science occupied me as well. Thus I believe I was the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">first</hi>
               </seg> to have recognised a separate species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Potamogeton</seg>, which is more rigid than the normal form of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">P. pectinatus</seg> and occurs in brackish ditches quite close to houses near the harbour of Husum; it is remarkable particularly in that it is reluctant to form fruit, for which I searched in vain late into the autumn, even till the ditches were iced over. If I am not mistaken this species has since been described from Sweden. Consideration for Nolte, with whom I corresponded from 1841, prevented me from bringing this species before the public independently of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">then</hi>
               </seg> best <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Potamogeton</seg> specialist in the world.<note xml:id="ftn32" type="footnote" n="32">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's judgement of Nolte is greatly coloured by his obvious respect for the man, but was not shared by later critics of Nolte's importance or achievements (see Fischer-Benzon (1890), pp. 40-4). Elsewhere, M, too, was more critical; see M to J. Hooker, 28 July 1866 (in this edition as 66-07-26a).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And finally, we poor imperfect human beings should always remember God's power and kindness, and so I add as most important before anything else, that I am patron of the Christian Association of young men in one of the largest Scottish churches in Melbourne,<note xml:id="ftn33" type="footnote" n="33">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. at the West Melbourne Presbyterian Church; see M to R. Tate, 18 May 1890.</p>
               </note> where I give occasional free lectures and never miss an opportunity to urge involvement with the Church, to listen to the up-lifting prayers and sermons and to join in the hymn singing. How many tears would remain unshed, how many tortures of remorse could be avoided, if <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">everybody</hi>
               </seg> took an intimate part in the life of the Church.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The 'Breviary' was already completed in 1845, but due to my emigration publication was delayed until 1853.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My influence on the geography of Australia (and now also on New Guinea) was deemed so significant, that during the Geographical Congress in Venice I received one of the five votes of recognition for the promoters of geography.<note xml:id="ftn34" type="footnote" n="34">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Report upon the third international geographical congress and exhibition at Venice, Italy, 1881 …</seg>. (Washington, 1885). p. 22.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>About a dozen works in several fields of science have been dedicated to me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have produced much that is new for technological industry and vegetable chemistry here in my own laboratory.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Much of the fauna of Australia first became known through me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A high peak in Spitzbergen, a large waterfall in Brazil, a mountain in New Guinea, a major river in Australia and a glacier in New Zealand bear my name.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
               </seg> culture in all other parts of the globe was almost entirely instituted by me, and the French Government [honoured] me for it almost 30 years ago.<note xml:id="ftn35" type="footnote" n="35">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was appointed to the French Légion d'Honneur in 1863.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Key to the system of Victorian plants</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn36" type="footnote" n="36">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B86.04.05.</p>
               </note> I have placed the <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name> before the <name key="Rosaceae">Rosaceae</name> and before Planchon the <name key="Viniferae">Viniferae</name> to the <name key="Araliaceae">Araliaceae</name>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I was made a Baron through the great kindness of His Majesty the King of Württemberg during the celebrations of His Majesty's silver wedding anniversary with the sister of the late Czarina.<note xml:id="ftn37" type="footnote" n="37">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Karl I, King of Württemberg, to M, 6 July 1871.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You and Dr Prahl will get to know my simplification of the Jussieu-De Candolle system through my Census.<note xml:id="ftn38" type="footnote" n="38">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.03.04, with several later supplements.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0in; text-align: start; hyphenation-ladder-count: no-limit; font-family: Geneva; hyphenate: false; hyphenation-remain-char-count: 2; hyphenation-push-char-count: 2; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am extraordinarily pleased that you and Dr Prahl will work exhaustively on the Flora of Schleswig-Holstein.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Araliaceae">Araliaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Epipogium%20Gmelinii">Epipogium Gmelinii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gentiana%20Pneumonanthoides">Gentiana Pneumonanthoides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hieracium%20virescens">Hieracium virescens</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Potamogeton%20pectinatus">Potamogeton pectinatus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Rosaceae">Rosaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Trifolium%20spadiceum">Trifolium spadiceum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Viniferae">Viniferae</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
