<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the King. ¶ Report of the State Minister of Church and Educational Affair concerning the birthday of Dr Baron Ferdinand von Mülller in Melbourne (Australia) ¶ Stuttgart, 14 May 1895. ¶  ¶ Your Maje...</title>
            <author>[…] von Sarwey</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1890-9/M95-05-14-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Hauptstaatsarchiv, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M95.05.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>[…] von Sarwey</author>
               <title>To the King. ¶ Report of the State Minister of Church and Educational Affair concerning the birthday of Dr Baron Ferdinand von Mülller in Melbourne (Australia) ¶ Stuttgart, 14 May 1895. ¶  ¶ Your Maje...</title>
               <date when="1895-05-14">1895-05-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1890-9/M95-05-14-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>space</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Wilhelm II, King of Württemberg</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">To the King. ¶ Report of the State Minister of Church and Educational Affair concerning the birthday of Dr Baron Ferdinand von Mülller in Melbourne (Australia) ¶ Stuttgart, 14 May 1895. ¶  ¶ Your Maje...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M95.05.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">[…] von Sarwey to Wilhelm II, King of Württemberg</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Hauptstaatsarchiv, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="space"
               style="font-family: Geneva; text-align: center; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>An den König.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">Anbringen</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">des Staats-Ministers</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">des Kirchen- und Schul-Wesens</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">betreffend</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">den Geburtstag des Dr. Freiherrn Ferdinand von Müller in Melbourne (Australien)</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Stuttgart, den 14 Mai 1895.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Euer Königlichen Majestät erlaube ich mir unterthänigst zur Allerhöchsten Kenntnis zu bringen, dass nach einer Anzeige des Iten Konservators des Naturalienkabinetts dahier, Professor Dr Lampert, Dr Freiherr Ferdinand von Müller, Direktor des botanischen und zoologischen Gartens in Melbourne in Australien, am 30. </seg>Juni d. J. seinen 70ten Geburtstag feiert. <seg style="">Derselbe ist geboren in Rostock, steht aber seit lange zu Württemberg in nahen Beziehungen durch die überaus reichen und wertvollen Schenkungen, welche er seit lange hieher gemacht hat. Nachdem er nämlich schon früher dem Naturalienkabinett dahier eine derartige Schenkung gemacht hatte, hat er auf Veranlassung des damaligen Iten Konservators, Oberstudienrats Dr von Krauss, im Jahre 1869 sich entschlossen, </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> seine Sendungen an Naturalien dem </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hiesigen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Naturalienkabinett zuzuwenden, was zur Folge hatte, dass die höchst eigentümliche und interessante Fauna und Flora Neuhollands in hervorragender Reichhaltigkeit dahier in der Staatssammlung verteten ist. Zugleich hat Müller eine Geldstiftung zu einem Riesestipendium für einen jungen württembergischen Naturforscher behufs der Ausbildung in naturwissenschaftlichen Fächern gemacht, wovon schon vielfach Gebrauch gemacht, und wodurch nicht nur der Bildungszweck wesentlich gefördert, sondern mittelbar auch dem Naturalienkabinett ein Vorteil insofern zugewendet worden ist, als statuengemäss die Stipendirten sich verpflichten müssen, die von ihnen ersammelten Gegenstände dem hiesigen Naturalienkabinett zuzuwenden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Anerkennung seiner ganz hevorragenden Verdienste um Würtemberg ist dem Genannten im Jahre 1867 das Ritterkreuz des K. Kronordens verleihen, und ist sodann derselbe, nach dem Vorgang des in früheren Jahren durch seine Schenkungen aus Südafrika berühmt gewordenen Barons von Ludwig, durch Allerhöchste Entschliessung vom 8. Juli 1871 in den erblichen Freiherrnstand des Königreichs erhoben worden. Seither nach hat von Müller mit seinen Schenkungen hieher fortgefahren, so dass auch er als ein wahrer Wohlthäter der hiesigen Naturaliensammlung bezeichnet werden kann.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Hinblick auf die dem Freiherrn von Müller nach Vorstehendem zuteil gewordenen Allergnädigsten Auszeichnungen dürfte nach meinem unterthänigsten Erachten von der Verleihung einer weiteren Auszeichnung an denselben aus Anlass der Zurücklegung des 70ten Lebensjahres abgesehen werden können, dagegen, wenn Euer Königliche Majestät nicht anders zu verfügen geruhen wollen, jedenfalls angezeigt sein, dass ich dem Freiherrn von Müller zu seinem 70ten Geburtsfest die Glückwünsche des Kultministeriums ausspreche.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Allerhöchsten Enschliessung Euer Königlichen Majestät habe ich jedoch alles Wietere unterthänigst anheimzugeben.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ehrfurchstvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sarwey.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">[…]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Schreibens an den K Staatsminister des Kirchen- &amp; Schulwesens</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">v. Sawrey</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">d. 15 Mai 95.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es beehre ich mich […] mitzutheilen, dass ich K Sr. K. M. […] </seg>Anbringen vom 14. d M., betr. den Geburtstag des Dr. Frhnn v. Müller in Melbourne, zu unterbreiten habe. Sr Maj. sind vollkommen damit einverstanden, wenn Ew. dem Genannten zu seinem 70. Geburtsfeste den Glückwunsch des Kultministeriums ausprechen, u. lassen Ew. auftragen, dem […] […] zugleich […] aufrichtigen Glückwünsche zu übermitteln.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der […]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">O Beilage</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">—<seg style=""> </seg>1173</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">To the King.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Report of the State Minister of Church and Educational Affair concerning the birthday of Dr Baron Ferdinand von Mülller in Melbourne (Australia)</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgart, 14 May 1895.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your Majesty I most humbly venture to bring to your supreme knowledge that according to a notice of the 1st Curator of the Natural history Cabinet in this place, Professor Dr Lampert, Dr Baron Ferdinand von Müller, Director of the botanical and zoological garden in Melbourne, Australia, will celebrate his 70th birthday on 30 June this year. He was born in Rostock but for a long time has been closely connected to Württemberg through the extremely copious and valuable gifts, that he has made for many years to this place. After he had already had made a gift of that kind to the Natural History Cabinet here, he decided in 1869 at the instigation of the 1st Curator of the time, Senior educational Councillor Dr von Krauss, to give <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> his consignments of natural history objects to the Natural History Cabinet <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">here</hi>
               </seg>, which had the consquence that the very strange and interesting fauna and flora of New Holland is represented in the State collection here in remarkable abundance. At the same time Müller has made an endowment for a travelling scholarship for a young Württemberg natural history researcher with a view to education in natural science fields, of which much use has already been made and through which not only the educational purpose essentially has been promoted but also indirectly the Natural History Cabinet has been given an advantage in so far as according to the statutes the scholarship holder has to commit himself to give the objects collected by him to the Natural history Cabinet here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In recognition of his quite excellent service to Württemberg the Knight Cross of the Royal Order of the Crown was awarded to the above-named in the year 1867 and then he was raised through supreme resolution of 8 July 1871 into the hereditary barony of the Kingdom according to the precedent of Baron von Ludwig made famous in previous years by his gifts from South Africa. Since then von Müller has continued with his gifts to this place, so that he also can be described as a true benefactor of the natural history collection here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In consideration of the most gracious mark of honour granted to Baron von Müller according to the above, in my most humble opinion the awarding of a further mark of honour to him on the occasion of the completion of the 70th year of life should be dispensed with; however, if your Royal Majesty does not intend to be pleased to decree otherwise, at least it could be indicated that I express to Baron von Müller the best wishes of the Culture Ministry for his 70th birthday.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have, however, humbly to leave anything further to the supreme resolution of your Royal Majesty.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sarwey</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[…] of a letter to the Royal State Minister of Church &amp; Educational Affairs […] von Sarwey</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">15 May 1895</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[…] I have the honour to inform that I have not failed to lay your report of the 14th of this month concerning the birthday of Dr Baron von Müller In Melbourne before His Royal Majesty. His Majesty is completely in agreement with it, if you express to the above the best wishes of the Culture Ministry for his 70th birthday, and instructs you at the same time to convey his sincere best wishes to the Baron</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[…]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
