<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TO THE EDITOR ¶ Sir — ¶  ¶ The late Baron Ferdinand von Müller, K.C.M.G., was my oldest European acquaintance in Australia, and I can therefore give some particulars which may be interesting to South ...</title>
            <author>Friedrich Krichauff</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1890-9/M96-10-10a-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M106, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M96.10.10a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Friedrich Krichauff</author>
               <title>TO THE EDITOR ¶ Sir — ¶  ¶ The late Baron Ferdinand von Müller, K.C.M.G., was my oldest European acquaintance in Australia, and I can therefore give some particulars which may be interesting to South ...</title>
               <date when="1896-10-10">1896-10-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1890-9/M96-10-10a-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of Advertiser (Adelaide)</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">TO THE EDITOR ¶ Sir — ¶  ¶ The late Baron Ferdinand von Müller, K.C.M.G., was my oldest European acquaintance in Australia, and I can therefore give some particulars which may be interesting to South ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M96.10.10a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">Friedrich Krichauff to the Editor of Advertiser (Adelaide)</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RB MSS M106, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof</seg>
                     <seg style="color: #0815fb; font-weight: bold; ">. I did not fully proof, only enough to be sure of the source</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is the published version, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Advertiser</seg> (Adelaide), 12 October, p. 5, col. f.</p>
               </note>TO THE EDITOR</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The late Baron Ferdinand von Müller, K.C.M.G., was my oldest European acquaintance in Australia, and I can therefore give some particulars which may be interesting to South Australians, and which not even his only surviving sister, Mrs. Clara Wehl of Millicent, may recollect. He was born in Rostock, in Mecklenburg, in 1825. In 1842-3 I made his acquaintance in Husum, in the duchy of Schleswig, where he was and had been an apprentice in Mr. Becker's chemist shop.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Commenced with Albert Becker, concluded with Ernst G. E. Becker.</p>
               </note> As he had never passed through the higher classes of any college it is only to be ascribed to his abnormal energy and studiousness into the early hours of the morning, that he succeeded in mastering languages and did become such an authority on botany. He had probably thus early as good a knowledge of the flora of the duchies of Schleswig and Holstein as Professor E. Nolte, who I believe never went beyond editing his "Novitiae." After Müller had passed his pharmaceutical examination at the University of Kiel in 1846 he wrote a paper on "Thalspi bursa pastoris," for which he received his first honor, viz., D.Ph. The health of late sister Bertha, subsequently married to the late Mr. Doughty, of near Penola, required a warmer climate, and Dr. Preiss, of Herzberg in Hanover, a botanist just then returned from Western Australia, advised him to go to South Australia, which would also be a great field for a botanist. After consultation with me, who was to follow later on, he decided to go from Bremen on board the Hermann von Beckerath, which arrived at Port Adelaide on the 18th day of December, 1847. Several well-known South Australians were his fellow passengers, as Messrs. F. Heuzenroeder, sen., and C. G. Schedlich, also Sobels, Gerke, and Rodemann long since deceased. Until my arrival on December 6, 1848, he was engaged in the chemist's shop of the late Mr. Moritz Heuzenroder in Rundle-street; but had also made botanical excursions to the Murray scrub, Guichen Bay, and to Mounts Arden and Brown. At our request Sir Samuel Davenport purchased on the 24th December, 1848, from the Government, jointly with us, for subsequent division, a section of land in the Bugle Ranges. On Müller's part of 20 acres, next to mine, ha had a cottage built, and remained there with his sister, Clara, for some months intending to farm. This life, however, did not suit him, and he returned again to Adelaide for the small salary of 15s. a week until the diggings tempted him to go to Victoria, where he intended to open a chemist's shop, but was soon selected by Governor Latrobe as Government Botanist. As such he travelled all over Victoria, and also joined Gregory's expedition to North Australia. On his return he accepted the position of director of the Botanical Garden at Melbourne until relieved of that duty in 1873. I doubt whether any other botanist has published as many works on botany and kindred sciences. His "Select Plants" is translated into ever so many languages. The many decorations and honors received by him show the high appreciation in which he was held everywhere, and perhaps more so abroad than in his adopted home, which is, however, indebted to him chiefly for the discovery or else the description of numberless plants, and also practical suggestions connected with farming, horticulture, forestry, geographical expeditions, &amp;c. —</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I am, &amp;c.,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. E. H. W. KRICHAUFF</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Norwood, September 10, 1896<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
