<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 15 July 1871. ¶  ¶ How can I find the words, noble Count, to thank you for the singular favour with which you deigned to erect a geographical memorial in the glacier region...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-07-15b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sy 3350, Fürstliche Waldburg-Zeil'sche Bibliothek, Schloss Zeil, Leutkirch, Germany.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>71.07.15b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 15 July 1871. ¶  ¶ How can I find the words, noble Count, to thank you for the singular favour with which you deigned to erect a geographical memorial in the glacier region...</title>
               <date when="1871-07-15">1871-07-15</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-07-15b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Karl von Waldburg-Zeil</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 15 July 1871. ¶  ¶ How can I find the words, noble Count, to thank you for the singular favour with which you deigned to erect a geographical memorial in the glacier region...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">71.07.15b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Karl von Waldburg-Zeil</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Sy 3350, Fürstliche Waldburg-Zeil'sche Bibliothek, Schloss Zeil, Leutkirch, Germany.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter sent as an enclosure with M to A. Petermann, 14 July 1871. On 2 October 1871, on receipt of M's letter, Waldburg-Zeil wrote in his diary: 'Eine sehr grosse Freude bereitete mir heute ein Paquet aus Melbourne – Victoria Australien! 74 photographien als Stereoskope aus Land u Leben in Gypesland! von einem Dr v. Mueller Botaniker im botanischen Garten in Melbourne angestellt. Der erste Dank vor meinen Nordpolexpedition, für Benennung eines Berges nach seinem Namen. Wenn Alle Leute ebenso dankbar wären! Ja wenn! Das Geschenk ist sehr interessant u diese Anerkennung v. einem Wissenschaftsmann freut mich mehr als wenn man mir 3 Orden gebe! “Was ich mir davor koofe”!' [A packet from Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, brought me very great pleasure today! 74 photographs as stereoscopes from land and living in Gippsland from a Dr von Mueller, botanist employed at the botanical garden in Melbourne. The first thanks for my North Pole expedition, for naming a mountain after him. If only all people were so grateful! Yes, if only! The gift is very interesting and this acknowledgment by a scientific man pleases me more than if I had been given three Orders! What good will that do me?]. (The final sentence, in Berlin patois, is from 'Berlin wie es weint und lacht', a farce popular at the time by O. F. Ebersberg, who wrote as 'O. F. Berg', and David Kalisch, Berg &amp; Kalisch (1858). See entry for Ebersberg in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie.</seg>)</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Waldburg-Zeil goes on to quote most of M's letter and then continues: 'Warum sollte der Mann der ich nicht kenne mir solches zu schreiben wenn er nicht überzeugt wäre davon – Schmeicheln ohne Nuz giebt es nicht. So muss ich die Sache auffassen. Endlich will er mir einen Landtheil in Australien widmen. Wogegen ich nichts einzuwenden habe, wie es ihm schreiben werde mich für die Photographien bedankend die sehr sehr interessant sind besonders die dadurch veranschaulichte Flora Australiens' [Why should a man I do not know write this to me unless he is convinced of it; there is no such thing as flattery without [a desire for] gain. Thus must I understand the affair. Finally, he wants to dedicate to me a part of the country in Australia, to which I have no objection, as I shall write to him when I thank him for the photographs, which are very, very interesting, especially in that they illustrate the Australian flora] (NZA 56/X, Fürstliches Waldburg-Zeil'sches Gesamtarchiv, Schloss Zeil, Leutkirch, Germany). Waldburg-Zeil's letter of thanks not found.</p>
               </note>Melbourne im botanischen Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 15 Juli 1871.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie soll ich Worte finden, edler Herr Graf, Ihnen für die ausserordentliche Huld zu danken, mit welcher Sie sich herabliessen, mir dem im fernen Australlande waltenden Fremdling, ein geographisches Denkmal in den Gletscher-Regionen der arctischen Zone zu setzen! Von allen den Auszeichnungen, auf welche ich stolz sein kann, ist <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">diese</hi>
               </seg> von Ihnen, von Herrn v. Heuglin u Prof Petermann mir gewidmete diejenige auf welche ich den <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">höchsten</hi>
               </seg> Werth lege; u solche rührt mich um so mehr, als ich auf eine solche Ehrenbezeugung, die an jedem Thron mit Dank entgegenommen<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">entgegen genommen.</p>
               </note> wäre, nur so geringen Anspruch habe. Nehmen Sie also, edler Mann, meinen innigen Dank hin, dann aber auch den Ausdruck meiner Bewunderung, über die Hochherzigkeit, welche Sie veranlasste aus eignen Mitteln ein für immer denkwürdiges Unternehmen auszuführen und so die Geograph[ie]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — obscured by binding. All square brackets following have this meaning.</p>
               </note> wunderbar zu bereichern, wo es am wenigsten erwartet wurde. Sie u Herr von Heuglin müssen mit Genugthuung u Freude auf Ihre Errungenschaften des letzten Sommers blicken, wenn plötzlich nach 250 Jahren neue mächtige Gebirg[e,] neue Meeresstrassen, neue versprechende Küsten vor die geographische Welt gebracht werden! Und mit welchem patriotischen Enthusiasmus rissen Sie sich, Herr Graf, von dem glänzenden Entdeckungspfade los, um an dem Heldenzug, der für immer Deu[tsch-]lands Grösse feststellt, theil zu nehm[en.] Möge mir die Vorsehung Leben u Stärke erhalten, um hier den Wissenschaften förderlich zu sein, vielleicht nun, wenn auch schon spät im Leben, mög[e] mir das Glück den beschwerlichen Pfad erleuchtet.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">erleuchten.</p>
               </note> So hoffe ich Ihnen u Ihren geographischen Freunden auch hier im Austral-Lande einen hervorragenden Landschafttheil zu widmen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Anschauen der Karte von Spitzbergen treibt es mich fast, das eisige Wunderland, von dem wir Alle ja schon im zartesten Kindesalter hörten, selbst zu sehen!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als ein ganz geringes Erinnerungs Zeichen sende ich Ihnen mit dieser Monatspost durch die gütige Vermittlung des Herrn Professors Dr Petermann eine Anzahl stereoscopischer Photographien, die wenigstens den Reiz der Neuheit haben, u Ihnen von der Natur Süd-Ost Australiens ein volleres Bild geben mögen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr Andenken in tiefer u bewundernder Dankbarkeit bewahrend bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">15 July 1871.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How can I find the words, noble Count, to thank you for the singular favour with which you deigned to erect a geographical memorial in the glacier regions of the arctic zone to me,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mount Müller, on Edgeöya Island, Spitzbergen (Svalbard), discovered by Heuglin and Waldburg-Zeil during their expedition to Spitzbergen in 1870 and named in M's honour at Petermann's request.</p>
               </note> a stranger working in distant Australia! Of all the distinctions I can be proud of, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">this one</hi>
               </seg> dedicated to me by you, Mr von Heuglin, and Professor Petermann is the one to which I attach the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">greatest</hi>
               </seg> value; and it touches me all the more as I have so little claim on an honour such as would be accepted with gratitude by any Throne. So accept, noble Sir, my sincere gratitude, but also my expression of admiration at the generosity that induced you to carry out at your own expense an enterprise that will remain memorable for ever, and so wonderfully to enrich geography where it was least expected. You and Mr von Heuglin must look on the attainments of the last summer with satisfaction and joy when suddenly, after 250 years, new mighty mountain ranges, new straits, new promising coastlines were placed before the geographic world! And with what patriotic enthusiasm, dear Count, you tore yourself away from the lustrous path of the explorer, to take part in the heroic march that will establish Germany's greatness forever.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Franco-Prussian war, 1870-1.</p>
               </note> May Providence grant me life and strength to further the sciences here, and may good fortune illuminate my onerous path. I hope to be able to dedicate to you and your geographic friends an eminent feature in the landscape here in Australia.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M arranged for Ernest Giles to name Mount Zeil during his 1872 expedition to Central Australia and the Waldburg Ranges, WA, during his 1876 expedition.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Looking at the map of Spitzbergen, I feel almost compelled to see this icy wonderworld myself, of which we all heard already during our earliest childhood!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As a very small token of remembrance I am sending you with this month's mail, through the kind agency of Professor Petermann, a number of stereoscopic photographs that at least have the charm of novelty, and may give you a fuller picture of nature in south-eastern Australia.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The photographs were probably by the German photographer Charles Walter; cf. M to A. Petermann, 14 July 1871, n. 10.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Remembering you with deep and admiring gratitude I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
