<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 14 July 1871. ¶  ¶ How can I thank you, noble Sir, for the boundless kindness with which you have done me the incomparably great honour of erecting to me a memorial of eter...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-07-14-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>71.07.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 14 July 1871. ¶  ¶ How can I thank you, noble Sir, for the boundless kindness with which you have done me the incomparably great honour of erecting to me a memorial of eter...</title>
               <date when="1871-07-14">1871-07-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-07-14-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 14 July 1871. ¶  ¶ How can I thank you, noble Sir, for the boundless kindness with which you have done me the incomparably great honour of erecting to me a memorial of eter...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">71.07.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Petermann: 'Erh. 12. Sept. 1871. A. 15. —' [Received 12 Sept. 1871. Answered 15]. For a published version of this letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 99-101. Petermann’s letter not found.</p>
               </note>Melbourne im botanischen Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">14/7/71.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie soll ich Ihnen danken, edler Herr, für die überschwängliche Güte, durch welche Sie mich so unvergleichlich hoch geehrt haben, mir ein Denkmal ewiger Dauer in dem grossartigen Polarland zu errichten! Dieses Merkmal Ihrer Zuneigung hat mich tief gerührt, zumal da grössere Männer, mit reicheren Mitteln auf Ihre Gunst höhere Ansprüche hatten. An jedem Throne würde eine Gabe <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dieser</hi>
               </seg> Art mich<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">mit.</p>
               </note> dankbarster Anerkennung entgegen genommen werden. Auch dem Grafen von Zeil und dem Herrn von Heuglin fühle ich mich tief verpflichtet, Ihren grossmüthig<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">grossmüthigen.</p>
               </note> Vorschlag so aufopfernd secundirt zu haben. Diese edlen Männer hätten ja mit dieser Gabe Anerkennungen zu erlangen vermocht, die ich selbst nie in demselben Werthe werde leisten können. Ungewiss über den Aufenthaltsort dieser Herren erlaube ich mir, einige Dankworte an dieselben Ihrer freundlichen Vermittlung zuzusenden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wahrlich, es treibt mich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">jetzt</hi>
               </seg> es zu versuchen die eisige Grösse Spitzbergens einst im Leben selbst anzuschauen. Sollte mir die Vorsehung Leben u Kraft erhalten, so hoffe ich innerhalb der nächsten Jahre Ihnen, edler Mann, u auch diesen Edelleuten einen wichtigen geographischen Punkt in Australien zu widmen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um einstweilen, wenn auch in noch so geringer Weise, thatsächlich meine Dankbarkeit zu bekunden, sende ich Ihnen u dem Grafen Zeil u Herrn von Heuglin mit dieser Post eine Anzahl stereoscopischer Photogramme, die jüngst von einem <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">deutschen</hi>
               </seg> Künstler hier angefertigt wurden u. australische Landschaften u auch einige Eingeborene darstellen, die dem höchsten Geographen der Zeit vielleicht nicht ohne Werth sein werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dieselbe Post, welche mir diese <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hohe</hi>
               </seg> geographische Auszeichnung brachte, war auch die Bringerin einer sehr herrlichen Gabe des Kaisers von Russland, indem S. Maj. sich herabliess mir dem anspruchslosen im fernen Australlande weilenden Naturbeobachter einige Zeichen seiner Huld zu senden, bestehend in 2 kostbaren Jaspisvasen u einem andern grössern Gegenstand aus diesem werthvollen Mineral. Alles dies rührt mich tief, sehr tief; u ich flehe von der Vorsehung dass Sie mir Stärke gebe, mich diesem hohen wissenschaftlichen u. fürstlichen Wohlwollen würdig zu erweisen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Jahre 1870 u in der ersten Hälfte dieses Jahres habe ich viel Widerwärtigkeiten durchlebt, solche wie sie nur in einem jungen Lande mit allgemeiner Wahlfreiheit möglich sind. Jetzt indessen gestalten sich auch für mich die Verhältnisse freundlicher, u. so hoffe ich mit frischem Lebensmuthe auch Ihnen fortan nützlicher zu werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Für Hr Dr Hermann Wagner habe ich die statistischen Documente über Australien soweit herbeigeschafft, wie solche zur Zeit erlangbar waren; einige Papiere werden aber erst über 1870 im Aug. des Jahres erscheinen. Ist Hr Dr Wagner meinem dahingeschiedenen Freunde Prof Rudolph Wagner, dem grossen vergleichenden Anatom u Physiologen, irgendwie verwandt? </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Dr Haast hat unter günstigen Umständen die Untersuchungen von Colenso u Andern über die den Moaries<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Maoris.</p>
               </note> vorangegangene Race der "Moa Jäger" glänzend weiter verfolgt u nachgewiesen, dass diese ersten Bewohner Neu Seelands den Moaries erlagen. Mir ist die Idee entstanden, die ich den Herrn Dr Haast u Dr Hector mittheilte, dass vielleicht die Moa Jäger dem selben Stamme angehörten, von dem noch eine geringe Zahl in tiefster Unterdrückung unter den Moaris<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Maoris.</p>
               </note> der Chatham Inseln lebt. Die neue Reise des jungen Travers nach dieser kleinen Inselgruppe wird wohl weitere Materialien für Schädelvergleiche u vielleicht weitere Nachforschungen über die Traditionen der Chathamier liefern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In tiefster Ehrerbietung u. Dankbarkeit der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Für mehrfache literarische Sendungen bin Ich Ihnen dankbar verpflichtet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Bevölkerung Südaustraliens ist 185,000.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14 July 1871.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How can I thank you, noble Sir, for the boundless kindness with which you have done me the incomparably great honour of erecting to me a memorial of eternal duration in the grandiose Polar country!<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mount Mueller on Edgeöya Island, Spitzbergen (Svalbard).</p>
               </note> This token of your affection has touched me deeply, especially as greater men with greater means had higher claims on your favour. Any Throne would accept <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">such</hi>
               </seg> a gift with the most grateful appreciation. I also feel under a deep obligation to Count von Zeil and Mr von Heuglin, who so unselfishly seconded your generous proposal. These noble men could, after all, have gained approbation with this gift, which I myself shall never be able to provide in the same measure. Uncertain of these gentlemen's place of domicile, I take the liberty of addressing a few words of thanks to them for your kind transmission.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to C. von Waldburg-Zeil, 15 July 1871 (In this edition as 71-07-15b). Letter to Heuglin not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Truly, I am <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">now</hi>
               </seg> driven to attempt myself to gaze on the icy grandeur of Spitsbergen at some time in my life. If Providence preserves my life and strength, I hope to dedicate within the next few years an important geographical feature in Australia to you, noble Sir, and also to these noble gentlemen.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was as good as his word, arranging for Ernest Giles during his 1872 expedition to Central Australia to name three prominent features as Petermann Creek, Mount Heuglin (now Mt Heughlin) and Mount Zeil. (Other features named included the Krichauff Range, Ellery Creek, Rudall's Creek, Mount Sonder, Mount Liebig, Haast's Bluff and the Ehrenberg Range.) During his 1873-4 expedition Giles named the Petermann Range, west of Mt Olga (Kata Tjuta). In 1876, he named the Waldburg Range in WA.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the meantime, to show my gratitude in deed, even though only in a very small way, I am sending you, Count Zeil, and Mr von Heuglin a number of stereoscopic photograms with <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>this mail,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Waldburg-Zeil, in a diary entry of 2 October 1871, mentioned 74 steroscopic photographs of Gippsland, forwarded to him by Petermann. He wrote 'The gift is very interesting, and this acknowledgement from a man of science gives me greater pleasure, than if I were given 3 Orders. ... They are very, very interesting, especially by illustrating the Australian flora.' (NZA 56/X, Fürstliches Waldburg-Zeil'sches Gesamtarchiv, Schloss Zeil, Leutkirch, Germany.)</p>
               </note> produced here recently by a local <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">German</hi>
               </seg> artist,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Charles Walter.</p>
               </note> showing Australian landscapes and also some Aborigines, that may perhaps be of some value to the greatest geographer of our time.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This same mail, that brought me this <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">high</hi>
               </seg> geographical distinction, was also the bringer of a very glorious gift from the Emperor of Russia,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Alexander II.</p>
               </note> in that His Majesty deigned to send me, the modest naturalist living in distant Australia, some token of his graciousness, consisting of two precious vases of jasper and another larger article of this valuable mineral.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See E. Regel to M, 1 April 1871.</p>
               </note> All of this touches me deeply, very deeply; and I pray that Providence will give me strength to prove myself worthy of such high scientific and royal benevolence.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In 1870 and in the first half of this year I have suffered many adversities, such as are possible only in a young country with universal suffrage. However, conditions are now becoming more favourable for me and, with new zest for life, I hope to continue to be of more use to you, too, in the future.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have just about brought together the statistical documents on Australia for Dr Hermann Wagner as far as they were available at present; a few papers for 1870, however, are not going to be published until August. Is Dr Wagner in some way related to my late friend, Professor Rudolph Wagner, the great comparative anatomist and physiologist?<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hermann Wagner was Rudolph Wagner's son.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Haast has brilliantly continued the research of Colenso<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">William Colenso.</p>
               </note> and others under favourable circumstances into the race of the Moa hunters, that preceded the Maoris and has shown, that these first inhabitants of New Zealand fell victim to the Maoris.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Haast (1872).</p>
               </note> An idea came to me, which I communicated to Dr Haast and Dr Hector,<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Haast, 8 April 1871. Letter to Hector not found.</p>
               </note> that perhaps the Moa hunters belonged to the same tribe, of which a small number is still living in abject subjugation under the Maoris on the Chatham Islands. The new journey of young Travers to this small group of islands should provide further materials for comparisons of skulls and perhaps further researches into the traditions of the Chatham Islanders.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With deepest respect and gratitude</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I am gratefully obliged to you for repeated literary transmissions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The population of South Australia is 185,000.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
