<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot Garden ¶ 6/5/71. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In compliance with your request for information in the intended ascent of Mount Bellenden Ker, ¶ The Colonial Secretary's Office, Brisbane, wrote to the Chief...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-05-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Z71/5776, unit 576, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>71.05.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot Garden ¶ 6/5/71. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In compliance with your request for information in the intended ascent of Mount Bellenden Ker, ¶ The Colonial Secretary's Office, Brisbane, wrote to the Chief...</title>
               <date when="1871-05-06">1871-05-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-05-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Odgers</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot Garden ¶ 6/5/71. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In compliance with your request for information in the intended ascent of Mount Bellenden Ker, ¶ The Colonial Secretary's Office, Brisbane, wrote to the Chief...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">71.05.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Odgers</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Z71/5776, unit 576, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">6/5/71.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In compliance with your request for information in the intended ascent of Mount Bellenden Ker,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Colonial Secretary's Office, Brisbane, wrote to the Chief Secretary, Melbourne, on 11 April 1871, asking for information about an expedition to the Bellenden Ker Hills proposed by M, about which the Surveyor General in Queensland had made recommendations about departures and cost. The Undersecretary, W. Odgers, had forwarded the letter to M on 25 April with the note: 'Will Dr von Mueller be good enough to report if he knows anything in the correspondence to which Mr Secretary Palmer refers'.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have the honor to inform you, that I had no strictly official communications with the Government of Queensland on this subject, but that I interchanged occasionally since several years letters with members of the Queensland Government, with one or the other of whom I was personally acquainted, and had also communications with some Gentlemen in Queensland on this subject, who are interested in the progress of geography, just as I now am in communication with the authorities in Queensland concerning the final disclosure of Leichhardt's fate.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is not known to what M is referring here.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The special interest, which to me arises in the the ascent of the Bellenden Ker Range, is resting on the fact, that the botanical collector of the Department under my surveillance is stationed at Rockingham's Bay,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>John Dallachy.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and that a track to the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">highest</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>mountain of Queensland would give him a most favorable line for new operations, with a view of augmenting the plants in my conservatories and museum, and for obtaining new material for interchanges.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As regards the proposition of the Surveyor General of Queensland, that any ascent of the Bellenden Ker Range should be made from a near inlet of the sea, I beg leave to remark, that altho' such arrangement would be most important to try of adding a new harbour or coast settlement to the possessions of Queensland and would for exploration purposes be an admirable plan, it would involve far greater expense and far more risk, then a mere cutting of a track for packhorses from the nearest occupied position towards the Mount. The plan of proceeding by sea would moreover have the disadvantage of depriving the party of the use of horses for packs or burden, whereas a direct advance by land on the mount would at once connect the police station of Cashmere and the sugarplantation, formed by Mr Davidson, with the new line through the forests. The party in the event of distress could in the latter case always fall back on the settlements with a clear calculation of time, while<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in the other case the voyagers and land-party would be<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for a length of time separated<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and either of them depend on wind and weather for their return.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My own ideas are simply to this effect, that a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">few</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the native troopers, stationed in the Rockingham's Bay district, should for any ascent of the Bellenden Ker ranges be rendered available, if the Queensland Government should wish this range, the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">highest</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in their territory, to be reached; that a few bush-labourers should be engaged to accompany the troopers; that a surveyor should lead the party; that they should start from the nearest place occupied, and advance by land; that they should cut a track, where jungle cannot be avoided, simply wide enough to allow horses in a single line to pass; that the members of the party should keep together until they approach towards the higher parts of the range, from whence without any fear whatever from natives, who do not live there, some of the explorers could reach the summit on foot; that rations for a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">few</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>weeks should be provided, within which time the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>ascent is almost certain to have been accomplished; that some oats should be taken for the horses to feed them where no grass can be found;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that the collector of our botanic Garden should accompany the party. Under such an arrangement, if a few volunteers join and the police and settlers afford the loan of the horses, the whole outlay of the expedition ought not to exceed one hundred pounds (£100) to the Queensland Government, and no risk would be incurred. Supposed the party did unexpectedly meet with unsurmountable obstacles, the members can all earlier return, without their retreat being ever endangered, and so much additional knowledge of the country would be gained.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My own opinion does not limit the result of this ascent to the mere obtaining of new plants because 1, a very important position would be gained at the highest elevation of Queensland for the trigonometric survey, and a set of important angles be obtained for mapping a wide tract of unexplored country from this commanding hight.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2, the geologic nature of these very high mountains would be ascertained, their geologic structure being indiscernible from any distance and their<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>elucidation requiring absolute traversal. It would then be shown, whether the country is likely auriferous, or what other ore such mount may possess, as no high range is without metallic riches.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3, It would simultaneously be ascertained by views from the summit, in what direction the approaches to these mountains can afterwards best be effected from various points, and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>what line offers the best access from the sea.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4, It would be made out, whether any open available pastoral land was stretching towards these mountains</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5, the gathering of plants would not be a mere matter of curiosity, but be instituted with a view of finding out new substances for medicine, commerce and industries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6, there are several other objects to be obtained for the gain of knowledge, on which the intended brief scope of this letter forbids me to dwell.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It remains for me only yet to point out, that so important a geographic exploit, at so small a cost within a few weeks time, does in my humble opinion not require any aid from the Victorian Government, unless the honorable the Chief Secretary, Sir James M'Culloch, would<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>concede<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>a subsidy of perhaps fifty pounds (£50) with a view of permitting the botanic collector of my establishment to purchase a saddle horse and a pack horse and the trifling outfit, which he will stand in need of; this recommendation deserves all the more favorable consideration, as the collector in the execution of his duties for the Victorian Government lost lately a fine horse, his private property.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is almost needless to add, that any tour<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the Bellenden Ker mountains must be carried out in the least rainy season. It seems, that a visit, very recently made by the honorable the Minister of Lands of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Quueensland<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to Rockingham's Bay, where the honorable Gentleman met the collector of our botanic Garden, has more immediately given rise to the communication now before us</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to be, Sir, your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gov. botanist &amp;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Director of the botanic Garden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">W. H. Odgers Esqr</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Undersecretary</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by the Chief Secretary, J. McCulloch, 14 May 1871: 'I have to request Dr Mueller to forward all communications with other Govts through this office It is evident that the Queensland Govt consider that suggestions have been made by Dr Mueller which will [see expenditure<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[... ... ...<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>...] It would be of great advantage if Dr Mueller would confine his letters <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[... ... ...] his time<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on those [... ... ...]'.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
