<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Opinions of the Government Botanist on the proposed alterations in the Thistles Prevention Statute of 9th May 1865. ¶ A,  ¶  ¶  ¶ Proceedings of Shires, Boroughs and Road Boards conference. ¶  ¶ Secti...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-09-09-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>B72/4671, unit 598, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>71.09.09</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Opinions of the Government Botanist on the proposed alterations in the Thistles Prevention Statute of 9th May 1865. ¶ A,  ¶  ¶  ¶ Proceedings of Shires, Boroughs and Road Boards conference. ¶  ¶ Secti...</title>
               <date when="1871-09-09">1871-09-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-09-09-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Cryptostemum calendulaceum</term>
               <term>Centaurea Melitensis</term>
               <term>Medicago denticulata</term>
               <term>Carduus lanceolatus</term>
               <term>Onopordum Acanthium</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/60b42d5e-535b-4b5a-897b-ab9c573a8953">Rumex conglomeratus</term>
               <term>Carduus benedictus</term>
               <term>Carduus palustris</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/11072f54-8547-49bd-aeb0-ff4681846358">Xanthium spinosum</term>
               <term>Carduus Marianus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/9969bc3c-76c9-4aa9-aa0e-301b767d1e3c">Rumex crispus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>tab alignment</term>
               <term>even tabulation</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Charles Gavan Duffy</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Opinions of the Government Botanist on the proposed alterations in the Thistles Prevention Statute of 9th May 1865. ¶ A,  ¶  ¶  ¶ Proceedings of Shires, Boroughs and Road Boards conference. ¶  ¶ Secti...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">71.09.09</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Charles Gavan Duffy</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">B72/4671, unit 598, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter written by a clerk and signed by M </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Odgers referred the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Proceedings of Shires, Boroughs &amp; Road Boards conference, 1871</seg> to M on 30 August 1871, asking for his views on the proposed amendments to the thistle statute printed on p. 4, and on other proposals on the same topic. M evidently also sought the views of William Ferguson and included his reasponse, dated 9 September, along with his own report, when he returned the file, minuted: 'The opinions of the Gov. Botanist on these documents are appended, also some notes of the Forest inspector. Ferd. von Mueller. 9/9 71'. Ferguson reported his successful experience in eradicating thistles 'when they were beginning to show their flowers', and suggested that 'the "Dock" and "Bathurst Burr" be included in an amended Thistle Statute'. M added a note in the margin of Ferguson's report: 'The Bathurst Burr is already included among the plants enumerated in the Thistle Prevention Statute of 1865. It is an annual plant and therefore with at least quite as much facility destroyed as the ordinary biennial Thistle'. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a report of the discussion on thistles, see 'Shires, Boroughs and Road Boards conference', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg> (Melbourne), 22 July 1871, p. 3.</p>
               </note>Opinions of the Government Botanist on the proposed alterations in the Thistles Prevention Statute of 9th May 1865.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">A, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Proceedings of Shires, Boroughs and Road Boards conference.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Section 3.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In as much as the term "prickly thistle" is not scientifically or even popularly recognized, I beg to advise that this clause should be amended as follows:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"In the construction of this act the word "thistles" shall be held to mean and include the plants known by the botanical and vernacular names of <name key="Carduus%20Marianus">Carduus Marianus</name> or Milk or Spotted Thistle, <name key="Carduus%20lanceolatus">Carduus lanceolatus</name> or Spear Thistle, Carduus arvensis or Creeping Thistle, <name key="Carduus%20palustris">Carduus palustris</name> or Marsh Thistle, <name key="Onopordum%20Acanthium">Onopordum Acanthium</name> or Real Scotch Thistle or Cotton Thistle, and <name key="Xanthium%20spinosum">Xanthium spinosum</name> or Bathurst Burr; and that the onus or proof that any plant on account of which law proceedings are taken, does not belong to any of those named in the act shall be with the defendant.["]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It will be observed that the <name key="Carduus%20benedictus">Carduus benedictus</name> mentioned in the act is omitted in this amended clause, that particular plant, the Holy Thistle,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation: '?retain'.</p>
               </note> having lately almost disappeared, it moreover having never been really abundant; but two additional Thistles are now specified, which invaded more lately this colony, probably from Tasmania, where they are long naturalized, and I deem it particularly desirable that these should be included, as both are troublesome, and particularly so the Carduus arvensis<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation: '?as to stringent provisions of the Act — how are they to be destroyed'.</p>
               </note> on account of its creeping <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">perennial</hi>
               </seg> root, which is very tenacious of life. I may add that all the other thistles can be destroyed by preventing their seeding; and this measure can be effected by cutting or uprooting the plants when coming into flower — which may be required a second time — and burning them; all the thistles now mentioned, except the Creeping Thistle, have roots of only one or two years duration.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In my opinion it is however advisable, that provision should be made in the new act, to add to the list of thistles any other kinds, which may successively find their way into this colony, and which may be deemed by the Government Botanist as sufficiently noxious to be operated against in conformity with this act.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation: 'If this suggestion be adopted it will be sufficient to give power to the Gov. in C. [Council] to add. —'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reference to the Docks, of which two kinds have become frequent in Victoria, namely the Curled Dock (<name key="Rumex%20crispus">Rumex crispus</name>) and the Clustered Dock (<name key="Rumex%20conglomeratus">Rumex conglomeratus</name>) I would observe, that it is impossible to destroy them by merely cutting the plants, their roots being of several years or even many years duration, requiring to be dug up. To cut the Docks and to burn the herb before the seeds have ripened will however prevent the further dissemination of these weeds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Section 9</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">13, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The proposition asked for by Councils or Boards, to lease or let unoccupied lands of absent proprietors for a term so long as even <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">seven</hi>
               </seg> years, to recover expenses for destroying thistles, seems a measure of severity, though the leasing of the land would be far preferable to its sale; but it would in my opinion be required to mitigate this power as regards length of time, and also to fix by law the maximum rate of expense for destroying the thistles, such rate not to exceed a fixed sum per acre.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I see no objection to the adoption of the other clauses, proposed by the Conference.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">B. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Glenlyon, Franklin and Daylesford Agricultural Society.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It seems to me, that it cannot well be made compulsory to destroy under the "Thistle Act" such plants as the Docks and Wireweed, unless the whole scope of the statute is extended, and unless many other troublesome weeds, such as the Burr Clover (<name key="Medicago%20denticulata">Medicago denticulata</name>) the South European Star Thistle (<name key="Centaurea%20Melitensis">Centaurea Melitensis</name>), Cryptostemum<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cryptostemma</seg>?</p>
               </note> calendulaceum and many other weeds, were also included in the operations of the act. The thistles are particularly dangerous in spreading, because the seeds by means of their feathery downs are easily and widely blown about, while the prickly fruit of the Bathurst Burr is likewise readily carried from spot to spot, particularly by flocks. It is desirable that Docks should be suppressed, still they do not spread with the facility of Thistles.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">C. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr. McKnights<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">C. H. Macknight?</p>
               </note> Propositions.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The proposition of destroying thistles on runs <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">solely</hi>
               </seg> through depasturing of sheep is open to this objection, that in very many places the seeds will ripen to be carried from the pastures to agricultural land. At all events it should be compulsory to allow no thistles to grow on pasture land within a certain number of miles from agricultural areas, although even this exemption from the law would not likely prove desirable.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The removal of each separate set of flowers, as suggested, would entail far too much labor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To exhaust widely the soil for thistles through their own growth seems to me an impossibility, even if thus the impoverishing of the soil was not objectionable in itself. But as already remarked the thistles when uprooted or cut should be collected and burnt, or they might be covered up in holes for decay. Whereever the destruction of the thistles through sheep can be completely effected, there will be no necessity whatever of adopting other measures of eradication, and consequently no occasion will arise for enforcing the Thistle Act.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am satisfied that the tonic effect, which the thistle may have on sheep, is produced by many other always available herbs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I see no applicable means to attain the object of depriving the thistles of their successive buds before flowering, by framing and enforcing a clause to that effect in a legal statute. If pastoral areas are to be exempted from the act at all I would suggest certainly that the law of destroying the thistles should be kept with rigour along all the boundary lines of such areas. To effect the destruction of these plants through sheep is assuredly open to any one, who likes to adopt this method.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">D, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ballarat Agricultural and Pastoral Society.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The name "Prickly Scotch Thistle" is not universally recognized. By adopting along with the botanical name the accepted English vernacular names for the various thistles now common here, all misconceptions are obviated, and yet a clear definition is gained, while the exclusive adoption of vernacular names might lead to legal disputes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">2, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All species of real thistles must be injurious to agricultural land, though they may possibly be innocuous on pastoral land. I hold however, that thistles even on runs should be supplanted by more nutritious herbs and by the best perennial grasses; and I believe that by the total suppression of the thistle in favor of more useful plants also the pastoral interests of our colony will be very much advanced.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The thistle florishes in Victoria throughout the year, hence to limit the thistle season from September to May is inadmissible.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All the other clauses suggested by the Society seem to be just and to have a practical bearing.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>9/9/71.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Parsons (1973) for a discussion of noxious weeds, including thistles: in a review of the history of legislation the author points out (pp. 14-15) that changes were not made to the thistle legislation until <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Carduus arvensis</seg> was added in 1885.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Carduus%20benedictus">Carduus benedictus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Carduus%20lanceolatus">Carduus lanceolatus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Carduus%20Marianus">Carduus Marianus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Carduus%20palustris">Carduus palustris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Centaurea%20Melitensis">Centaurea Melitensis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cryptostemum%20calendulaceum">Cryptostemum calendulaceum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Medicago%20denticulata">Medicago denticulata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Onopordum%20Acanthium">Onopordum Acanthium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Rumex%20conglomeratus">Rumex conglomeratus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Rumex%20crispus">Rumex crispus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xanthium%20spinosum">Xanthium spinosum</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
