<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 1 December 1871. ¶ My dear friend, ¶  ¶ Since the day before yesterday I have the following articles in my possession: 1. a map of Melbourne; 2. a pamphlet for the natural history society; ¶ ...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-12-01-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M99.8, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>71.12.01</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 1 December 1871. ¶ My dear friend, ¶  ¶ Since the day before yesterday I have the following articles in my possession: 1. a map of Melbourne; 2. a pamphlet for the natural history society; ¶ ...</title>
               <date when="1871-12-01">1871-12-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1871/71-12-01-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Aconitum</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 1 December 1871. ¶ My dear friend, ¶  ¶ Since the day before yesterday I have the following articles in my possession: 1. a map of Melbourne; 2. a pamphlet for the natural history society; ¶ ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">71.12.01</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M99.8, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg d 1 Dec 71.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mein lieber Freund,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit vorgestern bin ich im Besitz der nachstehenden Gegenstände 1, Karte von Melbourne. 2, Broschüre für den naturw. Verein. 3, Abdruck von New veget. Fossils. 4, 16 Stereoskopen Bilder. Dieselben kamen via Brindisi, ein Brief war nicht dabei, vielleicht kommt der über England nach. Dass Sie wohl sind, vermuthe ich aus den erwähnten Sendungen. — Herzlichen Dank für die interessanten Geschenke[.] Die Stereoskopen sind täglich mit vielem Interesse betrachtet, u vielfache Betrachtungen u Muthmassungen darüber angestellt, namentlich unter den Kindern bei denen der Baron von Müller immer die erste Rolle spielt. Was die Karte von Melbourne anbetrifft, so kann ich Ihnen leider kein Gegenstück von Hamburg anbieten, wir haben noch keine solche Ansicht aus der Vogelperspektive, ein Zeichen dass Australien uns in manchen Dingen voraus ist. Die paläontologische Schrift habe ich mit Vergnügen gelesen, welche schönen Entdeckungen in diesem Felde sind von Australien noch zu erwarten. Hoffentlich werden Sie darüber unsere lebenden Pflanzen nicht ganz zurücksetzen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vom alten Freund Hampe habe ich Ihnen einen herzlichen Gruss zu bestellen, Sie möchten ihm nicht übel nehmen, dass er Ihnen noch nicht geantwortet habe, er ist aber seit seiner Rückkehr von Rostock nicht ganz wohl, u namentlich soll er seine Augen vorläufig nicht anstrengen. Seine sonst sehr kräftige Natur wird bald alles überwunden haben. Er hat mir in diesen Tagen auch die letzten Ihrer Moose bestimmt zurückgeschickt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe Ihnen wohl im vorigen Brief geschrieben, dass Prof. Lindberg mir einen Catalog u.s.w. der in der Flora danica enthaltenen Moose übersandt hat. Aber immer hat er nicht geschrieben, worüber ich mich nicht beruhigen kann u ihn in diesen Tagen nochmals auffordern werde, mir den Empfang der Flora Tasmaniae doch endlich mit Worten anzuzeigen. Ebenso die Ankunft der zuletzt gesandten Laubmoose. Wenn er nur Sie davon in Kenntnis gesetzt hat, so bin ich zufrieden, aber das scheint nicht der Fall zu sein. Hampe erzählte mir schon vor einem Jahre, Lindberg habe über Ihre Moose etwas publicirt u ein neues Genus beschrieben, das er (Hpe) aus der Beschreibung nicht erkennen könne; auf meine Anfrage an Lindlberg keine Antwort! und doch corrrespondirt er mit Rabenhorst u sonstigen Bekannten in Deutschland.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Haage &amp; Schmidt habe ich nicht, wie mir geschrieben wurde, ein <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Kistchen</hi>
               </seg> sondern eine <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">grosse Kiste</hi>
               </seg> mit Sämereien für Sie gestern erhalten. Die Herren hätten die Kiste richtiger auf <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ihre</hi>
               </seg> Kosten nach England befördern können oder sollen, damit Ihnen nicht die Unkosten zufallen. Ein zweites Mal soll es nicht wieder passiren. — Eine zweite kleine Kiste wird mit der Samenkiste zugleich abgesandt, worin lebende Exemplare von <name key="Aconitum">Aconitum</name> Arten. Möge alles glücklich ankommen. — Kann ich die Drucksachen für Sie gleich mit beifügen, so soll es heute noch geschehen, sonst in einem Separatpacket.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit der vorigen Briefpost sandte ich etwas an die Addresse des Herrn Groener, der Inhalt ist aber für Sie bestimmt, u das Ganze darauf berechnet, Ihnen eine kleine Freude zu machen. Der Auszug aus dem Port Denison Times nennt mich mit einem neuen Namen. Mich wundert, dass Ihr Name nicht dabei genannt ist, wahrscheinlich haben Sie den Artikel selbst geschrieben. Ich werde jedenfalls noch einige Ex. meiner Arbeit für Hr Killner u. a. senden, umso mehr, da die Schriften des naturwiss. Vereins nicht in den Buchhandel gelangen. — Ich ersehe aus Ihrem Briefe vom 6 Sept, dass das Telegramm über Ceylon angelangt ist, aber was nützt das Telegraphiren, wenn es nicht schneller geht. Aber ich hatte doch auch mit der Post geschrieben, u begreife nicht, dass der Brief nicht angekommen ist. Hoffentlich ist er nachträglich angelangt. Die so eben angekommene Londoner Post hat wieder keinen Brief von Ihnen gebracht. Dass Sie Ihren Eindringling los werden, ist eine grosse Freude für mich. Ihre Rede über die Austral. Waldcultur ist von mir aus schon durch mehrere Hände gegangen. Die Melbourner müssten wahnsinnig sein, wenn sie aus der Arbeit oder Rede nicht ersehen sollten, wie nutzbringend Ihre Bestrebungen für das Land sind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der beifolgende Brief war nach meiner Meinung für Sie bestimmt, obgleich auf dem Couvert meine Addresse stand. Die Kreuzbandsendung ist bis zu diesem Augenblick noch nicht eingetroffen. Hoffend in den nächsten Tagen einen Brief von Ihnen zu erhalten</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">grüssend der Ihrige</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 1 December 1871.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dear friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since the day before yesterday I have the following articles in my possession: 1. a map of Melbourne; 2. a pamphlet for the natural history society;<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Natural History Society (Naturwissenschaftlicher Verein), Hamburg.</p>
               </note> 3. a reprint about New vegetable fossils;<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B71.08.01.</p>
               </note> 4. 16 stereoscopic pictures. They came via Brindisi, no letter was enclosed, perhaps it will come via England. I assume from the parcel, that you are well. Sincere thanks for the interesting gifts. The stereoscopes are viewed daily with a great deal of interest, and many observations and conjectures are advanced about them, especially among the children, with whom Baron von Mueller always plays the most important role. Concerning the map of Melbourne, I can unfortunately offer nothing equivalent of Hamburg in return; we do not yet have such a bird's eye view, a sign that Australia is ahead of us in many things. I have read the palaeontological essay with pleasure; what beautiful discoveries in this field we can yet expect from Australia. But I hope you will not neglect our living plants completely for them. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am to pass on to you sincere regards from our old friend Hampe, and you must not be offended, that he has not yet replied to you. Since his return from Rostock he has not been really well, and in particular is not supposed to strain his eyesight at present. But his otherwise robust good health will help him to get over this soon. During the last few days he returned to me your mosses with identifications. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I think I wrote to you in my previous letter, that Professor Lindberg sent to me a catalogue of the mosses contained in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora danica</seg>. But he still has not written, and I cannot help worrying about that. In the next few days I will request again, that he acknowledge receipt of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora Tasmaniae</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker (1860). See M to O. Lindberg, 15 July 1871 (in this edition as 71-07-15c).</p>
               </note> in writing. And the same about the arrival of the recently sent musci. As long as he has notified you, I will be content, but that does not seem to be the case. Hampe told me more than a year ago, that Lindberg published something about your mosses and described a new genus, which he (Hampe) did not recognise from the description. On my inquiry to Lindberg no reply! — yet he corresponds with Rabenhorst and other acquaintances in Germany.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> Yesterday I received from Haage &amp; Schmidt not, as they had written, a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">small box</hi>
               </seg>, but a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">large case</hi>
               </seg> with seeds for you. The gentlemen really could, or rather should have shipped it to England at <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">their</hi>
               </seg> expense, so that you will not have to bear the cost. It will not happen a second time. — A second small case containing live specimens of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Aconitum">Aconitum</name>
               </seg> will be dispatched at the same time as the case with the seeds. May everything arrive safely! — Should I be able to send the printed matter for you at the same time, it shall be attended to today, otherwise in a separate parcel.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With the previous letter mail I sent something to Mr Groener's address, but the contents are for you, and the whole intended to give you a little pleasure. The extract from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Port Denison Times</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Extract not found.</p>
               </note> cites me with a new name. I wondered that your name was not cited with it, probably you have written the article yourself. I will send a few more reprints of my work<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder (1871).</p>
               </note> for Mr Killner<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">F. Kilner.</p>
               </note> and others, especially as the publications of the Naturwissenschaftliche Verein do not get into the book trade. — I see from your letter of 6 September, that the telegram arrived via Ceylon,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Neither the letter nor the telegram has been found.</p>
               </note> but what is the use of telegrams, if they do not get there any faster. But I had also written through the mail, and cannot understand that the letter has not reached you.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> The London mail has just arrived, but again no letter from you. It is a great joy to me, that you are getting rid of your intruder.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">William Ferguson.</p>
               </note> Your lecture about Australian forest culture<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably B71.13.03.</p>
               </note> has passed through several hands through me. Melbournians must be mad, if they can not understand from your work or your lecture, how useful your endeavours are for the country.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The enclosed letter was, I think, meant for you, even though my address was on the envelope.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not identified.</p>
               </note> So far the dispatch of printed matter has not yet arrived. Hoping to receive a letter from you during the next few days, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain with best regards</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your W. Sonder.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Aconitum">Aconitum</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
