<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ In recent times, noble friend, I have made further consignments of algae to you from time to time, and I shall also continue to send such in the future as soon as I get more. But now I have a parti...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-08-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>82.08.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ In recent times, noble friend, I have made further consignments of algae to you from time to time, and I shall also continue to send such in the future as soon as I get more. But now I have a parti...</title>
               <date when="1882-08-12">1882-08-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-08-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jacob Agardh</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ In recent times, noble friend, I have made further consignments of algae to you from time to time, and I shall also continue to send such in the future as soon as I get more. But now I have a parti...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">82.08.12</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Jacob Agardh</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">12/8/82</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Zeit zu Zeit, edler Freund, habe ich Ihnen weitere Sendungen von Algen in letzterer Zeit gemacht, u werde ich auch fortfahren in Zukunft solche zu schicken, so wie ich mehr erlange. Nun habe ich aber eine besondere Bitte; es ist diese, dass Sie mir ein Exemplar jeder Art, wenn auch nur fragmentarisch, für das Staats-Herbarium von Melbourne zurück senden, besonders auch von verschiedenen Standorten. Es ist dies um so wichtiger jetzt, da ich für die Regierung von Victoria das ganze Herbarium unseres verewigten Freundes Sonder gekauft habe. Da nun die Algen darin so reich vertreten sind, ist es eine Ehrensache, dass ich es auch fürder bereichere, namentlich aus Australien. Sie werden mittlerweile auch wohl von der Frau Dr Sonder die noch unbearbeiteten Algen erhalten haben, an welchen der Verstorbene in letztem Winter arbeiten wollte. Dann ersuche ich Sie auch besonders, wo etwas extra abzulassen ist, 1 Ex. Sr Excellenz dem Admiral Acton in Rome, dortigen Marine Minister u eifrigen Algen Sammler, zuzuwenden. Ich hatte einen Brief vom Admiral mit letzter Post, und da ich überzeugt bin, dass Sie meine Bitte gewähren, habe ich Sr. Exc. gerathen, dem Consul Italiens in Lund Auftrag zu geben, Ihre Sendungen anderen, die von Ihrer Stadt zeitweilig nach Rome an die Italienische Regierung gehen, beizufügen. Auf diese Weise wären Sie aller Mühe und jeder Ausgabe überhoben. Nun habe ich noch ein anderes Ersuchen, lieber Herr Professor, es ist dies, mir von Zeit zu Zeit Notizen über neue Arten für Australien u. auch über neue Standorte zu geben, damit ich solche in die Fragm. phytogr. Austral. aufnehmen kann ohne Verzug längerer Zeit. Dazu kommt noch, dass ich 1883 die Evasculares für den 3ten Theil des Census der Pflanzen-Arten Australiens zu veröffentlichen habe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Für dies Opus werde ich auch in Bezug auf die geographische Verbreitung und die ursprüngliche Literatur in zweifelhaften Fällen Ihre Hülfe anrufen müssen oder vielleicht würden Sie mir die Gefälligkeit erweisen, das Manuscript, welches ich ja leicht per Post schicken könnte, zu revidiren, eine Gunst die ich auch bezüglich der Moose, Flechten u Pilze von anderen Special Forschern erbitten muss.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoffend dass Sie sich fester Gesundheit erfreuen, und so noch recht lange in Ihrer Lieblingswissenschaft grossartig fortwirken werden, bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Port Jackson ist sehr arm an Algen, sonst würde ich diese "Brocken" gar nicht gesandt haben.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; text-align: end; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="de">12/8/82</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In recent times, noble friend, I have made further consignments of algae to you from time to time, and I shall also continue to send such in the future as soon as I get more. But now I have a particular request; it is this, that you send back to me a specimen of each species, even if only fragmentary, for the State Herbarium of Melbourne, particularly also of different localities. This is so much more important now, since I have purchased for the Government of Victoria the whole herbarium of our late friend Sonder. Now since the algae are so richly represented in it, it is a matter of honour that I also further enrich it, particularly from Australia. Meanwhile you will probably also have received from Mrs Sonder the still unworked algae on which the deceased intended to work in the last winter. Then I also ask you, particularly where something extra is to be disposed of, to give one specimen to His Excellency Admiral Acton in Rome, Marine Minister there and keen algae collector. I had a letter from the Admiral by the last mail,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> and since I am convinced that you will grant my request, I have advised His Excellency to instruct the Italian Consul in Lund to enclose your consignments with others that go at times from your city to Rome to the Italian Government. In this way you would be freed of all trouble and any expense. Now I have yet another request, dear Professor, it is this, from time to time to give me notes on new species for Australia and also on new localities, so that I can incorporate them in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg> without the delay of a longer time. In addition, in 1883 I have to publish the Evasculares for the 3rd part of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Census</seg> of plant species of Australia.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M's MS of the proposed publication survives in the Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne, but was never published.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For this opus I will have to call on your help in respect to the geographical distribution and the original literature in doubtful cases, or perhaps you would show me the kindness to revise the manuscript, which I could certainly easily send by post, a favour that I also have to request from other specialists in respect to the mosses, lichens and fungi.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoping that you enjoy robust health and so will long continue nobly working in your favourite science, I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Port Jackson<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sydney.</p>
               </note> is very poor in algae, otherwise I would by no means have sent these "scraps".</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
