<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne ¶ 24 January 1882 ¶ His Eminence Cardinal Dr L. Haynald, Archbishop of Kalocsa, Grand cross of orders of Austria, Belgium and Gotha. ¶  ¶ The friendly courtesy that your Eminence has shown m...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-01-24-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Magyar Természettüdományi Múseum, Budapest.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>82.01.24</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne ¶ 24 January 1882 ¶ His Eminence Cardinal Dr L. Haynald, Archbishop of Kalocsa, Grand cross of orders of Austria, Belgium and Gotha. ¶  ¶ The friendly courtesy that your Eminence has shown m...</title>
               <date when="1882-01-24">1882-01-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-01-24-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Quercus magnolifolia</term>
               <term>Amaryllideae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/06088234-a79e-4ec1-b194-7fbf5e727f87">Pinus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Lajos Haynald</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne ¶ 24 January 1882 ¶ His Eminence Cardinal Dr L. Haynald, Archbishop of Kalocsa, Grand cross of orders of Austria, Belgium and Gotha. ¶  ¶ The friendly courtesy that your Eminence has shown m...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">82.01.24</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Lajos Haynald</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Magyar Természettüdományi Múseum, Budapest.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation [by Haynald]: 'B. Müller Ferd. respr 13/3/1882, resp. 18/3. congruere quisivi [...] Mexicanum. Ejus autem responsum in transcripto ei communicavi. 16/9. 1882' [received 13/3/1882, answered 18/3. I sought to agree about the Mexican [...]. I have however communicated his reply in a copy for him]. Haynald's reply has not been found, but see M to L. Haynald, 22 November 1882.</p>
               </note>Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 24 Jan. 1882</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Sr. Eminenz dem Herrn Cardinal Dr. L. Haynald, Erzbischof von Kalocsa, Grosskreuz von Orden Österreichs, Belgiens und Gothas.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die freundliche Aufmerksamkeit, welche Ew. Eminenz mir erwiesen haben, ermuthigt mich, Sie im Interesse unsere Lieblings Wissenschaft um Ihre Hülfe anzurufen, zumal da Ihr grosser Einfluss die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">baldige</hi>
               </seg> Erfüllung meiner Bitte möglich machen würde. Es ist meine Absicht, deo volente, im Jahr 1883 eine neue Ausgabe meines Werkes "select extratropical Plants for industrial culture and naturalisation" erscheinen zu lassen; und in diese neue Auflage, für welche ich bereits zahlreiche Zusätze gesammelt habe, möchte ich die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wichtigsten Nutz-Pflanzen Mexico's</hi>
               </seg> aufnehmen. In den früheren Ausgaben (denen von Melbourne, San Francisco, Calcutta u Sydney) und auch in der deutschen Übersetzung durch Dr Goeze fehlen noch immer die Eichen und Tannen Mexicos fast gänzlich, so dass wir nach mehr denn 3 Jahrhunderten noch nicht einmal wissen, welche Coniferen u Eichen dort das beste Bauholz für alle besondere Zwecke, u. welche Quercus- u andere Baum-Arten die beste Gerbe Rinde liefern! Über Fasern der riesigen Amaryllideen liefert mein Werk übrigens, wie Ew Eminenz aus jetzt abgeschickten Exemplare ersehen werden, einige Notizen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich übertreibe nicht, wenn ich sage, dass ich mich an einige mexicanische Professoren, wissenschaftliche Vereine, Herausgaber von Zeitungen und noch Andere seit mehr denn 10 Jahren vergeblich gewandt, um Materialien zu erlangen, nach welchen ich die grosse Lücke in meinen "select plants" ausfüllen könnte. Da ich nun wohl in Gerechtigkeit zu mir selbst sagen darf, dass dies Buch einstweilen das <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">einzige</hi>
               </seg> sei, in irgend einer Sprache, welches in modern wissenschaftlichen Benennungen und in bündigen Haupt-Notizen die sämmtlichen aussertropischen Nutzpflanzen (mit Einschluss der höhern Bergpflanzen intertropischer Regionen technologisch und cultural bis auf die Neuzeiten zusammenbringt, so ist mein bescheidenes Buch vielleicht Ew. Eminenz mächtiger Hülfe wohl werth, zumal da Sie selbst in Ihrem wichtigen Studium der Bibel-Pflanzen in dem Felde der Pflanzen-Technik gewirkt haben. Dürfte ich daher den Vorschlag machen, dass Ew. Eminenz eine kurze <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Zuschrift</hi>
               </seg> an die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Haupt Präleten Mexicos</hi>
               </seg> richteten, mit dem Ersuchen, uns von den besten <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Coniferen, Eichen, Futterkraütern Gräsern</hi>
               </seg> u. s. w. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">blühende</hi>
               </seg> und <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Fruchttragende</hi>
               </seg> Exemplare zu senden mit Notizen über den vorwiegenden Nutzen jeder Art, z. B. über die besonderen <name key="Pinus">Pinus</name>-Arten, aus welchen in Mexico die Fussboden-Bretter gesägt werden, die besten Eichen, welche Holz zum Schiffbau liefern, die vorzüglichsten Eichen, welche die Rinde für Gerbereien darbringen etc. Kleine Packete getrockneter Pflanzen sind ja auch aus Mexico mit der Post früher gesandt erlangbar, u jeder Mexicanische <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Bischof</hi>
               </seg> könnte doch leicht von den Tischlern, Gerbern, Schiffs-Zimmerleuten, Drechslern, Herrden-Besitzern, Holzsägern in den Wäldern einige Zweige derjenigen Pflanzen erlangen, welche als einheimisch von hohen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Nutz</hi>
               </seg>-Wichtigkeit sind, u. auf welche sich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unirrbar</hi>
               </seg> die Notizen über technischen oder Weide-Werth bezögen, mit Einschluss hypsometrischen Angaben. Ich bin nicht einmal sicher, ob es <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">bloss</hi>
               </seg>
               <name key="Quercus%20magnolifolia">Quercus magnolifolia</name> ist welche für mexicanische Seiden Raupen die Blätter liefert.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vielleicht würden sich Ew Eminenz sogar soweit herab lassen, meines Werkes neue Ausgabe, welche im Jahre 1883 erscheinen soll, mit einigen eignen Notizen aus dem reichen Schätze Ihrer Erfahrungen in der Pflanzenwelt zu ehren! Hoffentlich sind die 2 Packete Pflanzen, welche ich mit den beiden letzten Posten an Sie beförderte, an Sie ohne weitere Ausgaben gelangt. Zwei andere Packete, von etwa demselben Umfang, liegen für die nächsten Posten zur Absendung bereit, u. bis dahin wird hoffentlich der Drucker auch weitere Abdrücke neuer Schriften zur Mitsendung geliefert haben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Noch bleibt mir zu bemerken, dass ich dankbar Notizen über Nutzpflanzen aus <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">irgend</hi>
               </seg> einen Theile Mexico's entgegenehmen würde, denn 1) die Hälfte jenes grossen Reiches ist ja aussertropisch, 2) und in der südlichen Hälfte sind ja alle Pflanzen, welche in einer Höhe von über 3000 Fuss vorkommen, auch in wärmeren aussertropischen Erdgegenden cultivirbar. Zwar ist Mr Hemsley, wie auch Prof Asa Gray, Prof Baroeta, an der Bearbeitung von Pflanzen Mexicos beschäftigt, aber nur in Systematischen Sinne. Erfragungen über die Nutz-Gewächse Mexicos werden ja auch dem Lande selbst dort erspriesslich sein, da durch solche literarische Verkundungen ja dem Handel u der Ausfuhr neue Wege eröffnet werden. Bittend meinen ergebenen Gruss an S. K. H. den Prinzen Philipp zu vermitteln, u auch selbst meine ehrerbietige Salutation entgegennehmen zu wollen, bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">24 January 1882</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">His Eminence Cardinal Dr L. Haynald, Archbishop of Kalocsa, Grand cross of orders of Austria, Belgium and Gotha.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The friendly courtesy that your Eminence has shown me encourages me to call on your help in the interests of our favourite science, especially since your great influence would make the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">rapid</hi>
               </seg> fulfillment of my request possible. It is my intention, God willing, to have a new edition of my work <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select extratropical Plants for industrial Culture and Naturalisation</seg> come out in 1883; and in this new edition, for which I have already assembled numerous additions, I would like to include the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">most important useful plants of Mexico</hi>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A German edition appeared in 1883 (B83.13.06), and a United States edition in 1884 (B84.13.22), both based on B81.01.04; the next edition by M was not published until 1885 (B85.12.03).</p>
               </note> In the earlier editions (those of Melbourne, San Francisco, Calcutta and Sydney<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B76.12.04, B80.13.07, B81.01.04. By the San Francisco edition, M presumably means the republication by Ellwood Cooper of B71.06.02, B71.07.03, B74.13.06 and B75.13.11, which M described as the precursor of B76.12.04; see B76.13.15 to B76.13.18.</p>
               </note>) and also in the German translation by Dr Goeze,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.13.06.</p>
               </note> the oaks and pines of Mexico are still almost entirely lacking, so that after more than 3 centuries we still do not know what conifers and oaks there produce the best timber for all special purposes, and what <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Quercus</seg> and other species of trees produce the best tanning bark! By the way my work provides some notes about fibres of the giant <name key="Amaryllideae">Amaryllideae</name>, as your Eminence will ascertain from the example now sent off.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B81.01.04 contains entries for five genera of Amayrllideae, of which <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Agave</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fourcroya</seg> species are recommended as sources of fibre.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not exaggerate when I say that I turned in vain to several Mexican professors, scientific associations, publishers of newspapers and others for more than 10 years in order to get material with which I could fill in the large gaps in my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select plants</seg>. Since I could probably now say in justice to myself that this book for the present is the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">only one</hi>
               </seg> in any language that brings together in modern scientific nomenclature and in succinct primary notes the entire extra-tropical plants (with the inclusion of higher mountain plants of intertropical regions[)]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> technologically and culturally useful up to modern times, my modest book is perhaps worthy of your Eminence's powerful assistance, particularly since you yourself in your important study of Bible plants have worked in the field of plant technology.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">See Haynald (1879a).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> May I therefore make the suggestion that your Eminence addresses a short <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">letter</hi>
               </seg> to the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">principle prelates of Mexico</hi>
               </seg>, requesting them to send us <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">flowering</hi>
               </seg> and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">fruit-bearing</hi>
               </seg> specimens of the best <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">conifers, oaks, fodder plants, grasses</hi>
               </seg> and so on, with notes about the predominant uses of each species, e.g. about the particular species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Pinus">Pinus</name>
               </seg> from which floorboards are sawn in Mexico, the best oaks that produce timber for shipbuilding, the most excellent oaks that give bark for tanning etc. Small parcels of dried plants previously sent from Mexico by post are certainly attainable, and surely each Mexican bishop could easily get some twigs of those plants from the carpenters, tanners, ship's carpenters, wood turners, cattle owners, sawyers in the forests, which as native are of high commercial importance and to which notes about technical or pasture value refer <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unmistakably</hi>
               </seg>, with inclusion of hypsometric data. I am not even certain, whether it is <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">only</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Quercus%20magnolifolia">Quercus magnolifolia</name>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Quercus magnoliifolia</seg>
                        <seg style="">?</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg> that produces the leaves for Mexican silk worms.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Perhaps your Eminence would even deign to honour the new edition of my work, which is to come out in 1883, with some of your own notes from the rich stores of your experience in the world of plants! It is to be hoped the 2 parcels of plants that I forwarded to you with both the last mails, arrived without further expense. Two other parcels of about the same size lie ready for dispatch by the next post, and by then it is to be hoped the printer will have delivered even more reprints of new papers for sending together.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It remains for me still to remark that I would thankfully accept notes about useful plants from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">any</hi>
               </seg> part of Mexico, because 1) half of that great empire is indeed extra-tropical, 2) and in the southern half there are indeed all plants that occur at a height of over 3000 feet, also cultivatable in warmer extra-tropical regions of the earth. It is true Mr Hemsley and also Prof Asa Gray and Prof Barroeta are engaged in the working up of Mexico's plants,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hemsley (1878-80) and Hemsley (1879-88). Gray was at this time working on his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Synoptical flora of North America</seg>, in which he considered Mexican plants as well as those of the USA and Canada. The work was continued and the earlier volumes revised after his death by B. L. Robinson and published as A. Gray (1878-97); see TL2 for the complicated publishing history of this work. No publication on this subject by Barroeta has been found. </p>
               </note> but only in the systematic sense. Inquiries about the useful plants of Mexico will certainly also be profitable there in the country itself, since new ways are opened even to commerce and export by such literary announcements. Imploring to pass on my devoted greeting to His Royal Highness Prince Philipp and also wanting you yourself to accept my respectful salutation, I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Amaryllideae">Amaryllideae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus">Pinus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Quercus%20magnolifolia">Quercus magnolifolia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
