<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>10/2/82 ¶  ¶ Enclosed I am sending you, highly respected Professor, a reprint of Mr Tepper's paper ¶  on the germination and development of  ¶ Cymodocea ¶  (or I suppose now better  ¶ Amphilobis) anta...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-02-10-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>82.02.10</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>10/2/82 ¶  ¶ Enclosed I am sending you, highly respected Professor, a reprint of Mr Tepper's paper ¶  on the germination and development of  ¶ Cymodocea ¶  (or I suppose now better  ¶ Amphilobis) anta...</title>
               <date when="1882-02-10">1882-02-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-02-10-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Amphilobis antarctica</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/935e755a-18f3-4e1a-804a-4380de9057e5">Cymodocea antarctica</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/c712431b-9b6a-4177-b60c-06441d31f5ef">Amphibolis</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Paul Ascherson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">10/2/82 ¶  ¶ Enclosed I am sending you, highly respected Professor, a reprint of Mr Tepper's paper ¶  on the germination and development of  ¶ Cymodocea ¶  (or I suppose now better  ¶ Amphilobis) anta...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">82.02.10</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Paul Ascherson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">10/2/82</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hierbei sende ich Ihnen, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, einen Abdruck von Mr Tepper's Abhandlung über die Keimung und Entwicklung von Cymodocea (oder wohl nun besser Amphilobis) antarctica)<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">The extra parenthesis is</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in MS</seg>.</p>
               </note>. Sie werden vermuthlich auch von Herrn Tepper selbst diese Druckschrift erhalten haben, und es mag Sie wundern, dass Ihrer wissenschaftlichen Erklärungen der Organe, welche Mr Tepper von dieser Pflanze beschreibt, keiner Erwähnung geschehen. Dies erfordert eine Auseinander Setzung der Gründe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie Ihr Brief mit den Bemerkungen über die Cymodocea an mich gelangte, war ich als einer der Commissäre u Preisrichter (für Chemie, Forstproducte und alle andern Pflanzenstoffe) so sehr für die Weltaustellung in Anspruch genommen, dass alles nicht officiell Dringende in meinem Departement liegen bleiben musste; ja ich konnte nicht einmal Zeit gewinnen den <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>-Atlas fortzusetzen. So häufte sich eine enorme Correspondenz in meinem Departement auf, und auch Ihr Brief wurde damals zur Seite gelegt, da ich erwartete, dass Herr Tepper mir seine Abhandlung und Zeichnungen vorlegen würde, ehe solche in den Druck gelangten, zumal da er durch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mich</hi>
               </seg> überhaupt erst in die Pflanzenkunde gezogen wurde u. zwar erst seit 2 Jahren, denn seine früheren wissenschaftlichen Beschäftigungen waren in der Entomologie u Geologie. Jetzt plötzlich erscheint seine Abhandlung u. nicht nur ich bin ausgeschlossen, sondern auch Sie, was noch viel mehr zu bedauern ist. Selbstverständlich hätte er der <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name> gar keine specielle Aufmersamkeit gewidmet, hätte ich ihn nicht auf den Umstand aufmerksam gemacht, dass wir über die Befruchtungs Organe noch sehr Dunkelen schwebten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Er <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wohnte</hi>
               </seg> an einem Theil der Küste, wo diese keineswegs sehr weit verbreitete Pflanze vorkommt, u. hatte so bessere Gelegenheit solche zu beobachten, als ich sie je gehabt. In Gerechtigkeit zu Tepper muss ich bemerken, dass er mir einiges Material in Alcohol schickte, auch einige <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">kurze</hi>
               </seg> Notizen, aber, da alles dies noch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unvollständig</hi>
               </seg> war, blieb auch dies bis nach der Ausstellung liegen, u ich habe mich aus dem Rückständigen vielerlei Art noch jetzt nicht ganz herausgearbeitet. Die Correspondenz, welche ich eigenhändig in meinem Departement führe, beläuft jährlich sich auf zwischen 2000-3000 Briefe; und nun kann ich unter den noch nicht absolvirten Papieren Ihren Brief über <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name> nicht finden! Seit ich nach dem Nordamerikanischen System (êntre nous) in einer so sinnlosen, grausamen und unverdienten Weise aus dem Garten gestossen wurde, der meine Schöpfung war, um einem ganz unwissenschaftlichen Vetter einer Frau Ministerin Platz zu machen, der nie einen andern Staats-Garten als den von Sydney sah, — bin ich selbst nachdem ich das für meine Arbeiten in 17 Jahren gebaute Haus räumen musste, in einer so kleinen u. engen Wohnung, dass leicht etwas verlegt wird, und so ist es leider mit Ihrem Briefe gegangen. Sie werden mir verzeihen, wenn ich bemerke, dass ich eine Menge Werk im ersten Versuch nicht zu entziffern vermochte, sonst hätte ich den Brief gleich an Tepper abgesandt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie die Sache jetzt steht, möchte ich Sie bitten, Ihre Erklärung der von Tepper gegebenen Vorgänge über die Reproduction von <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name> in einer deutschen bot. Zeitung zu veröffentlichen, u vielleicht <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">einfach</hi>
               </seg> bemerken, dass ich seine Aufmerksamkeit auf diese Pflanze lockte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Haben Sie ein Exemplar von Prof Eichler’s Syllabus seiner syst. Anordnung der Pflanzen abzulassen, u würde Sie so freundlich sein darin zu notiren, in welchen Punkten Sie von seinen Ansichten abweichen. Ich sende Ihnen hiermit mein eignes Verzeichniss der Pflanzen-Gattungen Australiens.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Herr Tepper ist jetzt in eine Innland Localität </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>übergesiedelt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">10/2/82</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Enclosed I am sending you, highly respected Professor, a reprint of Mr Tepper's paper<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Tepper (1882).</p>
               </note> on the germination and development of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cymodocea</seg> (or I suppose now better <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Amphilobis) antarctica</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name> antarctica</seg>
                     <seg style="">?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Presumably you will also have received this publication from Mr Tepper himself,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">From Ascherson's letter to Tepper, in Ascherson (1882), we learn that this was indeed the case.</p>
               </note> and it may surprise you that no mention occurred of your scientific explanations of the organs that Mr Tepper describes from this plant. This requires a discussion of the reasons.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When your letter with the remarks about the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cymodocea</seg> reached me,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> my time was so much taken up as one of the commissioners and judges (for chemistry, forest products and all other plant materials) for the International Exhibition<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">International Exhbition, Melbourne, 1880-1.</p>
               </note> that everything not officially urgent in my department had to be left; indeed I could not even get time to continue the <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> Atlas. So an enormous correspondence accumulated in my department and your letter was also put aside at the time because I expected that Mr Tepper would show me his paper and drawings before they reached the press, especially since he was after all first drawn to the study of plants through <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">me</hi>
               </seg> and in fact only in the last 2 years, because his previous scientific activities were in entomology and geology. Now suddenly his paper appears and not only am I excluded but also you, which is even more to be regretted. Of course he would not have devoted any special attention at all to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name>
               </seg>, had I not made him aware of the fact that we were groping very much in the dark about the fertilization organs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>He <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">lived</hi>
               </seg> on that part of the coast where this by no means very widely distributed plant occurs and had much better opportunity to observe it than I ever had. In justice to Tepper I have to remark that he sent me some material in alcohol, even some <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">short</hi>
               </seg> notes, but because all this was still <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">incomplete</hi>
               </seg>, this was also left until after the Exhibition and I have not yet quite worked my way out of the arrears of many different kinds. The correspondence that I carry on in my own hand in my department amounts to between 2000-3000 letters annually; and now I cannot find your letter about <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name>
               </seg> among the pages not yet completed! Since I was pushed out of the Garden, which was my creation, according to the North American system (entre nous) in such a senseless, cruel and undeserved manner to make a place for a quite unscientific cousin of the wife of a minister, who had never seen another state garden but that of Sydney — after I had to move out of the house built for my work for 17 years, I am in such a small and cramped dwelling that something is easily mislaid and so it has happened with your letter unfortunately. You will excuse me if I remark that I was not able to decipher much of the work at the first attempt, otherwise I should have sent the letter straight to Tepper.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As the matter now stands, I should like to ask you to publish your explanation of the details given to Tepper about the reproduction of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name>
               </seg> in a German botanical journal and perhaps <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">simply</hi>
               </seg> remark that I called his attention to this plant.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ascherson's explanation, including due acknowledgement of M's role, was presented by Tepper to the Royal Society of South Australia on 13 June 1882 and subsequently published in the Society's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions</seg>; see Tepper (1882b) and O. Tepper to M, 18 June 1882.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Have you a copy of Professor Eichler's syllabus of his systematic arrangement of plants<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A. Eichler (1876).</p>
               </note> to give away and would you be so kind as to note in it on which points you differ from his views? I am sending you herewith my own list of the plant genera of Australia.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B82.07.05.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Mr Tepper has now moved to an inland locality.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Tepper moved from Ardrossan, on the western shore of St Vincent's Gulf, to Clarendon in the Mount Lofty Ranges, SA, in August 1881.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Amphibolis">Amphibolis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Amphilobis%20antarctica">Amphilobis antarctica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cymodocea%20antarctica">Cymodocea antarctica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
