<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>21/12/82. ¶  ¶ I intended to have written you a long letter, dear Mr Dyer, but the hour of closing the mail has arrived, and amidst other work I left the writing to you, till too late. I have however ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-12-21c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Miscellaneous Reports 7.7, Victoria, Phylloxera, 1876-90 (MR/415), ff. 65-68.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>82.12.21c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>21/12/82. ¶  ¶ I intended to have written you a long letter, dear Mr Dyer, but the hour of closing the mail has arrived, and amidst other work I left the writing to you, till too late. I have however ...</title>
               <date when="1882-12-21">1882-12-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-12-21c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Thiselton-Dyer</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">21/12/82. ¶  ¶ I intended to have written you a long letter, dear Mr Dyer, but the hour of closing the mail has arrived, and amidst other work I left the writing to you, till too late. I have however ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">82.12.21c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Thiselton-Dyer</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Miscellaneous Reports 7.7, Victoria, Phylloxera, 1876-90 (MR/415), ff. 65-68.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">21/12/82.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Annotated by Thiselton-Dyer</seg>: 'And [<seg style="color: #000000; font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>] 3/ 83'. (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Letter not found</seg>).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I intended to have written you a long letter, dear Mr Dyer, but the hour of closing the mail has arrived, and amidst other work I left the writing to you, till too late. I have however yet time to acknowledge the receipt of a copy of your most valuable Report on the Phylloxera-Congress.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Thiselton-Dyer (1882).</p>
               </note> I have after reading it at once forwarded it to the honor. Dr Smith,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">L. L. Smith.</p>
               </note> a member of the Ministry, who takes here a leading interest in viticulture and brought it through his parliamentary influence about, that £20000<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Smith recommended to the Chief Secretary that the sum of £20,000 be set aside for compensation (Appendix B, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Report from the Select Committee upon the Phylloxera vasatrix</seg> …, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Victoria Parliamentary Paper, No. 10, 1880). Provision for compensation for wine growers in Victoria was included in the Phylloxera Vine Disease Act 1880, based upon a maximum compensation based on a valuation of three years’ crops.</p>
               </note> was spent in eradicating <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> vines in the Geelong district, with a view of "stamping out" the horrible insect. That such expenditure and all collateral exertions are not incurred on light ground, you might imagine; and it speaks not well for Victorian intelligence and casts a slur on Australian science, when Mr Trimen and some of his entomologic friends cannot even be fully persuaded yet that the Phylloxera vastatrix exists at all in Victoria!<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Robert McLachlan FRS, Roland Trimen FLS and Edward A Fitch FLS were ‘appointed to consider a communication from the Colonial Office relative to the supposed occurrence of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Phylloxera Vastatrix</seg> upon the Vines in the Colony of Victoria’. They reported that ‘a large mass of this evidence, both as regards the questions put to the parties examined and their answers thereto, have little or no bearing upon the subject. From the conflicting nature of the evidence, it is tolerably clear that more than one insect, or animals allied to insects, have been accused of being the actual <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Phylloxera</seg>. The question remains as to whether the pest actually exists in the Colony.’ They suggested that the organisms might be ‘harmless <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Acari </seg>(mites)’. They considered that the accompanying plates undoubtedly illustrated <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Phylloxera,</seg> but expressed doubts ‘whether the figures on the plates ... were taken from actual Victorian Specimens or copied from other figures in some European or American work’ and recommended that specimens of both the insect and infected vine-roots be sent to the Entomological Society, London, for examination (copy [ff. 56-60] of a report to the Council of the Entomological Society from McLachlan, Trimen and Fitch, undated; the accompanying letter transmitting the report to Thiselton-Dyer [f. 55] is dated 3 November 1881).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The archival volume also contains 1880. Victoria. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Report from the Select Committee of the Legislative Assembly of Victoria upon the Phylloxera vastatrix …, </seg>(ff 14-46). A letter from the Entomological Society (f. 96; signature obscured by binding) dated 11 January 1884 transmits an undated copy of a report by McLachlan and Fitch (ff 97, 98) — who state that Trimen is ‘no longer in England’— confirming that specimens sent to Kew from Melbourne in September 1883 and passed on to the Society by Joseph Hooker were indeed <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Phylloxera vastatrix</seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The insect is so well described and illustrated, that there is no mistaking it from a mere biomorphic point of view. Irrespective of this, its ravages are so precisely alike here to its devastations in S Europe, that no one need entertain any scepticism of the Phylloxera being here in all its destructiveness; but it is a very different question, whether we can get rid of it, notwithstanding heroic efforts, even though our vine-fields are not in close contiguity, as the winged insect <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">might</hi>
               </seg> alight on any other place of grape-culture, carried thither for miles by the wind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>One serious matter, seemingly not noted in Europe, was found out by us here, and first recorded by the two Phylloxera Commissioners as mentioned in my letter before you went to the Congress,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> namely that remnants of roots of Vitis vinifera, left unavoidably in the ground after the extirpation-process, did after <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">three</hi>
               </seg> years still harbour phylloxera, as I have seen with my own eyes. Prof Planchon sends me regularly his periodical on the “Vignes Américaines”, and I keep up some communication with Prof Millardet also.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Copies of Millardet (1877) and Millardet (1881) in the Library of the Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne are known to have been owned by M; he probably also had the copies of Planchon (1875) and Planchon (1876) although the RBG Melbourne copies do not show his ownership (the latter has an inscription to Millardet!).</p>
               </note> In the Gardeners Chronicle I have made an appeal for fresh seeds of the safest American Vines<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B81.09.01.</p>
               </note> and so in Meehan’s Monthly in Philadelphia.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was a regular correspondent of Thomas Meehan, editor of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">The Gardener's monthly and horticulturalist</seg>, but no published request of this nature has been found.</p>
               </note> Our Bordeaux friend sent me a few. I had lots of the best American Vines (but sine Phylloxera) around my House in the bot Garden since 1860 for observation; but you know that lawns and florist-flowers are there now the main order of the day. We cannot get quick enough stock from cuttings for grafting, so must raise seedlings, to cope with future possible eventualities. The main-operations on affected vineyards I gave in the enlarged german edition of my select plants, which Dr Goeze brought out in 1882, and of which he, as a former Kew inmate, will doubtless have sent you a copy.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.13.06, pp. 422-4. Later editions (e.g. B84.13.22, pp. 391, 393-4, 397) contain extensive notes, including notes on other <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Vitis</seg> spp. that had been used as a rootstock.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have at once recommended by letter to Dr Smith, that the Victorian Government should communicate with those of N.S W. &amp; S.A., to acknowledge gratefully your kindly undertaking this mission, and to recompense you for the outlay, incurred by you.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your document on Phylloxera gave me the first intimation of our gracious Sovereign having nominated you to a Companionship of the Order of St Michael &amp; St George.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Thiselton-Dyer was appointed Companion of the Order of St Michael and St George on 24 May 1882, 'for services rendered to colonial Governments' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">London gazette</seg>, 24 May 1882, p. 2461).</p>
               </note> Accept my best felicitation and let me add the hope, that as you have yet a long life before you, that in the course of time you will be promoted in the order, as a reward for your zeal in advancing the interest, not only of the great Home Department, but also the advantages of the colonies.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Regardfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Can you oblige by sending me an other copy of your &amp; Mr Trimens Reports.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
