<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>22/11/82 ¶  ¶ Today, highly esteemed Professor, after I had already posted a letter to you, ¶  your letter of 8 October 1882 reached me, which I hasten to answer. Firstly I express my thanks for the l...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-11-22a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>82.11.22a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>22/11/82 ¶  ¶ Today, highly esteemed Professor, after I had already posted a letter to you, ¶  your letter of 8 October 1882 reached me, which I hasten to answer. Firstly I express my thanks for the l...</title>
               <date when="1882-11-22">1882-11-22</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1882/82-11-22a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Claudea bennetti</term>
               <term>Cliftonaea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jacob Agardh</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">22/11/82 ¶  ¶ Today, highly esteemed Professor, after I had already posted a letter to you, ¶  your letter of 8 October 1882 reached me, which I hasten to answer. Firstly I express my thanks for the l...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">82.11.22a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Jacob Agardh</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">22/11/82.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nachdem ich heute, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, bereits einen Brief für Sie auf die Post gegeben, erreicht mich Ihr Schreiben vom 8. Oct 1882, welches zu beantworten ich mich beeile. Zunächst spreche ich meinen Dank für die Namensliste der Algen des Herrn J. B. Wilson aus, welche Selbigem sofort zugehen soll. Da dieser Herr (ein Schul-Director) sich in den Ferien mit dem Aufsuchen u. Studien der Polyzoa beschäftigt, so wird ihn die volle Auskunft (manche Namen hatte er bereits von mir) zum Weitersammeln ermuntern; u da er seine Exemplare recht nett präparirt werden Sie<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">sie.</p>
               </note> Ihnen auch gewiss künftig willkommen sein. Ganz anders ist es freilich mit den einfach "en gros" gesammelten u unpräparirten Algen-Massen, u. da über diese Art des Sendens eine längere Correspondenz mit dem mir so theuren Freunde Sonder obwaltet, werden Sie mir erlauben zu erklären, wie diese Algen zu ihm kamen. Er war immer sehr begierig den <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Verbreitungsgrad</hi>
               </seg> der Algen Arten weiter zu erforschen, und dann die Lücken unserer Kenntnis über Varietäts Formen und über die Frucht-Organe auszufüllen. Dafür geben grosse crude Massen doch manchmal Nachweise, und ihm schienen die Überzahl der Exemplare stets zum Austausch willkommen zu sein. Fern ist es von mir, Ihnen, dessen Zeit so werthvoll ist, mechanische Arbeiten aufzubürden, u ich würde nie wagen an Sie solche ungethüme Rohmassen zu senden, obwohl Hr Prof Areschoug, Hr Prof Eaton u Mons Lenormand solche Sendungen wünschten, die freilich wohl nicht immer so einförmig waren, wie Miss Bunburys. Ich würde rathen das Roh-Material einem jüngern Algen Sammler zu geben, der ja dann wohl eine Menge guter Exemplare heraus suchen u zum Austausch verwerthen kann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie viel wir noch geographisch u morphologisch über die Algen Australiens zu lernen haben, zeigt doch das neuliche Auffinden von <name key="Cliftonaea">Cliftonaea</name> in der Port Phillip Bay u zwar in Frucht. Um die Erlangung von Claudea Bennetti in Frucht habe ich auch seit Jahren mich bemüht, u es soll mir eine wahre Freude sein, wenn ich Ihnen solche eines Tages vorlegen kann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gestatten Sie mir auch in Zukunft Ihnen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Alles</hi>
               </seg> Algologische zu senden u zwar so, dass es kosten frei ankomme, u schicken Sie nur etwas Seltneres zurück. Sie können ja das Unbrauchbare wegwerfen. Wenn Exemplare, wie die des Mr Wilson numerirt sind, dann bedarf es keiner Rücksendung. Aber auf Eins von Wichtigkeit möchte ich Sie doch noch aufmerksam machen, nämlich dass <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Polyzoa</hi>
               </seg> und <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Diatomeae</hi>
               </seg> den unausgewaschenen u unpräparirten Algen häufig anhaften, so dass gewiss irgend einer Ihrer benachbarten Freunde die Rohmassen nach solchen Dingen durchspähen möchte, zumal da bisher so wenige der Diatomeae für Australien identificirt sind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vielleicht ist der Inhalt der 3ten Kiste, deren Sie als von Hamburg angekommen erwähnen, mehr freudebringend für Sie gewesen, u. hat Ihnen nicht auch noch Täuschung bereitet! Ich kann mich ganz in Ihre Gefühle versetzen; denn aus allen Theilen Australiens gehen mir Vasculares zur Benennung zu, u oft opfere ich den Sammlern viel mehr Zeit, als gerecht ist, denn unter hunderten von Exemplaren sind vielleicht nur 1 od 2 für neue Standorte wichtig, Neues giebt es fast nie. Dennoch halte ich es am Besten, die Sammler nicht zu entmuthigen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die arme Mrs Meredith hat vor einigen Monaten einen Anfall von Apoplexia gehabt, was bei deren vorgerückten Alter die grössten Besorgnisse erregen muss.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Besten Glückwunsch zum neuen Jahre.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">22/11/82</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Today, highly esteemed Professor, after I had already posted a letter to you,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Agardh, 21 November 1882.</p>
               </note> your letter of 8 October 1882 reached me, which I hasten to answer. Firstly I express my thanks for the list of names of the algae of Mr J. B. Wilson, which shall be sent to him immediately.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Agardh's letter has not been found, only the list that he enclosed with it of his determinations of J. B. Wilson's algae collections from Port Phillip Heads. The list is annotated by M: 'Sent copy to Prof. Wilson, 22/11/82. Rec. 21/11/82'. It is reproduced in this edition as J. Agardh to M, 8 October 1882.</p>
               </note> Since this gentleman (a school principal) occupies himself in the holidays with the search and study of polyzoa, the complete information (many names he already had from me) will encourage him to further collecting; and since he his specimens are prepared very neatly they will also certainly be welcome to you in the future. It is quite otherwise of course with the algae masses simply collected "wholesale" and unprepared, and since a longer correspondence about this kind of consignment existed with Sonder, such a dear friend to me, you will allow me to explain how these algae came to him. He was always very eager to continue researching the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">degree of distribution</hi>
               </seg> of algal species, and then fill the gaps in our knowledge about varietal forms and about the fruiting organs. For this, large crude masses did sometimes give information, and the surplus of specimens always seemed to be welcome to him for exchange. It is far from me to encumber you, whose time is so valuable, with mechanical work, and I should never dare to send you such huge raw masses, although Professor Areschoug, Professor Eaton and Monsieur Lenormand requested such consignments, which admittedly were probably not always as uniform as Miss Bunbury's.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Agardh had been sent specimens collected by Diana Bunbury (see M to J. Agardh, 25 January 1872) and named <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Thamnoclonium bunburyens</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">e</seg> in her honour in J. Agardh (1848-1901), vol. 3, part 1, p. 170.</p>
               </note> I would advise giving the raw material to a young algae collector, who certainly then can probably pick out a large number of good specimens and make use of them for exchange.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How much we still have to learn geographically and morphologically about the algae of Australia, is shown by the recent discovery of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cliftonaea">Cliftonaea</name>
               </seg> in Port Phillip Bay<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Vic.</p>
               </note> and actually in fruit. For years I have also endeavoured to get <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Claudea%20bennetti">Claudea bennetti</name>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Claudea%20bennetti">Claudea bennetti</name>ana</seg>
                     <seg style="">?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> in fruit, and it will be a real joy for me if one day I can submit it to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Permit me also in the future to send you <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">everything</hi>
               </seg> algological, in fact such that it arrives without cost while you send back only anything rare. You can certainly throw away what is unusable. When specimens such as those of Mr Wilson are numbered, then no return is necessary. But I should like to draw to your attention one thing of importance, namely that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">polyzoa</hi>
               </seg> and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">diatoms</hi>
               </seg> often cling to the unrinsed and unprepared algae, so that certainly some of your neighbouring friends might like to examine the raw masses for such things, especially since up till now so little of the diatoms are identified for Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Perhaps the contents of the 3rd box that you mentioned as having arrived from Hamburg has brought more pleasure for you and has also not given you disappointment! I can completely agree with your feelings, because vasculares from all parts of Australia are sent to me for determination and often I sacrifice much more time to the collectors than is right, because among the hundreds of specimens perhaps only 1 or 2 are important for new localities, there are almost never new things. Nevertheless I regard it as best not to discourage the collectors.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Poor Mrs Meredith has had an attack of apoplexy some months ago, which in the case of her advanced age must arouse the greatest apprehension.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, '﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽ Symbol'; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Best wishes for the New Year.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Claudea%20bennetti">Claudea bennetti</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cliftonaea">Cliftonaea</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
