<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>THE MELBOURNE BOTANICAL GARDENS. ¶ To the Editor of the Argus ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ I have very recently arrived in the colony, and being fond of horticultural pursuits, I made inquiries as to the whereabouts...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1850-9/56-02-05[…]-Argus.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>56.02.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>THE MELBOURNE BOTANICAL GARDENS. ¶ To the Editor of the Argus ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ I have very recently arrived in the colony, and being fond of horticultural pursuits, I made inquiries as to the whereabouts...</title>
               <date when="1856-02-05">1856-02-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1850-9/56-02-05[…]-Argus.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">THE MELBOURNE BOTANICAL GARDENS. ¶ To the Editor of the Argus ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ I have very recently arrived in the colony, and being fond of horticultural pursuits, I made inquiries as to the whereabouts...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">56.02.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Editor</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Trans. 19.4.94. To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the above copy see: <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 9 February 1856, p. 6.</p>
               </note>THE MELBOURNE BOTANICAL GARDENS.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; font-style: italic; "
               xml:lang="en">To the Editor of the Argus</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir, —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have very recently arrived in the colony, and being fond of horticultural pursuits, I made inquiries as to the whereabouts of the Botanical Gardens, which having found I was surprised to see among the code of regulations printed on a large board at the entrance — "That no visitor do interrupt the gardeners, by conversation or otherwise." I at once suspected that the gardens must be wrought by convict labor when the rules were so stringent. In all botanical gardens in Great Britain and Ireland I have ever visited the men therein employed are allowed to answer questions put by visitors concerning any of the plants under cultivation, — such as their properties, their uses in the arts and manufactures, or anything curious connected with them; which rules should be more strictly adhered to in the so-called Melbourne Botanic Garden than in any other garden I have ever visited, as there are not one hundred species of plants with labels attached — every thing bundled together without any attempt at classification, so that the men employed in such a place should be free, able, and willing to give any information required, and more particularly in a new colony, where a great many of the new arrivals may wish to know something of the Flora of their adopted country, I have always understood botanical gardens to be meant for the introduction of new and useful plants, and the general information of the people, by having every thing properly named and classified, and, if required (by visitors), their culture and properties; so that a botanical garden may be called the garden of the people, as it is meant for the improvement of the people; but where such rules as the above are put in practice, the gardens can be of little value unless as a promenade ground. Yet, notwithstanding the stringency of this rule, there are times when a visitor may venture to ask any of the gardeners a question, when he will get it civilly answered (at least it happened so with the writer of this), that is, after six o'clock, when they are leaving off work: as that time appears to be their own, they are not then afraid of transgressing Rule No. 6. I asked the party whom I met with about several plants, natives of New Holland, of which he seemed to know everything: but he said they were not in the gardens. Amongst the plants I enquired about is a plant extensively used in hat-making in this colony — the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Corypha Australis</seg>, or cabbagetree-palm. Seeing the place so bare, I made inquiries as to how long it was made, how supported, how many men employed, and how they were paid. In the first place I was very much surprised to hear the length of time it has been in existence: and so little done: but when hearing that there are only five constant men kept, with only 8s per day, when the rate of wages advertised in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> for men on the roads is 10s. and 12s., I was not so much surprised to see the place in its present backward condition. Is it not a shame for the Government to keep men working for such a low rate of wages, when contractors and private individuals are giving so much more? Can they expect as good a day's work done for 8s. s for 10s. or 12s. when men see their fellow-men get so much more encouragement than they? When wages came down they were reduced to the present rate; but now when they are on the rise again they are kept at the low rate. Still the men thus treated are expected to be skilled and educated workmen; in fact, none other would do in such a place.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My reason for troubling you, Sir, with this is, for the purpose of trying to get some one more skilled in the science of horticulture to take up the case, as horticulture in every country has been the forerunner of a good system of agriculture.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">AN OBSERVER.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 5th Feb., 1856.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
