<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Kiel, 6 September 1850. ¶ Dear Sophie, ¶  ¶ Sincere thanks for your letter of 24 August. It was like a balm for my poor heart, troubled by much restlessness. As far as you are concerned, and also in r...</title>
            <author>Lars Hansen</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M50-09-06-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Private hands.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M50.09.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Lars Hansen</author>
               <title>Kiel, 6 September 1850. ¶ Dear Sophie, ¶  ¶ Sincere thanks for your letter of 24 August. It was like a balm for my poor heart, troubled by much restlessness. As far as you are concerned, and also in r...</title>
               <date when="1850-09-06">1850-09-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M50-09-06-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Sophia Hansen</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Kiel, 6 September 1850. ¶ Dear Sophie, ¶  ¶ Sincere thanks for your letter of 24 August. It was like a balm for my poor heart, troubled by much restlessness. As far as you are concerned, and also in r...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M50.09.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Lars Hansen to Sophia Hansen</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Private hands.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Transcribed 16.3.92.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope 'Demoiselle Sophia Hansen | in | Huesbye | bei Flensburg | Abzugeben bei Fr. Harboe's | Witwe, Hafermarkt | in Flensburg'. Letter postmarked 'K.O.P.A. Hamburg | 10 | 9'</p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To be deleted later, — For Sara (Hypercard entry) and for Johannes: </seg>MS is owned by Mrs Jensen, Ausacker (near Flensburg), Schleswig Holstein, Germany, who is married to a descendant of Lars Hansen. Photocopy, typescript of letter and envelope and comments from Mr Wilhelm Sell, Beselerstr. 6, 2390 Flensburg, Germany, received February 1985. — Mr Sell is a retired history teacher and works at the Archives in Flensburg. He has researched Lars Hansen and published his letters with commentary, also publ. on the history of Schleswig-Holstein during the period before and during the Danish wars.</p>
               </note>Kiel, den 6. Sept. 1850.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Liebe Sophie!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herzlichen Dank für Deinen Brief vom 24. v. Mts. Er war wie ein Balsam für das von so mancher Unruhe wunde Herz. Sowohl was Euch selbst betrifft als unsern lieben Christian in Australien, hat er mir zwei schwere, schwere Sorgensteine vom Herzen genommen. Ich kann Gott nicht innig genug für diese neuen Beweise seiner unwandelbaren Liebe und Vatertreue danken. Es hat mich unendlich gefreut, dass Ihr gesund und den Umständen nach vergnügt lebt. Nicht wahr, Ihr Lieben, wir erfahren es täglich, dass <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">der</hi>
               </seg> Gott, der die Last auflegt, sie auch tragen hilft. So wollen wir denn auch in Gott ergebenem Sinne uns allerwege in die Zeit schicken, und dem vertrauen, der nach Sturm und Ungewitter wieder seine Sonne scheinen lässt. Fahret Ihr auch so fort, Geliebte, und ihr werdet vor manchen Übeln, die die Verhältnisse mit sich bringen, bewahrt bleiben. Danket Euren Nachbarn und besonders P. Jensen's herzlich [...], dass Ihr an Ihnen so treue Stütze habet, und Ihr im Falle der Noth Eure Zuflucht zu ihnen nehmen dürfet. Gott vergelte es allen den guten Menschen, die sich Eurer wohlwollend annehmen. Die Nachrichten von Christian sind mir sehr beruhigend; ich habe sie allen seinen hiesigen Freunden mitgetheilt, und überall die wärmste Theilnahme gefunden. Besonders erfreut spricht sich der gute Eggers darüber aus. Gott wolle unsern Christian denn ferner leiten, beschirmen, und seine Unternehmungen gelingen lassen, dass er nach einigen wenigen Jahren wieder nach Europa zurückkehren und in unsre Arme eilen kann. Auch August geht es wohl; er ist jetzt in eine höhere Klasse versetzt worden. Der Junge macht mir viel Freude. Ich habe ihn in diesen Tagen hier erwartet, er ist noch nicht gekommen, weil er wahrscheinlich viel zu thun hat. Claus hat mich vor Kurzem besucht; aber zu ihm komme ich wohl nicht hin, es kostet mir zuviel. Neuerdings bin ich auch zu einer längeren Seereise aufgefordert worden, aus mehreren Gründen, insonderheit aber wegen Gesundheitsrücksichten bei der vorgerückten Jahreszeit kann ich mich nicht dazu entschliessen. Möchtet Ihr hierin mit mir einerlei Meinung sein. Bei Sengerob komme ich öfter; er ist ungemein freundlich und zuvorkommend gegen mich; über Christian spricht er mit herzlichem Bedauern, aber auch mit Liebe und Anerkennung. Damit ich es nicht vergesse, will ich es hier gleich bemerken: hebt die Briefe von ihm und F. Müller gut auf und schickt sie nicht ab. Zu Deinem und Anna's Geburtstage habe ich Euch geschrieben; ich hoffe, Ihr werdet die Briefe jetzt empfangen haben. Schreibt wenn Ihr könnt, recht bald wieder. Jac. Brix war gestern in meiner Abwesenheit hier. Er hat ein Geldgeschäft mit Marcus. Von ihm erfuhren wir denn zugleich, dass sein Bruder und J. Jensen wohlauf sind. Das Nämliche kann ich Euch, gottlob! von mir berichten. Grüsset Schwester Maria recht herzlich, und saget ihr, dass ich zu ihrem Geburtstage schwerlich an sie schreiben werde, sie möge mir dies nich übel nehmen<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">sie ... nehmen <seg style="font-style: italic; ">inter.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>. Grüsset <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Alle</hi>
               </seg> mit dem besten Grusse. Meinetwegen seid unbesorgt. Ich halte mich an Gott und an den Spruch: Ich habe noch nie gesehen den Gerechten verlassen noch seinen Samen nach Brodt gehen. So auch Ihr, und dann werdet Ihr täglich erfahren, dass er uns nahe ist mit seiner Gnade. Mit unaussprechlicher Liebe</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">der Eurige</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illeg.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Notes to the letter (by Wilhelm Sell, Flensburg, Germany, D.Sinkora pers. comm.):</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als kurz vor der Schlacht bei Idstedt am Abend des 18. Juli 1850 dänische Truppen Husby besetzten, flohen Pastor Simonsen und Lars Hansen, Küster in Husby, in der Dunkelheit nach Lutzhöft und von dort weiter nach Süden. Fast ein Jahr lebte Lars Hansen als Emigrant in Kiel, wo er zunächst Aufnahme bei dem Lehrer Marcus Schlichting fand, der einige Zeit zuvor Lehrer im Nachbardorf Ausackerholz gewesen war. Die drei Töchter von Lars Hansen blieben im Küsterhaus in Husby zurück. Zwischen Husby und Kiel wurde noch einige Monate zwischen Dänen und Schleswig-Holsteinern gekämpft. Die Briefe von Lars Hansen an seine Töchter und die Antworten erreichten ihre Empfänger über das neutrale Hamburg; siehe Stempel. Der Briefwechsel endet Mai 1851; offenbar ist Lars Hansen nach Husby zurückgekehrt. Seine Wohnung war vom Nachfolger besetzt. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Anmerkungen zum Brief:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1. Lars Hansen tarnt seine Identität, man findet weder Absender noch lesbare Unterschrift. Die Töchter können die Schrift erkennen.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. In dem Brief wird der Sohn Christian erwähnt, der nach Australien ausgewandert war. Nach der Husbyer Chronik ist dieser Sohn Hans Christian Nicolai, geb. ca. 1820 in Treia, später in New Zealand verschollen. In diesem Zusammenhang werden auch Briefe von einem F. Müller genannt. Dieser Brief ist der einzige, in dem der Name genannt wird. Offenbar ist dieser F. Müller der Mann, der mit Christian nach Australien ausgewandert ist und dort sehr viel für die Erforschung der Flora geleistet hat. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. Christian hatte in Hamburg den Kaufmannsberuf erlernt. Er soll sich bei dem Brand von Hamburg bei Lösch- und Rettungsarbeiten ausgezeichnet haben. Der Herr Sengerob ist offenbar sein Dienstherr in Kiel gewesen.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4. Mit der Bemerkung, August sei eine Klasse höher gekommen, deutet L. Hansen an, dass er in der Schleswig-Holsteinischen Armee zum Leutnant befördert worden ist. Er wurde wenige Tage später beim Sturm auf Friedrichstadt am 4 Oktober 1850 schwer verwundet.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. Mit der Seereise deutet Lars Hansen das Angebot des Amtmanns Warnstedt an, dass er die geflohenen Pastoren und Lehrer im Amt belassen würde, wenn sie auf dem Seewege unter Umgehung der Fronten reumütig zurückkehren würden. In späteren Briefen schildert L. H. die Gewissenskämpfe über diese Entscheidung.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>(When Danish troops occupied Husby shortly before the battle near Idstedt on the evening of 18 July 1850, Pastor Simonsen and Lars Hansen, verger in Husby, fled under cover of darkness to Lutzhöft and from there further south. For almost a year Lars Hansen lived as a refugee in Kiel, where at first he found shelter with the teacher Marcus Schlichting, who had been located at the neighbouring village of Ausackerholz some years previously. The three daughters of Lars Hansen remained in the verger's house in Husby. Fighting continued between Husby and Kiel for some months between Danish and Schleswig-Hostein troops. The letters from Lars Hansen to his daughters and their replies reached their respective recipients via the neutral Hamburg; note the postmark.The correspondence ends in May 1851; evidently Lars Hansen has returned to Husby. His home was occupied by his successor.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Notes to the letter:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1. Lars Hansen masks his identity, one finds neither sender nor a legible signature. His daughters know his handwriting.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. The letter mentions the son Christian, who emigrated to Australia. According to the Husby Chronicle this refers to the son, Hans Christian Nicolai Hansen, born ca. 1820 in Treia, later missing in New Zealand. In this connection letters from a certain F. Müller are mentioned. This is the only letter in which the name occurs. Evidently this F. Müller is the man, who emigrated to Australia with Christian, and who has accomplished a great deal for the flora there. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. Christian had trained in Hamburg as a businessman. He is supposed to have distinguished himself with fire fighting and rescue work during the great fire of Hamburg [May 1842]. Mr Sengerob was evidently his employer in Kiel. </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4. With the remark, that Claus [that should read August] has been promoted to a higher class, L. Hansen indicated that he was promoted to the rank of Lieutenant in the Schleswig-Holstein Army. Not many days later he was severely wounded during the attack on Friedrichstadt on 4 October 1850.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. With his reference to a sea voyage Lars Hansen refers to the offer by Magistrate Warnstedt, that the escaped pastors and teachers could remain in office, if they would repent and return by sea, circumventing the fighting front. In later letters Hansen describes his inner conflict about this decision.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Kiel, 6 September 1850.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Sophie,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sincere thanks for your letter of 24 August. It was like a balm for my poor heart, troubled by much restlessness. As far as you are concerned, and also in regard to our dear Christian in Australia, it has lifted two very, very heavy burdens from my heart. I cannot thank God enough for these renewed proofs of his unchangeable love and fatherly care. I was so very glad, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that you are well and, under the circumstance, are getting along quite happily. Is it not true, my dear ones, that we daily experience, that the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">same</hi>
               </seg> God, who lays the burden on us, will also help us carry it. So, resigned to God's will we will always put up with the times and put our trust in Him, who after thunder and storms will always let his sun shine again. Continue to live like that, my darlings, and you will be preserved from much evil brought about by circumstances. Thank your neighbours, and especially P. Jensen's, that they give you such faithful support, and that you are able to take refuge with them in case of an emergency. May God reward all the good people, who care for you with such kindness. I am greatly relieved by the news from Christian, I have passed it on to all his friends here, and they all have shown the warmest interest. The good Eggers in particular expresses his pleasure about it. May God continue to guide our Christian, protect him, and prosper all his undertakings, so that he will be able to return to Europe in a few short years to hurry back into our arms. August is also well, he has been promoted into a higher class. The boy is a joy to me. I had expected him here around this time, he has not come yet, probably he has too much to do. Claus visited me a little while ago, but I don't think I will be able to go to him, it costs too much. The latest is, that I was requested to go on a long sea voyage; for several reasons, particularly for health reasons during this well advanced season of the year I cannot make the decision to accede. I hope you will be of the same mind. I go to see Sengerob every so often; he is extremely friendly and obliging to me. He speaks of Christian with sincere regret, but also with love and acknowledgment. So I will not forget, I want to write this down at once: keep all the letters from him, and also those from F. Mueller, and do not post them. I have written for your and Anna's birthday, I hope you will have received the letters by now. Write, when you can, soon. Jac. Brix was here yesterday, while I was out. He had some money business with Marcus. At the same time we found out from him that his brother and J. Jensen are well. I can, thank God! say the same about myself. Give my kindest regards to sister Maria, and tell her that I will hardly be able to write to her for her birthday, she must not hold that against me. Greet everybody with my best regards. Do not worry about me. I keep to God and to the proverb: 'I have never seen the just man deserted, nor his off-spring beg for bread'. You keep to that, too, and you will experience daily, that He is close to us with His grace. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With inexpressible love</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
