<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 5 January 1853 ¶ Esteemed Sir, ¶  ¶ When I received the Australian Dodonaeae back towards the end of September with the request to also send you the ones collected by Preiss, I did not expect...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M53-01-05-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M53.01.05</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 5 January 1853 ¶ Esteemed Sir, ¶  ¶ When I received the Australian Dodonaeae back towards the end of September with the request to also send you the ones collected by Preiss, I did not expect...</title>
               <date when="1853-01-05">1853-01-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M53-01-05-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
               <term>'Times New Roman'</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Standard</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Diederich von Schlechtendal</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 5 January 1853 ¶ Esteemed Sir, ¶  ¶ When I received the Australian Dodonaeae back towards the end of September with the request to also send you the ones collected by Preiss, I did not expect...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M53.01.05</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Diederich von Schlechtendal</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: 10pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>MS not seen; extracted from Tkach, Neubauer &amp; Roser (2022), Brief 12.</p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 5 Janr. 53 </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter Herr!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als ich gegen Ende September die austral.</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">Dodonaeen</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">zurückerhielt mit der Aufforderung, Ihnen auch die von Preiss gesammelten zukommen zu lassen, erwartete ich nicht, dass zu der Ausführung dieses Ihres Wunsches so viel Zeit gehören werde. Theils waren es die zahlreichen Geschäfte die mich abhielten, theils das Aufsuchen der gewünschten Pflanzen, die bei dem häufigen Gebrauche hinter die Müller’schen gerathen sind, und die selbst heute noch nicht alle mitkommen, endlich aber vermutete ich einen Tag nach dem anderen die Sendung von Müller, die in England liegen geblieben war und die Ihnen etwas zum Drucken für die Linnaea bringen sollte. Sie erhalten also noch nicht alle Dodonaeen, 2 oder 3 Arten sind noch versteckt, müssen sich aber in den nächsten Tagen auffinden, da ich nun auch ein Dutzend Packete durchzusehen habe; sie sollen bald nachfolgen. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn Sie den Druck des Müller’schen </seg>
               <seg style="">Manuskripts</seg>
               <seg style=""> bald vornehmen lassen können, so wäre es mir in sofern lieb, als ich in Anfang März Gelegenheit habe, eine Kiste nach Australien zu senden. Wie interessant Müller’s Pflanzen jetzt werden, ersehen Sie aus den beiliegenden Beschreibungen, die wunderschön aufgelegten Exemplare sind alle in meinen Händen. </seg>
               <seg style="">Mit Einschluss</seg>
               <seg style=""> der auf Vandiemensland</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">gesammelten Arten beläuft sich nach meiner oberflächlichen Annahme die Zahl der geschickten auf fast 1500 Species. Und was ist bei dem wirklich ausserordenlichen Eifer Müller’s nicht noch zu erwarten. Vielleicht ist Müller jetzt schon in Port Philipp,</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">da ihm die Vegetation von</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">Adelaide u dem Murray nicht Neues genug mehr bot. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe jetzt wirklich angefangen die ganze Sammlung kritisch durchzunehmen, hätte aber gerne noch Hülfe dabei. An Bentham habe ich wegen der sehr zahlreichen Acacien</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">u Leguminosen</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">geschrieben, Lindley wird die Orchideen nachsehen (weil Müller es wünscht, sonst hätte ich sie Reichenbach jr. geschickt), Fenzl habe </seg>
               <seg style="">ich auch aufgefordert.</seg>
               <seg style=""> Wenn ich den nur noch 1 oder 2 Mitarbeiter hätte, so sollte das ganze bald fertig sein. Mit den zahlreichen und manches neue enthaltenden </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Compositeen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> bin ich beinahe zu Ende, ich denke Ihnen in 14 Tagen bis 3 Wochen die Aufzählung derselben zuzusenden, ich möchte gerne, dass nach dem Druck des Mü</seg>
               <seg style="">l</seg>
               <seg style="">ler’schen Manuskript meine Enumeratio sogleich folgen könnte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Müller hat ausser der Calotis cuneifolia, noch die erinacea Steetz, die scapigera Hook. </seg>
               <seg style="">und 3 oder 4 andere gesammelt.</seg>
               <seg style=""> Ueber </seg>
               <seg style="">Ihre Gnaphalia</seg>
               <seg style=""> 210 u 211 werden Sie näheres </seg>
               <seg style="">bei mir finden;</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">Ihr Aster? Behrii</seg>
               <seg style="">187 ist Eurybiopsis gracilis Hook. fil, welche Müller u wohl mit Recht unter dem Namen E. hookeri mit E. scabrida Hook. zusammenzieht.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zwiebelgewächse sind seit längerer Zeit nicht aus Südafrika angekommen und wohl deshalb, weil wir die letzten von Zeyher geschickten nicht gut verkaufen konnten. Man hat hier die Erfahrung gemacht, dass diese Zwiebeln sich nicht lange halten, sie werden immer kleiner und gehen allmälig aus. Wollen Sie übrigens deshalb Zeyher schreiben, so will ich den Brief gerne einlegen oder befördern, mit Dr. Pappe werden Sie nichts anfangen. Zeyher hat im vorigen Monate wieder Sämereien geschickt, Drège lässt glaube ich, jetzt die Verzeichnisse drucken. Auch Müller hat Saamen aus Australien geschickt, die ich auch an Drège gegeben habe. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Lindley’s Folia orchidacea werden Sie gesehen haben, das Werk ist prächtig gehalten.</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">Es wäre zu wünschen, dass Reichenb. fil. sich bemühte, sich an Lindley anzuschliessen; unsere Gärtner hier bei Hamburg sagen, die Reichenbach’schen Diagnosen seien ihnen zu weitläufig u nicht so verständlich als die Lindleys’schen. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. Müller möchte gerne 12 Abdrucke seiner Arbeit haben, er meint, er könne durch Vertheilung einiger Exemplare an dortige gewichtige Leute seine botanischen Bestrebungen fördern. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Päckchen für Dr. Areschoug wird erst mit dem ersten Frühlingsschiffe abgehen. Areschoug ist aber selbst Schuld daran, denn er antwortete mir so spät auf meinen Brief, sodass ich die Kiste mit Spongien</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">nicht mehr p.</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">Dampfschiff expedieren konnte. Areschoug beabsichtigt über die Spongien zu arbeiten. Wir haben hier viel u schönes Material davon, das ich ihm übergeben will. Schade dass kein Deutscher sich bis jetzt dazu hergegeben hat, bei der Arbeit glaube ich sind Loorbeeren zu erringen. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich wollte eine kleine Bemerkung zu dem Müller’schen Manuskripte hinzufügen, habe es aber vergessen, und nun ist das Packet versiegelt. Möchten Sie nicht als Anmerkung dazu setzen, dass diese neuen Pflanzen einen Theil der an mich gesandten käuflichen Müller’schen Sammlungen ausmachen und dass eine Aufzählung sämtlicher Arten folgen werde. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Die beigelegte Dodonaea</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">von Sieber finde ich nicht in DCandolle.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0.1665in; text-align: end; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung </p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0.1665in; text-align: end; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr </p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; margin-top: 0in; margin-bottom: 0.1665in; text-align: end; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">ergebenster </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">W. Sonder </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie wundern sich vielleicht, dass ich zwei der Mueller’schen Compositen durchstrichen habe; dieselben sind aber neuerdings von Asa Gray in Hooker’s London Journal beschrieben.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 5 January 1853</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When I received the Australian Dodonaeae back towards the end of September with the request to also send you the ones collected by Preiss, I did not expect that it would take so much time to fulfil your wish. Partly it was the numerous business matters that prevented me from doing so, partly it was the search for the desired plants, which have fallen behind Mueller's due to their frequent use and which even today do not all come along; but finally I expected one day after the other that Mueller's consignment, which had been left behind in England and which was supposed to bring you something to print for the Linnaea. Therefore you do not yet receive all the Dodonaeae, 2 or 3 species are still hidden but must be found in the next few days as I now have but a dozen packages to look through; they should follow soon. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If you can have Mueller's manuscript printed soon, I would appreciate it, as I will have the opportunity to send a box to Australia at the beginning of March. You will see how interesting Mueller's plants are now becoming from the enclosed descriptions; the beautifully presented specimens are all in my hands. Including the species collected in Van Diemen's Land, my superficial assumption is that the number of species sent amounts to almost 1500. And what else is not to be expected with Mueller's truly extraordinary zeal. Perhaps Mueller is already in Port Phillip, as the vegetation of Adelaide and the Murray no longer offered him enough new things.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have now really started to go through the whole collection critically, but would still like some help. I have written to Bentham about the very numerous Acacias and Leguminosae.<seg style="background-color: #ffff00; "> Lindley will attend to the orchids (because Mueller wants it, otherwise I would have sent them to Reichenbach jr.).</seg> I have also asked Fenzl.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: 10pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See Sonder to Fenzl 15 November 1952, 27 December 1852.</p>
               </note> If I only had 1 or 2 more collaborators, the whole thing would be finished soon. I am almost finished with the numerous and many new <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">composites,</hi>
               </seg> I think I will send you the list of them in 14 days to 3 weeks. I would like that my listing could follow immediately after the printing of Mueller's manuscript.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Apart from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Calotis cuneifolia</seg>, Mueller has also collected <seg style="font-style: italic; ">erinacea</seg> Steetz, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">scapigera</seg> Hook. and 3 or 4 others. You will find more details about your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gnaphalia</seg> 210 and 211 in my contribution; your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Aster? behrii</seg> is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eurybiopsis gracilis</seg> Hook. fil, which Mueller probably rightly combines with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. scabrida</seg> Hook. under the name <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. hookeri</seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bulbous plants have not arrived from South Africa for a long time and probably because we could not sell the last ones sent by Zeyher very well. It has been our experience here that these bulbs do not last long, they become smaller and smaller and gradually die out. If, by the way, you want to write to Zeyher about this, I will gladly insert or forward the letter; you won't get anywhere with Dr. Pappe. Zeyher sent seeds again last month, and I believe Drège is now having the lists printed. Mueller has also sent seeds from Australia, which I have also given to Drège. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will have seen Lindley's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Folia orchidacea</seg>, which is a splendid work. It would be desirable for Reichenbach fil. to make an effort to follow Lindley; our gardeners here in Hamburg say that Reichenbach's diagnoses are too long-winded for them and not as comprehensible as Lindley's. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">Dr. Mueller would like to have 12 copies of his work; he thinks he could promote his botanical endeavours by distributing a few examples to important </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; background-color: #ffff00; "
               xml:lang="en">people there.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The parcel for Dr. Areschoug will only leave with the first spring ship. But it is Areschoug's own fault, because he answered my letter so late that I was unable to send the box of sponges per steamship. Areschoug intends to work on the sponges. We have a lot of beautiful material of them here, which I want to hand over to him. It's a pity that no German has so far anything to do with them, I think there are laurels to be won in this work. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I wanted to add a small remark to Mueller's manuscript but I forgot, and now the package is sealed. Would you not like to add as a note that these new plants make up a part of the Mueller collections sent to me for sale and that a list of all species will follow. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not find the enclosed <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dodonaea </seg>of Sieber in de Candolle.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 10pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">With sincere esteem, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 10pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 10pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>most devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 10pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; line-height: 0.1945in; font-family: Geneva; "
               xml:lang="en">You may be surprised that I have crossed out two of the Mueller composites; however, they have recently been described by Asa Gray in Hooker's London Journal.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
