<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Hamburg, 6 April 1857 ¶ Esteemed Professor, ¶  ¶ The enclosed is a short continuation of the Plantae Muellerianae, which you are kindly requested to print as soon as possible. I would appreciate it...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M57-04-06-nonsf.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M57.04.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title> ¶ Hamburg, 6 April 1857 ¶ Esteemed Professor, ¶  ¶ The enclosed is a short continuation of the Plantae Muellerianae, which you are kindly requested to print as soon as possible. I would appreciate it...</title>
               <date when="1857-04-06">1857-04-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M57-04-06-nonsf.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Diederich von Schlechtendal</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Hamburg, 6 April 1857 ¶ Esteemed Professor, ¶  ¶ The enclosed is a short continuation of the Plantae Muellerianae, which you are kindly requested to print as soon as possible. I would appreciate it...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M57.04.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Diederich von Schlechtendal</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="">MS not seen; extracted from Tkach, Neubauer &amp; Roser (2022), Brief 31.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 6 Apr. 57</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Geehrtester Herr!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Beifolgend eine kleine Fortsetzung der Plant. Müllerianae deren Druck Sie gefälligst, wenn es angeht, bald veranstalten wollen. Lieb wäre es mir, wenn Sie diesmal einige Abdrucke mehr anfertigen lassen wollten, da Dr. Gottsche davon abhaben will. Es thut mir leid, dass ich nicht mehr Manuskript zur Zeit senden kann; ich selbst habe zu wenig Zeit zum Arbeiten gehabt, und die Mitarbeiter sind gar zu langsam. Von den Herren Bartling Fenzl u Bentham ist nichts zu erhalten! Dr. Müller ist glücklich wieder mit der Expedition zurückgekehrt. Ich hatte gestern einen Brief von ihm. Er schreibt aus Sidney wo er bis ungefähr Mitte dieses Jahrs zu bleiben gedenkt, dann geht er wieder nach Melbourne. Er drängt auf die Beendigung der Bearbeitung, doch so gerne ich ihm gefällig sein will, mit Dampf arbeite ich nicht. Auch ist er mit mir unzufrieden, dass bei den Mimoseen seine Namen als Synonyme stehen geblieben sind. Bei diesen müssen mir viele entgangen sein, obgleich ich eine Anzahl durchstrichen; von nun an soll eben kein Müller’scher Name als Synonym mehr stehen bleiben. Sie werden indess mit mir einverstanden sein, dass es Dr. Müller gar nicht zum Schimpf gereicht, wenn er eine Pflanze für neu gehalten hat, die sich bei genauer Untersuchung als bekannt ergiebt. Kommen solche Synonyme nicht auch bei anderen Sammlungen vor, und hat der Verkäufer nicht auch Pflichten gegen seine Abnehmer? Ich glaube die Nichtanführung der Müller’schen Namen kann Confusion genug hervorrufen, wenn sie von dem Besitzer falsch bestimmt werden, der ohnehin unzufrieden damit sein wird, wenn er die Pflanzen nachbestimmen soll.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr Diplom nebst den Heften der Linnaea ist Mitte vorigen Monats abgegangen. – Ich habe heute keine Zeit nachzusehen, welche Hefte mir von der Linnaea fehlen, es soll nächstens geschehen. Ich werde Sie zu rechter Zeit benachrichtigen, wenn ich an Dr. Müller sende, ich denk Anfang oder Mitte Junis. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre Beilage für Dr. Pappe geht Mitte dieses Monats ab, die für Hr. Krüger auf Trinidad ist schwieriger zu befördern. Ich sende sie nächstens nach St. Thomas.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was sagen Sie zu den letzten Nummern der Bonplandia? Der Streit über die Begoniaceen fängt jetzt an unerquicklich und langweilig zu werden. Prof. Lehmann wird mit dem Exkurs des Hr. Seemann in der letzten Nummer nichts besonders zufrieden sein. Auch ich würde jetzt in einen Streit mit Dr. Steetz gerathen, wenn ich nicht ein zu entschiedener Feind solcher Diskussionen wäre. Dr. Steetz hätte die Sache nicht aufrühren sollen, er ist entschieden im Nachtheil. Ich sehe die Antheren anhängsel bei Leptorhynchos und Waitzia mit der Länge [Lupe?] ganz deutlich, ich brauche kein Mikroskop dazu. Ich weiss noch nicht, ob ich darauf antworte, geschieht es, so wird es sehr kurz sein u nur in Veröffentlichung der von mir, Grönland u.a. angefertigten Zeichnungen sein; d.h. wenn Herr Seemann etwas von mir aufnimmt. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hr. Kützing schreibt mir, dass Wallroth gestorben sei. Obgleich man vielerlei auf den Mann zu sagen wüsste, ich habe ihn immer für einen ausgezeichneten Menschen gehalten, seine Werke haben immer einen grossen Werth für mich gehabt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochachtungsvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Der Bearbeiter der Pittosporen ist ein hiesiger Lehrer oder Besitzer einer Privatschule, den ich gerne in die system Botanik einführen möchte.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hamburg, 6 April 1857</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The enclosed is a short continuation of the Plantae Muellerianae, which you are kindly requested to print as soon as possible. I would appreciate it if you would have a few more reprints made this time, as Dr Gottsche wants to have some. I am sorry that I cannot send more manuscript at this time; I have had too little time to work on them myself, and my co-workers are too slow. Nothing has been received from Messrs Bartling, Fenzl and Bentham! <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">Dr Mueller has safely returned again with the expedition. I had a letter from him yesterday. He writes from Sidney</seg>
               <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">i.e. Sydney.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style="background-color: #ffff00; "> where he intends to stay until about the middle of this year, then he will return again to Melbourne. He is pressing for the completion of the editing, but as much as I want to please him, I am not working with steam. He is also displeased with me that in the case of the Mimoseae his names have been left as synonyms.</seg> I must have missed many of them, although I have crossed out a number; from now on, no Mueller name shall remain as a synonym. You will agree with me, however, that it is no disgrace to Dr Mueller if he has considered a plant to be new which, on closer examination, turns out to be known. Don't such synonyms also occur in other collections, and doesn't the seller also have obligations towards his buyers? I believe that the failure to quote Müller's names can cause confusion enough if they are wrongly determined by the owner, who will be unhappy anyway if he has to re-determine the plants. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your diploma and the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg> parts left in the middle of last month. - I do not have time today to check which parts of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg> are missing, but I will do so soon. I will inform you in due time when I am sending to Dr Mueller, I think at the beginning or in the middle of June. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your enclosure for Dr Pappe will leave in the middle of this month, the one for Mr Krüger in Trinidad is more difficult to transport. I will send it to St Thomas next month.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What do you say about the last numbers of<seg style="font-style: italic; "> Bonplandia</seg>? The argument about the Begoniaceae is now beginning to become unedifying and boring. Prof. Lehmann will not be very happy with Mr Seemann's digression in the last issue. I, too, would now get into an argument with Dr Steetz if I were not too determined an enemy of such discussions. Dr Steetz should not have stirred things up, he is decidedly at a disadvantage. I can see the anther appendages in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leptorhynchos</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Waitzia</seg> quite clearly with the [hand lens?], I don't need a microscope. I do not yet know whether I will reply to this, but if I do, it will be very short and only in the publication of the drawings made by me, Grönland[?] and others, i.e. if Mr Seemann admits something of mine. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Kützing writes me that Wallroth has died. Although one could say many things about the man, I have always considered him to be an excellent person, and his works have always been of great value to me.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The editor of the Pittosporae is a local teacher or owner of a private school whom I would like to introduce to systematic botany.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
