<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tönning, 4 May 1857. ¶ My dearly loved precious Clara, ¶  ¶ Thanks, many thanks for your dear letter, which we received some time ago, and which gave us the news that you are all happy and well. Every...</title>
            <author>Marie [...</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M57-05-04-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS[…], Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M57.05.04</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Marie [...</author>
               <title>Tönning, 4 May 1857. ¶ My dearly loved precious Clara, ¶  ¶ Thanks, many thanks for your dear letter, which we received some time ago, and which gave us the news that you are all happy and well. Every...</title>
               <date when="1857-05-04">1857-05-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1850-9/M57-05-04-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Clara Wehl</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Tönning, 4 May 1857. ¶ My dearly loved precious Clara, ¶  ¶ Thanks, many thanks for your dear letter, which we received some time ago, and which gave us the news that you are all happy and well. Every...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M57.05.04</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Marie [... <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to Clara Wehl</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS<seg style="font-weight: bold; ">[…]</seg>, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope 'An lieb Clärchen', (To dear little Clara). Johannes: <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">married name needed [Koopmann?]. She is Clara's cousin (née Mertens). They were about the same age and grew up as sisters.Her husband seems to have been a school teacher in Tönning (see at the end of the letter).</seg> See also M to […] Koopmann, 21 October 1882. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Marie's son? or a relation on her husband's side?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Tönning, d. 4ten Mai, 1857.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Meine inniggeliebte theure Clara!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dank, herzlichen Dank für Deine lieben Briefe, die wir vor einiger Zeit erhalten, und die uns von Euer Aller Glück und Wohlsein benachrichtigten. Ich versetze mich bei jedesmaligen Durchlesen Deiner lieben Zeilen, meine süsse Clara, so ganz und gar in Deine Nähe, sehe Dich als Mutter Deine lieben Kinder pflegen, warten, sie herzen und küssen, und als thätige Hausfrau Deine Wirthschaft besorgen. O meine liebe Clara, das wir uns doch nicht mehr von Angesicht zu Angesicht sehen können, und auch so wenig Aussicht vorhanden ist, dass wir es in diesem Leben jemals wieder werden! Doch, der liebe Vater im Himmel hat es ja so für uns bestimmt, hat Dir Deinen Platz im fernen Welttheil angewiesen, und mir den meinigen hier, lass uns ihm denn für Alles recht dankbar sein, er weiss ja wie und wo es für uns am Besten ist. Hat er uns doch auch ein Mittel in die Hand gegeben, welches uns einander nahe bringt, ob wir uns gleich fern sind, lass uns dies Mittel denn nur recht oft gebrauchen, ich meine, lass uns recht oft an einander schreiben! Schon lange wollte ich an Dich schreiben, meine liebe Clara, doch Du weisst wie es geht, es kommt so manche Abhaltung, namentlich wenn eine solche Catastrophe dazwischen kommt wie bei mir in letzterer Zeit. Ja, der liebe Gott hat uns wieder reich gesegnet, er hat uns wieder ein theures Kind in unsere Arme, an unser Herz gelegt, ein theures, liebes Söhnchen. Dank, unaussprechlichen Dank sei dem treuen Herrn dafür gebracht, er hat dadurch wieder milden Balsam auf unser wundes Herz geträufelt, die Tränen des Schmerzes wieder in Freudentränen verwandelt. O, meine Clara, ich weiss es, Du hast mit mir gefühlt bei der Nachricht, dass der liebe Gott unser süsses, theures Kindchen, unsere süsse Louise oder Ide wie wir sie gewöhnlich nannten, zu sich genommen. O, nur das feste Anklammern an den wahren göttlichen Trost konnte das zerrissene, so tief betrübte Elternherz beruhigen, und es zur vollen Ergebung in den Willen des Höchsten bringen. Wir wissen ja wohin unsere liebe theure Ide gekommen ist, sie ruht ja in des lieben Heilandes Armen und an seinem Herzen, er hatte ja die Kinder so lieb. Keine Thräne benetzt ihre kleinen Wangen mehr, und Schmerzen und Leiden sind fern von ihr, sollten wir uns daher nicht ihretwegen freuen, da sie glücklich ist, so glücklich, wie sie es hier auf Erden nie hätte werden können? Will gleich das schwache Herz oft nicht schweigen, so spricht Gottes Wort: "Wir sollen uns wiedersehen! Ja wir sollen uns wiedersehen, der liebe Heiland bewahrt uns das theure Kind auf, um es uns einst wieder zuzuführen. Ist das nicht ein schöner Gedanke, o er zieht so mächtig zum Himmel! — Es thut mir so leid, dass wir kein Portrait von unserm kleinen seligen Engel haben, es ist so angenehm, obgleich ihr theures Bild in unserm Herzen stets fortleben wird. Sie war gerade in dem Alter, wo Kinder so viele Freude machen. Sie lief so niedlich, und sprach schon so Vieles, obgleich sie erst 5/4 Jahr alt war; sie hatte die Blumen so lieb, und werde ich diesen Sommer ihr theures Grab recht mit Blumen schmücken. Doch genug davon, das Herz will schon wieder traurig werden, ich reisse die Wunden wieder auf, doch möchte ich gar nicht aufhören Dir von ihr zu erzählen, sie war gar zu lieb und gut. Aber der liebe Herr nimmt nicht nur, er giebt auch wieder aus seiner Gnadenfülle. Das haben wir denn auch erfahren. Am 19ten Februar schenkte er uns einen lieben Sohn. Du kannst denken, liebe Clara, wie mein Herz von Dank und Freude überströmte, wie Alles überstanden war, und ich mein Kind, einen dicken kräftigen Jungen, an mein Herz drücken konnte. Ich hatte eine recht leichte Entbindung, musste jedoch in der letzten Zeit der Schwangerschaft viel an Rücken und Kreuzschmerzen leiden, doch sind das ja Alles leicht wieder vergessene Schmerzen. Auch mit der Brust und den Warzen ist es dieses Mal ganz gut, nur 8 Tage wie der Kleine die Sprähe hatte, wurden auch die Warzen davon befallen, wodurch sie ziemlich empfindlich wurden, doch verlor sich das wieder. Am Stillfreitage hielt ich meinen Kirchgang, und gehe seitdem, wenn das Wetter und die Zeit es erlauben öfters mal spazieren, da das ja für die Gesundheit sehr stärkend ist. Ich bin fast ganz munter und wohl, und habe ungemein viel Nahrung für mein Kind. In der 5ten Woche wurde der Kleine getauft, und standen der lieber Vater als Grosspapa, mein Schwager, der Bischof Koopmann aus Altona und meine Schwägerin Iette, welche bei ihm ist, Gevetter. Er bekam die Namen: Ferdinand, Wilhelm, Heinrich, und nennen wir ihn Ferdinand, da das doch solcher Familienname bei uns ist. Er gedeiht prächtig, ist wohl schon mal so schwer geworden seit der Geburt, kleine dicke Pausbacken, und seines Papas Ebenbild, blondes Haar und bläuliche Augen. Gott erhalte ihn uns nur, so es sein Wille ist, man möchte die Kinder doch so gerne behalten, nicht wahr, meine Clara? — O wie gerne möchte ich Deine beiden kleinen süssen Kinder mal sehen und in meine Arme schliessen. Die kleine Bertha ist ja wohl ein klein reizendes Mädchen nach den Beschreibungen, die wir von ihr haben, und so klug und vernünftig, dass Ihr gewiss Eure wahre Freude an ihr habt. Und klein Edy ist gewiss seines Papas Vorzug und seiner Mama Stolz. Recht lebhaft kann ich mir in Euer glückliches Familienleben hineinversetzen, möchte der liebe Gott Euch dieses Glück recht lange ungetrübt erhalten! Vielleicht wirst Du, wenn dieser Brief bei Euch anlangt, schon Dein Haus durch ein 3tes kleines Wesen bereichert haben, meine liebe Clara, welches ich aus Äusserungen, die Du in Deinem letzten Brief gabst, entnehme. Möchte der liebe Gott Dir denn recht beistehen in der Stunde der Noth, und Dir die verlorenen Kräfte bald wieder schenken! — Du hast ja einen recht grossen Hausstand, meine liebe Clara, und was für einen grossen Hühnerhof, da bekommst Du ja eine Menge Eier, woraus Du wohl viel Geld löst. Auch Brodbacken, Bierbrauen und Lichtziehen musst Du? Nun, da hast Du auch mit zwei Mädchen genug zu thun, die Kinder nehmen auch ja viel Zeit in Anspruch. Dass es auch dort bei Euch so schwer wird ein gutes Mädchen zu bekommen, wundert mich, ich glaubte es wäre nur hier in Europa der Fall. Ich habe ja nur ein Mädchen, also auch mit dem Kinde und der Haushaltung genug zu thun, doch wenn der liebe Gott mich nur gesund erhält, so macht die Arbeit mir Freude, und die Pflege und Wartung des Kindes mag ich lieber selber besorgen, und es nicht gerne einem Kindermädchen anvertrauen. Man kann es ja so einrichten, wenn das Mädchen in der Küche fertig ist, dass sie dann das Kind noch ein wenig warten kann, mit 2 Mädchen giebt gar zu leicht Unannehmlichkeiten. Die ich jetzt habe ist aus Lunden, ein ganz ordentliches stilles Mädchen, nur unerfahren und nachlässig in der Arbeit. Doch was hilfts, mit dem öfteren Wechseln kommt auch nichts daraus, man muss zufrieden sein, wenn es einigermassen geht. Mit der Lohnerhöhung sind sie hier auch sehr bei der Hand, jedes Jahr müssen auch wir mehr geben. Ihr habt wohl oft Eheleute als Domestiken? Ich meine Du schriebst es mal. — Dass die liebe Bertha sich mit ihrem George Doughty so glücklich fühlt, freut uns ungemein, und hat sie uns in der letztern Zeit 2 Mal durch liebe Briefe erfreut. Hoffentlich befindet sie sich wohl, ich habe in dieser Zeit viel an sie gedacht, Du schriebst ja sie fühlte sich Mutter, und da könnte die Zeit ihrer Entbindung wohl so ungefähr jetzt fallen, meiner Berechnung Deinem Briefe nach. Möchte diese Catastrophe denn eine recht gute Wirkung auf ihren Gesundheitszustand ausüben, oftmals pflegt dies der Fall zu sein, und wie glücklich wird die liebe Bertha sich fühlen, wenn sie einen kleinen Engel bekommt. Mit rechter Spannung sehe ich Euren nächsten Nachrichten entgegen, vielleicht bringen sie uns schon näheres darüber, sowie auch über Dich, meine liebe Clara. Wie schade, dass Ihr so weit auseinander wohnt, es ist doch eine unendliche Annehmlichkeit mit den lieben Angehörigen nahe zusammen zu wohnen, dazu kommt noch, dass bei Euch weder Chauseen noch Eisenbahnen sind, die das Reisen doch ungemein erleichtern. Du solltest jetzt nur mal unser Tönning wiedersehn, die Gegend beim Badehause und bei den Mühlen würdest Du wohl kaum wieder erkennen, so hat es sich dort verändert, es entsteht dort ein ganz neues Stadtvirthel, täglich kommen und gehen 3-4 Eisenbahnzüge, und nehmen sich die damit verbundenen Neubauten ganz hübsch aus. Doch ich denke davon werden die Andern Euch wohl schon erzählt haben, und will ich Dir lieber etwas von Deinen Bekannten erzählen. Du erkundigst Dich, liebe Clara, nach Therese Wiese, wie es ihr ginge. Ach, es ist doch ein recht trauriges Loos was uns getroffen, wenn man daran denkt, der Mann in Amerika und sie mit dem Kinde hier. Doch findet sie sich ganz gut darin, sie war grade bei uns, wie ich Deinen lieben Brief erhielt, und konnte ich Deinen Gruss gleich ausrichten. Sie sieht jetzt viel wohler und munterer aus, als da ihr Mann noch bei ihr war, man sagt ja auch, dass er nicht gut gegen sie gewesen sein soll, doch lässt sie sich nie darüber aus. Vor einiger Zeit zeigte sie mir einen Brief von ihrem Mann, worin er recht liebevoll an sie schrieb, und die Hoffnung aussprach, dass sie doch noch wieder zusammen kämen, und es auch einsah, dass er es durch seinen Leichtsinn verschuldet habe. Es geht ihm eben nicht besonders dort in Amerika, wie so Manchen, die dort Glück zu finden hoffen. Er muss bald dies bald jenes thun, um sein Fortkommen zu gründen, bald Arbeitsmann, bald Koch, bald etwas anderes. Ist dies nicht schrecklich, und hier hatte er ein hübsches Haus, Frau und Kind. Doch wir wollen hoffen, dass er sich diese Schule zu Nutzen nimmt, und ein besserer Mensch wird, dann kann mit Gottes Hilfe ja noch Alles gut werden. Es ist ein Glück für Therese, dass sie ihre Eltern hier am Ort hat, welche das früher Gaje's Gewese bewohnen, da hat sie doch immer Stütze daran. Ihre Waaren aus der Handlung hat sie in einer oder vielmehr mehreren Auctionen verkauft, hat das Unterhaus vermietet, und lebt nun mit ihrem Sohne oben. — Von Christine Nielsen habe ich lange nichts gehört, sie wohnt ja in Jütland, ist dort an einen Arzt verheirathet, doch glaube ich, dass ihre Ehe bis jetzt kinderlos ist, vielleicht kommt sie diesen Sommer viel zu Besuch her zu ihren Eltern, welche die kleine Enkelin Hanne Schmidt aus Elmshorn, das Kind ihrer ältesten Tochter bei sich haben. Bertha Gaje hat Carl Sievers ja geheirathet, wohnt in dem früher Bumb'schen Hause am Hafen und hat bereits zwei Töchter. Ihre Schwester Doris wohnt in Heide an einen gewissen Herrn Brandt verheirathet, welches ein sehr netter Mann sein soll, doch ist sie wohl nicht eben beliebt dort, Du kennst sie ja. Sie soll einen niedlichen Jungen haben, ein kleines Mädchen starb bald nach der Geburt, und jetzt erwartet sie wieder eins. Magna ist jetzt bei der Mutter, sie war verlobt mit einem alten Candidaten, die Verlobung ist jedoch wieder zurückgegangen, da wenig Aussicht auf feste Anstellung da war. Nanny ist jetzt verlobt mit einem jungen Apotheker, welcher die Apotheke in Meldorf gekauft hat, wahrscheinlich theilweise durch Nanny's Mittel, doch soll er sehr nett sein, Nanny ist jedoch ein ziemlich putzsüchtiges, kokettes Mädchen geworden, vielleicht ändert sie sich als Frau. So sind denn nur Magna und Agnes noch bei der Mutter noch, ich höre sie wollen mit nach Meldorf ziehen. — Emilie Peers ist nun auch ein kleines Fräulein geworden, übrigens ein sehr liebenswürdiges Mädchen. Sie ist recht gross geworden, und spielt sehr fertig auf dem Fortepiano, woran die Eltern auch viel gewirkt hatten. Nach ihrer Confirmation war sie 1 Jahr in Kiel in Pension, um sich auszubilden, die Sitte ist jetzt ziemlich allgemein geworden, in der vorigen Woche brachte Madame Ducker ihre Tochter Friedchen, die Du wohl noch erinnerst auch nach Brunsbüttel ins Institut, sie wurde Ostern confirmirt. Diese Familie hat in letzter Zeit einen herben Verlust erlitten, Du erinnerst die Söhne doch noch, liebe Clara, nicht wahr? Der 2 jüngste, Gustav, studirte in Copenhagen zum Thierarzt, war bereits mehrere Jahre dort, und bereitete sich jetzt vor zum Examen. Da bekommen sie plötzlich pr telegraph. Depesche die Nachricht, dass er am Stillfreitag Morgen plötzlich nach einer 2 tägigen Krankheit gestorben sei. Ist das nicht ungemein hart für die arme Mutter, da sie nicht einmal wusste, dass er krank sei. Die eigentliche Krankheit weiss die Mutter gar nicht, da sie ihr verheimlicht ist, aber es heisst für bestimmt, er sei an der Tollwuth gestorben. 14 Tage vor seiner Krankheit hatte er nemlich heimlich einen tollen Hund sessirt, und sich wohl durch eine Ritze in der Hand die Ansteckung zugezogen. Durch eine Caraffe mit Wasser, die ein Wärter des Hospitals hereingebracht, ist die Wasserscheu ausgebrochen. Es ist sehr hart, solch kräftiger junger Mann, und so fern von den Angehörigen! Wir machten Mad. Ducker neulich unsern Contulationsbesuch<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kondolenzbesuch.</p>
               </note>, sie war jedoch schon recht gefasst. Den Todesfall mit Consul Jansen und Sohn werden die Andern wohl schon mitgetheilt haben. Samman ist jetzt erst an seiner Stelle zum Consul ernannt, doch nun erst instituirt, er ist noch unverheirathet. — Bei Schubart's sind die Töchter nun auch alle confirmirt, jedoch noch keine verlobt. Helene und Mathilde sind jetzt zu Hause, Agathe ist nach der Confimation nach einem Gute auf dem Lande gekommen, um sich für die Haushaltung auszubilden. Diesen Sommer wollen sie ihr Haus niederreissen und neu aufbauen, haben sich zu dem [Emme] am Hafen eingemiethet so lange. Sie sind sehr für das gesellschaftliche Leben, und haben die jungen Mädchen einen Leseklub. Doris Riess, die Du auch wohl noch erinnerst, lieb Clara, ist an einen Witwer mit 4 Kindern, einem Kaufmann Jansen, verheirathet voriges Jahr, und hat bereits ein Söhnchen. Man fürchtete erst, dass sie etwas zu leicht und zu flüchtig wäre, um gleich bei 4 Kindern Mutterstelle zu vertreten, doch hat sie sich ganz gut genommen, und sollen die Kinder viel von ihr halten. Ihr Bruder Johannes, Du erinnerst ihn wohl, nimmt sich jedoch nicht so gut. Er hat hier eine Wattenfabrik mit dem Bruder seiner Frau in Comp., doch treibt er sich jeden Tag in Wirthshäusern herum, und hat nicht Lust sich um sein Geschäft zu kümmern, macht Schulden und seinen Eltern Herzeleid. — Sophie Schenk wohnt jetzt bei ihren Eltern als Putzmacherin. Sie hat die Putzarbeit in Altona gelernt, und macht ganz niedliche Sachen, soll auch viel zu thun haben, und ist ein achtbares Mädchen geworden. Ihre Schwester Wilhelmine, welche auch zu Hause ist, ist leider etwas gefallen. Sie hatten einen Engländer in Logies, welcher bei der Eisenbahn angestellt war, und sich nach einiger Zeit mit ihr verlobte. Bald verbreitete sich das Gerücht: sie sei guter Hoffnung, welches sich leider bestätigte. Doch konnten sie sich nicht heirathen, da es sich nun wohl herausstellte, dass er in England Frau und Kinder habe. War das nicht hart für diese Familie? Sie bekam eine kleine Tochter, welche sie bei sich hat. Dergleichen Fälle fallen in dieser verderbten Zeit ungemein oft vor, auch bei Euch? — Hast Du noch sonst einige Bekannte, liebe Clara, worüber Du gerne Nachricht haben möchtest, so schreibe es nur, ich will Dir gerne etwas darüber mittheilen. Tante Ketelsen hat noch immer ihre Nähschule, ihr Sohn Fritz ist schon recht gross, 12 Jahre alt, und geht in der Rectorclasse zur Schule. Den 2ten Mai feierte sie ihren Geburtstag, die Schülerinnen hatten ein Geschenk für sie gekauft, dann trektirt sie sie, und sie bleiben den Tag da zu spielen. Meine Schwester Louise ist ja nun auch confirmirt, und ein grosses schlankes junges Mädchen geworden. So haben die lieben Eltern die Kinder nun alle aus der Schule, und fühlen sie sich recht glücklich dadurch, uns Alle so um und bei sich zu haben. Und wie glücklich wir darüber sind, die lieben Eltern stets bei uns zu haben, kannst Du wohl denken, es ist auch ein seltenes Glück so alle zusammen zu sein, und sind wir mal Alle bei den lieben Eltern versammelt, so kommt eine kleine ziemliche Reihe heraus, namentlich wenn die Enkelchen auch noch hinzukommen. Die liebe Johanna sieht nun auch ihrer Niederkunft entgegen im August; sie werden gewiss ungemein glücklich werden, wenn der liebe Gott ihnen ein Kind beschert, solch theures Band knüpft die Herzen der Eheleute ja nur noch fester aneinander. Doris ihre kleine Albertine ist ein kleines süsses Kind, nun schon bald 1 Jahr alt, will jedoch die kleinen Füsse nicht zum Gehen zusetzen, und hat auch noch keinen Zahn. Doch das will sich wohl kommen, je älter sie wird, desto kräftiger wird sie ja auch. — Bertha Mein in Husum wird in diesen Tagen Hochzeit geben, sie ist mit einem jungen Klempner namens Zink verlobt in Husum, und ist ihre Schwester hergekommen, um ihre Stelle bei Onkel Klander zu vertreten. Letzterer ist noch immer munter und unverändert. Doris und Lene Dunken geht es auch ganz gut, jede von ihnen hat 2 Kinder, bei Heinrich sind keine Kinder. — Nun, meine süsse Clara, da habe ich Dir nun so allerlei vorgeschwatzt, hoffentlich wird es Dich interessiren. Ich werde diesmal nicht wieder so lange warten ehe ich wieder schreibe, im Laufe dieses Sommers werde ich Dir noch mal wieder Zeilen zukommen lassen. Erst erwarte ich nun Briefe von Euch. Wie freuen wir uns auf die Ankunft Eurer Portrait's, Eure beiden lieben Männer, sowie die lieben Kleinen kennen wir ja noch gar nicht, und auch Dein und der lieben Bertha Gesicht sollen wir dann ja wiedersehn. Sollte auch vielleicht der liebe Ferdinand mit darauf sein? O wie freuten wir uns, als wir seine lieben Schriftzüge wieder erblickten, und danken mit Euch dem Herrn, der ihn aus den Gefahren wieder in Eure Arme geführt hat. Lebe denn recht wohl, meine liebe, liebe Schwester, grüsse Deinen lieben Mann, sowie die theure Bertha und Ferdinand herzlich von mir, und von meinem süssen Herzensmann, welcher grade jetzt in der Schule ist. Ich bin ungemein glücklich durch seinen Besitz, und danke dem lieben Gott innig dafür. Küsse Deine lieben Kinder von ihrer Tante Marie, und kann klein Bertha nicht bald mal an mich schreiben. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">In treuer schwesterlicher Liebe</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Deine Marie.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Tönning, 4 May 1857.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dearly loved precious Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thanks, many thanks for your dear letter, which we received some time ago, and which gave us the news that you are all happy and well. Every time I read your dear lines, my sweet Clara, I imagine myself close to you, watch you as mother, caring for and looking after your dear children, hugging and kissing them, and as a busy housewife going about your housework. O my dear Clara, that we should not see each other again face to face, and that there is so little chance that we shall ever be able to meet again in this life! But our dear Father in Heaven has determined it thus for us, has allotted you your place in a far-away continent, and me mine here. So let us be duly grateful to him for everything, for he knows how and where it is best for us. Has he not given us a means to bring us close, even though we are far apart? So let us use this means often, I mean, let us write to each other very often. I had meant to write to you long ago, my dear Clara, but you know how it is, so many things intervene, and especially when such a catastrophe happens as it did to me recently. Yes, the good God has richly blessed us again, and has placed once more a precious child into our arms, a precious dear little son. Thanks, inexpressible thanks be to the faithful Lord for that. With it he has spread soothing balm on our wounded <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>heart, and has changed our tears of grief into tears of joy. O my dear Clara, I know you have felt with me at the news, that the good God has taken our sweet, precious little child, our sweet Louise, or Ide, as we used to call her, to himself. Only by clinging firmly to the true Divine Consoler could the torn and deeply grieving parents' heart find calm and bring it into full submission under the will of the Most High. After all, we know, where our precious dear Ide has gone, we know she rests in the arms and at the heart of our dear Saviour, he who loved children so much. No tears will ever again touch her little cheeks, and pain and suffering are far from her. So should we not be glad for her sake? — for she is happy, happier than she could ever have been here on earth. Even though often the weak heart will not be silent, God's word speaks: 'We shall see each other again!' Yes, we will see each other again, our dear Saviour is looking after our precious child for us, only to restore it to us one day. Is that not a beautiful thought? O, it draws one so mightily towards Heaven!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am so sorry that we have no portrait of our blessed little angel, it would be so nice, even though her precious picture will always live on in our hearts. She was just at the age, when children bring such a lot of joy. She walked so nicely, and already talked quite a lot, even though she was only 15 months old. She loved flowers, and this summer I will decorate her precious grave with lots of flowers. But enough of that! — my heart is starting to get sad again. I am tearing open the wounds afresh, yet I do not want to stop telling you about her, she was so sweet and good. But the dear Lord does not only take, he also gives out of the fullness of his grace. We, too, have experienced this. On February 19th he blessed us with a dear son. You can imagine, my dear Clara, how my heart overflowed with gratitude and joy, when it was all over and I could press my child, a plump and sturdy boy, to my heart. I had quite an easy delivery, but had suffered a lot from back pain during the last part of the pregnancy. But those are pains easily forgotten. It also went quite well with my breasts and nipples this time, except for one week, when the child had <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">[Sprähe]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Johannes, what is 'Sprähe'? Not in my dictionary or in M's encyclopaedias.— Johannes suggests 'Sprue', a disease of the digestive system, but that does not sound right in this context. Some sort of skin infection seems likely, which would affect the nipples &amp; cause soreness. Something like thrush, perhaps? — Could we ask John Pearn for suggestions?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>, when my nipples were rather tender, but that passed again. On Good Friday I went to church, and have been going for walks fairly frequently since then, if weather and time permit, as that is so invigorating for one's health. I am quite bright and well, and have enormously much milk for my child. The little one was christened in his fifth week, and our dear father<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Ferdinand Mertens.</p>
               </note> as grandfather, my brother-in-law Bishop Koopmann of Altona, and my sister-in-law Iette who stays with him, were godparents. He was given the names Ferdinand Wilhelm Heinrich, and we call him Ferdinand, as that is a name that runs so much in our family. He is coming along splendidly, has just about doubled his birth weight, has chubby little cheeks, and is the image of his father: blond hair and blue eyes. May God preserve him to us, if it be his will. One wants to keep one's children so much, don't you agree, Clara? </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>O, how I would love to see your two sweet little children and put my arms around them! Little Bertha<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ottilie <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Bertha</hi>
                     </seg> Wehl, named after her aunt Bertha Müller (later Doughty), born 31 July 1854 (died 1 October 1922).</p>
               </note> must be a lovely little girl by now, according to the descriptions we get of her, and so clever and sensible, she must be a pure joy to you. And little Edy<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ferdinand <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Eduard</hi>
                     </seg> Wehl (later called 'Ted'), (7 October 1855-1908)</p>
               </note> is no doubt his Daddy's darling and his Mama's pride. I can imagine your happy family life, may the good God preserve this happiness for you for a long long time without the shadow of a cloud! Maybe, by the time this reaches you, you have already enriched your home with another little one<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Mathilde</hi>
                     </seg> Louise Wehl (6 March 1857-1946)</p>
               </note>, my dear Clara. I conclude this from some remarks you made in your last letter. May the good God assist you in your hour of need, and quickly restore your lost strength!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You do have a fairly large household, my dear Clara, and such a large chicken run, you must get a lot of eggs, from which you will make a lot of profit. And you also have to bake bread, brew beer, and make candles? Well, you have plenty to do, even with two maids, just the children take up a lot of time, too. I am astonished, that you find it so hard to get a good girl, I thought that was only the case here in Europe. I do have only one maid, so I have enough to do as well with the child and the housekeeping. But, as long as the good God keeps me well I enjoy the work, and would rather attend to the care and tending of the child myself, and don't like leaving it to a nursemaid. One can arrange things in such a way that the maid, when she has finished in the kitchen, can watch over the child for a little while; there are just too many disagreements with two girls. The one I have now comes from Lunden<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">About 5 km E-NE of Tönning.</p>
               </note>, quite a respectable and quiet girl, only inexperienced and slipshod in her work. But what is the use, frequent changes don't achieve much, one has to be satisfied, if things go reasonably well. Here, too, they are always quick about wanting pay increases, and each year we have to give more. I suppose you often have married couples as domestics? I thought you wrote that one time. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We are very pleased, that dear Bertha is so happy with her George Doughty<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">They married 24 June 1856.</p>
               </note>, and in recent times she has twice made us happy with letters. I hope she is also well, I have been thinking of her a lot in recent times. You wrote she is becoming a mother, and the time of her delivery<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">George Doughty junior was born in 1857, died in 1893. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">(I don't have precise dates)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> should be just about now, according to my calculations going on your letter. May this catastrophe have a very good effect on the state of her health, that frequently tends to be the case, and how happy dear Bertha will feel, when she gets a little angel. We are looking forward to your next news with a great deal of eagerness, perhaps it will already bring us some details about it, and also about you, my dear Clara. What a pity, that you live so far apart<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha and George Doughty were living on a cattle station between Portland and Port Fairy, Victoria.</p>
               </note>, it is so infinitely convenient to live close together with one's family. Added to that, you have neither surfaced roads nor railways, which provide for exceedingly more comfort of travelling. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You should just see our Tönning now, you would hardly recognise the areas near the bath house and near the mills, so much has changed there. A whole new suburb has sprung up there, there are three or four trains daily coming and going, And the new buildings erected in connection with it look rather nice. But I think the others will already have written to you about that, so I will instead tell you something about your acquaintances. You enquire after Therese Wiese, dear Clara, and how she is. Alas, it is rather a sad fate that is presented to us, when one thinks about it, the husband in America and she with the child here. But she seems to have come to terms with it quite well. She was just visiting us, when I received your dear letter, so I could pass on your greetings on the spot. She looks much better and happier now, than when her husband was still with her, it is said, that he did not treat her well, but she never remarks on it. Some time ago she showed me a letter from her husband, in which he wrote to her in quite loving terms, and expressed the hope that they would get back together again, and he realised that it was all his fault because of his irresponsibility. The truth is, he is not getting on too well over there in America, like so many, who hoped to find their fortune there. It seems, he has to do now this, now that, to provide for his livelihood, now a labourer, then a cook, then something else. Is that not awful! — and here he had a nice house, a wife and child. But let us hope, that this school will teach him a lesson and make him a better person, and with God's help it can still all end well. It is fortunate for Therese, that her parents are here on the spot, they live in what was formerly <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Gaje's farmhouse, she finds some support from them. She has sold the goods from the shop in one or rather several auctions, has let the ground floor of her home, and lives upstairs with her son. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have not heard from Christine Nielsen for a long time. She now lives in Jutland and is married to a doctor there, but I believe her marriage is childless so far. Perhaps she will come on frequent visits to her parents here this summer, who have their little granddaughter Hanne Schmidt from Elmshorn<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Northwest of Hamburg.</p>
               </note>, the child of their eldest daughter, staying with them. Bertha Gaje did marry Carl Sievers, and lives in Bumb's former house at the harbour, and already has two daughters. Her sister Doris lives in Heide<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">West of Kiel.</p>
               </note>, married to a certain Mr Brandt, who is said to be a very nice man, but she is not exactly popular there; however, you know her. She is supposed to have a cute little boy, a little girl died shortly after birth, and now she is expecting another one. Magna is now with her mother, she was engaged to an old admirer, but the engagement was broken off, as there was little prospect of a secure position. Nanny is now engaged to a young pharmacist, who bought the pharmacy in Meldorf<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Central town of southern Dithmarschen, on the North sea coast, south of Tönning.</p>
               </note>, probably in part with Nanny's means, but he is said to be very nice. Nanny has turned into a rather dressed up and coquettish girl, perhaps she will change with marriage. So only Magna and Agnes are left with their mother, but I hear they want to move along to Meldorf as well. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Emilie Peers has grown into a little lady; by the way, a very charming girl. She has grown very tall, and is an accomplished pianist, to which her parents contributed a great deal. After her confirmation she was in Kiel for a year in a finishing school to be educated, this custom has become quite common now. Last week Madame Ducker brought her daughter Friedchen, whom you will remember, into the Institute in Brunsbüttel<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In southern Dithmarschen, on the North Sea coast, south of Meldorf, at the mouth of the Elbe River.</p>
               </note>, she was confirmed at Easter. This family has recently suffered a bitter loss; you remember the sons, don't you, dear Clara? The youngest, Gustav, studied in Copenhagen to become a veterinary surgeon, had been there for several years, and was just preparing for his final examinations. Then out of the blue they received the news by telegraphic dispatch, that he had died suddenly on Good Friday morning after two days' illness. Is that not terribly hard on the poor mother, who did not even know, that her son was ill. The mother does not even know the real nature of the illness, it is being kept secret from her. But it is said with certainty, that he died of rabies. Because, you see, two weeks before his illness he had secretly sectioned a rabid dog, and must have become infected through a scratch on his hand. A jug of water brought in by a ward attendant at the hospital brought on the hydrophobia<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A sympton of rabies: a strong aversion to fluids, due to paralysis of the throat muscles causing choking in swallowing.</p>
               </note>. It is very hard, such a strong young man, and so far from the family! Recently we made our visit of condolence to Madame Ducker, she had herself fairly well in control by then. The others have probably already told you about the deaths of Consul Jansen and his son. Samman has been appointed Consul in his place only now, and has only just taken up his office. He is still unmarried.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At Schubart's all the daughters are now confirmed, but none of them are engaged yet. Helene and Mathilde are now at home, Agathe was sent to a country property after her confirmation to learn how to run a household. They want to pull down their house this summer and rebuild, they have rented accommodation with [Emme] at the harbour for the duration. They are very much in with social life, and the young girls have a reading circle. Remember Doris Riess, dear Clara? She married a widower with four children, a merchant Jansen, married last year, and has already a little son. It was feared at first, that she would be too flighty and fickle, to take a mother's place for four children, but she has settled in well, and the children think highly of her. Her brother Johannes, — you remember him? — has, however, not settled down so well. He has a cotton wool factory here in partnership with his wife's brother, but he hangs around public houses every day, and does not feel inclined to take care of his business, gets into debts, and breaks his parents' heart. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sophie Schenk now lives with her parents as milliner. She has learned millinery in Altona<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">At that time the most southern harbour of Holstein (then under Danish rule), now a suburb of Hamburg.</p>
               </note> and makes some quite pretty things, is said to have a lot to do, and has become a respected girl. Her sister Wilhelmine, who also lives at home, has unfortunately fallen a little. They had an Englishman as lodger, who was employed by the railways, and after a while they became engaged. Soon the rumour spread: she is expecting. This was unfortunately confirmed. But they could not marry, as it turned out that he already had a wife and children in England. Was that not hard on this family? She had a little daughter, who lives with her. Such cases occur here with singular frequency in these evil times; is it the same with you over there too?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Do you have any other acquaintances, dear Clara, about whom you would like to hear some news? Just write, and I will be happy to tell you something about them. Aunt Ketelsen still has her sewing school, her son Fritz is getting quite big, twelve years old, and he goes to the rector's class to school. She celebrated her birthday on 2 May, the pupils had bought her a present, she scolded them for it, and then they stayed all day to play. My sister Louise has also been confirmed now, and has grown into a tall and slim young girl. So our dear parents have all their children finished with school now. They feel very happy about having all of us with or around them. And you can imagine how happy we are, to have our dear parents always close to us. It is a rare good fortune, that we are all so close together, and when we are all gathered at our dear parents' place, it makes quite a fair crowd, especially if the grandchildren are also present. Dear Johanna is also looking forward to her confinement in August, I am sure they will be exceedingly happy, when the good God gives them a child. Such a precious bond ties the hearts of a couple more closely together. Doris' little Albertine is a sweet little child, now nearly a year old, but she will not set her little feet to walking, and has no teeth yet. But that will come in time, the older she gets, the stronger she will get. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bertha Mein of Husum is about to get married, she is engaged to a young tinsmith from Husum by name of Zink, and her sister has come here, to temporarily fill in for her at Uncle Klander's. The latter is still sprightly and has not changed. Doris and Lene Dunken are also quite well, each of them has two children, Heinrich is still without children. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My dear Clara, I have chattered away about all sorts of things, I hope you will be interested in it all. This time I will not wait so long, till I write again; I will send you some lines during the course of the summer. But first I expect a letter from you all. We are looking forward to the arrival of your portraits, after all, we do not even know yet the dear husbands of you two, nor the little ones, and we will also see again your and dear Bertha's face.<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Sara: I don't recall, but could that perhaps be one of the photos we have of Clara, isn't there one with 2 little ones? If so, it could be included, if this letter is used for publication.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Any chance of perhaps dear Ferdinand being on it as well? O, how happy we were, when we saw once again his dear handwriting, and we thank the Lord with you, who brought him out of dangers<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had returned early that year from the North Australian exploring expedition under Augustus Gregory.</p>
               </note> back into your arms.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Farewell then, my dear, dear sister, give my sincere regards to your dear husband, and to precious Bertha and Ferdinand, also from my sweet darling husband, who is at school<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Was the husband a school teacher? — Johannes. — doesn't know either.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> at the moment. I am exceedingly happy to have him, and sincerely thank the dear Lord for him. Kiss your dear children from their Aunt Marie, and won't little Bertha be able to write to me herself soon?</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With true sisterly love,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your Marie.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
