<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tönning, 28th August, 1851. ¶ Dear Ferdinand, Bertha and Clara, ¶  ¶ You can imagine with what great joy we received your dear letter ¶  this morning, which we had awaited for so long and with so much...</title>
            <author>Magdalene Mertens</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1851/51-08-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M106.10, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>51.08.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Magdalene Mertens</author>
               <title>Tönning, 28th August, 1851. ¶ Dear Ferdinand, Bertha and Clara, ¶  ¶ You can imagine with what great joy we received your dear letter ¶  this morning, which we had awaited for so long and with so much...</title>
               <date when="1851-08-28">1851-08-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1851/51-08-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Tönning, 28th August, 1851. ¶ Dear Ferdinand, Bertha and Clara, ¶  ¶ You can imagine with what great joy we received your dear letter ¶  this morning, which we had awaited for so long and with so much...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">51.08.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Magdalene Mertens</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M106.10, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS is part of a family letter that also includes J. F. Mertens to M, September 1851 (in this edition as 51-09-00a), and E. Mertens to M, 3 September 1851.</p>
               </note>Tönning, den 28ten August 1851.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Theurer Ferdinand, Bertha und Clara!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit welcher grossen Freude wir diesen Morgen Euren lieben Brief entgegen nahmen, könnt Ihr Euch denken, da wir schon so lange mit wahrer Sehnsucht einen erwartet hatten. Gott gebe das Ihr Lieben diesen bei eben so guten Wohlsein wie wir Euren erhielten, empfangen möget, und wo möglich noch in diesem Jahre, das würde eine grosse Freude auch für Euch sein, und Ihr würdet mit Jubel diese Zeilen von uns entgegen nehmen, ich kann mir recht denken wie Euch unsre Briefe beglücken, und fühle die Wonne mit Euch, wenn Briefe aus der geliebten Heimat ankommen. Also wir müssen die Hoffnung die uns lange so froh und glücklich machte wieder aufgeben. Du lieber Ferdinand wirst jetzt nicht zu uns zurück kehren, ja wohl wird es zu dem Glücke Deiner lieben Schwestern notwendigsein das Du noch dort verweilst, die armen Mädchen habe ich herzlich und innig bedauert, und dennoch mich an der Aussicht delabt Dich hier zu umarmen, ich konnte sie nur dem Schutze unsers Allvaters empfehlen, der uns allenthalben zur Seite steht und mit seiner Vaterliebe uns trägt, Sollte es nicht in seinem Rathe beschlossen sein, das wir uns noch wiedersehen in diesem Leben? es ist doch gar zu schön sich dieses Bild auszumalen, und in diesen Gedanken zu schwärmen. Du meine süsse Bertha hast Dich also wie Dein Bruder schreibt, schriftlich mit uns unterhalten und wir können also lieben Zeilen von Dir entgegen sehn, wie habt Ihr Euch wohl unserwegen geängstigt in der langen Schrecklichen Kriegszeitund wie begierig seid Ihr wohl immer auf Nachrichten aus dieser Gegend gewesen, um so lieblicher mach Euch die jetzige Kunde von unser Aller Wohlsein berühren, und Ihr werdet die Freude mit uns Theilen das wir wieder Ruhe im Lande haben. Dein Brief meine geliebte Clara hat mich recht erfreut, Du bist ja dann auch ein recht gesetztes Mädchen geworden, leid thut es auch mir das Du bis jetzt noch nicht hast confirmirt werden können, doch wenn wir unsere Pflichten kennen und die Ueberzeugung haben das die Ausübung derselben zu unserm wahren Heile nothwendig ist, so müssen wir mit Vertrauen auf Gottes Vatergüte fortschreiten, er wird uns, and ganz gewiss auch Dich meine theure Clara Kraft geben ihm wohlgefällig zu wandeln, und Dein stilles Gelübte, als für tausend Zungen ausgesprochen aufnehmen. Ich musste Lächeln wie Du Marie Deine kleine Schwester Machtest, ach wie würdest Du Dich wundern wenn Du sie sähest, sie ist gross und stark wie Deine seeliche Schwester Iwane, doch ich denke mir Dich auch so lieb Clärchen. Christine Nielsen lässt Dich aufs herzlichste grüssen, sie ist auch hoch und schlank gewachsen und ein recht hübsches Mädchen geworden. Unser Heinrich und Louise die Ihr als kleine Kinder verlassen habt, sind auch schon hübsch heran gewachsen, lernen auch brav und machen uns Freude, Louise ist in diesen Monat 10 und Heinrich bald 13 Jahre. Zu Deine bald eintreffenden Geburtstag gratulire ich aufs innigste, und mach Dich aufmerksam, das an dem Tage auch hier für Dich liebes Kind die aufrichtigsten wärmsten Wünsche für Dein Wohl zum Allvater aufsteigen werden. Jetzt will ich Euch, da die andern noch schreiben wollen, dem Schutze des Höchsten empfehlen, und Euch bitten unsrer oft in Liebe zu gedenken und recht bald wenn es möglich ist wieder etwas von Euch høoren zu lassen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eure Euch innig liebende Tante</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Magdalene Mertens.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Tönning, 28th August, 1851.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Ferdinand, Bertha and Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You can imagine with what great joy we received your dear letter<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> this morning, which we had awaited for so long and with so much longing. May God grant that you, my dear ones, will receive our letter in just as good health as we received yours, and if possible still this year. That would be a great joy for you, too, and you would receive these lines with much rejoicing. I can well imagine how happy our letters make you, and feel the joy with you when letters from the beloved homeland arrive. So we have to relinquish the hope which for long has made us joyful and happy. You, dear Ferdinand, will not return to us. It will probably be necessary for the happiness of your beloved sisters to remain there longer. I felt sorry for the poor girls, and yet comforted myself with the expectation to embrace you again here. I could only commend them to the protection of our Father, who will always support us and carry us with his fatherly love. Should it not be in his Divine Providence that we see each other again in this life? — it is too lovely to paint this picture in one's imagination and lose oneself in it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So you, my sweet Bertha, have had a little conversation with us in writing, as Ferdinand writes, and that means we can look forward to some dear lines from you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How you must have worried about us in the long and terrible time of war!<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Danish-German war.</p>
               </note> And how eager you must have been for news from this area, so that the news now that we are all well must bring you all the more relief, and you will share our joy with us that we have once more calm and quiet in the country. Your letter, my beloved Clara, pleased me greatly. You have grown into a quite mature girl now. I am only sorry that you could not be confirmed as yet. But if we know our duties and have the conviction that carrying them out is necessary for our true salvation, we must walk on with confidence in God's fatherly care, and he will give us — and most assuredly you, too, my dear Clara — the strength to live a life pleasing to him. He will accept your silent vow as if it had been spoken with a thousand tongues. How I had to smile, when you made Marie your little sister. How surprised you would be, if you could see her now. She is big and strong like your late sister Iwanne, but I imagine so will you be, dear little Clara.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Christine Nielsen sends sincerest greetings to you; she, too, has grown tall and slim and has turned into a very pretty girl. Our Heinrich and Louise, whom you left as little children, have also grown a good bit, are good pupils and bring us much happiness. Louise will be 10 this month and Heinrich is nearly 13. My most sincere congratulations for your birthday,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clara's 18th birthday on 14 October.</p>
               </note> which is coming up soon. I want you to know that on that day here, too, our sincerest and warmest wishes for your happiness will rise up to God our Father.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As the others want to write something as well I will now commend you to the protection of the Most High, and ask you to remember us often with love. Please let us hear from you again soon, if possible.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With deep love from your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Aunt Magdalene Mertens.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
