<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Woodhall nr Perth ¶ Tas. ¶ Septr 6th 1849. ¶ Dear Sir, ¶  ¶ I have been anxiously waiting for a letter from you in acknowledgement of two packages of specimens which I sent you &amp; therefore fear that f...</title>
            <author>Charles Stuart</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1840-9/1845-9/49-09-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M36, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>49.09.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles Stuart</author>
               <title>Woodhall nr Perth ¶ Tas. ¶ Septr 6th 1849. ¶ Dear Sir, ¶  ¶ I have been anxiously waiting for a letter from you in acknowledgement of two packages of specimens which I sent you &amp; therefore fear that f...</title>
               <date when="1849-09-06">1849-09-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1840-9/1845-9/49-09-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plantnames</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Woodhall nr Perth ¶ Tas. ¶ Septr 6th 1849. ¶ Dear Sir, ¶  ¶ I have been anxiously waiting for a letter from you in acknowledgement of two packages of specimens which I sent you &amp; therefore fear that f...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">49.09.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Charles Stuart</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RB MSS M36, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; "/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS envelope front: 'Dr F Müller | Care of Messrs Büttner &amp; Heüzenroeder | Chemists &amp; Druggists | Rundle Street | Adelaide | South Australia'. Front post-marked Launceston, 8 September 1849, and GPO South Australia, 15 October 1849.</p>
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a published precis of this letter see Daley (1935),<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>p. 133.</p>
               </note>Woodhall nr Perth<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Tas.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Septr 6th 1849.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have been anxiously waiting for a letter from you in acknowledgement of two packages of specimens which I sent you &amp; therefore fear that from the long time which has passed that you could not have received them, in order to make sure that they had left here safe (as I was not in Launceston at the time the vessells sailed) I went some time since to ascertain particulars respecting them &amp; find that the first box left Launceston in the "Shamrock" &amp; arrived at Port Adelaide on the 16th Aprill &amp; was left at Messrs Bennetts there who are agents for most of the vessils from hence, — the second Box left in the Tamar on the 2nd of May but I cannot learn the date of her arrival in your Colony — if therefore you have not received them I should advise your application to Messrs Bennetts without delay as they may become damaged — I should indeed feel much disappointment should any accident happen so that after all my trouble, there were in the two boxes about 600 Gen. &amp; sp. together with some musci &amp;c in addition — in fact all my summers collecting — do write me word on receipt of this respecting them</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have to acknowledge the reciept of a letter from you dated April 15th/49,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>but at which time you of course could not know about them as the first lot arrived at P. Adelaide on the day after — I did not answer this letter as I felt sure that you had received my letters which I wrote with the same vessels the boxes went by — respecting Mr Giles I beg you will not give yourself any trouble respecting him in the settling of my account as it is evident that he wishes to impose on me<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For some background to the financial dispute with Giles, who has not been identified, see C. Stuart to M, 8 June 1849, and other letters cited in n. 6<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>therein.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>, I would not give him a shilling more his object is to get my books which he thinks I will make a sacrifice for by paying him his unjust demand but let him keep them I am sorry to lose them but I will not be imposed upon by him, but his character is well known at Adelaide — he has treated me infamously, but I do not want any more to do with him, he had the empudence to write to me for about 20£ worth of Trees and plants a short time ago, without saying a word about my box which was an<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>extent of impudence I was not prepared for even in him, I wrote to him &amp; told him so — so that we will say no more about him, you say in your last letter that you intended to procure the herbarium at Mr Stephens I should be very glad of it,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For previous correspondence related to the collection held by Stephens, who has not been identified, see C. Stuart to M, 8 June 1849, and letters cited in n. 8 therein.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to see if I could get some of the seeds to grow &amp; if after paying any expense you would forward it &amp; the balance of the cash in your hands should be much obliged, unless indeed the specimens which I sent have not come to hand, in which case pray keep it as part payment of your favor to me when I left Adelaide which kindness believe me I do not forget altho our correspondence has been unfortunate &amp; may give you reason to think that I have not acted honorable, but trust me I have used my best endeavours to be as good as my word &amp; will continue to do so, I have got a lot of Musci Lichenes Fungi &amp;c ready for you but really do not like to send them together with some seeds from S. Africa &amp;c untill I hear from you — it is also my intention in the next month to take a journey to the Eastern part of V D Land where there are many plants not well known — I have to make much extra work in order to get time to go out as I have so much to attend to in my situation, there is a gentleman here (<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">whose address is W. Archer Esqr, Cheshunt near Deloraine</hi>
               </seg>)<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">V D Land</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>— with whom you would be much pleased to correspond who has commenced the pursuit of Botany to who I made use of your name &amp; gave him your address, &amp; who said he should much like to correspond with you, which I think would be a mutual benifit, as he has the means to carry out his views he lives about 50 miles from me &amp; has I expect written to you — I am sorry to hear by your last that your expedition to Rivoli bay was not very successful<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The trip was evidently at the instigation of Samuel Davenport, who had an extensive sheep run in the area. In<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the winter and spring of 1846 his<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>flock suffered catastrophic losses, attributed to the sheep eating a poisonous plant of some kind. Davenport asked M to investigate.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(It was not until<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the mid 1930s<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'coast disease' was discovered to be<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>caused by<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>a deficiency of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the trace elements<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>cobalt and copper (Marston et al. (1938)).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I must beg you not to suppose that I am in any hurry for the names of plants in my collection take your own time &amp; I shall feel gratified by the receipt of them when you are at leisure, — you may remember a plant which I found on the Murray Rivers growing sometimes in the water, which I then thought was an Aenothera, I have been since thinking it may be a Jussiaea, what think you? — I had commenced a new series of numbers with the last two lots of specimens sent in order to avoid confusion with those lost by the Henry &amp; which I have for the most part now replaced in what I have by me in Cryptogamia I mentioned in my last a request of you to send me if you could procure it a few seeds of the Donia formosa 2 or 3 in a letter would come safely we had a plant here but lost it — I have lately received some seeds from<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Swan River W. Australia but without names I have sown them and many are coming up — they are mostly in the order &amp; — hoping to hear from you on the first opportunity for which I wait with anxiety</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I am dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Yours sincerely</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Charles Stuart</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Aenothera</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Jussiaea<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Donia formosa</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Proteaceae</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Isopogon</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Banksia</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Dryandra</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Hakea</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
