<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tönning, 9 April 1849. ¶ Dear Ferdinand, dear Bertha and Clara, ¶  ¶ It is already a long time that we have not heard from each other. But with such a distance that is unavoidable. Just over a week ag...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand Mertens</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1840-9/1845-9/49-04-09-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M99.6, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>49.04.09</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand Mertens</author>
               <title>Tönning, 9 April 1849. ¶ Dear Ferdinand, dear Bertha and Clara, ¶  ¶ It is already a long time that we have not heard from each other. But with such a distance that is unavoidable. Just over a week ag...</title>
               <date when="1849-04-09">1849-04-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1840-9/1845-9/49-04-09-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Tönning, 9 April 1849. ¶ Dear Ferdinand, dear Bertha and Clara, ¶  ¶ It is already a long time that we have not heard from each other. But with such a distance that is unavoidable. Just over a week ag...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">49.04.09</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Ferdinand Mertens</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M99.6, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter is on the first page of a single folded sheet that also includes a letter from Marie Mertens to Clara Müller [April 1849] and, on the final page, J. F. Mertens to M, August 1849.</p>
               </note>Tönning, den 9. April 1849.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Ferdinand, liebe Bertha, u. Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist ziemlich lange schon, dass wir nichts von einander gehört haben. Das ist indes bei dieser Entfernung ja nicht anders möglich. Vor reichlich 8 Tagen bin ich wieder, durch den Krieg aus Rendsburg vertrieben, hier angelangt, u. säume daher auch nicht, Euch einige Zeilen aus der Heimath zukommen zu lassen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es sieht hier fast noch ebenso bunt aus, wie vor einem Jahre. Von dem bis zum 28. März abgeschlossenen Waffenstillstande wisst Ihr bereits. Derselbe wurde bis zum 3. Apr. verlängert. Die Friedensunterhandlungen, welche zu keinem günstigen Resultate geführt haben, wurden darauf abgebrochen, u. nachdem der Waffenstillstand von Dänemark an Preussen gekündigt war, ist jetzt wieder der Krieg über unser Land hereingebrochen. Aber anders sieht es jetzt bei uns aus, als vor einem Jahre. Damals standen eben am 9. Apr. ein paar ungeregelte Freischärlerhaufen, sowie vielleicht 1000-2000 Mann Linientruppen ohne Artillerie als Verfechter unserer guten Sache dem wohlorganisirten Heere bei Bau gegenüber u. wurde theils gefangen genommen, theils zurückgedrängt; jetzt dagegen haben wir ein kleines, meistens gut eingerichtetes Heer von circa 24.000 Soldaten, welches bereit ist, sich augenblicklich mit der um die Hälfte grössern dänischen Heeresmacht auf dem Festlande für Freiheit und Vaterland zu schlagen. So sind wir denn wohlgerüstet u. trotzen der Wuth der Dänen umso mehr, da unsere deutschen Brüder unaufhörlich zu unserer Hülfe herbeieilen. Während der letzten 8 Tage meines Aufenthaltes in Rendsburg kamen Militärzüge aus Sachsen-Altenburg, Sachsen, Meiningen, Braunschweig, Hannover, Baiern, Nassau, Hessen, etc. an, so dass wir jetzt auch wohl schon 30.000 deutsche Krieger im Lande haben. Unser Militär hat jedoch immer die Vorhut. Am 3. d. M. begannen dann also die Feindseligkeiten von dänischer Seite, die griffen von Alsen kommend, auf mehreren Stellen zugleich unsere Vorposten an. Diese zogen sich ihrer Ordre gemäss bis Gravenstein zurück. Zugleich besetzten die Dänen von Norden aus Hadersleben und drangen bis Apenrade vor. Hierbei sind dann einige blutige Gefechte vorgefallen. Näheres vom Norden wissen wir noch nicht. Gewiss werden sich die Dänen entweder von selbst zurückziehen, oder von den Unsrigen zurückgetrieben sein. Ich glaube nicht, dass die Dänen sich in eine Feldschlacht einlassen. Immer halten sie sich am Wasser, um bei etwaigen Niederlagen gleich auf ihre Schiffe retiviren zu können, weshalb es auch der Plan unserer Feldherrn stets ist, sie vom Wasser weg zu locken. Ganz besonders freudig bewegt ist aber das Herz jedes deutschen Schleswig-Holsteiners durch einen glänzenden Sieg, welchen wir am Gründonnerstag bei Eckernförde errungen haben. Bei Eckernförde, wie auch bei allen andern Städten der Ostküste sind feste Batterien zum Schutz gegen das Landen der Dänen angelegt. Da kamen nun am Donnerstag Morgen das einzige armirte grosse dänische Linienschiff Christian VIII u. die letzte dänische Kriegsfrigatte Gesion, ferner 2 Kriegs-Dampfschiffe vor Eckernförde an. Sie legten sich gravitätisch unsern Batterien nahe gegenüber u. antworteten denselben durch ein mörderisches Feuer. Mitttlerweile wurde das Linienschiff durch den starken Ostwind auf den Strand getrieben u. wurde von unsern Kugeln arg mitgenommen. Dem Gesion wurde bald das Feuerrohr abgeschossen. Die Dampfschiffe wurden herbeibeordert; allein das eine derselben musste sich sogleich mit zerschossenem Rad langsam wegschleppen, u. das andere wagte sich nicht heran. Nach einer 5-stündigen hitzigen Kanonade schickte der Däne einen Parlamentär ans Land, welcher freien Abzug verlangte, widrigenfalls sie die Stadt bombadiren würden. Er erhielt vom Herzog von Sachsen-Gotha die Antwort, dass er thun könne, was er nicht lassen wolle, wir aber keinen freien Abzug bewilligen würden. Bald ertönte darauf der Donner der Kanonen heftiger, als zuvor. Grässlich wurden die dänischen Schiffe zugerichtet. Sie wurden mit glühenden Kugeln beschossen u. geriethen mehrmals in Brand. Die in die Stadt geworfenen Kugeln thaten wenig Schaden. Das Gefecht war so heiss, dass das Linienschiff allein 68 glatte Lagen von 42 Schüssen gegeben hat, u. unsere Geschosse so heiss wurden, dass eine halbe Nassauische Feldbatterie sie ablösen musste. Gegen Abend gerieth das Linienschiff in Brand, u. beide grossen schönen Schiffe (die letzten der dänischen Flotte) mussten die Flagge streichen. Die Mannschaft ergab sich. Bald darauf erreichte das Feuer auf dem Linienschiff die Pulverkammer, u. dasselbe flog in die Luft. Gewiss ein erhabenes Schauspiel, doch nicht minder schrecklich, da sich noch fast 300 Menschen darauf befanden! Der Strand u. der Meerbusen bei Eckernförde sind wohl 1/4 Meile im Umkreis mit Splittern u. Leichen besät. Welche Aufregung mag dieser Schlag in Copenhagen hervorrufen! Wenn sich die Dänen nur nicht auf eine heimtückische Weise rächen. Wir erhielten ungefähr 900 Gefangene u. erbeuteten die schönste dänische Frigatte Gesion. Beim ganzen Gefechte haben wir nur ein paar Leute verloren. Wie Du ja schon weisst, lieber Ferd., stehen Dav. Samman u. Georg beim 2ten Jägercorps. Ihre Briefe werden jetzt sehr rar, u. doch sind wir so gespannt auf Nachricht, indem ihr Leben jede Minute auf dem Spiele steht. Es sind schon mehrere Tönninger im Gefecht gewesen. Das 2te Jägercorps steht in der Gegend von Hadersleben u. wird wahrscheinlich in den ersten Tagen nach Jütland aufbrechen. — Mit dem einigen Deutschland sieht es noch bunt aus. In der letzten Zeit wurde durch Stimmenmehrheit von der Nationalversammlung in Frankfurt beschlossen, den König von Preussen jetzt zur Zeit der Noth zum erblichen Kaiser der Deutschen zu wählen. Es wurde demzufolge eine Deputation nach Berlin gesandt, um ihm die Kaiserkrone anzutragen. Dieselbe zog dann unter grossem Jubel dahin, wurde indes nur ziemlich lau aufgenommen. Ob er jetzt Kaiser wird, ist noch nicht entschieden. Österreich reisst sich, wenn Preussen an die Spitze kommt, sogleich los von Deutschland u. droht im Bunde mit Russland mit Krieg. Auch Baiern u. a. freuen sich wohl nicht über diese Wahl. Wie soll das werden! — In Rendsburg ist jetzt Alles in grosser Bewegung. Die Festung ist vollständig armirt u. befestigt. Die Sondergaards traf diesen Winter der Schlag, dass der Vater (früher Kammerrath) ihnen durch den Tod entrissen wurde. Der eine Sohn ist Lieutenant auf einem Kanonenboot der jungen deutschen Marine geworden. Ich wollte Euch dieses nur mittheilen, da ich weiss, dass Ihr gewiss ebenso grossen Antheil an dem Schicksal dieser Familie nehmt, wie dieselbe an dem eurigen. Von Sondergaards, sowie von Mainzhusens soll ich viele freundliche Grüsse bestellen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Indem ich noch schliesslich Dir, liebe Bertha, zu Deiner Verbindung von Herzen Glück wünsche, zeichne ich mich</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Euer Euch nie vergessender Freund u. Vetter</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand Mertens.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Tönning, 9 April 1849.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Ferdinand, dear Bertha and Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is already a long time that we have not heard from each other. But with such a distance that is unavoidable. Just over a week ago I returned here, driven out of Rendsburg by the war.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first Schleswig-Holstein War between Germany and Denmark.</p>
               </note> So I will not delay to send you a few lines from your homeland. Here everything still is in the same mess as a year ago. You already know of the armistice, agreed to on 28 March. That was extended to 3 April. After that the peace negotiations, which did not lead to a favourable outcome, were broken off, and after Denmark had revoked the armistice with Prussia, war has once more broken out over our land. But the situation looks different for us now from a year ago. On the 9 April then, a few disorganised volunteer groups and perhaps about 1000-2000 regular troops without artillery were facing a well-organised army near Bau as champions of our good cause, and were partly taken prisoner and partly driven back. Now, however, we have a small, mostly well equipped army of approximately 24,000 soldiers, which is prepared to fight at a moment's notice for freedom and fatherland against the might of the Danish army, about half as large again as ours. Thus we are well prepared, and defy the fury of the Danes, all the more, since our German brethren are constantly hurrying to our aid. During my last week in Rendsburg military trains were arriving from Saxony-Altenburg, Saxony, Meiningen, Brunswick, Hanover, Bavaria, Nassau, Hessen, etc., so that by now we have probably already about 30,000 German soldiers in the land. But our military are always in the vanguard. On the 3rd of the month hostilities were commenced by the Danish side. Coming from Alsen they attacked our advance posts in several places at once. These withdrew to Gravenstein in accordance with their orders. At the same time the Danes, coming from the north, occupied Hadersleben and advanced as far as Apenrade. During all this a few bloody skirmishes took place. We have no further news from up north. Surely the Danes will either withdraw of their own accord, or be driven back by our side. I do not believe that the Danes will engage in a full scale field battle. They always stay close to the water, so that in case of defeat they can immediately retreat to their ships. Therefore the plan of our generals is to always try and lure them away from the water. But the heart of every German Schleswig-Holsteiner beat faster with joy over a glorious victory, which we won near Eckernförde on Maundy Thursday.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">5 April 1849.</p>
               </note> Near Eckernförde, as in all the other towns on the eastern coast, fortified batteries are set up as protection against a Danish landing. On Thursday morning the only armed large Danish battleship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Christian VIII</seg> and the last Danish war frigate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gesion</seg>, together with two steam-warships arrived before Eckernförde. They solemnly anchored closely opposite our batteries and answered them with a murderous fire. Meanwhile the battleship was driven on to the beach by a strong easterly wind and was harshly dealt with by our cannon balls. The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gesion</seg> soon had its funnel shot off. The steamships were ordered forward, however one of them immediately had to limp off slowly with a shot-up wheel, and the other did not dare to come closer. After a five-hour long heated cannonade the Danes sent a negotiator on land, who demanded free retreat, otherwise the town would be bombarded. But he received the reply from the Duke of Saxe-Gotha, that he could do what he liked, but we would not grant a free retreat. Soon afterwards the thunder of the cannons sounded more heavily than before. The Danish ships were horribly damaged. They were shot at with red hot cannon balls and caught fire several times. The cannon balls directed into the town did little damage. The battle was so fierce, that the battleship alone fired 68 broadsides of 42 shots, and our guns got so hot, that a Nassau field battery had to relieve them. Towards evening the battleship caught fire, and both great beautiful ships (the last of the Danish fleet) had to strike their flag. The crew surrendered. Soon afterwards the fire on the battleship reached the powder magazine and it blew up. Surely a great spectacle, but nonetheless terrible, as almost 300 men were still on board! The beach and the bay near Eckernförde were strewn for about a quarter of a mile around with splinters and corpses. What agitation this blow must cause in Copenhagen! If only the Danes do not take revenge in some treacherous way. We took about 900 prisoners and captured the most beautiful of the Danish frigates, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gesion</seg>. During the whole battle we only lost a few men.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As you already know, dear Ferdinand, Dav. Samman and Georg<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Georg Mertens.</p>
               </note> are with the 2nd Fusilier Corps. Their letters are becoming very rare now, yet we are so anxious for news from them, as their lives are on the line at every minute. Several Tönningers have already been in battles. The 2nd Fusilier Corps is stationed in the vicinity of Hadersleben and will probably set out for Jutland any day now.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As far as a united Germany is concerned, everything is still very confused. Recently the National Assembly in Frankfurt decided by a majority of votes to elect the King of Prussia as hereditary Emperor of the Germans in this time of affliction. In consequence a deputation was sent to Berlin to offer him the imperial crown. They went there under great jubilation, but received only a rather lukewarm reception. It has not yet been decided, whether he will become Emperor now. If Prussia gains the lead, Austria will immediately separate from Germany, and threatens war in alliance with Russia. Bavaria among others is not very happy with this choice either. What is to happen?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Rendsburg everything is in great turmoil. The fortress is completely armed and fortified. The Sondergaards received the blow, that their father (formerly Counsellor of the Exchequer) was torn from them by death. The one son has become Lieutenant on a cannon boat of the young German Navy. I only wanted to tell you this, as I am sure you are just as interested in the fate of this family as they are in yours. I am to convey many kind regards from the Sondergaards and from the Mainzhusens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finally I want to wish you with all my heart, dear Bertha, the best of luck for your union.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha was engaged to be married to Carl Schedlich but subsequently broke off her engagement, apparently because of his poor financial prospects; see D4302(L) Memoirs of Carl Gustav Schedlich, Mortlock Library, Adelaide.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your friend and cousin, who will never forget you,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand Mertens.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
