<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 3 March 1868. ¶  ¶ The last mail brought once more a wonderful letter from you, ¶  illustrious friend. O! how delighted I was to be able to gaze into your face, when I rece...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-03-03-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>68.03.03</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 3 March 1868. ¶  ¶ The last mail brought once more a wonderful letter from you, ¶  illustrious friend. O! how delighted I was to be able to gaze into your face, when I rece...</title>
               <date when="1868-03-03">1868-03-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-03-03-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>SaxonoGothaea conspicua</term>
               <term>Abies albertiana</term>
               <term>Gleditschia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/941a4b69-6953-4fa9-9378-812700eb6531">Marianthus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/7cc7f482-9966-4860-a834-2608a8949a0b">Myrtaceae</term>
               <term>Galatea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 3 March 1868. ¶  ¶ The last mail brought once more a wonderful letter from you, ¶  illustrious friend. O! how delighted I was to be able to gaze into your face, when I rece...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">68.03.03</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Martius: 'pr. 21/4 | B. 24 May' [received 21 April 1868; answered 24 May 1868]. Martius's letter not found.</p>
               </note>Melbourne im bot. Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 3 März 1968.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die letzte Post brachte mir abermals einen herrlichen Brief von Ihnen, erhabener Freund, u o! wie erfreuete es mich, Ihnen ins Antlitz schauen zu können, wie ich Ihr edles Bild empfing. Zwar hängt Ihr schönes grosses Portrait in meinem Studienzimmer und die geistreich-gedankenvollen Züge mahnen mich, nicht lässig zu werden auf der Bahn des Forschens in der grossen Natur, in welcher der ewig göttliche Ausdruck verliehen. Nun aber habe ich Sie freundlich herblickend aus erst jüngsten vergangenen Tagen! Das ist doch so schön.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein heilger Schauer durchrieselt den Sterblichen beim Hinblick auf höhere Gewalten, die uns vorempfinden lassen das einstige Freisein des Geistes von irdischen Hüllen! Ja, edler Mann, an dem Tage, an welchem Sie den fernen Fremdling werth hielten Ihrer geistigen Erfassung, gedachte ich auch Ihrer, wie ich die Granitgipfel des malerisch-wilden Porongorup erstieg und inmitten einer unbeschreiblich schönen Pflanzen[mengung] nordwärts auf die stolzen aufgethürmten Felsmassen des hohen Stirlingsgebirges hinblickte und südwärts hinschauend auf die liebliche Bai des Königs-Georgs Sund und weiterhin auf den südlichen Ocean. Der Tag war so schön, die Lüfte wehten so rein, das bunte Pflanzengedränge war so ergötzend, der Himmel so klar und dem Geiste wars als sei er frei von irdischer Hülle. Da gedachte ich auch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihrer</hi>
               </seg>, edler Mann, u im Geiste erregte sich ein unnennbarer Wunsch, dass Sie neben mir sein u mich über das Wunderwirken der Schöpfung belehren möchten. Auch Schiller empfand in diesem freien Geistesschwung, wie er die denkwürdigsten seiner Worte schrieb, die ihn ein höheres geistiges Leben schon hier ahnen liessen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als am Weihnachtsabend, dem Abend welcher dem Teutonier so erhebend über alles feierlich ist, als an diesem Abend ich vereinsamt dasass unter einem <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name> Baum, den eine früh dahin geschiedene herrliche Schwester aus Samen erzog und nach ihrem Tode an mich übersenden liess, da fragte ich nicht ohne Thränen, ob die, welche wir hier so tief geliebt und die vor uns in die Ewigkeit schieden auch unserer liebevoll gedächte[n] in anderen Welten u auf unsere irdische Laufbahn wohl einen höheren leitenden Einfluss ausübten. Ich blickte auf den besternten Himmel, auf die goldnen Lichter vom südlichen Kreuz, u fühlte es müsse so sein! — Es war an jenem Abend, wie mich der edle Herrscher Würtembergs<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Württembergs?</p>
               </note> unter die Ritter seiner königl Krone aufnahm u. mich adelte! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der armen Gemahlin des Dr. Bayer entbot ich Ihren theilnehmenden Gruss, wie Sie ihn so fühlend in dem jüngst angelangten Schreiben ausdrückten. Mag die Arme in der Erziehung ihrer Kinder Trost u. Geistesfrieden suchen. — Sie möchten mir so gütig ein häusliches Glück heraufbeschwören, nach dem ich in früheren Jahren mich wohl sehnte, und welches, selbst nachdem ich den Zenith des Lebens überschritten, noch aus jugendlicher <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">deutscher</hi>
               </seg> Grazie, die über Alles steht, mir erblühen möchte. Indessen inmitten des Gewoges eines regen Lebens in einer schnell schaffenden jungen Colonie, wo eine Arbeit u Obliegenheit fast die andere überstürzt, flossen die Jahre der Jugend dahin wie im Traum, u selbst jetzt weiss ich nicht einmal, ob ich nicht in wenigen Monaten als Befehlshaber die Aufsuchungs Expedition zu leiten habe, welche auf Leichhardts Geschick Licht werfen und den grossen Westen des Austral-Continentes aufschliessen soll. Ich bin wohl der Einzige, der das Glück dieses Feldzugs für Wissen u Barmherzigkleit zu wenden vermag, u dann liegt noch darin für mich ein hoher Reiz, dass ich die Verbreitungsgrade der Vegetation von West nach Ost u von Süd nach Nord näher zu bestimmen vermöchte u zum weitern Schluss längerer Arbeiten die geologischen Verhältnisse mit den entsprechenden Pflanzen Formen verknüpfen könnte. Entweder ich müsste diesen Plan einer 2jährigen Forschungsreise, der indessen einstweilen Geheimniss bleiben muss, aufgeben oder ich müsste ein armes aufopferndes Wesen sich abhärmend zurücklasssen um vielleicht auf Immer von ihr zu scheiden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Überaus gern entspreche ich Ihrem Wunsche, in einer Reihe Briefen die auffallendsten Bilder unserer Natur zu entfalten. Dafür habe ich ja in Humboldts Ansichten der Natur und in Ihren "Reisen" vortreffliche Vorbilder. Indessen Sie möchten mir wohl freundlich etwas Frist gönnen, denn ich habe Bentham das letzte Material für den 4ten Band der Flora Australiens zu liefern und demnächst den 6ten Band der Fragmenta zu schliessen, für solche Schilderungen habe ich manches Material in meinen unveröffentlichten Reisenotizen. Mit dem Schiffe "Great Britain" sende ich innerhalb der nächsten Tage eine Sendung, welcher dann auch die Palmen Australiens, wenige wie es sind, und einige unserer Alpenpflanzen beigegeben werden sollen. Auch meine einfache Photographie folgt demnächst und eine recht gute neue Generalkarte Australiens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Prinz Alfred während seines Besuchs liess sich herab eine Saxono-Gothaea conspicua u Abies Albertiana in meinem Garten zu pflanzen. Dies erinnert mich daran dass das Pflanzen Genus <name key="Galatea">Galatea</name>, das seiner Fregatte gleichnamig ist, von Herbert unrichtig geschrieben wurde, da es der Nereide <seg>γαλατεια</seg> gewidmet ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr inhaltsvoller Brief vom 18 Aug., den ich nach meiner Rückkehr aus Westaustralien zu empfangen das Glück hatte, ist ein Document von viel zu hoher Wichtigkeit, um im Strudel der auf mich damals hereinbrechenden Amtsarbeiten von mir, selbst wenn ichs vermöchte, so besprochen zu werden, als es die Tiefe der grossen Wahrheiten erfordert. Inmitten des Scepticismus der Jetztzeit ist es beruhigend für das Gemüth, wenn auf dem Todtenbette Goodsir erklärt, dass derjenige kein wahrer Anatom sei, der an die Möglichkeit von organischen Verwandlungen denke. An Pfeiler solcher Grösse mag der Schwankende sich anklammern. Und dass Sie, der Hervorragende unter den Naturweisen, auch höhern Idealen anhängen, und ein unabhängiges geistiges Leben, das nicht nach Gesetzen menschlichen Wissen erforscht werden kann, anerkennen, hat für mich etwas stärkend-Ermuthigendes. Bis jetzt ist noch nichts in dem Erforschungsprojekte der Osterinseln gethan. Indessen schreibe ich heute umständlich an Sir Henry Barkly u gebe Seiner Excellenz alle die Punkte an, auf welche Sie vorzugsweise wünschen, dass Rücksicht genommen werde</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie lenken meine Aufmerksamkeit auf gewisse Verhältnisse der trockenfrüchtigen Myrtaceen. Sind nicht solche auch im Wiener Becken im Tertiar Sediment begraben gefunden? Dann bin ich überzeugt, dass in manchen Ländern, wie in Neu Zealand, wir zwei oder mehr Perioden der Schöpfungsentwicklung annehmen müssen, der einen gehören hauptsächlich die Pflanzen der Alpenregionen dort an, die vielfach mit denen Australiens übereinstimmen, während die Baumvegetation des Flachlands die Trümmer zu sein scheinen des Pflanzenlebens eines grossen Continents, Trümmer welche nur in Neuseeland übrig blieben u. anderswo versunken im Ocean einst wieder bei vulkanischen Erhebungen als fossile Gebilde zu Tage gefördert werden mögen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich kann nicht ohne Rührung meinen Dank ausdrücken, dass Sie Ihr edles Augenlicht schwächen um an den jüngern Entferntstehenden zu schreiben u in den Dank muss ich den an Ihre vortreffliche Tochter einschliessen, die Ihnen so freundlich sorgsam u kenntnissreich zur Seite steht. Gott erhalte Sie, Edler, das ist der innige Wunsch </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihres</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit dem edlen Grafen Castelnau stehe ich in beständigem Verkehr. Er hat eben eine lange Reihe von neuen theils von mir gelieferten Käfern beschrieben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zwar habe ich manche Ihrer Denkreden, aber nicht alle. Sie sind so wundersam dichterisch u ergreifend, dass ich das gesammelte Ganze überaus schätzen würde. Dr Sonder vermittelt stets am Besten die Versendung.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The following paragraph is on a separate sheet but the reference to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Galatea">Galatea</name>
                     </seg> suggests that it belongs to this letter.</p>
               </note>Als Wink möchte es Prof Wittstein für sein Wörterbuch neben dem passus über <name key="Galatea">Galatea</name> willkommen sein zu wissen, dass Herr Baron v. Huegel, wie er mich brieflich belehrt das Genus <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name> der Fürstin Maria Melanie v. Metternich widmete.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">3 March 1868.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last mail brought once more a wonderful letter from you,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> illustrious friend. O! how delighted I was to be able to gaze into your face, when I received your noble picture.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Picture not found.</p>
               </note> Indeed, your beautiful large portrait hangs in my study, and your intelligent thoughtful features exhort me, not to become idle on the path to investigate nature, which bears the eternal divine imprint. But now I also have you from only just recent times, benignly looking down on me. That is so lovely.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A shiver of sacred awe pervades the mortal at the sight of higher powers, giving us an anticipation of the freedom of the spirit from earthly bonds! Yes, noble Sir, on the day you considered the distant stranger worthy of your intellectual acceptance I, too, was thinking of you as I climbed the granite summits of the wild, picturesque Porongorup Ranges,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Visited by M during his holiday voyage to WA in October 1867.</p>
               </note> and in the midst of an indescribably beautiful variety of plants looked to the north to the proudly towering rock formations of the lofty Stirling Ranges, and gazed south on the lovely bay of the King George Sound and further out to the southern ocean. The day was so beautiful, the air so pure, the colourful display of massed plants so delightful, the sky so clear, and the spirit felt as if it had been freed from its earthly frame. And there I also thought of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>, noble Sir, and an inexpressible desire stirred in my soul for you to be beside me to instruct me on the wondrous workings of creation. Schiller, too, felt this free soaring of the spirit, when he wrote his most memorable words, that gave him already here a presentiment of a higher spiritual life.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When on Christmas Eve, the evening that is so uplifting and solemn more than any other to a German, when on this evening I sat, lonely, under a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>
               </seg> tree, which a wonderful, early departed sister<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha Doughty née Müller died on 7 September 1861.</p>
               </note> raised from seed and had sent to me after her death, I asked not without tears, whether those we have loved so deeply and who have passed into eternity before us also remember us lovingly in other worlds and exercise a guiding influence over the course of our earthly sojourn. I looked up at the starry sky, at the golden lights of the Southern Cross, and felt it had to be thus! It was on that evening, that the noble Sovereign of Württemberg elevated me as one of the Knights of his Royal Crown, and raised me to nobility!<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">20 December 1867, not Christmas Eve; see A. von Egloffstein to M, 20 December 1867.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I passed on your condolences to the poor widow of Dr Bayer, as you expressed them with so much sympathy in your recently arrived letter.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> May the poor lady find consolation and peace of mind in the raising of her children. — You are trying so kindly to conjure up domestic bliss for me, for which I longed in younger years, it is true, and which might yet flourish for me even now that I am past the zenith of my life, from youthful <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">German</hi>
               </seg> grace that surpasses everything.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M offers no clue as to whom he had in mind. His brief engagement to Rebecca Nordt was long over by this time.</p>
               </note> However, in the midst of the surge of a busy life in a fast growing young colony, where one labour and responsibility almost precipitates another, the years of my youth were swept away like a dream, and even now I do not yet know, if in a few months I may not have to lead as commander the search expedition, that is to throw light on Leichhardt's fate and open up the great West of the Australian continent.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to F. Barlee, 28 February 1869 and M to A. Petermann, 29 March 1868 (in this edition as 68-03-29a).</p>
               </note> I am probably the only one, who can still change the fortunes of this campaign for knowledge and mercy, and then there is for me the great added incentive, that I should be able to determine more accurately the distribution of the vegetation from West to East and from South to North, and be able to tie in with it the geological formations with their respective plant forms for further conclusions in longer works. I would either have to give up this plan of a 2-year exploration expedition which, however, must remain a secret for the present, or leave behind a poor self-sacrificing being to pine away, and perhaps part from her for ever.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am extremely pleased to comply with your wish and display before you in a number of letters the most conspicuous features of our environment. For that I have excellent examples in Humboldt's<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Humboldt (1845-62).</p>
               </note> views of nature and in your <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Travels</hi>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">C. Martius (1821-31).</p>
               </note> However, you might be so kind to grant me a little time, because I have to consign the last of the material for the 4th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg> to Bentham, and shortly to conclude the 6th volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>. I have much in my unpublished travel diaries for such accounts.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's diaries were already missing a few years after his death, and have not been located.</p>
               </note> Within the next few days I am sending a consignment with the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg>, to which are to be added the Australian palms, few as they are, and some of our alpine plants. My simple photograph is also to follow soon and a very good general map of Australia.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Map not identified.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During his visit here Prince Alfred condescended to plant a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Saxono-Gothaea conspicua</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Saxegothaea conspicua?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and an <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Abies%20albertiana">Abies albertiana</name>
               </seg> in my Garden. That reminds me, that the plant genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Galatea">Galatea</name>
               </seg>, which bears the same name as his frigate, was spelled incorrectly by Herbert, as it is dedicated to the nereid <seg>γαλατεια</seg>. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your news-rich letter of 18 August 1867,<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> which I was pleased to receive after my return from Western Australia, is far too significant a document, for me to have discussed it, — even if I were able to, — in such a way in the rush of official labours which at that time overwhelmed me, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as the depth of the great truths demanded. In the midst of the scepticism of the present time it is reassuring for the spirit, when on his deathbed Goodsir declares, that anybody who even thinks of the possibility of organic transmutation is not a true anatomist. The wavering may cling to pillars of such greatness. And that you, who are prominent among the wise men of natural science, also adhere to higher ideals, and acknowledge an independent spiritual life that can not be explored according to the laws of human knowledge, is fortifying and encouraging for me. Nothing has as yet been done about the project to explore the Easter Islands. However, I am going to write in detail to Sir Henry Barkly today,<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> and shall enumerate to His Excellency all those points, to which you wish to be given preferential consideration.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You direct my attention to certain conditions in the dry fruiting <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>. Have not such been found also in the Viennese basin buried in tertiary sediments? Furthermore, I am convinced, that in many countries, like New Zealand, we must assume two or more periods in the development of creation; to one belong mainly the plants of the alpine regions there, that frequently agree with those of Australia, while the tree vegetation of the plains appear to be the remnants of the vegetation of a large continent, remnants which have survived only in New Zealand, but have sunk into the ocean elsewhere, to be at times brought up again to the light of day in fossil form during volcanic eruptions.<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On this theme see also M to J. Haast, 8 April 1871.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I can not express my gratitude without feeling deeply touched, that you weakened your noble eyesight to write to the young far distant man, and I have to include in my thanks that to your excellent daughter, who stands by you with so much caring kindness and knowledge. May God keep you, noble Sir! That is the sincere wish of </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I am in constant communication with the noble Count Castelnau. He has just described a long series of new beetles, in part furnished by me.<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Castelnau (1868).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have, indeed, many of your memorial speeches, but not all of them. They are so wonderfully poetic and gripping, that I should greatly value the whole collection.<note xml:id="ftn21" type="footnote" n="21">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Forty four eulogies and one general biographical essay, 'Erinnerung an frequentirende Mitglieder', delivered by Martius at meetings of the Leopoldina, are collected in Martius (1866). <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Each life was evidently issued separately; those for Franz von Paula von Schrank, Joseph Gerhard Zuccarini, Christian Samuel Weiss and Joh. Andreas Wagner survive in the Library at MEL. There is no copy of the collection, but M described it in glowing terms in M to C. Mücke, 29 September 1869 (in this edition as 69-09-29a).</p>
               </note> Dr Sonder is always the one to best facilitate the transmission.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Apart from the passage about <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Galatea">Galatea</name>
               </seg> it might also be a welcome hint to Professor Wittstein for his dictionary,<note xml:id="ftn22" type="footnote" n="22">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Wittstein (1856).</p>
               </note> that Baron von Huegel, as he informed me by letter,<note xml:id="ftn23" type="footnote" n="23">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> dedicated the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name>
               </seg> to Princess Maria Melanie von Metternich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Abies%20albertiana">Abies albertiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Galatea">Galatea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Saxono-Gothaea conspicua</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
