<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 22 May 1868. ¶  ¶ It is always a joyful day for me, noble Sir, when I receive a letter from your hand. Thus it was again last week. ¶  You overwhelm me with so much kindnes...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-05-22-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>68.05.22</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 22 May 1868. ¶  ¶ It is always a joyful day for me, noble Sir, when I receive a letter from your hand. Thus it was again last week. ¶  You overwhelm me with so much kindnes...</title>
               <date when="1868-05-22">1868-05-22</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-05-22-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Areca monostachya</term>
               <term>Ptychosperma</term>
               <term>Casuarinas</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus</term>
               <term>Livistona</term>
               <term>Calamus</term>
               <term>Caryota</term>
               <term>Acacia</term>
               <term>Cocos</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 22 May 1868. ¶  ¶ It is always a joyful day for me, noble Sir, when I receive a letter from your hand. Thus it was again last week. ¶  You overwhelm me with so much kindnes...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">68.05.22</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Martius: 'pr. 17 Jul | b. 30 Aug' [received 17 July 1868, answered 30 August 1868]. Martius's letter not found.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im bot. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 22. Mai 1868.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist stets ein freudiger Tag für mich, edler Herr, wenn ich einen Brief aus Ihrer Hand begrüsse. So war es wieder in letzter Woche. Sie überschütten mich mit soviel Güte, dass ich Ihnen nicht genug danken kann. Und doch habe ich so wenig für Sie gethan! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Endlich nach dem ich meinen Theil zu der Arbeit von Bentham's 4ten Band geliefert, war es mir möglich die Palmen zu ordnen u. nebst einem Packet Pflanzen von Nord-Ost-Australien an Sie abzusenden, was nun kürzlich in dem Schiffe Essex geschehen ist. Dr Sonder wird mit gewohnter Güte die Weitersendung vermitteln. Da nun die nothwendigsten Arbeiten beseitigt sind, welche sich während meiner Krankheit anhäuften, werde ich auf diesen kleinen Beitrag andere folgen lassen, um Ihnen die Gestalten der Pflanzenwelt Australiens nach u nach weiter vorzuführen. Von den Palmen erhalten Sie <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">meine ganze Originalsammlung</hi>
               </seg> zum Darlehn, u es macht mir eine besondere Freude, dem grossen Kenner dieser fürstlichen Pflanzen das geringe Material vorlegen zu können, was die in dieser Beziehung offenbar arme Flora Australiens bisher geliefert hat. Es sind indessen doch 17 Arten (soweit ich urtheile) was immerhin die von R. Br. exponirten Palmen vervierfacht. Unglücklicherweise sind mir diese Gewächse nur unter den ungünstigsten Verhältnissen zugänglich gewesen, was das Mangelhafte der Exemplare entschuldigen muss. Ich fürchte, Sie, hoher Freund, werden das dürftige Material keiner genauern Durchschau werth halten. Sollte dies aber dennoch der Fall sein, dann gewinnen wir für den 6ten Band der Flora Australiens einen classischen ewig denkwürdigen Beitrag. Ich bitte Sie irgend ein Exemplar, welches es auch immer sei, für Ihre eigne Palmen Sammlung zurück zu behalten, den Rest aber Bentham durch Dr Sonder zustellen zu wollen im Jahr 1868, da Bentham in allen Fällen mein Original-Material mit R Br's u Hookers Sammlungen zu vergleichen wünscht. Soweit ich urtheile finden Sie <name key="Ptychosperma">Ptychosperma</name> 3, <name key="Cocos">Cocos</name> 1, Livistonia 4, <name key="Calamus">Calamus</name> 3, <name key="Caryota">Caryota</name> 1, Areca 1. Die 4 übrigen sind von mir nicht generisch erkannt. <name key="Areca%20monostachya">Areca monostachya</name> hat prächtig rothe Früchte mit fleischigem Pericarp u erstreckt sich wenigstens bis nach Wide-Bay.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meinen eilig im vorigen Monat geschriebenen Brief werden Sie, verehrter Herr, wohl erlangt haben. In Ihren Briefen spricht sich stets eine solche rührende u von mir nur wenig verdiente Theilnahme aus, dass ich oft gewünscht habe, Ihre häuslichen Verhältnisse belauschen zu können, um zu wissen, wie ein grosser Weiser dieses Zeitalters die herrlichen Abendstunden eines ruhmreichen Lebens verlebt. Gewiss umringen Sie liebliche Enkel mit fröhlich unschuldigen Gesichtern und rufen die rosigen Tage der eignen Jugend in die Erinnerung zurück!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mich jagen die Verhältnisse in dem unruhigen Lande, in welchem das Eine immer das Andere überstürmt recht unstet umher. Ich fühle es dass ich, um meine Arbeiten später einer Vollendung entgegen zu führen, den Welttheil noch mehrfach zu durchkreuzen habe, u ich hätte wohl schon wieder im Felde gestanden, zwänge mich nicht der Fortgang des Werkes Bentham's meinen Verpflichtungen als Mitarbeiter oder vielmehr Hülfsarbeiter ehrenhaft nachzukommen. Eigentlich bin ich ein wenig unzufrieden, dass unser berühmter Freund die Arbeit so gar arg vorwärts drängt, u. ich hätte es lieber gesehen, dass seine unvergleichlich grosse Erfahrung als Phytograph dem Werke über die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Gattungen</hi>
               </seg> mehr ausgedehnt zugewandt wäre. Bentham lebt in der glücklichen Unabhängigkeit des Reichthums u des Privatlebens, u so wird es mir, der im Amte um Broterwerb bekümmert den grössten Theil der Zeit andern Pflichten als literarischen opfern muss, schwer dem Präsidenten der Linné-Gesellschaft vorarbeitend voranzueilen, zumal da ich doch der Medicin u Geographie nicht ganz abhold werden darf.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So sind denn auch meine Pläne für weitere ausgedehnte Reisen vereitelt, u ich möchte [nicht]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg>.</p>
               </note> zu sehr die Elasticität der Jugend hinschwinden sehen, um viel später noch grössere Entdeckungsreisen durchzuführen. Ihre rastlose Thätigkeit als Nestor der Phytologen setzt uns Alle in die tiefste Bewunderung! Wäre ich in Europa würde ich mir das Privilegium erbitten einen Theil der Flora Brasiliana schreiben zu dürfen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Darwin hat mir seine beiden neuen Bände "Variation of Animals &amp; plants under Domestication" eben zugesandt. Die Beobachtungen, soweit ich flüchtig bisher gesehen, sind gewiss glänzend, aber die Schlüsse, welche der vortreffliche Mann daraus zieht jedenfalls oft bestreitbar! Mit allen Erfolgen in der Ziehung und Veredlung der Racen wird es ihm nimmer gelingen die Arten als Glieder einer Kette ununterbrochen zusammenzufügen, noch den Didus ineptus &amp;c in die Reihen belebter Formen durch Brütungsprocesse zurück zu rufen, was doch eine practische Probe wäre, aber gewiss eine ebenso vergebliche als die Versuche der Alchymisten einen Stein der Weisen oder eine Quint-Essenz zu finden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die letzte Post brachte mir die formale Trauerbotschaft von dem Dahinscheiden des grossen Sir David Brewster in einer Mittheilung seines Schwiegersohnes. Er verschied im Trost des christlichen Glaubens, würdig eines Weisen, der wie Newton inmitten grosser Entdeckungen sich zu der Erkenntniss erhoben sah "More worlds than one". —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben so viel Schätze bereits vor mir hingestreut, dass ich zage, noch irgend etwas, wie Sie es wünschen, zu fordern. Aber dies möchte ich doch erbitten, den Band Ihrer plastisch schönen u poetisch-genussreichen Reden, gehalten vor der Akademie. Mir stehen diese von wissenschaftlichem Geiste ausströmenden Worte viel höher als die gehaltlosen Poesien vieler gefeierter Dichter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre[m] Wunsch, die schnell wachsenden Bäume Australiens, namentlich die Eucalypten, Casuarinen u Acacien in die wasserleeren Gegenden Brasiliens einzuführen, würde ich aufs Bereitwilligste entsprechen, wenn sich dieser hochherzige Wunsch auf eine solide Basis des Operirens hinführen liesse. Wie wäre es, wenn sich der Gesandte Brasiliens mit den Ministern des Kaisers beräthe, um Massregeln zu treffen, dass die Aussaat verwirklicht u geschützt würde. Ich habe Natal, [...]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>illegible — cut off or covered by binding. </p>
               </note> dem indisch Hochland, Jerusalem, der Wüste der Atacama, den Plata-Ebenen die Gelegenheit zur weiteren Verbreitung jener Bäume gegeben, u. der Kaiser Frankreichs ist so sehr von der Wichtigkeit der durch mich in Algier sehr unterstützten Baumcultur überzeugt, dass S. Maj. mich auffordern liess, meine Ideen in einem directen Schreiben an den Kaiser auseinander zu setzen. Nun wieder mit dieser Post ruft ein hervorstehender Mann meine Hülfe für die Prärien von Kansas an, u der Graf Maillard de Marafy wünscht dieselbe Hülfe im Interesse der Regierung Ägyptens. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich vergass leider, die für Sie bestimmte Charte Australiens den andern abgesandten Gegenständen beizufügen; sie soll schon folgen. Die schönste aller Karten Australiens ist aber das liebliche zwar kleiner aber genaue u vollständige Blatt des ausgezeichneten Prof Petermann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn immer sich wieder einige Flechten anfinden, sollen solche Herrn v Krempelhuber zugesandt werden. Ihres Wunsches für ornithologische Beiträge zu dem akadem Museum werde ich eingedenk bleiben. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit dem innigsten Wunsche für Ihr Wohlergehen Ihr Sie Ehrender treuer</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. v. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Dr. Neumayers letztes ausgezeichnetes Werk liegt vor mir. Es ist eine Pracht-Arbeit! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auch einige Algen habe ich gesandt ebenso etwa 90 Arten Flechten, freilich nicht immer in guten Exemplaren.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Witwe des Dr Bayer wird Sie in München aufsuchen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">22 May 1868.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is always a joyful day for me, noble Sir, when I receive a letter from your hand. Thus it was again last week.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> You overwhelm me with so much kindness, that I can not thank you enough. And yet I have done so little for you!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At long last, after I had dispatched my share of the work for Bentham's 4th volume,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bentham (1863-78), vol. 4. M sent the final box of material for vol. 4 in March 1868. See M to J. Hooker, 12 March 1868 (in this edition as 68-03-12a).</p>
               </note> it became possible for me to sort the palms and send them to you, as well as a parcel of plants from North-East Australia, as has recently been done by the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Essex</seg>. Dr Sonder will facilitate the further transmission with his usual kindness. As the most necessary labours, which had accumulated during my illness, have now been dealt with, I shall let others follow this small contribution, to demonstrate to you in the course of time the forms of the Australian vegetation. You receive <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my complete original collection</hi>
               </seg> of palms on loan, and it gives me particular pleasure to be able to place the little material, that the in this respect evidently poor flora of Australia has displayed so far, before the great expert on these princely plants. None the less, there are 17 species (as far as I can judge), and that, after all, quadruples the number of palms expounded by R. Br. Unfortunately these plants were accessible to me only under the most unfavourable conditions, and that must excuse the inadequacies of the specimens. I fear that you, exalted friend, will not consider the poor material worth a close examination. However, should you do so none the less, we should gain a classic, eternally memorable contribution for the 6th volume of the Flora of Australia.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius died on 13 December 1868, only a few months after M's specimens would have reached him. He did not publish anything based on these materials. Bentham (1863-78), vol. 7, in his section on palms, pp. 132-47, refers only to C. Martius (1823-53).</p>
               </note> I beg you, to retain any one specimen, which ever it may be, for your own palm collection, but send the rest through Dr Sonder to Bentham during 1868, as Bentham in any case wishes to compare my original material with that of R Br's and Hooker's collections. As far as I can judge, you will find <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Ptychosperma">Ptychosperma</name>
               </seg> 3, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cocos">Cocos</name>
               </seg> 1, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Livistona">Livistona</name>
               </seg> 4, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Calamus">Calamus</name>
               </seg> 3, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Caryota">Caryota</name>
               </seg> 1, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Areca</seg> 1. I did not recognise the genera of the four remaining ones. <name key="Areca%20monostachya">Areca monostachya</name> has magnificent red fruit with a fleshy pericarp and extends at least as far as Wide Bay.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On the central Qld coast.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will probably have received my hastily written letter of last month, noble Sir.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No letter from M to Martius for April 1868 has been found.</p>
               </note> Your letters always express such a touching interest hardly deserved by me, that I have often wished I could eavesdrop on your domestic life to learn, how such a great wise man of our own epoch spends the wonderful evening of a glorious life. Surely you are surrounded by lovely grandchildren with happy innocent faces and recall the memories of the rosy days of your own youth!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Circumstances are driving me restlessly in this turbulent country, where one thing always precipitates another. I feel that, to lead my labours to some conclusion later on, I shall have to cross this continent several times, and I would have been back in the field already, if the continuation of Bentham's work<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg>.</p>
               </note> did not force me to meet my obligations honourably as co-worker or rather assistant.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to G. Bentham, 29 March 1868.</p>
               </note> To tell the truth, I am a little dissatisfied, that our famous friend pushes the work along quite so hard. I should have preferred, had he extended his incomparable, great experience as a phytographer more on the work on the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Genera</hi>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bentham &amp; Hooker (1862-83).</p>
               </note> Bentham lives in the fortunate independence of prosperity and as an independent scholar, and thus it becomes difficult for me as someone who, concerned with earning his bread in employment, has to sacrifice the major part of his time to duties other than literary work, to rush ahead of the President of the Linnean Society with the preparatory work, especially as I do not want to turn my back completely on medicine and geography.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thus my plans for further extended travels are thwarted, and I am too much aware of the elasticity of youth dwindling away for me still to carry out larger exploration expeditions much later. Your restless activities as the nestor of phytologists fills us all with the deepest admiration. Were I in Europe, I should request the privilege to write a part of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora brasiliana</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. Martius (1840-1906).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Darwin has just sent me his two new volumes <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Variation of animals &amp; plants under domestication</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Darwin (1868). M was sent a copy of the second printing; see Burkhardt <seg style="font-style: italic; ">et al</seg>. (1985-), vol. 16, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>p. 984.</p>
               </note> The observations, as far as I could tell from a fleeting glance, are admittedly brilliant, but the conclusions drawn from them by the excellent gentleman certainly often disputable! With all his successes in the breeding and improvement of the races he will never succeed in joining together the species as links in an unbroken chain, nor in achieving a throw-back to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Didus ineptus</seg> etc. in the series of living forms by breeding processes, which would be a practical test, but surely just as useless as the attempts of the alchemists to find a stone of wisdom or a quintessence.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last mail brought me in a communication from his son-in-law officially the sad news of the passing away of the great Sir David Brewster.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> He died in the solace of the Christian faith, worthy of a wise man who, like Newton, came in the midst of great discoveries to the recognition 'More worlds than one'.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have already heaped so many treasures on me, that I hesitate to do as you suggest and ask for more. But there is one thing I should like to request: the volume of your beautifully structured and poetically enjoyable speeches given before the Academy.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. Martius (1866). M had already requested a copy of this work in M to C. von Martius, 3 March 1866. While there is now no copy at MEL, M described it in glowing terms in M to C. Mücke, 29 September 1869 (in this edition as 69-09-29a).</p>
               </note> I place these words full of scientific spirit much higher than the empty poems of many celebrated poets.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall be happy, to carry out your desire to introduce the fast growing Australian trees, especially the eucalypts, casuarinas, and acacias, into the waterless areas of Brazil, if this high-minded wish can be put on a solid basis of operation. How would it be, if the ambassador of Brazil took council with the Minister of the Emperor<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dom Pedro II, Emperor of Brazil.</p>
               </note> to take measures to make the sowing a reality and protect it. I have given the opportunity for a greater distribution of those trees to Natal, the Indian highlands, Jerusalem, the Atacama desert and the Plata<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>La Plata, Argentina.</p>
               </note> plains, and the French Emperor<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Napoleon III.</p>
               </note> is so convinced of the importance of the tree cultivation in Algier, which I am greatly supporting, that His Majesty requested me to expound my ideas in a direct letter to the Emperor.<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found, but see a review of Trottier (1868) <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in Pall Mall gazette</seg>, 16 May 1868, p. 1851, reprinted in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 16 July 1868, p. 7: 'The Emperor of the French is greatly interested in the work, and has written to thank Dr Mueller, of Melbourne, Mr. Wilson, and M. Ramel for the efforts with which they have taken to supply Algeria with seeds.'</p>
               </note> Even just with this mail an eminent gentleman requests my help for the prairies of Kansas, and Count Maillard de Marafy desires the same assistance in the interests of the Egyptian Government. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unfortunately I forgot to enclose the map of Australia for you with the other materials, but it will follow soon. The most beautiful of all the maps of Australia is the lovely sheet, though smaller, but accurate, from the excellent Professor Petermann.<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The map promised by M has not been identified. With respect to Petermann's map, M is probably referring to the map by Petermann published in Stieler (1867), or an earlier version of this in an earlier edition of this work.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Whenever lichens are found, they shall be sent to Mr von Krempelhuber. I shall keep in mind your wish for ornithological contributions for the Museum of the Academy.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With my sincerest wishes for your welfare </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your faithful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dr Neumayer's latest excellent work is before me. It is a fine work!<note xml:id="ftn21" type="footnote" n="21">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Presumably Neumayer (1867). </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have also sent a few algae, further about 90 species of lichens, though admittedly not always good specimens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The widow of Dr Bayer will visit you in Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Areca%20monostachya">Areca monostachya</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Calamus">Calamus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Caryota">Caryota</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarinas">Casuarinas</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cocos">Cocos</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Livistona">Livistona</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ptychosperma">Ptychosperma</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
