<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[5 February 1868] ¶  ¶ We sow them [cinchonas] in greenhouses where we keep the young plants for some time, in order to harden them gradually to the variations in meteorological conditions that they w...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-02-05c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>68.02.05c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>[5 February 1868] ¶  ¶ We sow them [cinchonas] in greenhouses where we keep the young plants for some time, in order to harden them gradually to the variations in meteorological conditions that they w...</title>
               <date when="1868-02-05">1868-02-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-02-05c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Melaleuca ericifolia</term>
               <term>Cinchona condaminea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Société Impériale Zoologique d’Acclimatation, Paris</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[5 February 1868] ¶  ¶ We sow them [cinchonas] in greenhouses where we keep the young plants for some time, in order to harden them gradually to the variations in meteorological conditions that they w...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">68.02.05c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To the Société Impériale Zoologique d’Acclimatation, Paris</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin de la Société Impériale Zoologique d'Acclimatation</seg>, series 2, vol. 5 (1868), pp. 438-9 (B68.06.02). The extract is included in a long article by J. L. Souberain, meetiing secretary of the Société Impériale Zoologique d'Acclimatation in Paris, and Augustin Delondre on the acclimatization of Cinchonas. The extract appears in a section headed 'Introduction et acclimatation des Cinchonas en Australie, et notamment dans les États de Victoria et de Queensland' [Introduction and acclimatization of Cinchonas in Australia, and notably in the States of Victoria and Queensland]. Under 'Etat de Victoria', the extract is introduced as follows: 'D'après les renseignements qui nous ont été fournis, avec une amabilité dont nous ne saurions trop le remercier, par le délégué de la Société impériale d'acclimatation de Paris à Melbourne, M. le docteur Ferdinand Mueller, directeur du Jardin botanique de Melbourne, dans lequel personne n'ignore qu'il cultive depuis longtemps les Cinchonas, il n'y aurait aucune difficulté à faire germer les graines des Cinchonas en Australie. "Nous les semens", nous écrit M. Ferd. Mueller à la date du 5 février 1868…' [According to the information we have been given, with an amiability for which we cannot thank him too much, by the representative in Melbourne of the Société impériale d'acclimatation of Paris, Dr Ferdinand Mueller, director of the Melbourne Botanic Garden in which, as everyone is aware, he has long cultivated Cinchonas, there would be no difficulty in making Cinchona seeds germinate in Australia. "We are sowing them", Mr Ferd. Mueller writes to us on 5 February 1868,…’]. M had supplied some information in response to a letter of 29 July 1867 (not found) from the President, see M to E. Drouyn de Lhuys, 7 December 1867. The receipt of 'quelques documents relatifs à l'acclimatation des Cinchonas dans le Jardin botanique de Melbourne' [some documents relating to the acclimatization of Cinchonas in the Melbourne Botanical Garden] was also reported (p. 356). It is not known what additional documents, if any, M sent with this letter, although B67.02.03 is cited on p. 443 (note 2), and further comments are discussed on p. 445.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nous les semons dans des serres où nous gardons pendant quelque temps les jeunes plants, afin de les endurcir graduellement aux variations de conditions météorologiques qu'elles rencontreront à l'extérieur. Nous les mettons ensuite en plein air, en les abritant au moyen de branches d'arbres (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>
               </seg>). La terre qui leur convient est une terre légère, riche et fraîche, composée au moins en partie de détritus de matières végétales. Nous avons à peu près, pour le moment, dix mille jeunes plants de Cinchonas prèts, pour la plupart, à être transplantés l'automne prochain dans les vallées abritées de nos montagnes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dans le Jardin botanique de Melbourne, quelques plants de <seg style="font-style: italic; ">C. condaminea</seg> ont résisté pendant l'hiver dernier à une température de 2 degrés centigrades au-dessous de zéro (30 degrés Fahr.), bien qu'ils fussent placés dans un endroit peu favorable et tout à fait découvert. Il ne faudrait toutefois pas penser à réussir si l'on tentait la culture des Cinchonas dans des localités exposées à des vents chauds ou froids, ou dans des endroits convenables pour la culture du blé ou des céréales. Les Cinchonas demandent un terrain frais, profond, naturellement riche et léger, une localité bien abritée et d'une irrigation facile; on recontre assez fréquemment ces conditions dans les vallées et les ravins des montagnes en Australie. Je ne doute pas que, dans le sud de l'Europe ou sous un climat semblable à celui de l'Australie, la culture de ces plantes précieuses puisse très-bien réussir.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">[5 February 1868]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We sow them [cinchonas] in greenhouses where we keep the young plants for some time, in order to harden them gradually to the variations in meteorological conditions that they will meet outside. We then put them in the open air, sheltering them by means of tree branches (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>
               </seg>). The earth that suits them is a light, rich and fresh earth composed at least in part of vegetable detritus. At the moment we have approximately ten thousand young Cinchona plants ready, for the most part, to be transplanted next autumn in the sheltered valleys of our mountains.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the Melbourne Botanic Garden some plants of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">C. condaminea</seg> last winter withstood a temperature of 2° below zero (30° Fahr.) even though they were placed in an unfavourable and completely exposed position. Yet one could not think to succeed if one tried to grow Cinchonas in locations exposed to hot or cold winds, or in places suitable for growing corn or cereals. Cinchonas require a fresh, deep, naturally rich and light terrain, a well sheltered and easily watered situation; one meets these conditions often enough in the valleys and gorges of the mountains in Australia. I do not doubt that in southern Europe or in a climate similar to that of Australia, the growing of these precious plants will succeed very well. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cinchona%20condaminea">Cinchona condaminea</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
