<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, in the Botanic Garden,  ¶ 18 June 1868. ¶ Your autographic consignment of the valuable Danish scientific journal, noble sir, has encouraged me, in addition to the thanks that I most sincere...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-06-18e-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Håndskriftafdelingen, Kongelige Bibliotek, Copenhagen.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>68.06.18e</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, in the Botanic Garden,  ¶ 18 June 1868. ¶ Your autographic consignment of the valuable Danish scientific journal, noble sir, has encouraged me, in addition to the thanks that I most sincere...</title>
               <date when="1868-06-18">1868-06-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-06-18e-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Japetus Steenstrup</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, in the Botanic Garden,  ¶ 18 June 1868. ¶ Your autographic consignment of the valuable Danish scientific journal, noble sir, has encouraged me, in addition to the thanks that I most sincere...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">68.06.18e</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Japetus Steenstrup</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Håndskriftafdelingen, Kongelige Bibliotek, Copenhagen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im botanischen </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Garten, am 18 Juni 1868.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihre autographische Übersendung der werthvollen Dänischen wissenschaftlichen Zeitschrift, edler Herr, hat mich ermuthigt neben dem Dank, den ich aufs herzlichste auspreche, auch einige Fragen an Sie zu richten in Bezug auf die von mir, als Vice- Präsident der Acclimation's Gesellschaft lange gewünschte Einführung von Herringen u Stören in die Flüsse und Meere der südlichen Hemisphäre. Die triumpherichen Erfolge, welche wir gewonnen, indem wir die Lachse in den Gewässern Tasmaniens nun völlig naturalisiert haben, eine Aufgabe die man so vielseitig als unmöglich erklärte, lassen mich die Idee immer aufs Neue ergreifen, dass wir den Acipenser und den Clupia ihren hervorragenden nördlichen Genossen auch hier zugesellen sollten. Es scheint indessen, dass die ersten Entwicklungsstadien dieser wichtigen Nahrungsfische noch wenig belauscht sind, und eben daher fehlt es uns an Anhaltspunkten hier, um die für die Ubersiedlung dieser Geschöpfe alle nothwendigen Vorbereitungsmassregeln zu ergreifen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach den grossartigen Erfolgen, welche wir mit den Salmoniden gewonnen, drängt sich mir fort u fort den Gedanke auf, dass die Verschiffung der Ova vom Herring u Stör auch vielleicht möglich wäre in einer Eiskammer; und liesse sich dies durch einige vorläufige Experimente feststellen, so wäre die weitere Ausführung im Grossen einfach eine Geld-Aufgabe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist nicht meine Absicht, verehrter Herr Professor, Ihnen inmitten Ihrer vielseitigen hohen Obliegenheiten irgend eine Mühe aufzubürden, aber vielleicht sind Sie freundlich mich zu unterrichten, ob die neuesten Erfahrungen über den Entwicklungs-Process der gewünschten Fische meine Ideen begünstigen. Ich würde Ihre Mittheilungen hier vor meine Collegen bringen, und falls Sie uns ermuthigen, Massregeln treffen, dass Ihre Vorschläge verwirklicht werden. Vom Standpunkt der Philanthropie ebenso sehr als von dem der Natur-Philosophie ist die Lösung solcher Aufgaben eine Hehre. Das Meer mit seinen unerschöpflichen Nahrungsquellen muss den sich von Generation zu Generation so ausserordentlich vermehrenden Landbewohnern viel mehr ausgedehnt die Mittel der Subsistenz liefern als es bisher gethan! und muss daneben uns später in viel grösserem Masse die Alkalien u die Phosphorsäure <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>für die erneuete Befruchtung unserer Felder liefern, ohne dass dadurch je die Fruchtbarkeit des Oceans je abnehmen wird.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Recht lebhaft erinnere ich den Genuss, wie ich kaum den Knabenjahren entwachsen Sie, edler Herr, im Jahre 1847 die erste Licht auf die vielförmige Entwicklung der Taenien werfen sah, das so heil bringend für die Pathologie wurde, und abgesehen von Ihren anderen grossen Entdeckungen Ihren Namen in der Medicin u Zoologie für immer verherrlichen wird. Es war in Kiel, wie ich Sie das <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Räthsel lösen sah, u der Eindruck is ein so lebendiger geblieben, als sähe ich Sie heute noch vor mir stehen. Dies macht den Wunsch in mir rege, nachdem mehr denn zwei Decannien seitdem dahin geschwunden, Ihr Bild für die Reihe von Karten-Photogrammen zu besitzen, welche ich aus der Hand von mehr denn 100 grossen und befreundeten Zeitgenossen erlangte. Ich würde dem Bilde die ehrenvollste Stelle anweisen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Erholungsstunden beschäftige ich mich mit Medicin, die doch unter allen Wissenschaften wenn es Menschenliebe gilt, am höchsten steht. Daher war mir der Aufsatz von Herrn Prof Rasmussen über weitere Forschungen in dem Cyclus der Taenia-Gebilde, ausserordentlich willkommen, u ich werde ihn wohl für unsere medicinische Zeitschrifte übersetzen. Wenn daher zu irgend einer Zeit Sie mir freundlichst Schriften medicinischen Ihhalts durch meinen Freund Dr. W. Sonder in Hamburg wollen zugänglich machen, so wurde ich sehr verpflichtet werden. In dem sechsten Bande der Fragmenta, welcher seinen Vollendung naht, gedenke ich Ihrem berühmten Namen ein Denkmal zu setzen, damit er auch in der Pflanzenwelt Australiens verherrlicht werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M.D., F.R.S.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, in the Botanic Garden, </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">18 June 1868.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your autographic consignment of the valuable Danish scientific journal, noble sir, has encouraged me, in addition to the thanks that I most sincerely express, also to address some questions to you in respect to the introduction of herring and sturgeon in the rivers and seas of the southern hemisphere, long desired by me as Vice-President of the Acclimatisation Society. The triumphant success that we achieved, in which we have by now completely naturalized the salmon in the waters of Tasmania, a task that was so widely declared impossible, allows me to take up the idea again that we should also add its excellent northern companions the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Acipenser</seg> and the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Clupia</seg>. It seems, however, that the first developmental stages of these important food fishes are still little observed and therefore even important facts are lacking here in order to adopt all the necessary measures for the translocation of these creatures.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After the splendid success that we achieved with the salmon, the thought obtruded on me incessantly that the shipment of ova of herring and sturgeon might also be possible in an ice chamber; and if this were established by some preliminary experiments, its further carrying out would in general simply be a question of money.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is not my intention, respected professor, to burden you with any trouble in the midst of your extensive heavy obligations, but perhaps you will kindly inform me if the latest knowledge about the developmental process of the desired fishes favours my ideas. I would bring your communications before my colleagues here and if you encourage us take measures so that your suggestions are realised. The solution of such propositions from the standpoint of philanthropy just as much as from that of natural philosophy is a lofty matter. The sea with its inexhaustible sources of food must produce much more extended means of subsistence than it previously has done for the dwellers on land who are increasing so remarkably from generation to generation, and in addition to this must produce for us later in much greater mass the alkalis and phosphates for the renewed fertilization of our fields without thereby ever diminishing the fertility of the ocean.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I remember very vividly the pleasure as I, scarcely grown out of boyhood years, saw you, noble sir, cast the first light on the diversiform development of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Taenia</seg>, which was so salutary for pathology and, apart from your other great discoveries, will glorify your name in medicine and zoology for ever. It was in Kiel when I saw you solve the puzzle and the impression has remained as vivid as if I see you still standing before me today.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the German science congress at Kiel in 1846, Steenstrup presented an essay on the complex life cycles of parasitic worms, 'Untersuchungen übwer das Vorkommen des Hermaphroditismus in der Nature', showing the drafts of various drawings (Michaelis &amp; Scherk (1847)), p 139, and the appended <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Tageblatt</seg>, p. 50). The full essay was published as Steenstrup (1846).</p>
               </note> After more than two decades have vanished since then, this awakens the desire in me, to have your likeness for the series of card photographs, which I have acquired from the hands of more than 100 great and friendly contemporaries. I would assign the portrait the most honourable position.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In leisure hours I occupy myself with medicine which, when it is a question of humanity, really stands the highest among all the sciences. Therefore the memoir of Professor Rasmussen on further research into the cycle of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Taenia</seg> organism was extremely welcome and I will probably translate it for our medical journals.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B69.01.01.</p>
               </note> If therefore at some time you kindly wish to render memoirs of medical content accessible to me through my friend Dr W. Sonder in Hamburg, I would be very obliged. In the sixth volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>, which is close to completion, I propose to raise a memorial of your celebrated name, so that it will also be glorified in the plant world of Australia.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M did not name a species in Steenstrup's honour in the sixth volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg> or anywhere else (IPNI, accessed 15 September 2020).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M.D., F.R.S.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>At the meeting of the Acclimatisation Society of Victoria held on 8 July 1868, M reported having written to enquire about knowledge of 'the spawning and breeding of herrings and sturgeons' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 9 July 1868, p. 5). (The report mispelled the addressee's name as 'Henstrup').</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
