<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanical Gardens,  ¶ March 20, 1868. ¶  ¶ It affords me much pleasure, to send you a small essay, written under the direction of my venerable friend, Professor Wittstein of Munich, on the c...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-03-20-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>68.03.20</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanical Gardens,  ¶ March 20, 1868. ¶  ¶ It affords me much pleasure, to send you a small essay, written under the direction of my venerable friend, Professor Wittstein of Munich, on the c...</title>
               <date when="1868-03-20">1868-03-20</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1868/68-03-20-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Physostigma nenenosum</term>
               <term>Gastrolobium bilobum</term>
               <term>Swainsona Greyana</term>
               <term>Anagyris Foetida</term>
               <term>Lathyrus Aphaca</term>
               <term>Lotus Australis</term>
               <term>Laburnum</term>
               <term>arnica</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Frederick Barlee</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanical Gardens,  ¶ March 20, 1868. ¶  ¶ It affords me much pleasure, to send you a small essay, written under the direction of my venerable friend, Professor Wittstein of Munich, on the c...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">68.03.20</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Frederick Barlee</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'The gastrolobium or poison plant', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Perth gazette and</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">West Australian times</seg>, 24 April 1868, p. 2 (B68.04.04). The letter is prefaced by the following information: ‘The communication from Dr. Mueller which we append, and for which we are indebted to the Hon. Colonial Secretary, will somewhat surprise our readers. We can only attribute the fact which it announces, to the circumstances of the plant operated upon having lost its virtues during the process of drying; and it is undoubtedly the fact, at least we have always understood it to be so, that the poison principle it contains is active in all stages of its growth, but has been most destructive to sheep and cattle, when it first springs up upon ground over which bush fires have gone, and then offers a tempting bite upon runs which have but little feed. The question however is a most important one to have decided, and in order that it may be so, we solicit the attention of all our graziers to the request of Dr. Mueller for specimens of all kinds of the plant, and in all stages of growth, as also for specimens of soil, accompanied by explanatory remarks. Parcels of these may be forwarded to the Colonial Secretary by whom they will be promptly transmitted to Dr. McMueller (sic)’. </p>
               </note>Melbourne Botanical Gardens, </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">March 20, 1868.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It affords me much pleasure, to send you a small essay, written under the direction of my venerable friend, Professor Wittstein of Munich, on the chemical constituents of the <name key="Gastrolobium%20bilobum">Gastrolobium bilobum</name>, one of the most dreaded of your poison shrubs.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M's letter is followed by an English translation of part of a paper by Wittstein’s associate Heinrich Fraas ([Fraas 1866], pp. 79-81). This includes a translation of an extract included by Fraas in his paper of a letter from M to Wittstein (in this edition as 66-00-00h). The translation of this extract published in the newspaper differs in minor respects from that prepared by the editors of the present edition. </p>
               </note> The analysis has shewn the plant free of any alkaloid and thus it will be still more difficult to trace out the actual poison principle. I have fed sheep here on the dried foliage of this gastrolobium, and gave them also a strong infusion or the leaves, without any injury being caused to the animals. This however proves merely that the plant is poisonous only under certain conditions; perhaps in certain seasons, certain localities, and certain soils. This would accord with the equally, at times, poisonous <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Lotus%20Australis">Lotus Australis</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Swainsona%20Greyana">Swainsona Greyana</name>
               </seg> both likewise leguminous plants, which I have largely given to sheep without any ill-effect arising therefrom to these creatures, while in certain parts of the Darling the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Swainsona</seg> is deadly poisonous to herds as well as flocks, and while at Lake Torrens at one autumn masses of sheep died from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Lotus</seg>. In regard to the latter plant I experimented here with herb collected at Lake Torrens, and in about half an hour after administering only about 3 ounces each to two sheep both died under Tetanus, and yet no appreciable quantity of any alkaloid could be discovered. Perhaps the active and so dangerous constituent may be allied to cylisin, which in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="arnica">arnica</name>
               </seg> (when the flowers of that herb are administered in large doses) produces also Tetanus, and which is more particularly contained also in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">seeds</seg> of the English <name key="Laburnum">Laburnum</name>, rendering them poisonous in a very high degree. There are other leguminous plants, such as the English Broom, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Lathyrus%20Aphaca">Lathyrus Aphaca</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Amagyris Foetida</seg>, which produce deleterious seeds, and more it is a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">bean</seg> which ranks as one of the most dangerous of all existing poisons, namely the old Calabar Bean (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Physostigma%20nenenosum">Physostigma nenenosum</name>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">P. venenosum</seg>?</p>
               </note>) now so generally used in certain opthalmic operations. On reflection it occurs to me, that in all likelihood the poison principle of the various gastrolobia, of Lotus, and Swainsona, is contained only in the flowers and fruits, or perhaps exclusively in the seed. I should therefore be indebted for information, whether the young foliage of the gastrolobia is harmful, and I would gladly analyse the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">seeds</seg>, if I could get some ounces of them. Possibly but not probably the injurious properties may be volatile and not fixed; then the analysis will be surrounded with great difficulties. I have written to some length on the subject, being anxious to clear up the mystery and to express my dissent from opinion advanced by Mr. Fraas, that the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">gastrolobium bilobum</seg> was harmless. <space unit="chars" quantity="2"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reply to your remarks regarding the dangers which we anticipated both from poison plants, should have been introduced, it is of moment to consider that apparently never any animals of the kangaroo-tribe succumb under the gastrolobia. The Dingo, I anticipate, is chased off in your west as here in the east by strychnia, just as the large carnivora of South Africa are thus extirpated from the settlements. The hare moreover has bred here in parks and homesteads. <space unit="chars" quantity="2"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It would be important to get a package of gastrolobium from a locality where at the time the flocks died. We then would know the precise state of development of the plant, at which it is most injurious. Fungus growth, if present, could also be traced out. And a little <seg style="font-style: italic; ">soil</seg> of the spot would also be acceptable.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg> (Fremantle, WA), 3 May 1868, p. 2, in commenting upon this letter, argues that extensive experience of graziers confirms that all parts of the plant are poisonous, and suggests that the poisonous principle will be found to be volatile, and that '<seg style="">upon this theory the harmlessness of the dried shrub, and of the infusion, is reasonably and satisfactorily accounted for'. It ends by thanking M for his interest, suggesting that M 'has only failed in arriving at the truth, from not having had sufficient information and means of experiment, and it is to be sincerely hoped that the Dr's. wish to be supplied with specimens of every variety of the plant, in all stages of its growth, and a little of the soil in which they grow, will be at once complied with.'</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anagyris%20Foetida">Anagyris Foetida</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="arnica">arnica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gastrolobium%20bilobum">Gastrolobium bilobum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Laburnum">Laburnum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lathyrus%20Aphaca">Lathyrus Aphaca</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lotus%20Australis">Lotus Australis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Physostigma%20nenenosum">Physostigma nenenosum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Swainsona%20Greyana">Swainsona Greyana</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
