<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ ¶ Dr Mueller has safely returned again with the expedition. ¶  I had a letter from him yesterday. He writes from Sidney ¶  where he intends to stay until about the middle of this year, then he will ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-01-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>57.01.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>[ ¶ Dr Mueller has safely returned again with the expedition. ¶  I had a letter from him yesterday. He writes from Sidney ¶  where he intends to stay until about the middle of this year, then he will ...</title>
               <date when="1857-01">1857-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-01-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Mimoseae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="87">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="13">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Wilhelm Sonder</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[ ¶ Dr Mueller has safely returned again with the expedition. ¶  I had a letter from him yesterday. He writes from Sidney ¶  where he intends to stay until about the middle of this year, then he will ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">57.01.00a</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Wilhelm Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Letter not found. The text given here is extracted from Tkach, Neubauer &amp; Roser (2022), Brief 31, W. Sonder to D. von Schlechtendal, 6 April 1857. See n. 2 below for dating rationale.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">[Dr. Müller ist glücklich wieder mit der Expedition zurückgekehrt. Ich hatte gestern einen Brief von ihm. Er schreibt aus Sidney wo er bis ungefähr Mitte dieses Jahrs zu bleiben gedenkt, dann geht er wieder nach Melbourne. Er drängt auf die Beendigung der Bearbeitung, doch so gerne ich ihm gefällig sein will, mit Dampf arbeite ich nicht. Auch ist er mit mir unzufrieden, dass bei den Mimoseen seine Namen als Synonyme stehen geblieben sind.]</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">[</seg>Dr Mueller has safely returned again with the expedition.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The North Australia Exploring Expedition under Augustus Gregory returned to Sydney on 25 December 1856. M had undertaken a collecting expedition from Brisbane to the Glasshouse Mountains, north of that city, and did not accompany the main party to Sydney (Gregory (1858), pp. 134-5). He arrived on 1 January 1857 (</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sydney morning herald, </seg>
                     <seg style="">2 January 1867, p. 4). He left for Melbourne on 10 January (</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">M to W. Hooker, </seg>
                     <seg style="">11 January 1857) and returned to Sydney on 9 February (</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sydney morning herald, </seg>
                     <seg style="">9 February 1857, p. 4). He returned to Melbourne permanently on 27 May 1857 (M to A. Gregory, 4 June 1857).</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is probable that the letter to Sonder was written from Sydney in early January, and it is dated accordingly.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I had a letter from him yesterday. He writes from Sidney<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. Sydney.</p>
               </note> where he intends to stay until about the middle of this year, then he will return again to Melbourne. He is pressing for the completion of the editing,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of Plantae Muelleriana; Sonder enclosed MS for a short continuation, complained of his contributors being slow, and requested more reprints be provided. It is probable that the part for the Plantae Muellerianae enclosed is Gottsche (1856), issued in August 1857 (TL2), as Sonder wrote 'Sie diesmal einige Abdrucke mehr anfertigen lassen wollten, da Dr. Gottsche davon abhaben will.' ['</seg>I would appreciate it if you would have a few more reprints made this time, as Dr Gottsche wants to have some']. Sonder (1856c) and Klatt (1856) were issued at the same time. In a post-script Klatt was identified as 'ein hiesiger Lehrer oder Besitzer einer Privatschule, den ich gerne in die system Botanik einführen möchte' ['a local teacher or owner of a private school whom I would like to introduce to systematic botany'].</p>
               </note> but as much as I want to please him, I am not working with steam. He is also displeased with me that in the case of the <name key="Mimoseae">Mimoseae</name> his names have been left as synonyms.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This was a longstanding complaint. M had previously reported to others his discontent with Sonder's preserving manuscript names as synonyms. For example, in M to W. Hooker, 27 May 1854, he wrote that he was 'disagreably surprised to see even such reappear in print, which I had long ago after a better acquaintance with the species abolished'. He continued to complain about the use of MS names as synonyms, including quoting them from </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg>
                     <seg style="">, but in the context of preparing </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora Australiensis</seg>
                     <seg style=""> Bentham responded: 'You caution me continually against publishing as synonyms catalogue names unaccompanied by diagnoses and I shall avoid it except where they have got within reach of Germans who seeing specimens with the names in Sonder's herbarium or referred to in the Linnaea are sure to take them up as "species neglectae" if not disposed of in some way' (G. Bentham to M, 8 October 1862). See Lucas (1995) for discussion of the general problems of nomenclature arising from M's inadequate herbarium and his collecting and labelling practices.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Later in Sonder's letter he defended the practice, although agreeing to comply with M's request. He was concerned about problems that purchasers of sets of M's plants would have or cause; indeed, the published series was as much a catalogue of the sale sets as it was a vehicle for descriptions or geographic range:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.8661in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Sie werden indess mit mir einverstanden sein, dass es Dr. Müller gar nicht zum Schimpf gereicht, wenn er eine Pflanze für neu gehalten hat, die sich bei genauer Untersuchung als bekannt ergiebt. Kommen solche Synonyme nicht auch bei anderen Sammlungen vor, und hat der Verkäufer nicht auch Pflichten gegen seine Abnehmer? Ich glaube die Nichtanführung der Müller’schen Namen kann Confusion genug hervorrufen, wenn sie von dem Besitzer falsch bestimmt werden, der ohnehin unzufrieden damit sein wird, wenn er die Pflanzen nachbestimmen soll.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.8661in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">[You will agree with me, however, that it is no disgrace to Dr Mueller if he has considered a plant to be new which, on closer examination, turns out to be known. Don't such synonyms also occur in other collections, and doesn't the seller also have obligations towards his buyers? I believe that the failure to quote Müller's names can cause confusion enough if they are wrongly determined by the owner, who will be unhappy anyway if he has to re-determine the plants.]</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mimoseae">Mimoseae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
