<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Botanic Garden, Melbourne,  ¶ 21 July 1857. ¶ Venerable Professor, ¶  ¶ More than 10 years have passed, since I had the honour to make your personal acquaintance during the meeting of scientists in Ki...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-07-21a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>57.07.21a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Botanic Garden, Melbourne,  ¶ 21 July 1857. ¶ Venerable Professor, ¶  ¶ More than 10 years have passed, since I had the honour to make your personal acquaintance during the meeting of scientists in Ki...</title>
               <date when="1857-07-21">1857-07-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-07-21a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Roepera cleomoides</term>
               <term>Goodeniaceae</term>
               <term>Zygophyllum</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="62">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="38">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Johannes Roeper</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Botanic Garden, Melbourne,  ¶ 21 July 1857. ¶ Venerable Professor, ¶  ¶ More than 10 years have passed, since I had the honour to make your personal acquaintance during the meeting of scientists in Ki...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">57.07.21a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Johannes Roeper</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see Kobert (1911), p. 38.</p>
               </note>Bot. Garten, Melbourne, den 21. Juli 1857.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter Herr Professor!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mehr denn 10 Jahre sind verflossen, seitdem ich die Ehre hatte, mit Ihnen während der Versammlung der Naturforscher in Kiel persönlich bekannt zu werden. Kurz vor meinem Scheiden aus Europa übersandte ich ein paar hundert der selteneren Pflanzen, welche mir in meinen botanischen Ausflügen durch Schleswig-Holstein vorkamen. Auch ohne wiederholte Beobachtung der Roepera-Arten, welche Ihr grosser und nun auch schon verewigter Freund Adrian de Jussieu Ihnen widmete, würde Ihre Freundlichkeit zu mir während der Kieler Zusammenkunft meiner Erinnerung nicht entschwunden sein. — Die Untersuchung einer Reihe australischer und südafrikanischer Arten von <name key="Zygophyllum">Zygophyllum</name> zeigte mir die Unhaltbarkeit der Jussieuschen Gattung Roepera und ich habe deshalb mit grosser Freude ein ebenso merkwürdiges, als prächtiges neues Genus der Kapparideen, welches ich während der Reise des Mr. Gregory an den Quellen des Victoriaflusses zu entdecken das Glück hatte, als Zeichen meiner Verehrung mit Ihrem Namen geschmückt und bereits im Januarhefte der New<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kew.</p>
               </note> Garden Miscellany veröffentlicht, wozu der edle Mäcen Sir William Hooker freudig die Hand bot. Etwas später habe ich Ihnen gleichzeitig mit einer Karte unserer Reise, welche für unsern gnädigen Landesherrn, den Grossherzog von Mecklenburg-Schwerin bestimmt war, durch unsern Freund Herrn Dr. Sander,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder.</p>
               </note> ein Exemplar der neuen Roepera diamoides<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Misreading by Kobert for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">R. cleomoides</seg>?</p>
               </note> zugesandt. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mancherlei Umstände haben es für mich notwendig gemacht, hier eine festere Stelle als Mediziner einzunehmen , denn obwohl ich seit meiner Anstellung am hiesigen botanischen Garten nicht mehr ärztlich praktiziere, würde mir doch die Erlangung der medizinischen Doktorwürde eine bessere Stellung an der hiesigen Universität sichern, an welcher ich später mitwirken werde. Ich studierte in Kiel Pharmazie und Naturwissenschaften und erhielt dort das Diplom als Doktor der Philosophie und ich würde mich der Medizin schon damals ganz zugewendet haben, hätte nicht der Gesundheitszustand meiner ältesten Schwester es mir als einzigen Bruder zur Pflicht auferlegt, mit ihr sehr jung in eine wärmere Zone auszuwandern. Ich habe später durch Selbststudium genug von Medizin erlernt, um in einem Lande wie dem unsrigen, mich in dieser Richtung nützlich zu machen. Die Arzneikräfte mancher einheimischen Pflanzen habe ich gelegentlich untersucht, wie Sie vielleicht aus botanischen Zeitschriften erfuhren, und so habe ich u. a. zuerst die tonische Wirkung der hier überall massenhaft auftretenden Goodeniaceen nachgewiesen. Es würde mir zur grössten Freude und zu mannigfaltigen Vorteile gereichen, wollte mich die medizinische Fakultät meiner Vaterstadt Rostock promovieren und dieser Beweis von Anerkennung würde mich ermuntern, für Ihre Museen künftig nach Kräften beizutragen. Ich habe in der Hoffnung, dass die medizinische Fakultät durch Ihren gütigen Einfluss meiner Bitte Gewähr leisten werde, für die mit der Promotion verknüpften Kosten Herrn Doktor Sander den nötigen Fond zu Gebot gestellt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit den herzlichsten Wünschen für Ihr Wohlergehen, damit Sie, Herr Professor, noch lange unserer Wissenschaft als Zierde erhalten bleiben, schliesse ich diese Zeilen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit Hochachtung und Ergebenheit</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Herrn Prof. Dr. Roeper,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Rostock.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Botanic Garden, Melbourne, </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">21 July 1857.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Venerable Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>More than 10 years have passed, since I had the honour to make your personal acquaintance during the meeting of scientists in Kiel.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">24th meeting of German natural scientists and physicians (Deutsche Naturforscher und Ärtze), 18-26 September 1846 at Kiel. See Voigt &amp; Sinkora (1996).</p>
               </note> Shortly before my departure from Europe I sent you several hundred rare plants, which I had found during my excursions through Schleswig-Holstein. Even without repeated observations of the species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Roepera</seg>, which your great and now deceased friend Adrian de Jussieu dedicated to you, your kindness to me during the gathering in Kiel would not have faded from my memory.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The examination of a number of Australian and South African species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Zygophyllum">Zygophyllum</name>
               </seg> indicated to me that Jussieu's genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Roepera</seg> is untenable. For this reason I have been delighted to adorn a strange and magnificent new genus in the Capparideae with your name as a token of my veneration. I had the good fortune to discover it during the expedition of Mr Gregory at the source of the Victoria River, and published it already in the January issue of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">New Garden Miscellany</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hooker's Journal of Botany and Kew Garden Miscellany</seg>
                     <seg style="">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> with the glad assistance of the noble patron of science, Sir William Hooker. A little later I sent you through our friend Dr Sonder a specimen of the new <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Roepera%20cleomoides">Roepera cleomoides</name>
               </seg>, enclosed with a map of our journey,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> destined for our gracious sovereign, the Grand Duke of Mecklenburg-Schwerin.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Various circumstances have made it necessary that I should occupy a more secure position as a medical man here. Although I no longer practise medicine since my appointment to the Botanic Garden here, obtaining a medical degree would secure a better position for me at our local University, where I will be a participant later on. I studied pharmacy and natural science in Kiel and obtained there the diploma of a Doctor of Philosophy. I would have turned to medicine already then, had not the poor state of health of my elder sister<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. the elder of M's two surviving sisters, Bertha.</p>
               </note> placed on me as her only brother the duty to emigrate with her to a warmer climate. I have later learned enough of medicine through self-education to make myself useful in a country such as ours here. Later I have at times examined numerous indigenous plants for their medical properties, as you may perhaps have learnt from botanical journals, and I have, for instance, been the first to prove the tonic properties of the <name key="Goodeniaceae">Goodeniaceae</name>, which are found here in large masses. It would be my greatest joy and would lead to manifold advantages for me, if the medical faculty of the city of my birth, Rostock, would confer on me a medical degree, and this token of recognition would prompt me to henceforth contribute to your museums with all my power. In the hope that, through your kind influence, the medical faculty will grant my request, I have made the necessary funds, required for the costs involved with the conferment, available to Dr Sonder. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With my sincerest wishes for your well-being, that you, Professor Roeper, may be preserved for a long time yet as an ornament to grace our science, I close these lines.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With respect and devotion,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Professor Dr Roeper,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Rostock.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 26 October 1857, the Dean of the Medical Faculty, Prof. H. Spitta, wrote (in German, here translated):</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'Seventh Missive. | Promotio in absentia of Dr phil. Ferd. Mueller | of Melbourne in Australia.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The application of Dr phil. Mueller is furthered and supported by the following publications and documents, which are enclosed. | 1. By a letter from Dr Sonder of Hamburg of 3rd inst. to Prof. Roeper here. | 2. Enclosure from Dr Mueller of 21 July to the same address. | 3. By a second letter from Dr Sonder of 21st inst. with an enclosed biographical sketch of Dr Mueller. [See W. Sonder to J. Roeper, 21 October 1857 (in this edition as M57-10-21)] | 4. By the inaugural dissertation of Dr Mueller, published in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora</seg> 1853, No. 30 [B53.08.01, B53.08.02]. | 5. By three reports on 'Vegetation of the Colony' of the years 1853, 1854, 1855 [parts of B53.10.01, B54.10.01, B55.11.01]. | 6. By the botanical paper: 'Definitions of rare and hitherto undescribed Australian plants', published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions of the Philosophical Society of Victoria</seg>, August to September 1854 and 1855, vol. 1 [B54.13.06, B55.09.02]. | 7. By a second paper: 'Descriptive characters of New Alpine Plants from continental Australia', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">ibid</seg>., p.96 [B55.09.03]. | 8. By a translation by himself in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hamburger Gartenzeitung</seg>, vol.10, Heft 12, 1854 [B54.12.03]. | I place the matter before the proven judgement of my colleagues. Without meaning to anticipate your opinion I have taken the liberty to transmit my own vote in the form of an approving application to the Ministry, with a request for a possible improvement or addition to the application.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M's degree was approved by Friedrich Franz II (Grand Duke of Mecklenburg), and Professors Stannius, Bergmann, Veit, and Th. Thierfelder. 'Promotio in absentia' was not at all unusual at a number of universities in Germany at that time, though the faculty had the option, but did not avail itself of it, of conferring a degree <seg style="font-style: italic; ">honoris causa</seg>. See Kobert (1911), p. 40, and Jahn &amp; Schmidt (1996).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also Universität Rostock to M, 7 November 1857.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Goodeniaceae">Goodeniaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Roepera%20cleomoides">Roepera cleomoides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Zygophyllum">Zygophyllum</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
