<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May it turn out happy, fortunate and prosperous ¶  ¶ Under the highest auspices of our most serene prince and most merciful lord, Lord Friedrich Franz, Grand Duke of Mecklenburg, Prince of the Wends, ...</title>
            <author>Universität Rostock</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-11-07-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M200b.4, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>57.11.07</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Universität Rostock</author>
               <title>May it turn out happy, fortunate and prosperous ¶  ¶ Under the highest auspices of our most serene prince and most merciful lord, Lord Friedrich Franz, Grand Duke of Mecklenburg, Prince of the Wends, ...</title>
               <date when="1857-11-07">1857-11-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-11-07-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">May it turn out happy, fortunate and prosperous ¶  ¶ Under the highest auspices of our most serene prince and most merciful lord, Lord Friedrich Franz, Grand Duke of Mecklenburg, Prince of the Wends, ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">57.11.07</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Universität Rostock</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M200b.4, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS is a printed certificate.</p>
               </note>Quod felix faustum fortunatumque sit</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Summis auspiciis serenissimi principis et domini nostri clementissimi</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Domini FRIDERICI FRANCISCI magni ducis megapolitani principis venedorum suerini et raceburgi comitis suerinensis terrae rostochiensis et stargardiensis domini</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Universitatis hujus literariae patroni munificentissimi atque cancellarii magnificentissimi</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Rectore academiae magnifico FRANCISCO SCHULZE phil. doctore chemiae et pharmaciae p. p. o.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">professor publicus ordinarius.</p>
               </note> laboratorii academici directore apparatus physici condirectore cet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Virum amplissimum et praenobilissimum FERDINANDUM JACOBUM HENRICUM MUELLER Rostochii natum philosophiae doctorem artiumque liberalium magistrum horti botanici qui melburnii floret directorem indefessum et sagacem per remotissimas terrae regiones peregrinatorem de penitiore plantarum australasicarum cognitione earumque virium medicatricum scrutatione optime meritum</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Summis in medicina honoribus et dignitate ac privilegiis doctoris medicinae rite legitimeque ornatum esse manifestum facit et confirmat</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ad hunc actum clementissime constitutus procancellarius et promotor HENR. HELMERIC. LUDOV. SPITTA medicinae doctor et professor publicus ordinarius magno duci megapolitano-suerinensi a consiliis medicis supremis collegii cui res medicinales a serenissimo principe commissae sunt membrum ordinarium complurium societatum literariarum sodalis Ordinis Medicorum H. T.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hoc Tempore.</p>
               </note> Decanus.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">P. P.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Perfectum et Promulgatum.</p>
               </note> Rostochii sub sigillo ordinis medicorum die VII mens. Novembris A. MDCCCLVII.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The text of the Hippocratic oath, signed by M, is as follows:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'Ego Ferdinandus Jacobus Henricus Mueller juro atque promitto, me, quidquid ad existimationem, famam, honorem atque incrementum hujus universae Academiae Rostochiensis, et singulatim gratiosi ordinis medici, ullo modo facere potest, nullo non tempore et in quemcunque vitae statum transiero, sollicite observaturum, commoda, quantum in me est, provecturum, damna declinaturum, praeceptores instar parentum habiturum, deinceps, ubi ad exercendam medicinam fuerim requisitus, me nihil dolose et negligenter, sed omnia circumspecte, ad conscientiae rectitudinem at artis leges per rationem atque experientiam stabilitas acturum, morbos et affectus, silentii lege mihi revelatos, et, quidquid celare fas est, prudentur celaturum, aegris, sive pauperes illi sint, sive divites, pari cura ac sollicitudine consultorum, in relationibus officii ergo expediendis veritatem secuturum, reipublicae salutem perpetuo ante oculos habiturum, per omnem denique vitam ita me esse gesturum, ne umquam mei causa ars male audiat. Ita me Deus adjuvet! Ferd. Mueller.' See Kobert (1911) p. 41.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[I, Ferdinand Jakob Heinrich Mueller, swear and promise that, whatever can be done, by any means at any time and into whatever situation of life I shall have passed, towards the fame, reputation, honour and benefit of this University of Rostock and in particular the distinguished Faculty of Medicine, I shall sedulously observe it, shall advance its benefits to the limits of my power, shall avert any injuries to it, shall hold its teachers in the place of parents, finally, when I have been required to practise medicine, I shall perform nothing deceitfully and negligently, but everything circumspectly, in accord with correctness of conscience and the laws of the art, established by reason and experience, that I shall prudently [reading <seg style="font-style: italic; ">prudenter</seg>] conceal what is right to conceal of diseases and conditions revealed to me under the law of silence, that I shall consult [reading <seg style="font-style: italic; ">consulturum</seg>] the interests of the sick, be they poor or rich, with equal care and solicitude, that I shall follow the truth in official reports to be filed in consequence, that I shall continually hold the safety of the state before my eyes, finally that throughout the whole of my life I shall so conduct myself that the [medical] art is never ill spoken of because of me. So help me God!]</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">May it turn out happy, fortunate and prosperous</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Under the highest auspices of our most serene prince and most merciful lord, Lord Friedrich Franz, Grand Duke of Mecklenburg, Prince of the Wends, Schwerin and Ratzeburg, Count of the land of Schwerin, Lord of Rostock and Stargard</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>most munificent patron of this University of letters and its most magnificent chancellor</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>when the rector of the academy was Franz Schulze, doctor of philosophy, professor<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Literally 'public ordinary professor', i.e. full professor ('ordinarius') entitled to give public lectures.</p>
               </note> of chemistry and pharmacy, director of the university laboratory, co-director of the physical apparatus, etc.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Henr. Helmeric. Ludwig Spitta, most complaisantly appointed pro-chancellor and promotor for this act, doctor of medicine and professor to the grand duke by decree of the senior doctors of the college to which medical matters have been entrusted by the most serene prince, ordinary member of many literary societies, Dean of the Faculty of Medicine at this time publishes and confirms as having been duly and lawfully equipped with the highest distinctions in medicine and the dignity and privileges of a doctor of medicine</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>the most distinguished and noble Ferdinand Jakob Heinrich Mueller born at Rostock, doctor of philosophy and master of the liberal arts, tireless and wise director of the Botanical Garden which flourishes at Melbourne, explorer through the most remote regions of the land</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[an honour] well deserved from his intimate knowledge of Australasian plants and scrutiny of their medicinal properties.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Completed and issued at Rostock under the seal of the Faculty of Medicine, 7 November 1857.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
