<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 11 Oct. 1857 ¶ My dear Sir William. ¶  ¶ I gladly employ my last leisure hours before the close of the mail in giving a short summary of my botanical labours since the last mon...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-10-11-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no.170.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>57.10.11</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 11 Oct. 1857 ¶ My dear Sir William. ¶  ¶ I gladly employ my last leisure hours before the close of the mail in giving a short summary of my botanical labours since the last mon...</title>
               <date when="1857-10-11">1857-10-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1857/57-10-11-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Acacia verticillata var cephalantha</term>
               <term>Acacia deltoidea β pungens</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Brachybotryae</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Calamiformes</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Triangulares</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Brunioideae</term>
               <term>Boronia tetrathecoides</term>
               <term>Oxylobium obtusifolium</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Pungentis</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Uninerves</term>
               <term>Brachychiton discolor</term>
               <term>Eriochilus autumnalis</term>
               <term>Acacia lycopodifolia</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Aphyllae</term>
               <term>Polypodium rugulosum</term>
               <term>Acacia bossiaeoides</term>
               <term>Acacia chordophylla</term>
               <term>Acacia colletioides</term>
               <term>Acacia cultriformis</term>
               <term>Acacia nematophylla</term>
               <term>Acacia vomeriformis</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Armatae</term>
               <term>Didiscus albiflorus</term>
               <term>Phajus grandifolius</term>
               <term>Acacia asperulacea</term>
               <term>Acacia ephedroides</term>
               <term>Acacia Wilhelmiana</term>
               <term>Acacia sect Alatae</term>
               <term>Acacia leptoneura</term>
               <term>Acacia pravifolia</term>
               <term>Acacia pravissima</term>
               <term>Acacia sphacelata</term>
               <term>Acacia subternata</term>
               <term>Fagus Cunninghami</term>
               <term>Lindsaea linearis</term>
               <term>Tecoma floribunda</term>
               <term>Acacia cuspidata</term>
               <term>Acacia galioides</term>
               <term>Acacia imbricata</term>
               <term>Acacia pinifolia</term>
               <term>Acacia sublanata</term>
               <term>Sycios angulatus</term>
               <term>Acacia acinacea</term>
               <term>Acacia conferta</term>
               <term>Acacia Muelleri</term>
               <term>Acacia rupicola</term>
               <term>Acacia Brownii</term>
               <term>Acacia diffusa</term>
               <term>Acacia latipes</term>
               <term>Acacia lineata</term>
               <term>Acacia obliqua</term>
               <term>Acacia pungens</term>
               <term>Acacia vestita</term>
               <term>Acacia Gunnii</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 11 Oct. 1857 ¶ My dear Sir William. ¶  ¶ I gladly employ my last leisure hours before the close of the mail in giving a short summary of my botanical labours since the last mon...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">57.10.11</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no.170.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot. Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">11 Oct. 1857</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dear Sir William.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I gladly employ my last leisure hours before the close of the mail in giving a short summary of my botanical labours since the last month, having little else of interest to communicate, and I hope you will excuse the scantiness of the manuscripts transmitted this time, as my duties on the bot. garden, the preparations for the show to be held this week and several other extralabours absorbed nearly the whole of my time. Thus my labours on the Acacias are not yet closed and I can only give on this occasion a descriptive discourse on the sections Brunioideae, Triangulares, Aphyllae, Armatae, Pungentis, Alatae and Calamiformes. The elaboration of the sections Uninerves and Brachybotryae are under progress and will probably follow by the next mail.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last journey through tropical Australia, notwithstanding its great extent has brought no additions to the series Aphyllae, Alatae and Armatae, Cunningham's <name key="Acacia%20bossiaeoides">Acacia bossiaeoides</name> (if really an Acacia) not having been noticed by us.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The few remarks which I submit on these refer consequently to extra-tropical species of my former collections and are merely supplementary to Mr Benthams notes in the Linnaea.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1853).</p>
               </note> A. Muelleri I would prefer excluding from Alatae and transferring to Uninerves, as in many species of that section with which it also better agrees in habit, the phyllodia are becoming occasionally very much decurrent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The North Australian collections show only a single species of the series triangulares, seemingly Acacia deltoidea [<seg>β</seg>]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The character is ill-formed but the context suggests that <seg>β</seg> was intended; see Bentham (1842), p. 333.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>pungens [B]th<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition </seg>— obscured by binding.</p>
               </note> but [scarcely] the legitimate Cunninghamian plant. Of the very distinct A. pravissima from the Buffalo Ranges, belonging to this section, altho in habit closely approaching to A. vestita &amp; A. cultriformis, I beg to offer now a full account.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hooker did not publish M's expanded description of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">A. pravissima</seg>, which appeared in B58.03.01, p. 5, citing Bentham (1853), p. 608. M mentioned it without description in B53.10.01.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With A. Gunnii Bth I am obliged to combine A. vomeriformis A. C. according to a complete series of intermediate forms. A. obliqua A. C. amongst triangulares has the pod spirally twisted, by which character a close affinity is established of this plant with A. acinacea, amongst Uninerves, to which it likewise bears the greatest habitual resemblance. A. pravifolia doubtfully subjoint by Mr Bentham to A. sublanata, shares in the peculiarity of the cincinnate pod of the two last mentioned species and seems very remarkable for its large heartshaped bracteoles and for the pungent rigidity of its branches.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of the Pungentes group we found only two species in North Australia of which one strange to say resembles greatly the Tasmanian <name key="Acacia%20diffusa">Acacia diffusa</name> Ldl. Of Ac. colletioides, A. rupicola, A. cuspidata, A. Brownii, &amp; A. sphacelata follows the description of the fruit. The latter species A. leptoneura and A. latipes Bth belong to the flora of the country around Spencers Gulf and prove, that many of the West Australian species are extending around the Great Australian Bight. The variety of Acacia verticillata W., which I called cephalantha belongs assuredly to that species, altho the inflorescence becomes perfectly spherical. From intratropical Australia I possess two species of the Group Calamiformes, one probably A. pinifolia Bth. A. Wilhelmiana is scarcely combinable with A. nematophylla principally on account of the smallness of its pod. A. chordophylla, which we cultivate, approaches very much to A. ephedroides Benth. The Brunioideous section contains 5 species from North Australia vize A. lycopodifolia A. C., A. galioides Bth, A. conferta A. C., A. asperulacea n. sp., &amp; A. subternata n. sp., the latter remarkable for the hard flatt oblique septate pod of certain juliferae. A. imbricata from Spencers Gulf combined by Mr Bentham probably misled by very imperfect specimens, with the East Australian A. conferta ought to stand amongst the Uninerves, showing much affinity to A. lineata. It differs from A. conferta in terminal leaf-glands, angulate Branches, much narrower hardly compressed and stalked pods, one-nerved phyllodia, distinctly areolate seeds and a much dwarfer habit. No species of this section has hitherto been found in the colonies of South Australia and Victoria. To the numerous new kinds of juliferous Acaciae I have to add one from the Gulf of Carpentaria previously overlooked. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A small collection of plants arrived lately again from Mr Hill of Moreton Bay. It contains additional to our former collections <name key="Eriochilus%20autumnalis">Eriochilus autumnalis</name> (formerly not known to exist so far north), a parasitical orchid with minute flowers apparently new to the Australian Flora), <name key="Tecoma%20floribunda">Tecoma floribunda</name> A. C., <name key="Oxylobium%20obtusifolium">Oxylobium obtusifolium</name> Sweet, <name key="Boronia%20tetrathecoides">Boronia tetrathecoides</name> DC., <name key="Sycios%20angulatus">Sycios angulatus</name> L., <name key="Didiscus%20albiflorus">Didiscus albiflorus</name> D. C. <name key="Brachychiton%20discolor">Brachychiton discolor</name> and <name key="Lindsaea%20linearis">Lindsaea linearis</name> Sw. — For Professor Lindley I beg to enclose a few specimens of a Phajus from Wide Bay (East Australia) accompanied by a full description drawn up from a cultivated specimen.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably <seg style="font-style: italic; ">P. australis</seg> (B58.06.01, p. 42).</p>
               </note> I am not aware of any previous notice of the existence of this genus in Australia. The flowers are smaller than in Ph. grandifolius, but quite as beautiful.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I also enclose a few reprints of diagnostics of new plants from the papers of the Victorian Institute.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably B55.13.05, B55.13.06, and B55.13.07; however, no copies of these papers have been found in the collection of papers by M in either the bound volume (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">F. Mueller</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Opuscula</seg>) or the collections of pamphlets at Kew.</p>
               </note> My reason for publishing them here was to excite the interest of the different contributors to my collections, to continue to do so in the future.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A Polypodium, which I watched in its natural localities and found to be completely distinct from <name key="Polypodium%20rugulosum">Polypodium rugulosum</name> Lab. in coreaceous fronds exists in Gipps Land, Tasmania and New Zealand. It seems to be new and formerly confused with <name key="Polypodium%20rugulosum">Polypodium rugulosum</name>. The <name key="Brachychiton%20discolor">Brachychiton discolor</name> forms according to Mr Hill a tree 80' high.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Two fine Wardian Cases ful of plants (chiefly ferns and <name key="Fagus%20Cunninghami">Fagus Cunninghami</name>) are now officially handed over to the Colonial Storekeeper of Victoria, to be forwarded by the "Northumberland" to Kew. Most thankfully would I be to get the cases soon returned with American Mediterranean or Indian Oaks, for I am so anxious to advance this garden</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">15. Oct.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Just at the close of the mail, dear Sir William, arrives your kind letter of July 6th,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> which I beg to acknowledge. Those obligingly forwarded to Sydney will be returned only by Sir Will. Denison, probably after a good while, as his Excellency is probably now started on a voyage to Norfolk-Island.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To my excellent friends Harvey and Elsey my respects. In case those famous Botanists mentioned as working at Kew are yet there, I beg to enclose for them a few pamphlets.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">My best wishes for you and Dr Hooker.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Yours obediently</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20acinacea">Acacia acinacea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20asperulacea">Acacia asperulacea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20bossiaeoides">Acacia bossiaeoides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20Brownii">Acacia Brownii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20chordophylla">Acacia chordophylla</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20colletioides">Acacia colletioides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20conferta">Acacia conferta</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20cultriformis">Acacia cultriformis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20cuspidata">Acacia cuspidata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">Acacia deltoidea </seg>
               <seg>β</seg>
               <seg style=""> pungens</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20diffusa">Acacia diffusa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20ephedroides">Acacia ephedroides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20galioides">Acacia galioides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20Gunnii">Acacia Gunnii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20imbricata">Acacia imbricata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20latipes">Acacia latipes</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Acacia%20leptoneura">Acacia leptoneura</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20lineata">Acacia lineata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20lycopodifolia">Acacia lycopodifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20Muelleri">Acacia Muelleri</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20nematophylla">Acacia nematophylla</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20obliqua">Acacia obliqua</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20pinifolia">Acacia pinifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20pravifolia">Acacia pravifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20pravissima">Acacia pravissima</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20pungens">Acacia pungens</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20rupicola">Acacia rupicola</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20sphacelata">Acacia sphacelata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20sublanata">Acacia sublanata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20subternata">Acacia subternata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Acacia%20verticillata%20var%20cephalantha">Acacia verticillata var cephalantha</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20vestita">Acacia vestita</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20vomeriformis">Acacia vomeriformis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20Wilhelmiana">Acacia Wilhelmiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Alatae</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Aphyllae</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Armatae</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Brachybotryae</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Brunioideae</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Calamiformes</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Pungentis</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Triangulares</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Acacia, sect. Uninerves</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Boronia%20tetrathecoides">Boronia tetrathecoides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Brachychiton%20discolor">Brachychiton discolor</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Didiscus%20albiflorus">Didiscus albiflorus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eriochilus%20autumnalis">Eriochilus autumnalis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Fagus%20Cunninghami">Fagus Cunninghami</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lindsaea%20linearis">Lindsaea linearis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Oxylobium%20obtusifolium">Oxylobium obtusifolium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Phajus%20grandifolius">Phajus grandifolius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polypodium%20rugulosum">Polypodium rugulosum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sycios%20angulatus">Sycios angulatus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Tecoma%20floribunda">Tecoma floribunda</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
