<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Thus the fields in the vicinity of my present dwelling, a newly broken soil — peaty heath — with wonderful humus, form for us rye heads with 3- even 4-flowered heads, so that a full head contains 7...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1874/74-00-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>74.00.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title> ¶ Thus the fields in the vicinity of my present dwelling, a newly broken soil — peaty heath — with wonderful humus, form for us rye heads with 3- even 4-flowered heads, so that a full head contains 7...</title>
               <date when="1874">1874</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1874/74-00-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Anthoxanthum odoratum</term>
               <term>Anthoxanthum puelii</term>
               <term>Triticum</term>
               <term>Secale</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="63">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="37">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Thus the fields in the vicinity of my present dwelling, a newly broken soil — peaty heath — with wonderful humus, form for us rye heads with 3- even 4-flowered heads, so that a full head contains 7...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">74.00.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Library, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">MS is </seg>
                     <seg style="">a fragment of a sing</seg>
                     <seg style="">le sheet, found in a copy of Steudel (1855). </seg>The allusion to Eduard Graeffe in the letter suggest that this was written after 1873, when Graeffe returned to Germany from Samoa, but before he attained his permanent position in Trieste in 1875 (see n. 6). The letter is therefore dated to 1874 as the latest likely date it would have been written.<seg style=""> </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So bilden die Felder in der Nähe meiner jetzigen Wohnung, ein neuangebrochenen Boden — Torfheide — mit wundervollenem Humus, die Roggenähren mit 3- sogar 4-blüthigen Aehrchen uns, so dass eine volle Aehre 70-80 schöne Körnen enthält. Dabei bleibt das Rudiment selbst in der 4tn Blüthe noch unverändert, von einem Uebergange in die Gattung <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name> kann gar keine Rede sein (Kunth u a haben die Vereinigung von <name key="Secale">Secale</name> mit <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name> preparirt) Auch halte ich diesen Stiel der linienförmig blattartig ist, gar nicht für einen Ansatz zu einer neuen Blüthe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ausserdem zeigte sich auf Wiesen häufig mit dem <name key="Anthoxanthum%20odoratum">Anthoxanthum odoratum</name> das französische A. Puelii, das sich durch dichten Rasenwuchs auszeichnet aber durch die einjährige Wurzel u den niedrigeren Halm zurücksteht.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im gegenwärtigen Sommer werde ich einige andere Feldpflanzen beobachten, denn ich sehe immer mehr, dass das gewöhnliche bei uns am wenigsten genau gekannt ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wir erhalten endlich für Hamburg ein Gewerbemuseum, es wird ein schönes Gebäute errichtet, ich denke dass es im Laufe dieses Jahres fertig werden wird. Hamburg ist sehr günstig gelegen. Ich hoffe wir werden Berlin […]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Bottom of sheet cut off; the text that follows is on the verso.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...]mutter u hat dieser wahrscheinlich den zweiten Brief der letzteren zur Folge gehabt. Wir wollen nun sehen wie es wird. Ist der Sohn noch in Australian?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dieser Morgen erhielt ich mit der Post der Hefte der Royal Society of Tasmania (1872), u danke freundlichst für Ihren Vermittelung. Gleichzeitig kam auch ein leinener Beutel an mit der Aufschrift: Seaweed &amp; Sponges fr Westaustralia. Beim Offnen finde ich aber nur Spongien darin, keine Algen. Dies nur zur Notiz. Ihr nächster Brief, der vor Ende des Monats nicht eintreffen wird, wird wohl belehren, für wen die Spongien bestimmt sind, vielleicht für Dr Krauss, für den ich in Ihren letzten Briefe 2 Photographien neucaledonischen Insekten erhielt, die nächstens befördert werden sollen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der arme Dr Graeffe wandert noch umher und kann keine Anstellung finden, gegenwärtig ist er in Triest. Die Frau Dietrich soll nun in diesem Sommer […] nach neuester Bestimmung von Godefroy nach Neu Irland abgehen, um namentlich ethnographische Sammlungen zusammenzubringen. Geht sie hin, so bleibt das in Bezug auf die Pflanzen so wie ich Ihnen im vorigen Briefe geschrieben habe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">[…]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The letter evidently continued in a new paragraph on the part of the sheet that has been cut off, the tops of some letters in the next few words being still present. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thus the fields in the vicinity of my present dwelling, a newly broken soil — peaty heath — with wonderful humus, form for us rye heads with 3- even 4-flowered heads, so that a full head contains 70-80 beautiful grains. In so doing the vestige itself still remains unaltered in the 4th flower. There can be no question of a crossover in the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name>
               </seg> (Kunth and others have prepared the combination of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Secale">Secale</name>
               </seg> with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name>
               </seg>).<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No reference to Kunth's combination of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Secale">Secale</name>
                     </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name>
                     </seg> has been found. If the sense is a taxonomic combination of the genera, Kunth (1833-50), vol. 1, distinguished between <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name>
                     </seg> (pp. 438 ff) and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Secale">Secale</name>
                     </seg> (p. 449); if in the sense of hybridization, Focke (1881) records only one reported attempt to hybridize the genera, commencing in 1873 and reported in A. Wilson (1876). Neither Bentham &amp; Hooker (1862-83), vol. 3, part 2, pp. 1203-4, nor Steudel (1855), vol. 1, pp. 341-7 mention Kunth's having united these genera.</p>
               </note> I also I regard this stem, which is lineal leaf-like, by no means as an apophysis to a new flower. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In addition the French <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Anthoxanthum%20puelii">Anthoxanthum puelii</name>
               </seg> appeared in fields frequently with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">A. odoratum</seg>, which is characterized by thick grass growth, but takes second place through the annual root and the low blade.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the current summer I shall observe some other field plants, as I see more and more that the commonplace among us is the least known.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finally we are getting an industrial museum for Hamburg.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Founded 1874, but present building built 1873-75.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> A beautiful building will be erected. I think that it will be finished in the course of this year. Hamburg is very favourably located. I hope we will […] Berlin […]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See n. 2 above.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[…]and this has probably resulted in the the second letter of the latter. We will now see how it goes. Is the son still in Australia? </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This morning with the post I received the part of the Royal Society of Tasmania (1872) and thank you most graciously for your intervention.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder had been elected a corresponding member of the Royal Society of Tasmania at its meeting of 14 April 1868 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Papers and proceedings of the Royal Society of Tasmania for 1868</seg>, p. 4). There is no indication in the Society's Pa<seg style="font-style: italic; ">pers and proceedings for 1871 </seg>(published 1872) nor in the issues for the following three years that M was involved in a specific item related to Sonder; it is likely that Sonder had not received the 1872 issue of the journal and that M had intervened to ensure that he received it.</p>
               </note> At the same time a canvas bag also arrived with the label: Seaweed &amp; Sponges fr Westaustralia. On opening, however, I found only sponges in it, no algae. This only to note. Your next letter, which will not arrive before the end of the month, will probably say for whom the sponges are destined, perhaps Dr Krauss, for whom I received 2 photographs of New Caledonian insects in your last letter that will be forwarded in the near future.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Poor Dr Graeffe is still wandering around and cannot find a position. At present he is in Trieste.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Eduard Graeffe had returned from Samoa in 1873, and was appointed an inspector at the Zoological Station in Trieste in 1875.</p>
               </note> According to the latest stipulation of Godefroy, Mrs Dietrich is now to go off this summer to New Ireland<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">At the time part of German New Guinea, now part of Papua New Guinea.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> to assemble especially ethnographic collections.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Although the ADB entry for Amalie Dietrich asserts that 'on 4 March 1873, accompanied by two pet eagles, she returned to Hamburg', the major source for that article, a biography by her daughter, has been shown (Sumner (1988)) to be unreliable in detail. However, in this case an article in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hamburger Nachtrichten,</seg> 15 March 1873, p. 4 reports that two eagles brought by her were exhibited at the Hamburg Zoological Garden, supporting that assertion. Sonder saw Dietrich regularly after her return to Hamburg; in <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>W. Sonder to F. von Krauss 11 June 1873 (in this edition as M73-06-11), he spoke of hearing her discuss problems of collecting, and in W. Sonder to F. von Krauss, 8 March 1875 (in this edition as M75-03-08), he reported that she was expecting to go to Australia again to collect Queensland lung-fish. In the event, she never returned to Australia or the Pacific.</p>
               </note> If she goes there, then in reference to the plants what I have written to you in the previous letter remains so.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[…]<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">See n. 3 above.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anthoxanthum%20odoratum">Anthoxanthum odoratum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anthoxanthum%20puelii">Anthoxanthum puelii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Secale">Secale</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Triticum">Triticum</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
