<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ I venture to send you the result of my experience in Thistle cutting. Thistles are annuals, if cut low enough they do not grown again. In waste land they should be cut about one inch below the grou...</title>
            <author>James Ward</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/60-01-21 Ward - Service.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>A60/302, unit 719, VPRS 44/P inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>60.01.21</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>James Ward</author>
               <title> ¶ I venture to send you the result of my experience in Thistle cutting. Thistles are annuals, if cut low enough they do not grown again. In waste land they should be cut about one inch below the grou...</title>
               <date when="1860-01-21">1860-01-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/60-01-21 Ward - Service.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Service</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ I venture to send you the result of my experience in Thistle cutting. Thistles are annuals, if cut low enough they do not grown again. In waste land they should be cut about one inch below the grou...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">60.01.21</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">James Ward to James Service</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">A60/302, unit 719, VPRS 44/P inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Transcribed 25.3.93. To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I venture to send you the result of my experience in Thistle cutting. Thistles are annuals, if cut low enough they do not grown again. In waste land they should be cut about one inch below the ground, this method destroys the plant entirely. If they are cut in this manner just as they begin to blossom there is no seed to scatter, and milch cows feed greedily upon them, when they have been cut one day, and become partialy withered. The second crop appears in about three weeks after the first is destroyed, but owing to the lateness of the season, they do not grow to the same size before they flower, the second cutting is more troublesome than laborious. A third crop of the weakest and immature seed will appear in the summer, but they are easier disposed of than the second crop seldom growing above six inches in height.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I wish to point out the reason why I differ from a gentleman of Mr Wm Wade's experience. (I presume it is Mr Wade of Belford). If the thistles are cut with a mowing machine or scythe a stem will be left with buds upon it, each capable of becoming a separate stem, and the first cutting on alters the character of the plant and delays its growth. My plan of hand cutting eradicates the plant.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If the flowers are perfect when the Thistles are cut, the seed will ripen and distribute itself although the plant is dead and dying. They will not burn until the mischief is done. Cows and goats should, wherever it is practicable, follow the cutters, it is the most economical and effectual way of getting rid of the weeds. Two years will clear any district if properly attended to. I trust that you will excuse the liberty I have taken in this matter, but I am confident that Dr Meuller will confirm my statement as to the entire destruction of the plant, when cut through the crown of the root below the buds and leaves of the stem. Also as to the seed coming to maturity at a low temperature after the plant is cut, in fact the seed is so light, and contains such a small amount of moisture compared with the stems, that it is only common sense to expect such a result.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Any money spent by the government or the farmers to cut Thistles, and leave a stem above ground is wasteful.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Thistles will not be good specimen plants but they will carry several stems and produce much seed. Hand cutting with a sharp long handled hoe, or, as I found and used, a carpenters adze upon a long handle, is the quickest, cheapest, and most effectual plan of extirpating thistles. If any crops at all admit a scythe to be used, it will be the weak plants of the second years growth. I need not remind you of the distances thistle seed will travel in extirpating them it will be necessary to do so throughout an entire district, for unless there are high and densely wooded ranges defining the valley, it will be useless to attempt a portion of the lowland only. Again apologising for the length of my letter.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 23 January 1860 Service instructed that Ward's letter be acknowledged with thanks.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
