<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ [...] will be happy to facilitate such a literary exchange. Therefore, if you wish to send a notice to the Bavarian Academy, I ask you to address it as follows: ¶  ¶ To the Royal Academy of Science...</title>
            <author>Carl von Martius</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/66-02-15Martius-Haast.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </msName>
                  <msName>Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.02.15</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl von Martius</author>
               <title> ¶ [...] will be happy to facilitate such a literary exchange. Therefore, if you wish to send a notice to the Bavarian Academy, I ask you to address it as follows: ¶  ¶ To the Royal Academy of Science...</title>
               <date when="1866-02-15">1866-02-15</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/66-02-15Martius-Haast.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Progress note</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ [...] will be happy to facilitate such a literary exchange. Therefore, if you wish to send a notice to the Bavarian Academy, I ask you to address it as follows: ¶  ¶ To the Royal Academy of Science...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">According to the Library/archive catalogue this should read </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">66.02.15</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Carl von Martius to Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Haast family papers</seg>, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> [...]<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS is incomplete, an unknown amount of text is missing at the beginning of the letter. The letter is written in an unknown hand and signed by Martius.</p>
               </note> wird mit Vergnügen bereit sein, einen solchen litterarischen Verkehr zu vermitteln. Sollten Sie daher eine Mittheilung an die Bayerische Akademie machen wollen, so bitte ich Sie, solche folgenderweise zu adressiren:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An die königl. bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften, zu Handen ihres Classensekretär Geheimer Rath Dr. von Martius. In dem amtlichen Anschreiben ersuche ich Sie auch anzugeben, an wen nach London die diesseitigen Sendungen zu richten sind, und unter welcher Adresse. Es sollte mich sehr freuen, wenn unsere wissenschaftlichen Arbeiten auf solche Weise auch bei Ihnen Eingang finden könnten. Sollten sie dort für die Gründung einer Bibliothek auch ältere Schriften von unserer Akademie gerne empfangen, so bitte ich Sie, dies in Ihrem Schreiben an mich direct auszusprechen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich komme nochmals auf den pflanzengeographischen Inhalt Ihres Briefes zurück. Die von Ihnen angeführten europäischen Nutzpflanzen und Unkräuter sind wohl durch die Colonie eingeschleppt. Anders mag es sich mit Lycopodium und andern Cryptogamen verhalten, deren Cosmopolitismus ausser Zweifel ist. Ich betrachte solche Arten analog manchen Nebengebilden im Organismus, welche eine bestimmte Rolle in der Entwicklung desselben spielen, ohne dass es uns [immer] gelingt, ihre Bedeutung vollständig zu begreifen. Auch die niedrigern Cryptogamen und insbesondere die Pilze, welche Nees von Esenbeck eine nachbildliche Vegetation genannt hat, kommen vielleicht manchmal als complemetäre Geschöpfe neben andern auf die Bühne. Es wäre daher sehr verdienstlich, dieselben sorgfältig zu sammeln unter Bemerkung ihrer Unterlagen. Sehr wichtig sind für pflanzengeographische Betrachtungen auch die Algen, welche an der Südsee viel häufiger als zum Bspl. in Amerika vorkommen. Ich wage daher Ihre wohlwollende Berücksichtigung meiner Wünsche auch auf diese Gewächse auszudehnen. Beiliegend empfangen Sie auch meine Photographie. Möge Ihr Anblick einen Mann vergegenwärtigen, der Ihren rühmlichen Erfolgen mit der grössten Sympathie zugethan ist, und sich durch die Überzeugung beglückt fühlen wird, dass Sie den Ausdruck seiner hochachtungsvollen Ergebenheit in seiner ganzen Aufrichtigkeit und Wärme gerne entgegennehmen. Leben Sie wohl, zum Heile der Wissenschaft!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Martius</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">München, den 15 Febr. 1866.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...] will be happy to facilitate such a literary exchange. Therefore, if you wish to send a notice to the Bavarian Academy, I ask you to address it as follows:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To the Royal Academy of Sciences, care of its Section Secretary, Privy Councillor Dr von Martius. Would you please indicate in the official cover letter, to whom in London transmissions from here are to be sent, and under what address. I should be very pleased, if our scientific works could thus be introduced also to your country. Should you care to receive there for the founding of the library also older publications from our Academy, then please mentions this in your letter to me directly. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I want to touch again on the phytogeographical content of your letter. The European useful plants and weeds listed by you have probably been introduced as a result of the colonisation. The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Lycopodium</seg> and the other cryptogams may be a different story, their cosmopolitan distribution is without doubt, and I consider such species analogous to a number of secondary forms in the organism, which play a special role in its development, even though we do not always succeed in completely understanding their significance. The lower cryptogams and in particular the fungi, which Nees von Esenbeck called an [imitating vegetation],<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">lit. translation, or perhaps a subsidiary of supplementary vegetation?; I am not sure what exactly Martius means by this. Ask Tom, he might even know where and in what context Nees made this statement. (Nees travelled in S. America around the same time? or a little later? as Martius. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> do perhaps sometimes appear on the scene as complementary creations beside others.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Is he referring to symbiotic or host-specific relationships? (of which we now know a lot more, than they did then, e.g chemical interactions etc.)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> It would therefore be very meritorious to carefully collect these and note their details.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">This could also be translated as 'note their substratum'.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The algae are also very important for phytogeographic considerations; these are much more frequent in the southern oceans than for instance in America. I therefore take the liberty to extend your benevolent consideration of my wishes also to the algae. Enclosed you also receive my photograph. May it bring before your eyes a man, who follows your praiseworthy successes with the greatest sympathy and who feels happy in the conviction, that you will be pleased to accept the expression of his respectful devotion in its complete sincerity and warmth. Keep well, for the benefit of science!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Martius.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Munich, 15 February 1866.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Translated by D. Sinkora, 25 October 2000.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
