<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Esteemed Sir and dear friend, ¶  ¶ Here, in the beautiful alpine country beside the blue eye of the Kochelsee, where I have been spending the holidays with my family for many years, I had the great jo...</title>
            <author>Carl von Martius</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/66-10-01Martius - Haast.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </msName>
                  <msName>Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.10.01</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl von Martius</author>
               <title>Esteemed Sir and dear friend, ¶  ¶ Here, in the beautiful alpine country beside the blue eye of the Kochelsee, where I have been spending the holidays with my family for many years, I had the great jo...</title>
               <date when="1866-10-01">1866-10-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/66-10-01Martius - Haast.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Progress note</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Esteemed Sir and dear friend, ¶  ¶ Here, in the beautiful alpine country beside the blue eye of the Kochelsee, where I have been spending the holidays with my family for many years, I had the great jo...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">According to the Library/archive catalogue this should read </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">66.10.01</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Carl von Martius to Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Haast family papers</seg>, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter written on letterhead paper, showing a framed landscape view, with the caption 'Schlehdorf | von Au aus | Artist. Anst. [Peiffenstein &amp; Rosch]' <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">(the print of the source is so tiny, that I have trouble reading it even with my 10 x magnification field lens!)</seg> [Schlehdorf, viewed from Au. Artistic establishment Peiffenstein &amp; Rosch]. — Schlehdorf is S-SW of Munich in the Bavarian Alps on the NW shore of the Kochelsee.</p>
               </note>Hochgeehrter Herr u. lieber Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hier, in dem schönen Alpenlande am blauen Auge des Kochelsees, wo ich seit vielen Jahren mit meiner Familie die Ferien zubringe, habe ich die grosse Freude gehabt, Ihren inhaltsschweren Br v. 28 Juni gestern zu erhalten. Ich sage Ihnen für die vielen Beweise v. liebenswürdigster Theilnahme, welche er enthält, meinen wärmsten, wahrlich tief gefühlten Dank. Aber solchen Bewegungen des Herzens würde ich untreu werden, wenn ich nicht am Anfang mr.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">meiner.</p>
               </note> Antwort auch bezeugte, dass ich an der Familientrauer Antheil nehme, die Sie heimgesucht hat in dem schmerzvollen Ereignis mit Ihrem Schwager. Möchten Sie u. die Ihrigen (ich nehme an, dass Sie verheirathet sind) Sich über jenen Trauerfall bald erheben können in jenen Überzeugungen, die ja allein uns über die zahlreichen Stürme dieses Erdenwallens siegreich hinweg führen!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was hätte für mich erfreulicher seyn können, als die Gewissheit, dass Sie, ein rüstiger, hoffnungs- wie thatenreicher Forscher in jenem fernen wunderbaren Eilande, diesem subtropischen Island, meiner so freundlich gedacht haben, als Sie [zwischen] Schnee u. Eis hinaufstiegen, [von] [...]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">3 or 4 words <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">MS badly foxed or otherwise discoloured, — photocopiers don't like that.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> [Gipfeln] auf die Glorie des südlichen Firmamentes zu blicken! Ich lege einen sehr kleinen Werth an das, was ich für die Wissenschaft geleistet habe, bin dadurch befestigt in der Überzeugung, dass Mount Martius, den Sie so wohlwollend nach mir genannt haben, viel bessere Namen hätte führen können. Sehen Sie also zu, dass ich meine Freude über die Taufe eben so sehr aus <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">der</hi>
               </seg> Gewissheit ableite, "dort ist ein Mann gestanden, der dich nur im Geiste liebt", als aus der andern, "dass einstens, wenn wir beide nicht mehr sind, gar manche im Anblick des imposanten Eiskolosses fragen werden, wer war denn Jener"? <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Vivitur ingenio, caetera mortis erunt!</seg> So viele leuchtende Geister am liter. Himmel habe ich schon untergehen sehen; — aber immer noch glänzen ihre Reflexlichter auf dem ewig bewegten, unendlichen Ocean des Wissens! das ist ein Theil unserer Unsterblichkeit! — —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie, lieber Haast, sind in der glücklichen Lage im grossen Style<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">18th century spelling of Stile.</p>
               </note> Entdeckungen zu machen, und das Capital unserer Kenntnisse zu vermehren; eine allerdings bevorzugte Stellg<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Stellung.</p>
               </note> verleiht Ihnen überdies noch die Gelegenheit, Ehrenbezeugnung eigner Art zu ertheilen. So nehmen Sie meinen herzlichen Dank dafür an. Ich schliesse daran noch einen zweiten für das [reale] Geschenk, dass Sie mir mit der Flora jenes Gebirgs und mit andern Mittheilung. machen. Bereits habe ich nach London an Mss. Dalgety [Dulroy]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Ask Arthur, presumably Haast's London shipping agents. Or they might be mentioned in the Haast biography.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> et Co. geschrieben, mir die Kiste durch meinen Agenten in Hamburg <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">H. G. F. C. Röding</hi>
               </seg> zu senden. Sie wird wahrscheinl. in solcher Zeit ankommen, dass ich in der November Sitzung der math. physik. Classe einen Bericht über Ihre Mittheilungen erstatten u. die Vogelbälge an das Zool. Cabinet, die Samen an d. bot. Garten, die Bücher an d. Akademie abgeben kann. Ich werde es mir angeleg seyn lassen, Ihnen für Ihre Sammlungen ein Reciprocum zu verschaffen. Zumal für die Bibliothek, welche Sie anlegen, hoffe ich gute Beiträge zu bekommen. Vielleicht ist es geeignet dieselbe auch mit älteren Academicis zu bedenken. Jedenfalls wünsche ich über den Character, den Sie Ihrer öff.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">öffentlichen.</p>
               </note> Bibliothek zu geben wünschen, noch einige weitere Erklärungen. Weil aber hiemit eine Verbindung zwischen Ihnen und unserer Ak. eingeleitet wird, so wär' es mir auch angenehm, gelegentl. ausser Ihren Schriften für d. Akad. ein <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Curricul vitae</seg> zu erhalten. Eine Akademie soll nicht ohne persönliche Beziehung zu denen arbeiten, welche sich ihren Interessen hülfreich erweisen. Unser Freund Ferd. Müller ist heuer zum Corresp.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Correspondenten.</p>
               </note> unserer Ak. ernannt worden. Da die Zahl unserer Mitglieder eine gewisse Beschränkung hat, so wird eine längere Verbindung jedenfalls wünschenwerth, bis eine Vacanz eintritt. Wenn ich übrigens <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in anderer Weise</hi>
               </seg> Ihrer literarischen Beziehung zum Vaterlande dienen kann, so versteht es sich von selbst, dass ich hierin nicht lässig seyn werde. <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auf populäre Artikel, die in unseren Zeitungen, Hierüber künftig.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hierüber künftig. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">interline</seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">u. auf literar. Notizen, die als Correspondenzen in unsern Sitzgsberichten<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sitzungsberichten.</p>
               </note> d. Akademie bekannt gemacht werden könnten, mache ich Sie besonders aufmerksam.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es thut sich in jenen Antipoden eine neue Welt auf, zum Erstaunen u. Entzücken der europ. Pfleger der Wissenschaft, und wir gestehen gerne, dass Alles von dort uns erst orientiren muss. So wäre es auch eine glückl. Erwerbung, wenn wir die geogr. Erhebungen u. Karten, welche bei Ihnen auf Rechnung der Regierung (in einer bewundernswürdigen Vollendung) erscheinen, erhielten, denn in unsern Karten[handlungen] sieht man sich darnach vergeblich um. Bedenken Sie [überhaupt] dass unsere mediterran. Existenz uns von Vielem aus[schliesst], was das Alles trannende u. Alles verbindende [...]<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Two words <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>.</p>
               </note> bringt. Grosse Blicke in die Pflanzengeographie lassen sich bei Ihnen thun, und es schwimmen hundert Fragen vor meinem Geiste. Aber heute will ich von diesen noch keine verlautbaren. Ich verspare es auf die Ansicht Ihrer gütigen Zusendg. Nur das will ich noch bemerken, dass ich einen sehr grossen Werth auf die Kenntnis der isolirten Inselfloren in Ihren Meeren lege, weil sie ungeheuer weittragende Vermuthung. u. [...] heranfordert. Wenn Sie mir daher von den Chatham, Norfolk u. a. Inseln Etwas schicken, so werde ich es wie Diamanten beachten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine ethnographische Studie über den Zusammenhang Ihrer Autochthonen mit den südamerkan. Puetches, Tehuelkets ist <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in voti</seg>. Ich finde somatisch gar manche Anklänge, und wenn diese Völker nicht erst seit d. [Lander] stehen, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wie</hi>
               </seg> sie eingewandert wären, müsste man nicht <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">annehmen</hi>
               </seg>, dass hier Brücken abgebrochen sind? Aber die Osterinsel! neben dem menschenlosen Sala Y Gomez, dass Chamisso verherrlicht hat, diese Osterinsel auf der 27 F.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Fuss.</p>
               </note> hohe menschliche Stammstatuen stehen, die die jetzige Bevölkerung wie Mythen anstaunt, was ist das? Richten Sie doch gelegentl. die Blicke eines Seefahrers auf dieses einsame, so selten berührte Eiland.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn ich wieder in M.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">München.</p>
               </note> bin u. die akad. Arbeit. beginnen, werde ich wohl bald Gelegenheit haben, Ihnen weitere Meldung zu machen. — — In diesem Augenblick kommen Briefe aus der Stadt u. der erste, den ich eröffne, von Ferd. Müller meldet dass M'cIntyre am Fieber gestorben! Wie beklagensreich dies neue Opfer des unermüdlichen Forscherdranges. Dante setzt den <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">gerechten</hi>
               </seg> Fürsten in den Jupiter. Edle Geister, die ihre Existenz an die Wahrheit opferten verdienen ähnliches Paradies. [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Haec anima qua</seg>.] — — Sie aber, lieber Haast, leben Sie [gesund] [froh] [lang],<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Conjectural readings, these words are virtually <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>.</p>
               </note> wie es wünscht</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>dankbar ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">[Schlehdorf]<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Conjectural reading.</p>
               </note> am Kochlsee<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kochelsee.</p>
               </note> 1 Octobr. 1866.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Sir and dear friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Here, in the beautiful alpine country beside the blue eye of the Kochelsee, where I have been spending the holidays with my family for many years, I had the great joy yesterday of receiving your letter of 28 June with the weighty contents.<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Sara, you could ask in Munich, if Haast's letters to Martius are there. They have the M and Sonder letters (or at least some of them), so why indeed not Haast's?!</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I offer you my warmest, deeply felt thanks for the many demonstrations of your most benevolent interest it contains. But I would be unfaithful to such movements of the heart, did I not also show at the beginning of my reply, that I empathise with you in your family bereavement, that has afflicted you in the painful events with your brother-in-law.<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">George Dobson,aged 26, older brother of Haast's wife Mary, was brutally murdered by bushrangers on 28 May 1866. His body was not found until 6 July. The murderers were caught, tried, sentenced and hanged in October. During this time Mary Haast was in the early stages of pregnancy with her second child. (ref. Haast biogr.) See also M to Haast, 6 August 1866.</p>
               </note> May you and yours (I assume that you are married) soon be able to rise above that grief in the strength of that faith, that alone can lead us victorious through the numerous storms of this earthly sojourn!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What could possibly have been more pleasing to me, than the knowledge, that you, a vigorous, hopeful and active explorer in that distant, wondrous isle, this subtropical island, so kindly remembered me, when you climbed up through snow and ice, to gaze from [...]<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">German text illegible</seg>.</p>
               </note> peaks at the glory of the southern firmament! I put a very small value on what I have achieved for science, and I am therefore firm in my conviction, that Mount Martius,<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Details about the expedition and the naming of Mount Martius should be in the Haast biography.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> which you so kindly named after me, could have gone under much better names. Be aware, therefore, that I obtain my pleasure at the christening just as much from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">that</hi>
               </seg> certainty, that 'there stood a man, who loved me truly in spirit', as from the one, that 'one day, when both of us are gone, many will look at the imposing ice colossus and ask: and who was that?'<note xml:id="ftn21" type="footnote" n="21">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">What a refreshing attitude after M!</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Vivitur ingenio, caetera mortis erunt!</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn22" type="footnote" n="22">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Get Rod to translate this.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I have seen so many brilliant stars on the literary firmament depart; — but their reflected lights still shine on the eternally moving, infinite ocean of knowledge! — that is part of our immortality! — —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You, dear Haast, are in the happy position to make discoveries on a grand scale, and to increase the capital of our knowledge; in addition an admittedly privileged position gives you the opportunity to hand out marks of esteem of a special kind. So, receive my sincere thanks for it. I add to this another thank you for the [real] gift you gave to me with the flora of that mountain range and with other transmissions. I have already written to London to Messrs Dalgety [Dulroy] &amp; Co., so send me the case through my agents in Hamburg, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">H. G. F. C. Röding</hi>
               </seg>. It will probably arrive in good time, so that I can make a report about your consignment to the November meeting of the mathematical-physical section and pass on the bird skins to the Zoological Museum, the seeds to the Botanic Gardens, and the books to the Academy. I shall make it my business to obtain reciprocal material for your collections. I hope to obtain good contributions especially for the library that you are founding. Perhaps it is suitable to provide it also with older academic writings. In any case, I wish to obtain a few more details about the character you wish your public library to have. But because this initiates a communication between you and our Academy, I should be please to receive, when convenient, a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">curriculum vitae</seg>, apart from your publications for the Academy. An academy should not work without any personal connection to those, who prove themselves supportive to its interests. Our friend, Ferd. Mueller, has today been elected a Corresponding Member of our Academy. As the number of our members has a certain limit, a prolonged connection is certainly desirable, until a vacancy occurs. By the way, if I can serve your literary relationship with the fatherland <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in any other way</hi>
               </seg>, it goes without saying, that I shall not be remiss. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I draw your attention particularly to more popular articles, that could be published in our newspapers, — more about this later, — and to literary notices, which could be placed as correspondence in the proceedings of the Academy.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A new world is oping up in those antipodes, to the astonishment and delight of the European promoters of science, and we are happy to confess, that we still have to come to terms with everything from there. It would thus be a happy acquisition, if we could obtain the geographic topography and maps, which are produced there (in such admirable perfection) at the Government's expense, because one looks for them in vain in our book stores. Just remember, that our Mediterranean existence excludes us from much, that brings [...]<note xml:id="ftn23" type="footnote" n="23">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">German text <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>.</p>
               </note> all that divides and all that unites. Great views into phytogeography can be taken there, and a hundred questions are running through my mind. But for today I will keep quiet about these. I save that until I have seen your kind consignment. I want to remark just this now, that I place a great deal of value on the isolated island floras in your oceans, because they call for extremely far-reaching speculations and [...].<note xml:id="ftn24" type="footnote" n="24">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">German text <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>.</p>
               </note> Therefore, if you can send me anything from the Chatham, Norfolk, and other islands, I should look on it, as if it were diamonds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An ethnographical study on the connection between your aborigines with the South American <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">[Puetches]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn25" type="footnote" n="25">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">check German encyclopaedia, I assume some S. Amer. Indian tribe or population.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Tehuelche<note xml:id="ftn26" type="footnote" n="26">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Native inhabitants of northern Patagonia.</p>
               </note> is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in voti</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn27" type="footnote" n="27">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Prayer (Latin). <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">(= desired? requested?) </seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">
                        <hi rend="underline">Rod?</hi>
                     </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I find there many somatic similarities, and if these people are not present only since the [...], <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">how</hi>
               </seg> they immigrated, must one not <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">assume</hi>
               </seg>, that bridges have been destroyed here?<note xml:id="ftn28" type="footnote" n="28">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">This sentence does not really make sense in German, — it is not my translation!</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> But Easter Island! — next to the uninhabited Sala y Gomez, glorified by Chamisso,<note xml:id="ftn29" type="footnote" n="29">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Adalbert von Chamisso, German naturalist, traveller, poet. Accompanied Russian expedition (under Kotzebue? about 1834?) <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">check German encyclopaedia.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> this Easter Island, where 27 feet tall human statues are standing, before which the present population stands in wonder, what is that? Why don't you direct the attention of some seafarer towards this isolated, so rarely visited island, if the occasion arises.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When I am back in Munich and the academic work resumes, I should soon have opportunity, to report to you further. — — — Just now letters arrive from the township, and the first one I open, from Ferd. Müller, reports that McIntyre died of fever.<note xml:id="ftn30" type="footnote" n="30">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Duncan McIntyre, leader of the Ladies' Leichhardt Search Expedition. See M to Martius, 27 July 1866.</p>
               </note> How lamentable, this new victim of the untiring urge to explore. Dante places the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">just</hi>
               </seg> prince on Jupiter. Noble spirits, who sacrificed their existence to truth, deserve a similar paradise. [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Haec anima qua</seg>.]<note xml:id="ftn31" type="footnote" n="31">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Ask Rod to have a look at this, it is practically illegible, this was the best I could do with it, Does it make sense?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> — — But you, dear Haast, live [healthy], happy, and [long], this wishes you</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>gratefully devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Schlehdorf am Kochelsee, 1 October 1866.<note xml:id="ftn32" type="footnote" n="32">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Translated by D. Sinkora, 2 November 2000.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
