<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>My dearest Sir, ¶  ¶ The consignment announced in your kindly letter of 28 June [1866] ¶  has safely reached me and filled me with very great joy. ¶  ¶ The enclosures for President Carus and Dr Friedl...</title>
            <author>Carl von Martius</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1860-9/67-01-22Martius-Haast.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </msName>
                  <msName>Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.01.22</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl von Martius</author>
               <title>My dearest Sir, ¶  ¶ The consignment announced in your kindly letter of 28 June [1866] ¶  has safely reached me and filled me with very great joy. ¶  ¶ The enclosures for President Carus and Dr Friedl...</title>
               <date when="1867-01-22">1867-01-22</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1860-9/67-01-22Martius-Haast.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Progress note</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">My dearest Sir, ¶  ¶ The consignment announced in your kindly letter of 28 June [1866] ¶  has safely reached me and filled me with very great joy. ¶  ¶ The enclosures for President Carus and Dr Friedl...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">According to the Library/archive catalogue this should read </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </p>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">67.01.22</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Carl von Martius to Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Haast family papers</seg>, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Written on letterhead paper, with a decorated shield surmounted by a crowned eagle in the upper left corner, underneath the inscription 'ACADEMIA CAESAREA GERMANICA | LEOPOLDINO-CAROLINA'. — Letter written in an unknown hand and signed by Martius.</p>
               </note>Mein theuerster Herr!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die durch Ihr liebes Schreiben vom 28. Juni angekündigte Sendung ist am 11. Januar richtig in meine Hände gekommen und hat mich mit der grössten Freude erfüllt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Beipäcke an Präsidenten Carus u. Dr Friedleben sind auf der Stelle abgesendet worden. Der Erstere meldet, dass er Ihnen selbst schreiben werde. Mit der Pflanzensendung haben Sie mir ein unaussprechliches Vergnügen gemacht, und ich bringe Ihnen dafür meinen herzlichsten Dank dar, — werde auch keine Gelegenheit versäumen, wodurch ich von Worten zur That übergehen kann. Am 12. habe ich in Ihrem Namen die Schriften für die Akademie in einer Sitzung übergeben, und weil ich keine Sammlung von Thieren habe, gemäss Ihrer Bestimmung die Vogelbälge der königl. Sammlung übergeben. Sie sind von Prof. von Siebold mit Freude aufgenommen worden, und ich bin beauftragt Ihnen, geehrter Herr, im Namen der Akademie für Alles, was Sie ihr zugewendet haben, den lebhaftesten Dank auszusprechen. Ich habe Veranlassung genommen zu beantragen, dass von den Akademischen Schriften eine möglichst vollständige Reihe an Sie abgeschickt würden. Ich denke, dass die Sitzungsberichte, die gelehrten Anzeigen und vielleicht auch die Denkschriften [...]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg> (2 words)</p>
               </note> sein werden. Weil ich aber nicht weiss, welche Ausdehnung Sie der dort zu gründenden Bibliothek geben, wünsche ich hierüber noch eine besondere Erklärung auf einem Blatte, dass ich der Akademie als offizielles Actenstück vorlegen kann. Als Repräsentanten des deutschen Geistes werden wohl auch historische und philologisch-philosophische Arbeiten dort nicht unangehm sein, wenn schon die Richtung in einer neuen Kolonie zunächst auf das Praktische hingehen muss. Sollten Sie später Gelegenheit finden, auch merkwürdige Mineralien, besonders oryktognostische Stücke zu senden, so werden Sie unsern grossen Mineralogen von Kobell damit eine grosse Freude machen. Auch wird es mir angenehm sein zu erfahren, welchen Speditionsweg für grössere Kisten Sie uns empfehlen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was nun Ihre Pflanzensammlung betrifft, so war ich ganz entzückt, mir den physiognomischen Character der dortigen Vegetation mehr zur Klarheit zu bringen. Lebhaft war der Eindruck einer stärkeren Verwandtschaft mit der aussertropischen Vegetation Südamerikas, als mit Neuholland. Besonders die Dolden und die [Syngemischten], die Gattung [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">discaria</seg>], Gentianen und Scrophularinen erinnern viel an die Pflanzen der chilesischen Alpen. Dagegen Anklänge an Neuholland selten. Entsprechend diesem Eindrucke war es mir interessant, einige Vogelnamen zu finden, welche an Worte in der [Tupie]sprache erinnern, wie <seg style="font-style: italic; ">maco-maco</seg> (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">maco</seg> = Dieb); <seg style="font-style: italic; ">tui</seg>, in Neuseeland ein Singvogel ohne Zeifel [...]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">oliomayentisch? chomayentisch? ohomayentisch? <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>In English the ending would probably be -mayentic [= -Mayan?].</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> genannt (Tupie, ein Perikit.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">= Parakeet?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Auch das Wort <seg style="font-style: italic; ">pitangi-tangi</seg> erinnert an ein Tupiwort, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">piter</seg> schlürfen, aussaugen, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">angi</seg> Wohlgeruch u.s.w. Da ich überhaupt der Meinung bin, dass zwischen Neuseeland und Südamerika ein Continent gelegen sein könnte, welches in unvordenklicher Zeit vom Ocean verschlungen worden ist, so scheinen mir alle Beziehungen der gegenwärtigen Länder von grosser Bedeutung. Die Physionomie der Neuseeländer, und die Sitte, den Körper zu punktiren, nähert diese Völker besonders den kühnen Pampasindianern, deren Gesichtszüge ebebso markirt sind, wie die der Neuseeländer. Sollte ein Vocabular der Maorisprache bei Ihnen gedruckt sein, so würden Sie mich durch dessen Mittheilung sehr verbinden. Seit Jahren beschäftigt mich eine Arbeit über die wilden Völkerschaften von Brasilien. Der eine Band, welcher Glossarien enthält, ist 1863 gedruckt. Der Andere mit den ethnographischen Schilderungen steht nahe am Abschluss. So bald er fertig ist, werde ich das Vergnügen haben, Ihnen das Werk zu senden. Ich darf nicht übergehen, dass mir der grösste Theil der von Ihnen gütigst übersendeten Pflanzen auch dem Namen nach unbekannt ist, und dass ich mich deshalb bemühen werde, wenigstens das Wichtigere in England bestimmt zu [sehen],<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">conjectural reading, MS damaged.</p>
               </note> wo Hooker u Bentham die grössten Autoritäten für diese Flora sind. Weder die Augen noch die Musse reichen hin, um die Bestimmungen durchzuführen und ich würde Ihnen daher sehr verbunden sein, wenn Sie bei der Auswahl von Pflanzen der nördlichen Insel, welche Sie mir gütigst in Aussicht stellen, wenigstens die Gattungsnamen hinzufügen wollten. Ich bleibe aber durch diese Ihre gütige Mittheilung in Ihrer Schuld, und werde mich bemühen, so viel an mir ist, Ihnen gefällig zu sein. Für's Erste ersuche ich Sie noch mir in Ihrem nächsten Brief ein kurzes <seg style="font-style: italic; ">curriculum vitae</seg> und die Liste Ihrer Schriften mitzutheilen. Ich hoffe, dass meine erste Antwort vom 2 Oct. 66 zugegangen seyn werde, und wünsche von Herzen, dass Sie in Gesundheit und heiterer Kraft sich Ihrer hohen und rühmlich anerkannten Mission hingeben können. In dankbarer Anhänglichkeit</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr ganz ergebenster</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">München, den 22. Januar 1867.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dearest Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The consignment announced in your kindly letter of 28 June [1866]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">(unless it is in the Martius correspondence in Munich).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> has safely reached me and filled me with very great joy.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The enclosures for President Carus and Dr Friedleben were forwarded at once. The first reports, that he wants to write to you personally. You have given me inexpressible pleasure with the collection of plants, and I offer you my sincerest thanks for it, — and shall not miss any opportunity, to progress from words to deeds. In a meeting on the 12th [of January 1867] I have passed on the publications for the Academy in your name, and because I have no collection of animals, I have given the bird skins to the Royal collections, according to your instructions. They were accepted with joy by Professor Siebold, and I have been asked, esteemed Sir, to express in the name of the Academy the deepest gratitude for everything you have donated to it. I have used the occasion to request, that a series of the academic publications as complete as possible be transmitted to you. I expect, that the proceedings, the learned notices, and perhaps also the commemorative publications will be among them. But as I do not know, what extent you plan to give to the library you are founding there, I would like a specific explanation on this on a sheet of paper I can place before the Academy as an official document for filing. As representatives of the German spirit historical and philologic-philosophical works are perhaps not unwelcome, although in a new colony the general thrust must first be towards what is practical. If later on you should find the opportunity to send unusual minerals, especially of a palaeontologic nature, you would give great pleasure to our great mineralogist von Kobell.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">[...] <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">von Kobell: he may be in a 'Biographies of German scientists' kind of ref. work. Try also German encyclopaedia.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I would also be pleased to hear, which route you recommend to us for sending larger cases.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Concerning your plant collections, I was very delighted to gain greater clarity about physiognomical characteristics of the vegetation there. I had a vivid impression of a stronger relationship with the extra-tropical vegetation of South America, rather than with that of New Holland.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This conclusion contradicts somewhat M's, that the alpine vegetation of New Zealand resembles that of Australia, while that of the N. Z. lowlands does not. (M to Haast, 9 April 1871)</p>
               </note> Especially the Umbelliferae and [related],<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Conjectural translation, the German text is obscure.</p>
               </note> the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Discaria</seg>, Gentianae and Scrophulariae remind strongly of the plants of the Chilean alps. Against that, resemblance to those from New Holland is rare. In accordance with this impression I found it interesting to find a few bird names, that remind of words in the [Tupi]<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Try the German encyclopaedia, the word is not in my German dictionary, and I could not find anything like it in the Oxford dictionary either, unless I have misread the German word, which is a bit hard to decipher. I assume it is some South American Indian population or tribe.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> language, such as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">maco-maco</seg> (maco = thief); <seg style="font-style: italic; ">tui</seg>, In New Zealand a singing bird, without doubt called [...]<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">See note 3 above. Perhaps he means something like 'in oligo-Mayan'?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> (Tupi, a [parakeet].<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Conjectural translation. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Martius writes 'Perikit', again not in my German dictionary (perhaps German dialectic?)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The word <seg style="font-style: italic; ">pitangi-tangi</seg> also reminds of a [Tupi] word, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">piter</seg> = to slurp, to suck, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">angi</seg> = fragrance, etc. As I am of the opinion, anyway, that a continent could have been situated between New Zealand and South America, which in prehistoric times was swallowed up by the ocean, all relationships between the presently existing countries seem to me of great importance. The physiognomy of the New Zealanders and the custom to decorate the body with dots brings these peoples closer especially to the fearless Indians of the pampas, whose faces are similarly marked to those of the New Zealanders. If a dictionary of the Maori language has been published in New Zealand, you would much oblige me by sending it to me. For years I have been occupied with a work on the wild populations of Brasil. The one volume, which contains the glossaries, was published in 1863.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">What work is this? Obviously not </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; font-weight: bold; ">Fl. bras.</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">, but some other publication. Try in the vols. of books in the library of B.M.(N.H.) (it is unlikely to be listed in TL2). Is the book (or books, if Martius finished the second vol. before his death) in the MEL library?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The other one with the ethnographic descriptions is close to completion. As soon as it is ready, I shall have the pleasure of sending it to you. I must not forget to mention, that the major part of the plants you kindly sent me is unknown to me, including their names, and that I shall therefore try to have at least the more important ones identified in England, where Hooker and Bentham are the greatest authorities of this flora. Neither my eyes nor my spare time are adequate to carry out the determinations myself, and I should therefore be much obliged to you, if you would add at least the generic names to the plants from the North Island, that you so kindly promised me. But with all these kind consignments from you I remain in your debt, and I shall make every effort to be of service to you, as far as I am able. For a start I must still ask you to send me a short <seg style="font-style: italic; ">curriculum vitae</seg> in your next letter and a list of your publications. I hope that you have received my first reply of 2 October 1866,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This letter is in fact dated 1 October 1866. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">[see 66.10.01 Martius to Haast]</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and wish with all my heart, that you will be able to devote yourself to your great and gloriously recognised mission. In grateful attachment</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your most devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Translated by D. Sinkora, 10 November 2000.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
