<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>My dearest friend, ¶  ¶ I have to hand two letters, of 27 February and of 10 April [1868], ¶  that have given me sincere pleasure in more than one respect. Firstly, in that you show me once again your...</title>
            <author>Carl von Martius</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1860-9/68-06-22Martius-Haast.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </msName>
                  <msName>Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>68.06.22</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl von Martius</author>
               <title>My dearest friend, ¶  ¶ I have to hand two letters, of 27 February and of 10 April [1868], ¶  that have given me sincere pleasure in more than one respect. Firstly, in that you show me once again your...</title>
               <date when="1868-06-22">1868-06-22</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1860-9/68-06-22Martius-Haast.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Progress note</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">My dearest friend, ¶  ¶ I have to hand two letters, of 27 February and of 10 April [1868], ¶  that have given me sincere pleasure in more than one respect. Firstly, in that you show me once again your...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">According to the Library/archive catalogue this should read </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Haast family papers (Malm - Mayer), folder 200, </p>
            <p rend="Progress%20note"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; color: #0000ff; "
               xml:lang="de">.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">68.06.22</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Carl von Martius to Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Haast family papers, </seg>Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mein theuerer Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es liegen zwei Briefe vom 27 Februar und vom 10 April vor mir, welche mich in mehr als einer Beziehung herzlich erfreut haben. Für's Erste dadurch, dass Sie mir von Neuem Ihre liebevolle Theilnahme kund thun, wofür ich Ihnen denn meinen herzlichsten Dank darbringe, sodann, dass ich Sie von Ihrer westlichen Reise glücklich in Ihr Standquartier zurückgekehrt weiss. Möchten Sie sich nur immer derselben heiteren Kraft und Gesundheit erfreuen, welche Sie zum Besten der Wissenschaft so glücklich verwerthen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe nun auch Nachricht aus Hamburg, dass die Kiste mit den Moaknochen dort glücklich angekommen ist. Sie wird nun wohl auch in kurzer Zeit den Weg bis München glücklich zurücklegen und von unserer Akademie als ein schätzbares Geschenk ebenso aufgenommen werden, wie dies bei dem Vorläufer derselben nemlich<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">nämlich.</p>
               </note> den Photographien der ganzen Vogelskelette der Fall war. Diese habe ich binden lassen und werde sie im Namen der Classe an das paläontologische Cabinet abgeben, das schon viele schätzbare Zeichnungen in seiner Bibliothek aufbewahrt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Und nun hoffe ich Ihnen, lieber Freund, auch eine Freude zu machen, wenn ich Ihnen sage, dass unsere Akademie Sie in ihrer letzten Sitzung am 20 Juni einstimmig zum correspondierenden Mitglied gewählt hat. Diese Wahl unterliegt nun der königlichen Bestättigung<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bestätigung.</p>
               </note> und wird am 21t Juli in der öffentlichen Sitzung proclamirt werden, worauf ich denn das Vergnügen haben werde Ihnen das Diplom auszufertigen und versehen mit der Unterschrift unseres Vorstandes des genialen Chemikers Liebig zu übermachen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Tauschverkehr zwischen Ihrer literarischen Anstalt (um deren genaueren Titel ich Sie bitte) wird so wie bisher durch den Bibliothekar fortgesetzt werden. Erinnere ich mich recht, so gingen die Sachen durch Williams und Norgate. Wie ich aber höre wird wohl auch die hiesige britische Gesandtschft die Beförderungen übernehmen. Für diesen Zweck dürfte es noch geeignet sein, dass Sie mir ein amtliches Ansuchen an diese Gesandschaft [offen]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">die Beförderungen ... [offen] <seg style="font-style: italic; ">interline</seg>. </p>
               </note> überschicken sofern dieser Weg von den Colonien aus betreten wird.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben in Ihrem ersteren Brief meine Mitwirkung verlangt, dass der Dr Jakob Hector Mitglied der Leopoldinischen Akademie werde und in dem zweiten Briefe auch noch Gerhard Krefft? in gleicher Absicht genannt. Ich werde mich gern dieser Aufgabe unterziehen, muss Sie aber bitten, mir ausser dem deutlich und vollständig geschriebenen Namen und Titel auch noch die hauptsächlichsten Momente aus dem Leben der Candidaten, Geburtstag und =ort, litterärische Laufbahn, Leistung und Schriften mitzutheilen und zwar so, dass sich<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">ich.</p>
               </note> diese Angaben zu den Acten an das Präsidium geben und noch ein oder das andere Mitglied zur Unterstützung des Vorschlags auffordern kann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich weiss nicht, ob Sie der letzten Sendung einen Beitrag für mein Herbarium beigefügt haben. Wäre es der Fall, so sollen sie schon heute dafür bestens bedankt sein. Besonderen Werth lege ich auf die eigenthümlichen und characteristischen Formen Ihres wunderbaren antarctischen Islandes und hier wieder auf die Früchte der Coniferae, Cupuliferae u.s.w. Ich eröffne Ihnen zwar hiemit mein Herz, bitte Sie aber an mich und meine Liebhaberei nur dann zu denken, wenn damit Ihre übrigen Arbeiten nicht beeinträchtigt werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich wünsche sehnlich, dass unser Freund Ferd. Müller die von ihm beabsichtigte Entdeckungsreise nicht unternehme, sondern eher an Ausruhen denken möchte. Ich bemerke, dass seine geistige Aufregung immer mehr wächst. Es scheinen körperliche Zustände, geistige und gemüthliche Aufregungen bei ihm zusammen zu wirken, welche den grossen Prüfungen jener Expedition schwerlich gewachsen sind und ich würde seinen Verlust als ein grosses Unglück für die Wissenschaft betrachten müssen, als Freund tief beklagen. Er soll sich schonen. Reden Sie ihm ab.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was soll ich Ihnen von mir noch erzählen? Ich habe den heurigen Sommer, der sich durch eine ungewöhnliche Hitze auszeichnet, mehr als je an meinen gichtischen Beschwerden besonders in den Händen gelitten. Ausserdem manchen Kummer über die Krankheit meiner zweiten Tochter. Dabei liegen gar viele Arbeiten auf mir so dass ich nicht zum Ausruhen kommen kann es heisst also Geduld haben und sich in das Unvermeidliche ergeben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mein Freund Hermann von Meyer der Paläontologe in Frankfurt ist auch in einem bedenklichen Gesundheitszustande und setzt unsere Familie (seine Schwester ist die Tante meiner Frau d.h.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">das heisst.</p>
               </note> die Witwe vom Bruder meines Schwiegervaters) in grosse Sorge.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leben sie wohl lieber Freund und lassen Sie recht bald Gutes von sich hören</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihrem</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>treu ergebensten</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">München 22 Juni 1868.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An annotation in the bottom left corner in an unknown hand is illegible. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Haast's writing? He does have a terrible scrawl! (I had great trouble deciphering his letter to M in MEL.) — What did I let myself in for, suggesting you look for Haast to Martius letters in Munich!!! I must be a glutton for punishment!</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dearest friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have to hand two letters, of 27 February and of 10 April [1868],<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Perhaps in the Martius correspondence in Munich?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> that have given me sincere pleasure in more than one respect. Firstly, in that you show me once again your caring sympathy, and I offer you my sincerest gratitude for that, and also, that I know you safely returned back to your base from your western journey. May you always enjoy the same serene strength and good health, which you use so well to the benefit of science.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have now also received news from Hamburg, that the case with the Moa bones has safely arrived there. It is to be hoped, that it will now also happily conclude soon the short journey to Munich, to be accepted by our Academy as a valuable gift in the same way, as was the case with its precursor, the photographs of the complete skeletons of the birds. I have had these latter bound and shall present them in the name of our Section to the palaeontologic Museum, which already preserves many valuable drawings in its library.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And now, dear friend, I hope to be able to give some pleasure to you, too, by informing you, that our Academy has unanimously elected you as a corresponding member in their last session on 20 June. This election is now subject to Royal approval and will be proclaimed at the public session on 21 June, and after that I shall have the pleasure to draw up your certificate and, completed with the signature of our chairman, the genial chemist Liebig, send it to you. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The exchange with your literary institute (I ask you for its exact name) will be continued as before through the librarian. If I remember correctly, the transmission was made through Williams &amp; Norgate. I hear, however, that soon the British embassy here will also effect transmissions. To <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>this end it might be useful, if you could send me an open official application to this embassy, if this route is also open to the colonies. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In your first letter you have asked for my assistance, so that Dr Jacob Hector could become a member of our Leopoldina Academy, and in the second letter you also added Gerhard Krefft? for the same intention. I shall be happy to take on this task, but must ask you to provide me, apart from the clearly written complete name and title, also with the major events in the life of the candidates, their date and place of birth, their literary career, achievements and publications, and that in a form, that I can place on the files of the Presidium and so ask this or that member to support the application.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not know, whether you have added a contribution for my herbarium to your last consignment. Should that be the case, please accept already today my sincerest thanks. I place particular value on the singular and characteristic forms of your wonderful Antarctic islands, and here again on the fruit of Coniferae, Cupuliferae etc. I do open my heart to you with this, but ask you to think of me and my hobby only, if your other labours are not adversely affected by it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I dearly wish, that our friend Ferd. Mueller would not undertake the intended exploring expedition,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M withdrew from this expedition in search of Leichhardt in N-W Australia. The expedition was eventually led by John Forrest in 1869. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">(do we have a ref. for this? — not among the material I have dealt with.)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> but would rather think of resting. I notice that his mental agitation is increasing more and more. Physical conditions and mental and emotional excitement seem to work together in him, and would hardly be equal to the great ordeals of that expedition. I would have to look on his loss as a great misfortune for science, which, as a friend, I would deeply mourn. He must take care of himself. Talk him out of it!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What can I still tell you about myself? This present summer, distinguished by unusual heat, I have suffered more than ever with my arthritic condition, especially in my hands. In addition there is much worry about the illness of my second daughter. At the same time I am burdened with a lot of work, so that I can not get any rest, it means therefore: exercising patience and accepting the inevitable. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My friend Hermann von Meyer, who is palaeontologist in Frankfurt, is also in a precarious state of health and causes our family a great deal of worry (his sister is the aunt of my wife, i.e. the widow of my father-in-law's brother).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Fare well, dear friend, and let me hear good news from you soon.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>truly devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Munich, 22 June 1868.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Translated by D. Sinkora, 11 December 2000.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
