<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Hamburg, 31 August 1860 ¶ Most esteemed Professor, ¶  ¶ A long time ago I sent you a package of seeds from Dr Ferd. Mueller in Melbourne, I hope that it will have arrived safely, as well as my earl...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M60-08-31a-proofed.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M60.08.31a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title> ¶ Hamburg, 31 August 1860 ¶ Most esteemed Professor, ¶  ¶ A long time ago I sent you a package of seeds from Dr Ferd. Mueller in Melbourne, I hope that it will have arrived safely, as well as my earl...</title>
               <date when="1860-08-31">1860-08-31</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M60-08-31a-proofed.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="47">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="53">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Diederich von Schlechtendal</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Hamburg, 31 August 1860 ¶ Most esteemed Professor, ¶  ¶ A long time ago I sent you a package of seeds from Dr Ferd. Mueller in Melbourne, I hope that it will have arrived safely, as well as my earl...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M60.08.31a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Diederich von Schlechtendal</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="2"/>MS not seen; extracted from Tkach, Neubauer &amp; Roser (2022), Brief 34.</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>Hamburg d. 31 Aug 60</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Geehrtester Herr Professor!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe Ihnen vor langer Zeit ein Packet mit Sämereien von Dr. Ferd. Müller in Melbourne geschickt, ich hoffe dass dasselbe glücklich angekommen sein wird, ebenso meine frühere Uebersendung der Sparganien meines Herbariums.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Heute übersende ich Ihnen den 1 Band der von Harvey &amp; mir gemeinschaftlich bearbeiteten Flora capensis. Der 2te Band ist bereits im Druck wenn auch noch nicht fertig gearbeitet, er wird hoffentlich binnen einem Jahre erscheinnen. Ich werde mich freuen, wenn Sie in der Anzeige die Sie gefälligst davon in Ihrer botan. Zeitung machen wollen, nicht zu viel zu tadeln an meiner Arbeit finden. Ich habe keine Mühe gespart, sondern gearbeitet u nicht bloss Diagnosen abgeschrieben. Dass die Beschreibungen ganz englisch ausgeführt wurden, ist geschehen, weil das Werk doch hauptsächlich für die Bewohner einer engl. Colonie bestimmt ist, der mit der lateinischen Sprache vertraute Botaniker wird sich leicht mit dem englischen befreunden. Ich glaube, dass Harveyʼs Arbeiten ganz gut mit den meinigen übereinstimmen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie verstehen aus der Vorrede, dass wir eine ansehnliche Unterstützung von der Regierung oder dem Capparlament erhalten. Wir haben dafür aber den Druck auf eigene Kosten ausführen lassen müssen u baar ₤180. bezahlt. Rechnen wir die Unkosten der Beförderung u das Portos nach u von England, Schweden u in Deutschland, so haben wir ungefähr 300 Thal. zubezahlen müssen. Wir müssen deshalb schon eine ziemliche Anzahl Exemplare verkaufen, bevor wir auf einen Profit rechnen können. Der Preis des Bandes ist auf 12 engl. Schillg oder 4 Thal. preuss. Cnt festgesetzt. Ich habe bis jetzt noch keine Buchhandlung, der ich für Deutschland den Verkauf übertragen möchte, unsere Hamburgischen passen nicht recht dazu.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Schreiben Sie mir doch, wie viele Nummern ich Ihnen von Dr. Müllers Fragmenta phytogr. Austr. gesandt habe, damit ich Ihnen die Folge zustellen könne.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist zu bedauern, dass mir nicht die bei Prof. v. Mohl befindliche Hauptsammlung der Krauss’schen Pflanzen zu Gebote steht, ich muss sie mir von allen Ecken zusammenholen u erhalte sie doch vielleicht nicht ganz vollständig. Diese Pflanzen sind zum Theil recht mangelhaft<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>bestimmt u könnte das Normalherbarrium nur dabei gewinnen, wenn es mit zu unserer Arbeit benutzt würde. Im Allgemeinen ist man fast sehr liberal gegen uns in Mittheilung von Material, von welchen ich übrigens den grössten Theil selbst besitze, mehr als in der Flora bemerkt ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In der Hoffnung, dass Sie sich wohl befinden, verbleibe ich</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>ergebenster</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hamburg, 31 August 1860</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Most esteemed Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A long time ago I sent you a package of seeds from Dr Ferd. Mueller in Melbourne, I hope that it will have arrived safely, as well as my earlier dispatch of the sparganiae of my herbarium.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Today I am sending you the first volume of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Flora capensis</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>jointly edited by Harvey and myself. The 2nd volume is already in press, although not yet finished, and will hopefully appear within a year. I will be pleased if you do not find too much to criticize about my work in the notice that you will kindly publish in your botanical journal. I have not spared any effort, but have worked up and not merely copied diagnoses. The fact that the descriptions are entirely in English is because the work is mainly intended for the inhabitants of an English colony; botanists familiar with the Latin language will easily make friends with the English. I believe that Harveyʼs work accords quite well with mine.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will understand from the preface that we receive a respectable amount of support from the government or the Cape Parliament. However, we had to have the printing done at our own expense and paid ₤180. If we count the costs of transport and postage to and from England, Sweden and Germany, we have had to pay about 300 thalers extra. We must therefore sell quite a number of copies before we can count on a profit. The price of the volume is fixed at 12 English shillings or 4 thalers Prussian Courant. I have not yet found a bookshop to which I would like to entrust the sale of the book in Germany; our Hamburg bookshops are not quite suitable.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Please write to me how many numbers I have sent you of Dr Mueller's<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographica Australiae</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>so that I can send you the continuation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is regrettable that I do not have the main collection of Krauss's plants at Prof. v. Mohl's disposal; I have to gather them together from all corners and may not receive them in their entirety. Some of these plants are very poorly identified and the normal herbarium could only benefit if it were used with our work. In general, people are almost very liberal towards us in the communication of material, most of which by the way I possess myself, more than is noted in the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Flora</seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the hope that you are well, I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>most devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
