<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>June 4th [186]2 ¶ editorial addition. ¶ To the Editor of the Queensland "Guardian" ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I am induced to address a few lines to you upon a subject which I think only wants further attention to be...</title>
            <author>George Sprigg</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M62-06-04-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Unit 1, pp. 168-71, VPRS 2225 outward letter press copy books, Acclimatization Society of Victoria, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M62.06.04</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Sprigg</author>
               <title>June 4th [186]2 ¶ editorial addition. ¶ To the Editor of the Queensland "Guardian" ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I am induced to address a few lines to you upon a subject which I think only wants further attention to be...</title>
               <date when="1862-06-04">1862-06-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M62-06-04-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of the Queensland Guardian</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">June 4th [186]2 ¶ editorial addition. ¶ To the Editor of the Queensland "Guardian" ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I am induced to address a few lines to you upon a subject which I think only wants further attention to be...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M62.06.04</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">George Sprigg to the Editor of the Queensland Guardian</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Unit 1, pp. 168-71, VPRS 2225 outward letter press copy books, Acclimatization Society of Victoria, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">June 4th [186]2<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">To the Editor of the Queensland "Guardian"</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am induced to address a few lines to you upon a subject which I think only wants further attention to be drawn to it to receive from the inhabitants of Queensland the same attention which it is now attracting elsewhere. I allude to the subject of Acclimatisation, now that an Acclimatisation Society has been formed in South Australia, Queensland is the only colony (excepting Western Australia) in the group without a similar institution.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Acclimatisation is one you are aware a comparatively modern science. Hardly 8 years have elapsed since the "Société Imperiale d'Acclimatation de France" was founded at Paris with [Isidore] Geoffrey St Hilaire for its president and it was not until the middle of the year 1860 that an Acclimatisation Society was founded in England. In the month of February 1861 Mr Edward Wilson the great power of acclimatisation in this portion of the globe called a meeting of persons interested in the establishment of a similar society in Victoria the meeting took place in the Mechanics Institute Melbourne and the formation of the Acclimatisation Society of Victoria was the result, of which society Mr Wilson himself was elected president, Dr Müeller (who is a corresponding member of the French Society) Vice President Mr Sumner (of [...] Sumner &amp; Co) consented to act as Hony Treasurer and Mr Archer (the Registrar General) undertook the duties of Hony Secretary. During the first year the subscriptions and donations exceeded £1100 and this sum supplemented by Governmental grants has enabled the society to make some substantial progress at which we will glance hereafter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In August 1861 Mr Wilson visited Sydney and while there assisted in the inauguration of the Acclimatisation Society of New South Wales.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In January 1862 during a visit paid to Hobart Town Mr Wilson succeeded in establishing the Acclimatisation Society of Tasmania while about the same time a society calling itself the Acclimatisation Society of New Zealand sprang spontaneously into existence at Auckland. Sir R. G. Macdonnell on his visit to Melbourne in March last earnestly requested Mr Wilson to visit Adelaide in order that the subject might be brought prominently before the public in South Australia, this in consequence of Mr Wilson's immediate departure for Europe was impossible but before<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>leaving he addressed a letter upon the subject to the Editor of the "South Australian Register" and early last month a meeting presided over by Sir Dominic Daly was held and a society formed. Thus we have in these colonies five separate societies each under patronage of their respective Governors and in the immediate care of many of their leading men.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now for a glance at some of the results already shown although it must be remembered that time is required to develope the benefits accruing from the introduction of a new bird or quadruped. Thus although we all feel the benefit of the acclimatisation of the domestic animal it will only require time to make the Alpaca the Fallow deer, the Angora Goat and the Pheasant as common amongst us as the Horse the Cow the common Goat and the [barndoor] fowl are now.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>New South Wales is as you aware employed in trying the value [...] of the Alpaca an animal whose importance can hardly be overestimated. Tasmania by private enterprise has already succeeded in establishing the Fallow deer and the English Tench and is now anxiously awaiting the arrival of the "Bountiful Star" to learn the result of the experiment it made at an expense of over £3000 to bring the salmon ova to their colonies. New Zealand has completely acclimatised the English Pheasant and Victoria as you will see by the enclosed list is not behind hand on the work. (List enclosed) Besides which there have been liberated on [...] parts of the colony 34 thrushes, 32 Blackbirds, 18 Canaries, 20 Skylarks, 12 Californian Quail, 8 Starlings, 9 Pheasants, and 2 Partridges. Native animals for the purposes of exchange have been sent to London Paris, St Petersburg, Calcutta, Mauritius, Ceylon, Java, Amsterdam, Cologne, Copenhagen, Hobart Town &amp; Auckland and correspondence is continually kept up with the sister societies of London, Paris, Palermo, Sydney, Hobart Town &amp; Auckland.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Victoria will shortly receive an importation of 1500 Alpacas Mr Duffield a member of a firm which has received permission to export that number from Peru having personally visited Melbourne and made arrangement for their reception. The Society is also expecting a consignment of red deer presented by His late Royal Highness the Prince Ernest a correspondence is being carried on with the Government of the Cape of Good Hope &amp; Natal relative to the procuration of some of the beautiful stag tribe of South Africa such as the Eland Koodoo &amp;c &amp;c whilst by the kindness of Mr Mackinnon at London, Mr Layard at Colombo Captn Bayley of Point de Galle and the various Officers of the P &amp; O Compy continual additions are being made to the Society's possessions in the Royal Park.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I need hardly trespass upon your space to point out the adaptation of Queensland as far as regards climate and situation for experiments of this kind, all that is wanted is a beginning and that surely will not be delayed, once set on foot and placed in charge of an earnest working committee and no fear for the result need be entertained. I would<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>venture to predict that if a public meeting with His Excellency Si George F. Bowen in the chair were held such an inpetus would be given to the movement that an Acclimatisation Society of Queensland would speedily become "un fait accompli"</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I am</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your Obedt Servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>George Sprigg</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
