<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Pr. McC. presents his comps. to Mr Bruce and begs to thank him for his letter of the 9th of February and begs to say that on seeing Mr Bruce's note on the 14th of January offering to the N.M. half ...</title>
            <author>Frederick McCoy</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M62-02-13-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Outward letter book 2, no. 62/31, Museum of Victoria, Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M62.02.13</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Frederick McCoy</author>
               <title> ¶ Pr. McC. presents his comps. to Mr Bruce and begs to thank him for his letter of the 9th of February and begs to say that on seeing Mr Bruce's note on the 14th of January offering to the N.M. half ...</title>
               <date when="1862-02-13">1862-02-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M62-02-13-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Bruce</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Pr. McC. presents his comps. to Mr Bruce and begs to thank him for his letter of the 9th of February and begs to say that on seeing Mr Bruce's note on the 14th of January offering to the N.M. half ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M62.02.13</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Frederick McCoy to James Bruce</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Outward letter book 2, no. 62/31, Museum of Victoria, Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Trans 10.8.89. To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pr. McC. presents his comps. to Mr Bruce and begs to thank him for his letter of the 9th of February and begs to say that on seeing Mr Bruce's note on the 14th of January offering to the N.M. half of his great Meteorite while he retained half for the Brit. Mus. he begged of Mr. Daintree to go down and personally explain to Mr Bruce the claims of the Melb. Nat Mus. on his consideration as Mr. Abel for whom Dr. Mueller was agent had sent the other Cranbourne Meteorite home for the Brit. Mus. after the Exhibition and if Mr Bruce remained obdurate to thank him on behalf of the Victn Gov. Mus for the portion he had promised and to make arrangements for carrying the arrangement into effect. Mr. D. promised to go in a day or so and this was the reason why Mr. Bruce's note referred to was not answered immediately by letter and not any unwillingness to accept the half if the whole wd. not be given: On the part of the N.M. therefore Pr. McC. or Dr. (and armed by the kindly expressed wish of Mr. Bruce in his note of the 9th to see half of his specimens retained for the Melbn Museum) will proceed as soon as any money for the year can be got from the Treasury (in a few days) to carry out the arrangement for the transport and division of the Specimen Messrs Selwyn and Daintree having kindly promised to aid in superintending the operation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pr. McC. quite agrees with Mr Bruce that it was natural to suppose that Dr. Mueller had communicated with Pr. McC. before proceeding in a matter so much out of his department as to send his Botanical Assistant to secure the specimen but the matter was kept secret. Pr. McC wd also state that His Exy the Govr. was also quite unaware of the desire of the N.M. to possess one of those two Meteorites when he offered Dr Mueller to pay the cost of transit lest it shd fall into Mr. Abels or similar hands and His Exy had previously made some move to secure one at least of those two meteorites for the Govt of this Colony but on Dr M's applicn gave up his intention. He now writes to say that under the circumstances he approves of the decision of the specimen accompanied by casts as I formerly mentioned if there be no relenting on the part of those who contemplate the more than Ostrich-like glutting of the Brit Mus. swallowing up our two Victorian Meteorite iron masses, when one alone wd [...] fit food for all their philosoph speculations and leave us something to feast on as well. Pr. Neumeyer also is very strongly of opinion that this Meteor wd. be most advantageously retained with the other Meteorite irons in the Melb Nat. Colln sending a cast to the Brit Mus. as possessors of the other one</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">N.M.M. 13/2/62</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
