<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Referring to the letter received from you informing me that the Hon. the Chief Sec. had appointed a Board consisting of yr. self as Chn. and Messrs R. C. Selwyn, R. B. Smyth and myself to consider ...</title>
            <author>Frederick McCoy</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/M63-04-21-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>No. 63/70, outward letter book 2, Museum of Victoria, Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M63.04.21</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Frederick McCoy</author>
               <title> ¶ Referring to the letter received from you informing me that the Hon. the Chief Sec. had appointed a Board consisting of yr. self as Chn. and Messrs R. C. Selwyn, R. B. Smyth and myself to consider ...</title>
               <date when="1863-04-21">1863-04-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/M63-04-21-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>George Evans</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Referring to the letter received from you informing me that the Hon. the Chief Sec. had appointed a Board consisting of yr. self as Chn. and Messrs R. C. Selwyn, R. B. Smyth and myself to consider ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M63.04.21</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Frederick McCoy to George Evans</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">No. 63/70, outward letter book 2, Museum of Victoria, Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Referring to the letter received from you informing me that the Hon. the Chief Sec. had appointed a Board consisting of yr. self as Chn. and Messrs R. C. Selwyn, R. B. Smyth and myself to consider and report upon the question of the removal of the great Cranbourne iron Meteorite from the Colony and requesting that I should see that nothing was done in the matter until yr return from N. Zealand, when you wd summon the Board to meet, I have now the honor to inform you that Dr Mueller having applied to H. E. the Governor in furtherance of his views and H. E. having by last mail received a letter from the Keeper of the Mineralogical Coll. of the Brit. Mus. requesting that the large Meteorite in question shd. be at once sent home and stating that the Trustees had had a sum placed upon the Estimates for the purchase of a small meteorite sent home by Mr. Abel which it was intended to send out here in exchange for the large famous one wh. is referred to in the writings of Prof Haidinger of Vienna as now here, I have recd from H.E. a letter asking how I was prepared to act in the matter and I have the honor to inform you that in reply I acquanited H.E. with my having recd the letter from you acqainting me with the nomination of a Board to consider the matter and desiring that nothing shd be done meanwhile, and H.E. quite agreed with me that the proper course would bring the matter under yr notice so that official sanction shd. be given to whatever course was determined upon in relation to the disposal of the specimen. I promised if possible to communicate with H.E. on the subject on Thursday or in time for the mail —</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
