<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Munich, 17 December 1867. ¶ Very esteemed Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ The most recent news I received from you did not come directly, but through a letter about your latest discoveries, published by Professo...</title>
            <author>Carl von Martius</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M67-12-17-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M67.12.17</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl von Martius</author>
               <title>Munich, 17 December 1867. ¶ Very esteemed Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ The most recent news I received from you did not come directly, but through a letter about your latest discoveries, published by Professo...</title>
               <date when="1867-12-17">1867-12-17</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1860-9/M67-12-17-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Munich, 17 December 1867. ¶ Very esteemed Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ The most recent news I received from you did not come directly, but through a letter about your latest discoveries, published by Professo...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M67.12.17</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Carl von Martius to Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Only the date and the final paragraph of the letter are in Martius' hand, the rest is in an unknown hand. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">(Possibly that of the Secretary of the natural sciences section at the Royal Bavarian Academy? Or Martius' personal secretary?</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">to save Martius' eyes?)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>München 17 Dec. 1867</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrtester Herr und Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die neuesten Nachrichten, welche ich von Ihnen erhalten habe, waren nicht direkt, sondern durch einen Brief, welchen Professor Geinitz über Ihre letzten Entdeckungen veröffentlicht hat. Diese Nachrichten, welche uns gewissermassen in eine frühere Lebensperiode zurrückversetzen, sind auch in der Classe unserer Academie mit dem regsten Interesse aufgenommen worden, und als Herr College v. Siebold mittheilte, dass wahrscheinlich bereits eine Sendung den Küsten Europas nahe wäre, welche uns die Anschauung jener wundervollen 11' hohen Vogelscelette vermitteln würden, steigerte sich die academische Freude.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es muss in der That ein Anblick sein, welchen ich jedem Naturforscher wünschen möchte, den Vogel Rak aus "Tausend und einer Nacht" in seinem Knochengerüste vor uns zu sehen! Ein Urtheil über Schöpfungsglieder zu fällen, die früher verborgen waren, ist einer der höchsten Genüsse, den unsere Wissenschaft darbietet. Seien Sie nur nicht sparsam in der Erzählung aller Erfahrungen, die Sie bei der Erforschung der Merkwürdigkeiten gemacht haben. — Die Vergleichung der neu-seeländischen Flora mit der von Südamerika hat für mich ein ganz besonderes Interesse, und sie ist wesentlich erleichtert worden durch die theilweise Bestimmung, welche ich dem vortrefflichen Hooker und Herrn Oliver verdanke. Übrigens habe ich in Ihrer so gütig mitgetheilten Sammlung noch gar viele Formen vermisst, welche Hooker in den 2 schönen Bänden seiner Flora "<seg style="font-style: italic; ">novae selandiae</seg>" beschrieben und abgebidet hat, und obgleich es vielleicht wie eine Unbescheidenheit gedeutet werden könnte, will ich doch nicht verhehlen, dass es mir zur grössten Freude gereichen würde, wenn Sie Ihr Versprechen erfüllen u. mir bei guter Gelegenheit eine Fortsetzung Ihrer gütigen Mittheilungen zuwenden wollten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In der Bücherkiste, welche im Sommer an Sie über England abgeschickt worden ist, werden Sie auch meine academischen Denkreden und Beiträge zur Ethnographie und Sprachenkunde Amerikas vorfinden, welche ich Ihrer freundlichen Entgegennahme auf das Dringlichste empfehle. Ich bin bereit Ihnen auch mehrere Theile der <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora Brasiliensis</seg> , welche ein besonderes Interesse für Sie oder für die dortige gelehrte Gesellschaft haben könnten einer andern Expedition beizufügen, welche im nächsten Frühjahr vorbereitet werden soll. Es wäre mir übrigens angenehm zu erfahren. auf welche zumal academische Schriften man dort besonderen Werth legt und ich bitte Sie sich hierüber aufrichtig gegen mich zu äussern. Sind dort wohl auch academische Dissertationen von deutschen Universitäten willkommen?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bei Ihnen gedruckte Bücher, besonders naturhistorischen, geographischen u. ethnographischen Inhaltes sind bei uns selten und werden von gelehrten Vereinen mit besonderem Danke entgegengenommen werden. Ich selbst würde das Verzeichnis der neuseeländischen Flora, welches nach Ihrer letzten Nachricht nun wohl gedruckt sein wird, sehr gerne empfangen und bitte mir ein Exemplar zu kaufen, wofür ich den Betrag Ihrem Londoner Hause dankbarst zurückerstatten werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sehr begierig bin ich auf den Anblick der Gebirgslandschaft mit den Schneegipfeln des <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mount Martius</seg> und <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mount Carus</seg> und ich brauche Ihnen nicht wiederholt zu versichern, dass mir die freundliche Attention ruhmvoll in so weiter Ferne wirkender Landsleute ein um so grösseres Vergnügen gemacht hat, als ich mich neben meinem warmherzigen Freunde Carus geographisch verewigt finde. — Der Verkehr mit Ihnen kann vielleicht auch noch erleichtert werden, so dass kleinere Paquete von Zeit zu Zeit an Sie abgehen. Zu diesem Ende aber wäre es wünschenswerth, dass Sie einen Commissionär in Deutschland aufstellten, welcher solche kleinere Frachtstücke entgegennähme u. Ihnen periodisch auf den von Ihnen angegebenen Wegen zusendete. Ich habe so viele leidige Erfahrungen über den Verlust kleinerer Sendungen gemacht, dass ich im beiderseitigen Interesse wünsche, Sie möchten einer solchen Einrichtung den Weg bahnen. Unser vortrefflicher Freund, Ferdinand Müller, hat in Hamburg einen solchen wohlwollenden Vermittler. Da aber der Verkehr zwischen Hamburg und Neu-Seeland nur schwach ist, so dürfte in England die geeignete Person zu suchen sein. Dieser vortreffliche Freund erfreut mich nicht selten mit Briefen, welche ich immer so schnell wie möglich beantworte. Aber mit wahrem Kummer habe ich aus seinen letzten Mittheilungen die Befürchtung ableiten müssen, dass er sich, fortgerissen von seinem Wissensdrange und von einem lebhaften Gefühle möglichst viel zu leisten um seine Gesundheit bringt. Diese edle expansive u. vielumfassende Natur sollte der Menschheit recht lange erhalten werden und ich ersuche Sie ihn auf die Gefahren einer übergrossen Thätigkeit aufmerksam zu machen. Er hat schon so Vieles und Grosses geleistet, dass er sich nun anschicken darf inne zu halten und mit weniger Energie den vielfachen Erfolgen nachzugehen, die ihm auch mit grösserer Behaglichkeit noch in den Schooss fallen werden. Allerdings sehe ich wohl, dass das rege litterarische Leben, welches ihn umgibt, geeignet ist, um mit Plinius zu reden <seg style="font-style: italic; ">currenti calcar addere</seg>. Um so mehr ist es Freundes Pflicht dem raschen Laufe in die Zügel zu fallen. Ich komme zu solchen Betrachtungen, wenn ich meine eigene, wissenschaftliche Laufbahn betrachte, Mehr als 30 Naturforscher haben mit oder nach mir in Brasilien gearbeitet. Von Ihnen Allen leben nur noch Pöppig in Leipzig, Castelnau in Melbourne, Weddell in Poitiers und Spruce in England. Viele von den Übrigen haben ihre Laufbahn durch übermässige Anstrengungen in der Fremde oder zu Hause verkürzt. Ich selbst habe zwar die Arbeit mir immer sehr angelegen sein lassen und in den kräftigsten Mannesjahren nie länger als 5 oder 6 Stunden geschlafen; aber immer habe ich mir zum Gesetze gemacht nicht <seg style="font-style: italic; ">invita </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[<seg style="font-style: italic; ">attinerva</seg>] zu arbeiten und wenigstens ein Mal im Jahre alle geistige Beschäftigung bei Seite zu legen. So hat sich denn auch meine Constitution, Gott sei Dank, ziemlich rüstig erhalten und nur die Augen fangen an [mir die] feineren Dienste zu versagen, so dass ich das Microscop [nur] sehr selten in Anspruch nehme und<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">These last 3 lines of p. 5 of the MS are very difficult to decipher with any confidence, because the writing from the other side has bled through the paper rather badly. Another photocopy with black paper under the MS would be appreciated to ensure that my reading is correct.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> jüngere Augen für mich sehen lasse. Ich bitte Sie in Ihrem nächsten Briefe mir auch eine kurze Übersicht von den wissenschaftlichen Männern zu geben, welche in Ihrer Nähe gleiche Ziele verfolgen und überhaupt würde es dankenswerth erscheinen, wenn Sie Ihren fernen Landsleuten über den wissenschaftlichen Geist in der jungen Colonie und über die Mittel, welche die Forschung fördern sollen, Bericht erstatten. Mein Freund <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Carus</seg> war, wie er Ihnen ohne Zeifel gemeldet hat, durch die Übersendung der zwei Maori-Schädel hoch erfreut und rühmte mir, dass Sie ihm noch weitere Mittheilungen in Aussicht stellen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als Director Ephem. der Acad. Leop. Car. stehe ich mit ihm in vielfachem Verkehr u. irgend ein Anliegen, das Sie ihm nicht [direkt] vorbringen wollen bin ich gerne erbötig mir für Sie anzueignen. Sprechen Sie Sich also hierüber in Ihrem Nächsten offen aus. Ich würde mich freuen Ihren Wünschen entgegen zu kommen, wie ich denn auch an andern Orten zu rühmen weiss, was Sie für die Wissenschaft anstreben u. wirken. Ich flehe Gottes Segen für Sie herab. Möge 1868 Glück u Heil Ihnen bringen! Mit aufrichtiger Anerkennung, Verehrung u. Dankbarkeit</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr alter Freund</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Munich, 17 December 1867.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Very esteemed Sir and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The most recent news I received from you did not come directly, but through a letter about your latest discoveries, published by Professor Geinitz. These news, which, in a way, take us back into an earlier epoch of life, were also received with the greatest interest in our section of the Academy, and when our colleague von Siebold informed us, that a consignment was most likely already close to the European coast, which would enable us to gaze on those wonderful 11 feet tall bird skeletons, academic rejoicing increased even more.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It must indeed be a sight I would wish for every naturalist: to see before our eyes the bird Rak from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">A thousand and one nights</seg> as a skeleton! To pronounce a judgement on the links of creation that previously lay hidden is one of the greatest pleasures offered by our science. Now be sure not to be miserly in the telling of all the experiences you met with in the exploration for these rarities. — The comparison of the New Zealand flora with that of South America has a very special interest for me and has been made considerably easier by the partial identifications, thanks to the excellent Hooker and Mr Oliver. By the way, in the consignment you so kindly transmitted to me I have found many forms missing, that were described and illustrated by Hooker in the two fine volumes of his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora novae-zelandiae</seg>, and although it might be interpreted as immodest, I can not hide from you, that it would be the greatest pleasure for me, if you were to keep your promise to supply me with a continuation of your kind consignments.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the case of books that was dispatched to you during summer you will also find my academic memorial lectures and my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Contributions to the ethnography and philology of America,</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Check: is this the correct title: </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; font-weight: bold; ">Beiträge zur Ethnographie und Sprachenkunde Amerikas</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">. (The work may not have been translated into English.)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> which I strongly recommend for your kind acceptance. I am prepared to also send you several parts of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora brasiliensis</seg>, which might be of particular interest to you or to the learned Society there, to add to another expedition, that is to be prepared next spring.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">The German text following 'Society there' does not make sense, it sounds as if Martius mind ran ahead of his pen and he left something out at this point.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> It would, by the way, be handy to learn, which publications, - especially of an academic nature, — are of particular value there, and I ask you to give me your honest opinion about this. For instance, would academic dissertations from German Universities be welcome?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Books printed there, particularly on natural history, geography, and ethnography are rare here and are received with particular gratitude by the learned Societies here. I myself would very much like to receive the list of the New Zealand flora which, I assume, has by now been printed, and ask you to buy a copy for me, and I will gratefully repay the amount by sending it to your London agents.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am very eager to see the view of the mountain landscape with the snow-capped peaks of Mount Martius and Mount Carus, and I need not keep repeating my assurance, that the friendly attention of compatriots labouring meritoriously so far away has given me all the more pleasure, because I find myself geographically immortalised next to my warm-hearted friend Carus. — Communications with you could perhaps be made easier, so that smaller parcels to you can from time to time be dispatched to you. Towards this end it would be desirable, if you could acquire an agent here in Germany, who could accept such pieces of freight and send them to you periodically by a route determined by you. I have had so many bad experiences with the loss of smaller transmissions, that I wish in both our interests, that you would pave the way for such an arrangement. Our excellent friend Ferdinand Müller has such a well-meaning agent in Hamburg.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Wilhelm Sonder.</p>
               </note> But as the shipping traffic between Hamburg and New Zealand is only scanty, a suitable person may be found in England. This excellent friend often delights me with letters, which I always answer as soon as possible. But with real worry I had to deduce from his last communications<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to Martius, 25 July 1867 and 27 August 1867.</p>
               </note> the fear that, carried away by his thirst for science and a strong urge to accomplish as much as possible, he is destroying his health. This noble, expansive and versatile nature should be preserved to humanity for a long time, and I beg you to point out to him the dangers of too much activity. He has already accomplished so many and great things, that he can now afford to pause and to pursue with less energy the varied successes, which will continue to fall into his lap with a more comfortable life style. Although I do see, that the bustling literary life surrounding him tends, to speak with Plinius, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">currenti calcar addere</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Get Rod to check &amp; translate the Latin. (Something like 'to add a spur to the race'?)</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Therefore it is all the more the duty of a friend, to grab hold of the reins and slow the race. I reach such considerations, when I contemplate my own scientific career. More than 30 naturalists have worked with or after me in Brasil. Out of all these only Pöppig in Leipzig, Castelnau in Melbourne, Weddell in Poitiers, and Spruce in England are still alive. Many of the others have cut short their career by excessive exertions abroad or at home. Although I myself have always made a point of doing my work and during the best years of my manhood have never slept more than five or six hours, I have none-the-less made it my rule, not to work <seg style="font-style: italic; ">invita [attinerva]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">as prec. note.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and to put aside all mental occupations at least once a year. Thus, thank God, my constitution has remained fairly robust and only my eyes have begun to deny me their finer services,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Sounds as if he had macular degeneration.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> so that I use the microscope only very rarely and let younger eyes do the seeing for me. I ask you to give me a brief sketch of the scientific men in your area, who pursue the same goals, and generally it would seem to me worthwhile, if you were to report to your distant compatriots on the scientific spirit in the young colony and on the means, that are to promote research. My friend <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Carus</seg>, as he no doubt reported to you himself, was very delighted about the transmission of the two Maori skulls and boasted to me, that you hold out to him the prospect of still further communications.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As acting Director <note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">I suppose 'Director Ephem.' is abbrev. for ephemeral = transitory, or in modern English 'acting Director'?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the Leopoldino-Carolinae Academy I am in frequent communication with him, and if there is any wish you do not want to approach him with directly, I will gladly make it my own concern. So, tell me about it openly in your next letter. It would be a pleasure for me to meet your wishes, just as in other places I will know how to praise what you strive for and achieve for science. I pray for God's blessing on you. May 1868 bring you luck and happiness! With sincere approbation, respect and gratitude</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your old friend</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Translated by D. Sinkora, 3 December 2000.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
