<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ As Dr Mueller in his letters of 3rd and 16th inst has commented somewhat unfairly on the memorandum attached to my design for the improvement of the Treasury Reserve I beg to submit the following r...</title>
            <author>Clement Hodgkinson</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/M67-05-17.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>P67/5749, unit 631, VPRS 44 inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.05.17</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Clement Hodgkinson</author>
               <title> ¶ As Dr Mueller in his letters of 3rd and 16th inst has commented somewhat unfairly on the memorandum attached to my design for the improvement of the Treasury Reserve I beg to submit the following r...</title>
               <date when="1867-05-17">1867-05-17</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1860-9/M67-05-17.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>table</term>
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Grant</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ As Dr Mueller in his letters of 3rd and 16th inst has commented somewhat unfairly on the memorandum attached to my design for the improvement of the Treasury Reserve I beg to submit the following r...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">67.05.17</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">Clement Hodgkinson to James Grant</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">P67/5749, unit 631, VPRS 44 inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Transcribed 2.8.93. To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As Dr Mueller in his letters of 3rd and 16th inst has commented somewhat unfairly on the memorandum attached to my design for the improvement of the Treasury Reserve I beg to submit the following remarks relative to some of his statements.</p>
            <table n="Table1">
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.0556in; padding-right: 0.0556in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">Purport of Dr Mueller's statements</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.0556in; padding-right: 0.0556in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
                        xml:lang="en">Replies</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.0556in; padding-right: 0.0556in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">That another officer might more gracefully than himself have written to the Argus to correct the erroneous conclusions therein arrived at relative to memorandum on Mr Hodgkinson's plan.</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.0556in; padding-right: 0.0556in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">I proposed to two of my colleagues on the Board of Land &amp; Works (the Honble The President and Mr Ligar) that I should be authorized to send to the Argus a letter of similar puport to the private note which I hastened to write to Dr Mueller when I first saw, with regret, the mistatement in the Argus; they however both considered that it would be preferable to authorize Dr Mueller to write.</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.0556in; padding-right: 0.0556in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">That without consultation with Dr Mueller who originally planted the Govt House Reserve, 180 plants of specified kinds have been marked on Mr Hodgkinson's design for removal to the Treasury Reserve; and that it would be more equitable if 90 of these kinds of plants be taken out of reserves under Mr Hodgkinsons immediate supervision, and 90 be supplied by Dr Mueller <seg style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">at</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">his</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">own</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">discretion</hi>
                        </seg> from the Govt House Reserve.</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.0556in; padding-right: 0.0556in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">Having been requested to prepare with the least possible delay a plan for improving the Treasury Reserve, I had no time to communicate with Dr Mueller prior to completion of the photographing of my plan, and its presentation to Parliament. In the Govt House /reserve (<seg style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">which is under the control of the Board of Land &amp; Works</hi>
                        </seg>) it is <seg style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">generally known</hi>
                        </seg> that Dr Mueller has very laudably planted out several thousands of coniferous trees; therefore, in proposing to transplant only 180 of these trees to the Treasury Reserve I did not imagine that such a proposition would offend Dr Mueller, as he would be of course entitled to the credit of this source of supply.</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">When the Parliament House Reserve was planted about an equal number of trees were transplanted thereto from the Govt House Reserve, and from the Reserves under my immediate supervision, from with <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">latter reserves, </hi>
               </seg>some of the most valuable trees in the Parliament House Reserve were obtained, — for instance the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">finest Araucaria Cunninghami.</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This year however, in consequence of the coniferous trees in Fitzroy Garden occupying conspicuous positions near paths, it would be inexpedient to transplant any of those trees to the Treasury Reserve, — and I do not think it fair of Dr Mueller to place in the same category Fitzroy Garden (which is in the heart of the metropolis, and is daily traversed by thousands of people), and the Govt House Reserve, which is not now required for His Excellency's residence, — has never been proclaimed a park, — and is comparatively little frequented. I must protest against Dr Mueller's apparent desire to dictate to me what kinds of trees I shall plant, as the most essential part of my design is the grouping together of trees of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">specified</hi>
               </seg> kinds in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">predetermined</hi>
               </seg> positions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Mueller still considers that his claim to public acknowledgement, in the press, of plants supplied by him to the Board of Land &amp; Works should be allowed. This claim was disapproved of by the President of the Board of Land &amp; Works. The departmental letter took show that I have from time to time officially thanked Dr Mueller for plants supplied, and I have often addressed to him private notes conveying my personal thanks. If such a ridiculous practice as the publication in the daily papers of the thanks of one public department to another public department for supplies furnished gratis be adopted, the columns of the press would be crowded with such thanks to the Heads of the Crown Lands department for plans &amp; maps supplied gratis to other departments and to public institutions.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Hodgkinson</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Asst Commissioner of Lands &amp; Survey</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">17/5/67<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Grant remarked on 20 May 1867: 'As it is necessary that a portion of the coniferous plants in the Treasury Reserve should be of large dimensions, those specified in Mr Hodgkinson's memorandum for transplantation from Government House Reserve will have to be taken therefrom. I will however personally visit that ground in company with Mr Ligar, Mr Hodgkinson and Dr Mueller to decide from what parts of the ground the required plants should be taken. My objection to public acknowledgment by the Board of Land and Works of plants supplied by Dr Mueller remain unaltered.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation: 'Returned by Dr Mueller as requested by Mr Hodgkinson — Date of return 6/6/67. No minutes | [...] | 6/6/67'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
