<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Editorial practice ¶ Standard format ¶ A standard template for transcription has been used, comprising three meta-data fields, the transcribed text, and an additional meta data field if the item conta...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/static/about/editorial-practice.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier/>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Editorial practice ¶ Standard format ¶ A standard template for transcription has been used, comprising three meta-data fields, the transcribed text, and an additional meta data field if the item conta...</title>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/static/about/editorial-practice.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Heading1</term>
               <term>Heading2</term>
               <term>Firstparagraph</term>
               <term>Textbody</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>Definition</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name/>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Editorial practice ¶ Standard format ¶ A standard template for transcription has been used, comprising three meta-data fields, the transcribed text, and an additional meta data field if the item conta...</supplied>
            </head>
            <ab rend="Heading1"
                style="font-weight: bold; hyphenate: false; keep-with-next: always; margin-top: 0.1666in; margin-bottom: 0.0833in; font-size: 14pt; break-before: page; "
                type="heading">Editorial practice</ab>
            <ab rend="Heading2"
                style="font-weight: bold; font-style: italic; hyphenate: false; keep-with-next: always; margin-top: 0.1666in; margin-bottom: 0.0833in; font-size: 14pt; "
                type="heading">Standard format</ab>
            <p rend="Firstparagraph" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">A standard template for transcription has been used, comprising three meta-data fields, the transcribed text, and an additional meta data field if the item contains names of plants.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Item number</seg>. Each<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>item has a unique number based on the date of the item, e.g. 57.01.15a = second item of date 15 January 1857. Incomplete elements of the date are represented by ‘00’ e.g. 58.01.00 = item of date January 1858. Letters or fragments without any date are estimated, often as ‘earliest likely’ or ‘latest likely’ year and, if possible, month. Reasons for dating are given in the notes to the letter.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">File names</seg>. These match letter numbering conventions but use dashes since periods [‘.’] are not supported. Thus, letter number<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1850-9/1857/57-01-15a-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">57.01.15a</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is in file 57-01-15a, and appears as such in the ‘Preferred Citation’ given in the ‘Document Information’<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>pane for that letter.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Correspondent</seg>. Identifies the individual(s) or organisation to whom the item is addressed or from whom it comes using the format ‘First (or usual) given name Surname,’ e.g. ‘To John O’Shanassy’ indicates a letter from Mueller and ‘From John O’Shanassy’ one to Mueller. In some cases there is no specific recipient of text from Mueller. Where possible, a descriptive title e.g. ‘Testimonial’, is used. Correspondents who have been inferred are enclosed in square brackets, e.g. letter number<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1860-9/1865/65-12-12-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">65.12.12</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">To [John Knight]</seg>. Some correspondents in letters derived from published sources have been listed as they were described in the source, e.g. ‘<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">To a friend in Sydney</seg>’ is the correspondent entry for more than one letter, but it is impossible to know whether it was the same friend in each case. This type of letter is almost always a blind letter, e.g.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1860-9/1865/65-09-00a-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">65.09.00a</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(see discussion in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Preliminary/Scope/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">Scope</seg>
               </ref>). Those<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>who have been impossible to identify are given as an unknown correspondent, e.g. letter number<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1890-6/1896/96-03-12a-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">96.03.12a</seg>
               </ref>. Where part of a name has not been identified,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">[…]</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>replaces the missing part, e.g.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/letters/1840-9/1840-4/44-08-09-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">44.08.09</seg>
               </ref>, from a bookseller.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Location</seg>. The source of the item, e.g. RB MSS M104, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens, Melbourne. Where the item is known only in a published form, details of the source publication are given in a note. Where the item is treated as a publication by Mueller, e.g. a letter to a third party published in a newspaper, reference is made to the appropriate entry in the file of Mueller’s published works, prefaced by ‘B’, e.g. B56.13.02. Some organisations have changed their names, some archives have been transferred to other repositories since transcriptions started, others have been re-catalogued using new systems; it has not been feasible to update those details in all letters.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Text</seg>. Each transcription has standard placement of elements if present in the source: address and date, salutation, letter<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>paragraphs, valediction, addressee, and postscripts. Marginal notes are interpolated in the body of the letter following the author’s marks or placed at the end of the letter. Where orphaned marginal notes are placed at the end of postscripts, an indication of their MS [manuscript] location is given in a note.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Letters are transcribed into a normalised format designed to produce a clean reading text. Spelling and punctuation follow the MS. ‘<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Sic</seg>’ notes are not used, but in instances where the editors are<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>concerned that an unusual or erroneous spelling may lead to misunderstanding, a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>gloss is provided in a note.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Corrections</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>such as deletions, insertions and overwriting are usually noted only where they have several possible readings. Editorial comments on the text of the MS are given in notes in italics, e.g. <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">illegible</seg>. Physical information about the MS may be provided in a note, e.g. ‘MS edged in black’.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Translations</seg>. Items in languages other than English are followed by translations into English. The translations are intended to assist readers to gain an understanding of the contents. The translating style of the various editors has not been standardised. To minimise needless duplication, in some items comprising lists of plant names with comments, the translations are included within the list following the comment, e.g.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1880-9/1880/80-00-00e-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">80.00.00e.</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Occasionally an MS has both English and non-English text, its position in the text usually indicated by a note, e.g. letter<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/letters/1890-6/1890/90-05-16-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">90.05.16</seg>
               </ref>, note 1; that letter also has interpolated<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>translation of comments in the list of species.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Notes</seg>. Where Mueller is mentioned in notes the abbreviation ‘M’ is used. References to sources used by the editors are given in the ‘author (date)’ format, e.g. Acharius (1803). Where there is more than one<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>author of the same surname, as many initials are provided as are needed to distinguish them. Full citations are provided in the ‘Editors’ Citations’ file under Apparatus. References to newspaper articles and parliamentary papers are given in full in the notes. Items by Mueller are referenced by using the number given to that item in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/static/apparatus/muellers-publications/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">Mueller’s Publications</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>prefaced by ‘B’. Thus B53.04.01 cited in letter<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1850-9/1853/53-08-12-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">53.08.12</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>refers to M’s paper ’Diagnoses et descriptiones plantarum novarum, quas in Nova Hollandia australi praecipue in regionibus interioribus detexit et investigavit.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">25</seg>, 367–445.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Where an explicit reference to another letter is made in the text or annotation, that letter can be found using the letter number coding system, thus the letter mentioned in the annotation by Joseph Hooker ‘And Oct1/80’ on a letter is letter number 80.08.10. If a letter indicated in an annotation or text of a letter has not been found, the note ‘Letter not found’ is given. Editors’ cross-references given in the notes to other files in the correspondence are of the form ‘Author to Addressee, dd, month, yy’, e.g. ‘M to W. Lonsdale, 10 May 1853’, implying letter number 53.05.10, unless the reference is to a letter with a suffix in the file number when the letter<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>number is also given, e.g. ‘M to C. La Trobe, 10 May 1853 (in this edition as 53-05-10a)’.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Plant name list</seg>. Files containing plant names have an associated meta-data list of names that appear in the letters, including orthographic variants and names not formally published. Abbreviations have been spelled out. In those lists a generic name where it is used alone in the letter is included as such, unless it is also used as part of a full name in the same letter. Names appearing only in notes are not included<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in the meta-data list. A search of the corpus will not return letters that only include the name sought in notes.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Users should note that unpublished plant names appearing in transcriptions on this site are not effectively published. Moreover, the editors have not attempted to provide current names for those names now regarded as synonyms. This is also true of common names, which have not been linked to corresponding scientific names owing to the high risk of misapplication.</p>
            <ab rend="Heading2"
                style="font-weight: bold; font-style: italic; hyphenate: false; keep-with-next: always; margin-top: 0.1666in; margin-bottom: 0.0833in; font-size: 14pt; "
                type="heading">Other conventions</ab>
            <p rend="Firstparagraph" style="hyphenate: false; " xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Square brackets</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are used to enclose the text in transcriptions of blind letters where only summaries survive. Square brackets are also used to perform a variety of other editorial functions<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>but, except in the correspondent entry, mean uncertain reading unless otherwise specified in a note such as ‘editorial addition’ or ‘illegible — obscured by binding tape’.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Logical relationships</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are preserved. In many items, especially lists of species determinations, invisible tabulation has been introduced to ensure logical relationships are retained in screen displays, e.g. letter number<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1880-9/1880/80-00-00f-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">80.00.00f</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to Maurice Holtze.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">In tables of data and financial returns, tabulation has been used for similar reasons, but cell borders are shown where printed or manuscript lines occur<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in the source, e.g. letter number<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1880-9/1885/85-09-22a-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">85.09.22a</seg>
               </ref>.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Printed text</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in tables, forms and letterheads is indicated by coloured text, e.g. letter number<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1890-6/1891/91-01-07-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">91.01.07</seg>
               </ref>. When an item is transcribed from a printed source, such as a circular letter or printed testimonial with no or only minor manuscript components, the printed text is not coloured, but a descriptive comment is provided in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>note 1. For example, letters<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1880-9/1885/85-10-12-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">85.10.12</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/Mueller%20letters/1880-9/1887/87-08-24-final/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">87.08.24</seg>
               </ref>.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">Images within letters</seg>. Images are briefly described in a note linked to the position in the transcription nearest to the position of the drawing or other illustration. The note will link to the image.</p>
            <p rend="Textbody"
               style="margin-top: 0.0597in; margin-bottom: 0.0597in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">People mentioned in letters</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are not identified in notes, but those with similar names are disambiguated. If a person has not been identified a note is included. The<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <ref target="https://vmcp.rbg.vic.gov.au/text/static/apparatus/biographical-register/">
                  <seg rend="Definition" style="">Biographical Register</seg>
               </ref>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is a work in progress, and will contain names of correspondents, those of all people mentioned for whom full details have been found, and of those for whom full<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>details are not available if they appear in more than two letters. Where life dates have not been found, an<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">fl.</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(flourished) entry is given.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
