<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne botanic &amp; zoological Gardens ¶ August 3rd 1861. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In submitting a brief report on the labours in this establishment during the last two months, I am gratified to state, that it has ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-08-03a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>R61/6345, unit 749, VPRS 1189/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.08.03a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne botanic &amp; zoological Gardens ¶ August 3rd 1861. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In submitting a brief report on the labours in this establishment during the last two months, I am gratified to state, that it has ...</title>
               <date when="1861-08-03">1861-08-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-08-03a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Pinus Nordmanniana</term>
               <term>Mesembryanthemum</term>
               <term>Cryptostemma</term>
               <term>Wellingtonia</term>
               <term>Gleditschia</term>
               <term>Lawsonia</term>
               <term>Platanus</term>
               <term>Melia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Richard Heales</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne botanic &amp; zoological Gardens ¶ August 3rd 1861. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In submitting a brief report on the labours in this establishment during the last two months, I am gratified to state, that it has ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">61.08.03a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Richard Heales</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">R61/6345, unit 749, VPRS 1189/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS written by Ernst Heyne and signed by M.</p>
               </note>Melbourne botanic &amp; zoological Gardens</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">August 3rd 1861.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In submitting a brief report on the labours in this establishment during the last two months, I am gratified to state, that it has been in my power to supply numerous public institutions this season with plants &amp; seeds; indeed the distributions from our nurseries and seed magazine have been so extensive, that at a moderate computation of the value of these supplies a considerable proportion of the annual outlay for this garden is indirectly refunded.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We have also in anticipation of next season's requirements not only restocked the greater part of the nurseries of this garden, but also provided at the Royal park a stock of young plants required for the shrubberies &amp; copses there next season.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The interchanges with public institutions abroad continues with undiminished vigour. Thus amongst what we received during the last two months are contained glass cases with plants from Ghent, Hobarton, Brisbane, Manilla and Calcutta, living plants from Western Australia, dried plants and seeds from Petersburg &amp; Stuttgarth, importations of seeds from various parts of the globe; — the latter contain amidst numerous other highly desirable species both kinds of <name key="Platanus">Platanus</name>, the gigantic <name key="Wellingtonia">Wellingtonia</name>, the American Arbor Vitae, <name key="Pinus%20Nordmanniana">Pinus Nordmanniana</name>, the umbrageous Acacia Lebbek, the hedge forming <name key="Lawsonia">Lawsonia</name>, Deodar Cedars, Himalayan large Juniper, new kind of Liquorice, West India Copal plant, Catechu palm, Lebanon &amp; Atlantic Cedar.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During the last two months also considerable improvements have taken place in the garden and domains. The old wooden fences are now for the greater part removed with the completion of the new iron fences. Rearranging of the plants where needful, took place in the shrubberies. A number of rare plants were transferred from the nurseries to the general garden. The famous Chinese Rice paper plant and other botanical rarities have flowered for the first time in the garden during the last two months. A rich collection of pines has been planted out near the palm house; a valuable assortment of Oaks from Europe, Asia and America found a permanent place on the lawn between the Office building and the store house.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Many edgings had to be renewed. Mesembryanthema were planted on the rocky walls of the Quarries. Some of the old roads through the reserve have been obliterated and the bare places sown with grass, clover and shrub seeds. A circular iron enclosure has been erected at the rise beyond the Western entrance of the garden, whereon large Elms have been moved, in order to provide at that spot, where so extensive a view may be enjoyed, a delightful resting place for visitors. A new walk has been marked out through the reserve and has been lined with American planes, this being the first avenue of this beauty tree formed in all Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The line is intended to be prolongated to the entrance at the Immigration depot and thereby the shortest walk from the City bridge to South Yarra will be indicated. A line of Corsican pines has been planted along the St. Kilda road, and cross lines of American Locust trees and Black Poplars in the middle part of the reserve. A line of <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>'s has been arranged along the South side of the lake. The nursery ground at the experimental division of the garden has been considerably extended, and we have made arrangements to extirpate every where around the garden the all suffocating South African <name key="Cryptostemma">Cryptostemma</name>,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Cape weed.</p>
               </note> by hindering through methodical cutting the plant to seminate. A fine collection of cereals has been sown in one of the enclosures of the garden. The Orchestra pavilion has been surrounded with <name key="Melia">Melia</name>s 6 years old, capable of affording this season already a fine shade. Iron seats around these trees it is intended should be early provided.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So much difficulty being felt in providing water at the higher parts of our ground, I found it desirable to have a cistern sunk at the botanical Museum Building, by which means the carting of water to that part of our ground will be dispensed with.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Along the unsightly Lagoons near the City bridge I had some fair-sized Willows scattered, likely to improve greatly the aspect of that part of the environs of Melbourne. About 120 recently painted Iron labels have been distributed, for naming rare plants, over our garden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the zoological department we had an increase of our Angora goats by 2 young and a flock of our Cape Barren Geese. The Black swans hatched now also for the first time. Amongst the Donations are some Indian Deer, Peacocks, and Bengal sheep. The shipment of some native birds to the Society of Acclimatisation in Paris, of 5 kinds of Yarra fish to Regents Park,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Cf. M to P. Ramel, 25 July 1861 (in this edition as 61-07-25b).</p>
               </note> and of some Australian Eagles to Calcutta was effected.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A hayshed was erected in the Northern ground. Seven stately Curasows were imported on expense of the Government; for these birds a new special enclosure was finished. Some Murray Lobsters were liberated in the Yarra. The inclemency of the season having shown its effects on several of the more tender animals, we were obliged to provide heated stables for some of the Indian Deer.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Having been entrusted by his Excellency Sir Hercules Robinson of Hong Kong with the honoring duty to appoint a gardener for the formation of a Government garden at Hong Kong, my choice fell on Mr. Th. Donaldson who proceeded by the last Mailsteamer to his new destination.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See H. Robinson to W. Hooker, 13 April 1861, (RBG kew, Directors' correspondence, vol. 56, f. 194): 'I have been in correspondence with Dr Mueller and I have asked him to send me a good man to take charge of the [public garden here] giving him carte blanche as to salary &amp;c &amp;c., so I hope he will be able to find someone for me. Dr Mueller has been corresponding with me for some time — we have been mutually helping each other — I have been sending him tea seeds and he has been sending me the seeds of the Acacias &amp; other plants growing there, which he thinks will thrive well on our bare hillsides'.</p>
               </note> Since the heaviest winter labours have passed, I shall be in the position of resuming regularly my literary work, particularly on the Flora of Victoria,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See B62.03.03.</p>
               </note> for which two new sheets and several plates have been finished during the last two months.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But as it is very desirable, that I should have more assistance in my Office work, so that I may concentrate more of my time to strictly scientific labours, I have selected Mr Heyne, one of the most zealous and talented officers of my department for periodical aid in clerical work, and I would beg leave to propose to the Honorable the Chief Secretary, that I may be permitted to increase the income of that gentleman by one shilling additional daily payment.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Heales minuted on 20 August 1861: 'Read and increase approved'. The file was forwarded to M on 21 August and he returned it to the Chief Secretary's Office on 22 August annotated: 'Thankfully returned'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honour to be</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your most obedient &amp; humble</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The honorable the Chief Secretary</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cryptostemma">Cryptostemma</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lawsonia">Lawsonia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Melia">Melia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mesembryanthemum">Mesembryanthemum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Nordmanniana">Pinus Nordmanniana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Platanus">Platanus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Wellingtonia">Wellingtonia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
