<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanical and Zoological Garden, ¶ 12 May, 1861. ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, dated 10th May, ¶  conveying to me a resolution of the Newtown and ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-05-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.05.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanical and Zoological Garden, ¶ 12 May, 1861. ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, dated 10th May, ¶  conveying to me a resolution of the Newtown and ...</title>
               <date when="1861-05-12">1861-05-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-05-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Araucaria Cunninghami</term>
               <term>Robinia Pseudoacacia</term>
               <term>Araucaria Bidwillii</term>
               <term>Araucaria Excelsa</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/6d5b593f-e5e1-407d-883a-7a51b1cbcfc6">Grevillea robusta</term>
               <term>Araucaria Cookii</term>
               <term>Melia Azedarach</term>
               <term>Gleditschia</term>
               <term>Lophostemon</term>
               <term>Powlownia</term>
               <term>Platanus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Stephen Buckland</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanical and Zoological Garden, ¶ 12 May, 1861. ¶ Sir, — ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, dated 10th May, ¶  conveying to me a resolution of the Newtown and ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">61.05.12</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Stephen Buckland</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Planting street avenues', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geelong advertiser</seg>, 24 May 1861, p. 3 (B61.05.04). It is introduced by 'The following is Dr Mueller's letter to the Newtown and Chilwell Municipal Council regarding the planting of trees in streets and other public places:—'.</p>
               </note>Melbourne Botanical and Zoological Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">12 May, 1861.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir, —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, dated 10th May,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> conveying to me a resolution of the Newtown and Chilwell Municipality, to furnish results of my experiments in planting trees for useful and ornamental purposes.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">At the meeting of the Council held on 23 April 1861, Cr Jenkins gave notice of motion: </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.4929in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">That for the benefit of the inhabitants of this municipality the Chairman be respectfully requested to write the Corporation of Adelaide, South Australia, desiring that they will be pleased to furnish the result of their experiments in the planting of indigenous and other trees for useful and ornamental purposes; and that he also seek similar information from Dr Mueller and Mr Bunce, of the Botanical Gardens, Melbourne and Geelong (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geelong advertiser</seg>, 24 April 1861, p. 2).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The motion was carried when moved at the Council meeting of 7 May 1861 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geelong advertiser</seg>, 8 May 1861, p. 2). M's letter was received at the meeting of 21 May 1861, when it was 'ordered to be acknowledged accompanied by the thanks of the council' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geelong advertiser</seg>, 22 May 1861, p. 2). Letter of thanks not found. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In compliance with this request I beg to submit to you some notes on the respective value of those trees which are more particularly recommendable for lining public roads and streets on an extensive scale, referring you for information on plants otherwise desirable for general distribution over the colony, to an article which I furnished to the transactions of the Victorian Institute in the year 1857.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B58.05.02.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Defining, therefore, my observations to trees suitable for lining roads or streets in this country, it becomes of primary importance to decide whether evergreen or deciduous trees should receive preference for this purpose. For although in general the superiority of the latter when in full foliage cannot be questioned, it is still to be borne in mind that in the winterless zone of Australia, long and uninterrupted lines of defoliated trees do not contrast favorably with the beautiful verdure of our country during the cooler season. But since in the planting of trees along streets it can be less objectionable to select deciduous trees, than choosing them for lawns, parks, &amp;c., as predominant trees, I shall enumerate all the principal species which have claims on our attention, and shall endeavour to point out briefly their respective merits.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The British Elm ranks amongst deciduous trees, amidst the foremost, as regard hardiness, beauty, and celerity of growth. Its foliage withstands better than that of most other trees with deciduous leaves the exposure to hot winds. The elm will readily bear transmission to distant parts of the country when in a dormant state, and may be moved to the final places of their destination when it has attained already considerable size and strength. Being readily multiplied by cuttings, it may be obtained at the various nurseries in unlimited quantity, and at an extremely low price. The tree is content with poor soil, enduring considerable exposure, although its luxuriance increases with the fertility of soil, and under the benefit of shelter against heavy wind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Plane (<seg style="">
                  <name key="Platanus">Platanus</name>
               </seg>) is one of the most delightful amongst deciduous trees, both the Oriental and American Plane having respective merits. By the rigidity of their broad and beautiful leaves, they possess a still greater power to resist the effects of the hot winds than the elm. The plane is one of the most favorite trees cultivated for show in Middle and in South Europe. As yet, however this valuable tree is not available in large quantities in Australia. Our supplies are chiefly drawn from New South Wales.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The British Oak is amongst the most easily cultivated and rapidly growing trees with shedding leaves. Whilst in verdure during the spring and summer nothing can surpass its beauty. But in some varieties, the leaves drop tardily in autumn and winter, the dead foliage imparting by no means a cheerful appearance to the tree at that season.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Black or Spreading Poplar is well adapted for lining our roads and streets. Its firm leaves endure a considerable degree of drought. The Poplar is multiplied and transplanted with the same ease as the Elm, and purchaseable at a very moderate price.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The British Ash may also with great advantage be grown along roadsides, being hardy, and of comparatively quick growth.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Maple is recommendable for its beautiful foliage, and is easy of culture, and readily transplanted. But its rather tender leaves suffer under the influence of hot winds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To the Lime, the same remarks are applicable as to the Ash. If, however, the localities are sheltered, and the soil good, this tree, as well as the Horsechestnut, the Spanish chestnut, and the Walnut tree, become highly eligible for lining our walks.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Chinese and American <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>s are characterised by very spreading ramifications, and are thus remarkably adapted for overshading walks. The appearance of the trees is extremely handsome, and in favorable localities they attain finally a height from 60 to 80<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>feet <seg style="font-style: italic; ">omitted</seg>?</p>
               </note>. Their long thorns defend the trees well when grown to size.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The White Cedar (<seg style="">
                  <name key="Melia%20Azedarach">Melia Azedarach</name>
               </seg>) retains its deciduous foliage till late in the autumn, a quality which gives to this fine tree advantages over many others. Its branches are very spreading, but as the tree does not attain a very great size, although by no means diminutive, it is better suited for lining footpaths than roads. It is like the <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>s readily and cheaply obtainable.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Locust Tree (<seg style="">Robinia Pseudo-acacia</seg>) has proved well adapted to our climate. Judicious pruning of this tree is needed, in order to prevent its being deformed by the fracture of its branches in wet and stormy weather.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Japanese <name key="Powlownia">Powlownia</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Typesetter's error for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Paulownia</seg>?</p>
               </note> is of rapid growth and remarkable and showy on account of its large leaves. The latter however suffer from exposure to hot winds, and the tree is easily injured in localities subject to frost.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Ailantus recommends itself not merely on account of its truly noble appearance, but also as of great utility in affording food to a peculiar and liveley species of silkworm. It is not so rapid in growth as the elm, oak, and some other of the before mentioned trees.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The White Mulberry is one of the most easily grown and useful trees, probably fully entitled for selection in planting extensive avenues, irrespective of its great uses for rearing the silk-worm.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Japanese Gingko, an excellent tree, would claim our attention were it of quicker growth. Nor is this fine plant as yet cheaply and abundantly available.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Amongst evergreen trees the Pines rank foremost, whether we regard their noble forms or the variety of species eligible for being introduced into our plantations. It would lead too far to enumerate on this occasion all the kinds which could be made available, but special notice are deserving the Stone Pine, which produces a straight stem, a beautiful crown of foliage, and abundance of edible seeds. It is this tree which forms the most picturesque feature in the Italian landscape; and Cape Town is surrounded with ornamental lines of this tree. From analogy of the climate of its native country to ours, we may infer, that the Stone Pine is amongst the most desirable of all trees for avenues in this country.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Cluster Pine recommends itself also by its adaptation to our climate, and by its celerity of growth, for being made subservient for lining our roads, (especially A. Cunninghami, A. Excelsa, A. Cookii and A. Bidwillii)<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The parenthetical comment appears to be misplaced: Cluster Pine is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pinus pinaster, </seg>and the species listed here are <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Araucaria</seg>; it is possible that a marginal addition by M on his manuscript was misplaced in the transcription. It makes more sense if read as a parenthetical comment intended for the next paragraph.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Araucarias become also available to some extent for our public plantations, whenever a moderate outlay to obtain these noble trees is available. The same may be said of the Deodar. The Lebanon Cedar is unfortunately as yet not plentiful in Australia. Besides numerous pines we count amongst evergreen trees many species, which combine the very umbrageous foliage which so charmingly expresses the features of many British trees with never fading vendure. Thus the Illawarra flour<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Typesetter's misreading of flame? </p>
               </note> tree, the wattle trees, the <name key="Lophostemon">Lophostemon</name>, the <name key="Grevillea%20robusta">Grevillea robusta</name>, and several other trees might be selected for lining roadsides, although much more difficulty exists in the transport of these trees compared with the deciduous ones when dormant.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In exposed localities, where it is an object to raise within the shortest period trees for shelter, nothing becomes more adapted than the Tasmanian blue gum tree; but as its show<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Typesetter's misreading of shade?</p>
               </note> is imperfect, it answers well to interplant its lines with such trees as the elm or oak, which, when planted simultaneously, will advance independently of each other.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Experiments on the suitability of many other trees, including the Siris acacia, which is so much cultivated in India, are under progress, and the results of these trials will be duly brought to public notice whenever satisfactorily confirmed. Finally, I may state that it will afford me great pleasure to provide your municipality with such trees from my establishment as may remain, after the already extensive distribution of plants this season, available, when your preparations for planting will be completed.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Very obediently yours,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">F. W.</seg>
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Initials as in source.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">
                  <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Mueller.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To the Chairman of the Newtown and Chilwell Municipality.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Araucaria%20Bidwillii">Araucaria Bidwillii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Araucaria%20Cookii">Araucaria Cookii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Araucaria%20Cunninghami">Araucaria Cunninghami</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Araucaria%20Excelsa">Araucaria Excelsa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gleditschia">Gleditschia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20robusta">Grevillea robusta</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lophostemon">Lophostemon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Melia%20Azedarach">Melia Azedarach</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Platanus">Platanus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Powlownia">Powlownia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Robinia Pseudo-acacia</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
