<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Thanks for his letter of 25 July. Correspondent in London Mr L. Redhead, steamer agent between London and Le Havre, 59 Mark Lane in London, who will receive our packages and get them to both of us....</title>
            <author>René Lenormand</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-09-00b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Laboratoire de Phanérogamie, Paris.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.09.00b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>René Lenormand</author>
               <title> ¶ Thanks for his letter of 25 July. Correspondent in London Mr L. Redhead, steamer agent between London and Le Havre, 59 Mark Lane in London, who will receive our packages and get them to both of us....</title>
               <date when="1861-09">1861-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-09-00b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Desmidieae</term>
               <term>Epacrideae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/f48162c2-e198-4065-a64c-3d1081392043">Proteaceae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/7cc7f482-9966-4860-a834-2608a8949a0b">Myrtaceae</term>
               <term>Algae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Thanks for his letter of 25 July. Correspondent in London Mr L. Redhead, steamer agent between London and Le Havre, 59 Mark Lane in London, who will receive our packages and get them to both of us....</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">61.09.00b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From René Lenormand</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Laboratoire de Phanérogamie, Paris.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Item is a draft written on M to R. Lenormand, 25 July 1861. It is dated approximately to September 1861 as the earliest date by which M’s letter could have reached Lenormand and on the assumption that the latter would have replied reasonably promptly.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Remerciment pour sa lettre du 25 Juillet; Correspondant à Londres Mr. L Redhead, agent de steamer entre Londres et Le Havre 59 Mark Lane à Londres qui recevra nos paquets et nous les fera parvenir à l’un et à l’autre. Il faudra mettre sur l’adresse que les paquets devront m’être transmis par l’intermédiaire de Mr. Jules Gardye négociant au Havre, et faire suivre les frais qui seront remboursés par lui.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr. Müller ne m’a pas indiqué ce qu’il desire que Je lui envoye. Offrir des algues tant de nos cotes que de l’adriatique; de la Méditerranée et des mers étrangères. Voudrait-il une collection aussi complète que possible ou seulement les Espèces qui ne croissent pas en Angleterre? Algues d’eau douce Desmidiées et Diatomées, Mousses, Lichenes et même Champignons. En fait de phanérogames, espèces de France qui ne croissent pas en Angleterre, de diverses contrées de l’Europe &amp;a. Chaque espèce sera représentée, autant que possible, par des échantillons assez nombreux pour bien en donner l’idée. S’il en voulait davantage, Je le prierais de me le faire savoir… <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Je dois en recevoir du Canada; pourraient-elles lui faire plaisir.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Tout ce qu’il pourra m’envoyer en phanérogamie et en cryptogamie sera également bien-venu: échantillons aussi nombreux que possible. Une partie me servira pour lui procurer d’autres plantes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Fougères et algues recommandées encore plus particulièrement que le reste. Prières pour celle-ci d’en recueillir le plus possible et de les déssecher comme il le fait pour Mr. Harvey. Il n’y aurait que le petit nombre d’espèces que l’on ne peut pas préparer une seconde fois, qu’il faudrait arranger à fin.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Lichenes et mousses bien fructifiées. Protéacées légumineuses, Myrtacées Epacridées et autres familles plus particulières à l’Australie</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thanks for his letter of 25 July. Correspondent in London Mr L. Redhead, steamer agent between London and Le Havre, 59 Mark Lane in London, who will receive our packages and get them to both of us. One must put on the address that the packages should be sent to me through Mr Jules Gardye, merchant at Le Havre, and forward the expenses, which will be reimbursed by him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Müller did not indicate to me what he wants me to send him. Offer <name key="Algae">Algae</name> both from our coasts and from the Adriatic, the Mediterranean and foreign seas. Would he like as complete a collection as possible, or only the species that do not grow in England.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Fresh-water <name key="Algae">Algae</name>, <name key="Desmidieae">Desmidieae</name> and Diatoms, Mosses, Lichens and even Mushrooms. Concerning phanerogams, species from France that don’t grow in England, from different European countries, etc. Each species will be represented, as much as possible, by as many specimens as possible to give a good idea of it. If he wanted more, I’ll thank him to let me know. I should receive some from Canada; would they please him?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All he can send of phanerogamy and cryptogamy will be equally welcome: as many specimens as possible. Part I shall use to procure other plants for him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferns and algae still more particularly than the rest. For these please collect as many as possible and dry them as he does for Mr Harvey. There would be only the small number of species that can’t be prepared a second time that would need to be arranged completely.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Well fruited lichens and mosses, leguminous <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Some Proteaceous genera have pod-like fruits or follicles that open on one side only, unlike legumes that open on both sides.</p>
               </note>
               <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>, <name key="Epacrideae">Epacrideae</name> and other families more particular to Australia.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Algae">Algae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Desmidieae">Desmidieae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Epacrideae">Epacrideae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
