<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ The tea of commerce is obtained from the leaves of a small evergreen shrub, found growing wild, and also extensively cultivated, in China. Two varieties of this plant have been distinguished by bot...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-03-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.03.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ The tea of commerce is obtained from the leaves of a small evergreen shrub, found growing wild, and also extensively cultivated, in China. Two varieties of this plant have been distinguished by bot...</title>
               <date when="1861-03">1861-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-03-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Thea viridis</term>
               <term>Thea bohea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Board of Agriculture, Victoria</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ The tea of commerce is obtained from the leaves of a small evergreen shrub, found growing wild, and also extensively cultivated, in China. Two varieties of this plant have been distinguished by bot...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">61.03.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Board of Agriculture, Victoria</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see 'Notes on the cultivation of the tea-plant', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 18 March 1861, p. 6 (B61.03.01). It is introduced by ‘The following notes have been sent to the Board of Agriculture by Dr. Mueller:—”.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The tea of commerce is obtained from the leaves of a small evergreen shrub, found growing wild, and also extensively cultivated, in China. Two varieties of this plant have been distinguished by botanists under the names of thea bohea and thea viridis. The former is chiefly found in the southern part of China, whilst the latter seems to prevail in the northern districts. Formerly, it was erroneously supposed that the black teas could only be made from the thea bohea leaves, and those of thea viridis were thought to be suitable only for producing green teas. Mr. Fortune, during his travels in the tea districts of China,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Fortune (1853).</p>
               </note> has proved the fallacy of this idea by having seen that, through different treatment in the manufacturing process, green or black tea may be made from the leaves of either kind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In perusing the report of Mr. Fortune's journey to China we find that the most important tea-producing districts lay between the 25th and 31st degrees of N. lat. But it appears that the tea-plant is not confined to this zone, as Dr. Wallich reports to have seen plantations thereof in a flourishing condition under the 17th deg. of N. lat. in Cochin China, and others in the Japanese islands up to the 40th deg. of N. lat. The Indian Government formed numerous plantations in the Himalaya Mountains, at an elevation of from 2,500 ft. to 5,000 ft. above the level of the sea, between the 30th and 32nd deg. of N. lat. The variety of climate in such different zones and localities, where the tea-plant is known to be successfully cultivated, makes it almost impossible to fix a mean temperature necessary for its success. Mr. Fortune found, during the month of November, in the northern tea country of China, the mean temperature at sunrise 56 deg. F., and at noon 62 deg. F., but the plantations there seem to withstand a much lower degree, as he states that in many localities during the winter months the shrubs are covered with snow and ice. The Chinese are then in the habit of tying straw bands round the bushes to prevent their being spilt or otherwise damaged by the frost. In the Indian plantations mats are rolled on slight frames over the plants, for the purpose of sheltering them during severe weather.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The sites generally chosen for tea plantations are the slopes of hills; level lands or plains are only recommended if they are thoroughly drained and not subject to inundations. Mr. Fortune, in speaking of the extensive tea district of Woo e Shah, says:— "By far the greater portion of the tea in this part of the country is cultivated on the sloping sides of the hills, but I observed a considerable quantity also in gardens on the level land, in a more luxuriant condition even than those on the hill-sides, but these gardens were always a considerable height above the level of the river, and were consequently well drained." In speaking of another part of the country, he continues:— "After leaving the town of Yuen Shan we entered a large tea-growing country. The shrubs were dotted on the lower sides of all the fertile hills. Sometimes they were growing on level lands, but that was invariably dry and well drained by its position, and much higher than rice ground. The soil of these plantations consisted of a red loam mixed with a considerable portion of sand and gravel." The soil best adapted for the cultivation of the tea-shrub must be free and open and moderately rich, containing, besides the usual quantity of vegetable matter, sufficient of sand to keep it porous; a subsoil which allows all surface water to permeate freely through it is a great desideratum. But even adhesive clay seems to be fit for tea plantations, provided it be mixed with vegetable matter and sand. Mr. Fortune states that the tea lands near Woo e Shan consist of a brownish yellow adhesive clay. This clay when minutely examined is found to consist of particles of the rocks and of vegetable matter, it has always a considerable portion of the latter in its composition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The rocks referred to above he describes as follows:— The rocks consist of clay-slate, in which occur, in the form of beds or dykes, great masses of quartz rock, while granite of a deep black colour, owing to the mica, which is of a deep blueish black, cuts through them in all directions. This granite forms the summits of most of the principal hills in this part of the country. In describing the geological formation of another famed tea district (Sung lo). Mr. Fortune says — "The rocks in this part of the country are chiefly composed of silurian slate, like that found in England, and resting upon it is a red calcareous sandstone, similar to the new red sandstone of Europe."</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As a general rule for the selection of land for tea plantations, Mr. F. gives the following, being the conditions under which he found the tea-plants growing to great perfection in the Woo e Shan district:—</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"1. The soil was moderately rich, of a reddish colour, well mixed with the particles of rocks.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"2. It was kept moist by the peculiar formation of the rocks.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"3. It was well drained, owing to the natural declivities of the hills, or, if on plains, by being considerably above the watercourse."</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The superintendent of the Botanic Gardens in the North-Western Provinces of India confirms in an official report to his Government the foregoing; his experience in managing the tea-plantations in his district had shown him that tea-plants thrive best in perfectly well-drained, but not barren and dry, lands, which are of a porous and open nature, and of average medium quality. He adds, that pure stiff clay and all limestone lands should be avoided. All lands intended for tea-plantations ought to be trenched or ploughed to a depth of at least 18 inches; a greater depth, if it can conveniently be attained, will materially assist the growth of the trees.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; "
                     xml:lang="en">Jameson et al. (1854)?</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The propagation of tea-plants is chiefly effected through seeds (cuttings and layers will strike roots, but seedling plants are preferred, as being healthier and of quicker growth). The seeds ripen in China in the month of October. From three to six seeds are contained in each capsule. As the latter remains green for some time after the seeds are ripened, it is necessary to collect them whenever the seeds are ripe, which is easily seen by their becoming dark brown or chocolate-coloured. If left too long on the plants, the capsule will burst open and cause thus the seeds to be lost. The seeds, when gathered, are put into baskets, mixed with earth and sand, in a damp state. In this condition they are kept till spring. If this plan is not adopted only a small portion of them will germinate, as Mr. Fortune observes that, like the oaks and chesnuts, they lose their vitality when exposed to sudden changes of temperature and moisture. In the month of March the seeds are sown, rather thickly, about one inch deep, in drills 8in. to 10in. apart, on nursery beds. Should the weather be very dry, the seed-beds are watered occasionally, and straw or litter is placed between the rows, to prevent evaporation. Vacancies in existing plantations may be made up by sowing five or six seeds in each vacant space, leaving afterwards one or two of the strongest plants. Weeding the seedbeds and loosening the soil is all required by the young plants during the first year, during which they will attain a height of from 8 in. to 9 in. In the following spring, about the change of the monsoons, when fine warm showers are of frequent occurrence, but never during dry weather, the plants are transplanted to their permanent situations. In lifting them care must be taken to preserve, if possible, a ball of earth round the roots, and also not to cut or damage the perpendicularly-growing tap root. They are then planted on the lands prepared for them, in rows about 4ft. apart, allowing the same space between the plants in each row. Mr. Fortune frequently saw plantations in which the plants in the rows were much closer, forming a number of hedges across the fields. Loosening the soil round the roots and keeping it clear from weeds, seems to be the only attention required after the plants are established. Pruning is only resorted to when the uniform shape of the shrub threatens to be destroyed by rank and straggling growing branches.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A tea-shrub under cultivation will grow to about four feet in height. The first crop of leaves is taken from the plants in their third year. With careful management they will then continue to give annually a regular supply of leaves for 10 to 12 years; after that time they become exhausted, and are either taken up and replaced by young plants, or they are cut down close to the ground and allowed one year's rest, so as to enable them to form some fresh strong wood. The leaves should always be picked singly from the branches. Three crops are generally taken during each year, — the first, giving the best kinds of tea, about March, before the leaves are properly expanded; the second in April; and the third, and last, about June.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> published a follow-up letter from Thomas Embling correcting</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">one or two errors in my friend Dr. Mueller's report. Ler Teng, before the Tariff Committee, stated that tea can be well grown here. That at eight months the top branch should be nipped off, and three months after you gather the finest leaf the tree grows. Each year after the second year, the tree is cut down (as grape vines, so he explained it). The leaf is gathered every year. The evidence is at page 125 Tariff Committee.' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 21 March 1861, p. 5).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thea%20bohea">Thea bohea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thea%20viridis">Thea viridis</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
