<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exploration Committee ¶ Royal Society of Victoria ¶ Melbourne July 20th 1861 ¶ Mr Frederick Walker ¶ Sir...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-07-20-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS 13071 Royal Society of Victoria Exploration Committee records, box 2088B/5, letter copy book, pp. 56-9, La Trobe Australian Manuscripts Collection, State Library of Victoria, Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.07.20</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Exploration Committee ¶ Royal Society of Victoria ¶ Melbourne July 20th 1861 ¶ Mr Frederick Walker ¶ Sir...</title>
               <date when="1861-07-20">1861-07-20</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-07-20-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Frederick Walker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Exploration Committee ¶ Royal Society of Victoria ¶ Melbourne July 20th 1861 ¶ Mr Frederick Walker ¶ Sir...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">61.07.20</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Frederick Walker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">MS 13071 Royal Society of Victoria Exploration Committee records, box 2088B/5, letter copy book, pp. 56-9, La Trobe Australian Manuscripts Collection, State Library of Victoria, Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Exploration Committee</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Royal Society of Victoria</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne July 20th 1861<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At a meeting of the Exploration Committee on 18 July 1861 W. Gilbee, C. Ligar, D. Wilkie and M were appointed a sub-committee to confer with Capt. Norman about Walker's proposed search expedition. The sub-committee subsequently prepared this letter of instructions to Walker; it was discussed and adopted by the Exploration Committee on 20 July [Box 2088B/1].</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Mr Frederick Walker</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Exploration Committee of the Royal Society of Victoria believing that you have through Captain Mayne Auditor General of New South Wales accepted the Leadership of a party of Aboriginal Natives to proceed overland from Rockhampton<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Qld.</p>
               </note> to the River Albert<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gulf of Carpentaria, Qld.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>now forward to you through that Gentleman the following instructions for your guidance.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>From the high recommendations of your unequalled fitness for the difficult task that has been allotted to you which have reached the Exploration Committee from all quarters it is confidently expected that you will carry out the proposed expedition not only with credit to yourself but to the general satisfaction of all who are interested in the fate of those for whose succour you are sent.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. Robert O'Hara Burke and W. J. Wills and their two companions, Charles Gray and John King. Alfred Howitt, appointed to lead a search expedition, had telegraphed to Melbourne on 29 June to report that near Swan Hill, Vic, while heading north, he had met William Brahe who was heading to Melbourne with news of the expedition. From Brahe he had learned that at Cooper's Creek, Qld, Burke had decided that he himself, Wills, King and Gray would form the party to push to the Gulf of Carpentaria, leaving Brahe in command of the remainer of the group as a depot party at Cooper's Creek; and that, after waiting in vain for the forward party to return for a month longer than Burke had instructed him to stay, Brahe had brought the depot party back to Menindee, on the Darling River, NSW, and was now hastening to Melbourne to report.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is the desire of the Exploration Committee to leave you a very wide discretion in all your movements, believing that circumstances alone can determine from time to time what particular line of route you should adopt in steering for the Albert River. The discovery of traces or intelligence of Mr Burke's party should under all circumstances be your guiding principle. At the same time as there is a greater probability of Mr Burke's party being on the North than on the North East Coast it is important that your party should arrive at the Albert River with as much dispatch as a general search on the way will permit. Should you be so fortunate as to discover Mr Burkes Party on your way to the Albert River you will be pleased to communicate to Mr Burke all the information you may possess with regard to the arrangements that have been made for his relief and your own arrangements to meet the S. S. "Victoria," at the Albert River and you are desired to consult with that gentleman as to what course will be best under all the circumstances viz. as to whether you should at once return to Rockhampton with him or proceed with him to the Albert River. And as you are commissioned to convey relief to him you are to be guided as much as possible by his wishes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is the desire of the Exploration Committee that on your arrival at the Albert River you should at once report yourself to Commander Norman of the Victoria and furnish him with a journal of your progress and route.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Until your final departure from the North Coast the Exploration Committee will consider you as under the orders of Commander Norman so that it will be necessary for you to consult with Captain Norman before proceeding to undertake any further Exploration from the Albert River. The presence of two independent parties of search on the North Coast renders it imperatively necessary that all should act in concert with each other and that in all their efforts they should mutually support each other.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Commander Norman will be instructed to supply your party with all necessary stores and ammunition, and you may depend on receiving from him every assistance of which you may stand in need.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Commander Norman has kindly furnished the following signals which will at once enable you to determine the proximity of the "Victoria" at the Albert River.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"Each evening at 8 P.M., a gun will be fired, at 8.30 P.M. a Signal Rocket, at 9 P.M. a blue light."</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The same signals will be used by the Victoria's boat in the River until Commander Norman has an opportunity of communicating with you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Exploration Committee will confidently rely on your readiness to cooperate with Commander Norman if he so desires it in making an efficient search of the Coast and of the rivers and to ascertain through communication with the native tribes if they know anything of Mr Burke's party.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For the purpose of enabling you to form some opinion as to the probable route of Mr Burke's party and as to the best mode of pursuing the search, a copy of Mr Burke's instructions will be forwarded with your own also Mr Wills and Mr Brahe's diary accompanied by maps also Mr Brahe's journal in which he indicates Mr Burke's intentions, also the Surveyor General's<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Augustus Gregory.</p>
               </note> exploration maps and Captain Stokes survey of the Albert River.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Committee would again impress upon you the great importance of concerted action, so that different work may be allotted to each party and the search be prosecuted with the surest prospect of success when with the approval of Commander Norman your exploration of the Northern interior shall have been concluded, Commander Norman will give you a letter to the Exploration Committee Certifying his approval of your services also such other dispatches as he may deem it necessary to forward by your hands. And as there will be no means of reshipping the horses of the other land party the Committee will instruct Commander Norman to place these horses under your charge to return with your party overland to Rockhampton.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If you do not find the S. S. Victoria anchored off the mouth of the River you will certainly find the Victoria's boat in the River and the Victoria will be anchored in Investigator's Roads. It is expected that a small Steam Boat "Hotham" of 14 tons will arrive before the Victoria and you may happen to meet with this boat first.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The second land party to which reference has been made will be immediately organized under the directions of the Queensland Government to proceed by sea from Brisbane to the Albert River, and the Exploration Committee will rely on your hearty cooperation with the Leader of that party in the promotion of your common object.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Queensland Government have generously contributed £500 towards the outfit of this second party and in all your own arrangements you may confidently rely on the friendly cooperation and assistance of that Government.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With the best wishes of the Exploration Committee for the successful issue of your labours.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your Obedient Servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>pro John Macadam MD. Hon. Secty.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Robert Dickson Asst. Secty.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Expln Comtee R.S.V.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
