<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 25 October 1861. ¶ Revered and noble Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ In receipt of your kindly letter of May last ¶  as well as of the beautiful plants from Java, Suma...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-10-25a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Universiteitsbibliotheek, Hs 1873, Utrecht, Netherlands.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.10.25a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 25 October 1861. ¶ Revered and noble Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ In receipt of your kindly letter of May last ¶  as well as of the beautiful plants from Java, Suma...</title>
               <date when="1861-10-25">1861-10-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-10-25a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Miquel</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 25 October 1861. ¶ Revered and noble Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ In receipt of your kindly letter of May last ¶  as well as of the beautiful plants from Java, Suma...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">61.10.25a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Friedrich Miquel</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Universiteitsbibliotheek, Hs 1873, Utrecht, Netherlands.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS black-edged; M's sister Bertha Doughty died on 7 September 1861.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im bot. u. zool Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25. Oct. 1861</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrter würdiger Herr u Freund</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Besitze sowohl Ihres liebreichen Schreibens vom Mai d. J., als auch der schönen Java u Sumatra &amp;c Pflanzen, welche Sie mir zuzusenden die Güte hatten, u welchen Sie als weiteres Geschenk Ihre herrlichen Arbeiten über die Piperaceen beigefügt, danke ich Ihnen für Ihre vielseitige Güte, welche ich um so freudiger u dankbarer anerkenne, als Sie inmitten wichtiger literarischer Arbeiten, mit welchen Sie unsere Literatur schmücken, über so wenig Musse zu gebieten haben. Ich bemerke, dass Sie wie ich trauern. Möge ein nicht zu herber Verlust Ihre Familie betroffen haben u möge die Vorsehung Sie lange in Ihrem glänzenden Wirken erhalten!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre Flora des holländ. Indiens benutze ich fast täglich, da sich die Vegetation des tropischen Australien viel näher an die des indischen Archipelagus als an diejenige des Festlandes anschliesst. Wenn der 2. Band meiner Fragmenta u der erste des grössern Werkes über die Victoria Pflanzen in einigen Monaten vollendet sein werden, Beide sollen Ihnen selbstverständlich übersandt werden, gedenke ich an das Vertheilen mannichfacher<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">mannigfacher.</p>
               </note> Reihen getrockneter Pflanzen die hinlängliche Zeit verwenden zu können, u soll es mich denn freuen zu Ihrem Herbar weiter beizusteuern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie schade, dass Australien so wenig an Piperaceen liefert, wenn ich damit vergleiche, was ich selbst in Brasilien von dieser Pflanzenfamilie sah! – Hoffentlich erhielten Sie die wenigen Arten von Ficus u Piperaceen, welche ich Ihnen unlängst übersandte. Wie ist es doch zu bedauern, dass wir nicht mit dem grossen Holland in Buch-Postverkehr treten können. Ich habe unsern General-Postmeister gebeten, doch Schritte einzuleiten, dass der Verkehr in dieser Richtung, den wir mit England u allen brithischen Colonien haben, auch auf die Staaten des continentalen Europes ausgedehnt werden! Denn könnte man oft u schön Ihnen u den mannichfachen wissenschaftlichen Anstalten Ihres <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Reiches Beiträge liefern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Jetzt erhebt sich immer die Besorgniss, ob trotz grosser Verhandlungskosten, das Versandten auch wirklich über England seinen endlichen Bestimmungsorten richtig erreiche! – Zwar steht mir jetzt Ihr vortrefflichen Consul M. Ploos van Amstel auf die liebreichste Weise in den Versendungen bei, jedoch wäre es herrlich, wenn durch einen Erlass der holländischen Regierung alle etwaigen Contributionen von hier officiell an das General Consulat oder an die Gesandschaft in <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>London, gesandt werden könnten, denn es gebricht uns je fast immer an directer Gelegenheit von hier nach dem Continent Europe's zu senden. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">[...]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The text covers four pages on both sides of a single folded sheet and ends at the bottom of p. 4 without a valediction, suggesting that the letter continued on a second sheet, now missing.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; color: #000000; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; color: #000000; "
               xml:lang="en">25 October 1861.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Revered and noble Sir and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In receipt of your kindly letter of May last<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> as well as of the beautiful plants from Java, Sumatra, etc. that you had the kindness to send me, and to which you added as a further gift your glorious works on the Piperaceae,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Miquel (1843) [i.e. 1843-4].</p>
               </note> I thank you for your multifarious benevolence, which I acknowledge with all the more pleasure and gratitude as you have so little spare time at your disposal in the midst of important literary works with which you adorn our science. I note that you, too, are in mourning, as I am. May the loss that has struck your family not be too harsh, and may Providence long preserve you in your splendid work!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I use your Flora of the Dutch Indies<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Miquel (1855-9).</p>
               </note> almost daily, as the vegetation of tropical Australia is much closer to that of the Indian Archipelago<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. present-day Indonesia.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> than to the mainland. When the second volume of my Fragmenta and the first volume of the larger work on the plants of Victoria<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B62.02.01.</p>
               </note> are completed in a few months, —both will, of course, be sent to you, — I am intending to spend sufficient time on distributing numerous series of dried plants and it will then please me to contribute further to your hebarium.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A pity that Australia produces so <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>little in Piperaceae. When I compare with what I myself saw in Brazil of this family!<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During M's voyage from Germany to South Australia in 1847, he collected in and around Rio de Janeiro.</p>
               </note> It is to be hoped that you received the few species of Ficus and Piperaceae that I sent you recently. Indeed how it is to be regretted that we cannot enter into book postal communication with metropolitan Holland. I have requested our Postmaster General to initiate steps that the communication in this direction that we have with England and all British colonies also be extended to the states of continental Europe. Then one could often and easily send contributions to you and the various scientific institutions of your kingdom.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now the <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>apprehension always arises, whether in spite of the large transaction costs, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the item sent really reaches its ultimate destination safely via England! In fact now your excellent Consul Mr Ploos van Amstel helps me in the most kindly manner in the shipments; however, it would be splendid if eventually all contributions could be sent from here officially through an edict of the Dutch Government to the Consul General or the Ambassador in London, because there is almost always the lack of direct opportunity to send from here to the continent of Europe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[...]<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See n. 3.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
