<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 24 December 1861. ¶ My dear, noble friend, ¶  ¶ Your wonderful letter of 29 October ¶  was and remains for me a source of unspeakable joy. I have met few peo...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-12-24a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, folder 203, nos 521 &amp; 528, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>61.12.24a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 24 December 1861. ¶ My dear, noble friend, ¶  ¶ Your wonderful letter of 29 October ¶  was and remains for me a source of unspeakable joy. I have met few peo...</title>
               <date when="1861-12-24">1861-12-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1861/61-12-24a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 24 December 1861. ¶ My dear, noble friend, ¶  ¶ Your wonderful letter of 29 October ¶  was and remains for me a source of unspeakable joy. I have met few peo...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">61.12.24a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, folder 203, nos 521 &amp; 528, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS black-edged; M's sister Bertha Doughty died on 7 September 1861. The first part of this letter, including the first postscript, is filed as no. 521, folder 203. The remainder is filed elsewhere (see n. 3).</p>
               </note>Melbourne im bot. u. zoolog. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 24. Dec. 61.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Theurer edler Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr herrlicher Brief, datirt v. 29. Oct., war mir u. ist mir die Quelle unaussprechlicher Freude. Wenigen bin ich in meinem vielbewegtem Leben begegnet, welche sich mit der aufopfernden Innigkeit an mich angeschlossen, mit welcher Sie es gethan, u. Ihre steten Freundschaftsbeweise flössen mir eine um so höhere Verehrung für Sie ein, als ich solche um so weniger bis jetzt verdient. Vielleicht machen Sie mir im Stillen den nicht ungerechten Vorwurf, nicht immer aufmerksam gegen Sie zu sein. Im letzten Falle bin ich einigermassen zu entschuldigen da Ihr October Brief erst vor wenigen Tagen hier anlangte. Sofort nachdem ich selbigen erhielt legte ich Ihre geistreiche gehaltvolle Dissertation vor den Rath unserer Königl. Gesellschaft. Während der 3 Sommermonate werden meistens keine Sitzungen gehalten, indem soviele unserer Mitglieder dann abwesend sind. Sie sind aber gewiss, Ihre schöne Abhandlung für deren Ausarbeitung Sie inmitten Ihrer Berufspflichten viel kostbare Zeit verwandt haben müssen, volkommen hier anerkannt zu sehen u ich werde Sie unvorzüglich nach der Wiedereröffnung unserer Session zum Ehrenmitgliede vorschlagen, eine Auszeichnung die freilich gering genug ist, die indessen, wie Sie aus dem jetzt übersandte</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>übersandten</seg>.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> Bande unserer Verhandlungen ersehen werden, dennoch sehr sparsam vertheilt wird. Entweder heute mit Mr Brooke, der mir Hr Travers letzten Brief brachte, oder sonst in wenigen Tagen durch meinen vortrefflichen Freund, den Kaufmann Herrn Katzenstein, der sich jetzt bleibend in Otago niederlassen wird, sende ich Ihnen den 4. Band unserer Verhandlungen, den ich, da unserer Secretair gerade in Tasmanien ist, allein zur Hand habe. Ich gab Hr Dröge, der mich vor einem Jahr besuchte, denselben Band an Sie mit, muss aber fürchten, dass das Buch nie in Ihre Hände gelangte. Vom Jahr 1860 an ist unsere Gesellschaft "Royal Society" geworden. Diese kleine Ehrengabe unserer Seits Ihnen in unserer Mitte einen Ehrensitz zu geben, mag eine der ersten in einer Reihe </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The remaining text and the second postscript (which is a marginal note in the MS) is attached to letter no. 528 in the file, i.e. M to J. Haast, 29 July 1862. It is, however, clearly a continuation of the present letter.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">höherer Anerkennungen sein, welche Ihre herrlichen Arbeiten in vielen Ländern demnächst erlangen werden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie sind übergütig, mir Ihre Gastfreundschaft so liebevoll anzubieten! Möge es mir doch einst gestattet sein, mit Ihnen die Alpen hier sowohl wie dort zu durchwandern. Wenn immer es Ihnen möglich ist, uns hier zu besuchen, werde ich so recht innig erfreut sein, Ihnen es in meiner bescheidenen Wohnung so angenehm wie möglich zu machen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich muss mein Bedauern u meine Besorgnis ausdrücken, weder bis jetzt die Pflanzensendung erhalten zu haben, welche Hr Travers so gütig war mir vor einigen Monaten zu übersenden, noch die von Ihnen jüngst abgesandt Kiste. In diesen Wirren des Goldlandes ereignet es sich nur zu leicht, dass das Übersandte irgendwo liegen bleibt am Wege, was mich in diesen letzten Fällen recht beunruhigt. Ich habe bereits vielfache Nachfragen angestellt u unser Haus Dalgety &amp; Co. hat wegen den vermissten Sachen an Dagety Buckley &amp; Co geschrieben. Möge Alles dann bald anlangen und unversehrt! Inzwischen empfangen Sie meinen innigen Dank für Ihre vielseitige Güte. Ihrer Karte sehe ich besonders sehnsuchtsvoll entgegen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Idee einen Antheil an unsern Acclimations Unternehmungen zu nehmen ist vortrefflich! Möge selbige sich arrangieren.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Verzeihen Sie es, wenn ich vielleicht nicht so fleissig als ich wünschte, schreiben kann. Die Amtspflichten mit den vielen damit honoris causa verknüpften Nebengeschäften sind zuweilen fast erdrückend! So ist dies Jahr viel meiner Zeit wissenschaftlichen Arbeiten entzogen, um eine anständige Darstellung unserer vegetabilischen Erwerbsquellen vor die grosse Weltausstellung zu bringen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Jetzt eben hat mich auch der Präsident der Linnéischen Gesellschaft von London, der logische geistreiche grosse George Bentham, Erbe des berühmten Rechtsgelehrten Jeremiah Bentham, zum einzigen Associaten für die Universalflora Australiens erkoren, ein Werk welches Benthams Hauptzeit u meine Nebenzeit während der nächsten Decennie absorbiren wird!</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie schliessen Ihren Brief mit der Hoffnung, einen Strom Ihrer edlen Alpen, mit meinem Namen bezeichnen zu wollen! Gott weiss Sie sind übergütig! Viel unverdiente Anerkennung genoss ich in meinem Leben; die höchste ist es mir gewesen, ein ewiges Monument in den schneebekrenzten Alpen Ihrer classischen Insel zu besitzen u vielleicht einst den Geräusch des Stromes lauschen zu können, dass in einer reinen unversiegbaren Fluth das Andenken meines Namens erhalten soll.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets Ihr Sie ehrender</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Inmitten der vielen Geschäfte sind meine Skizzen über das Gebirge in welchem sich Mount Haast befindet noch nicht vollendet. Indessen beabsichtige ich etwa 2 Wochen diesen Sommer auf die Untersuchung der westlichen gegenüberliegenden Gebirge zu verwenden, wodurch ich meine Triangulation sehr vervollständigen kann.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Hr Katzenstein finden Sie einen sichern gütigen Freund, der gern unsere Sendungen vermitteln wird.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">24 December 1861.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dear, noble friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your wonderful letter of 29 October<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> was and remains for me a source of unspeakable joy. I have met few people in my eventful life, who have attached themselves to me with such unselfish sincerity as you have done. Your constant demonstrations of friendship instil in me all the more devotion to you, the less I have earned them until now. You may perhaps reproach me quietly and not without cause, that I have not always been attentive to you. In the most recent instance I might be somewhat excused in that your October letter arrived here only a few days ago. Immediately on receiving it I have placed your ingenious and substantial dissertation before the Council of our Royal Society. We do not usually hold sessions during the three summer months, as so many of our members are absent at that time. But you can be sure that you will see your splendid paper, on which you must have bestowed much precious time in the midst of your professional duties, will receive full recognition here. As soon as our sessions resume, I shall propose you without delay as honorary member,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The next ordinary meeting of the Royal Society of Victoria was not held until 26 May 1862. At this meeting a paper by Haast was read entitled 'On the physical geography and geology of New Zealand, principally in reference to the Southern Alps'. Haast was proposed as an Honorary Member of the Society at the meeting on 20 October 1862 and elected at the following meeting, on 17 November.</p>
               </note> a distinction which, it is true, is insignificant enough, but is, nonetheless, given sparingly, as you will see from the volume of our proceedings that I am sending you now. Either today through Mr Brooke,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not positively identified, but probably the same 'Mr. Brooke' mentioned in M to J. Haast, 6 July 1864.</p>
               </note> who brought me Mr Travers's last letter, or otherwise in a few days' time through my excellent friend, the merchant Mr Katzenstein,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">'J[oseph] Katzenstein Jun., General commission and shipping agent; representing Messrs. J. Katzenstein &amp; Co., Melbourne' advertised for business in </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Otago daily times</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 18 January 1862, p. 3.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> who intends to settle permanently in Otago now, I am going to send you the 4th volume of our <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions</seg>, which I happen to have to hand myself, as our secretary is at present away in Tasmania. I gave the same volume to Mr Dröge for you last year, when he visited me, but I fear that it has never reached you. Since 1860 our society has become the 'Royal Society'.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Approval for the Philosophiical Institute of Victoria to assume the title of Royal Society of Victoria was announced in a dispatch dated 8 November 1859 from the Secretary of State, the Duke of Newcastle, to the Governor, Sir Henry Barkly. The news was announced at a special meeting of the Society on 23 January 1860.</p>
               </note> This small token on our part of giving you a place of honour in our midst may be the first in a series of greater distinctions, which your wonderful labours will soon earn you in many countries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You are too kind to offer me your hospitality in such an amiable manner! May I be permitted one day to wander through the alps here as well as there together with you. If you ever have the opportunity to visit us here, I would be truly deeply happy to make your stay in my humble home as pleasant as possible.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I must express my regret and my anxiety that till now I have received neither the collection of plants dispatched so kindly by Mr Travers some months ago, nor the case recently sent off by you. In this confusion of the gold rush it happens all too easily that a consignment remains behind somewhere along the way, which in this latter instance troubles me considerably. I have already made enquiries several times and our firm Dalgety &amp; Co. has written to Dagety<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Dalgety?</p>
               </note> Buckley &amp; Co. concerning the missing articles. May it all arrive soon and without damage. In the meantime accept my sincere gratitude for your many kindnesses. I am looking forward with particular anticipation to your map.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The idea to share in the activities of our Acclimation Society is excellent! May it come to fruition soon.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Haast, 18 March 1862.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Forgive me, that I am not able to write as assiduously as I might wish. The official duties with the many connected additional honorary tasks are at times almost overwhelming! Thus much of my time this year is taken away from my scientific work in order to produce a comprehensive statement on our vegetable productions for the great International Exhibition.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An exhibition was held in Melbourne in 1861 in preparation for the London International Exhibition, 1862.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Also, the President of the Linnean Society of London, the logical, gifted, great, George Bentham, heir of the famous lawyer Jeremiah Bentham, has now chosen me as sole associate for the universal Flora of Australia, a work that will absorb all of Bentham's and part of my time for the next ten years!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You end your letter with the hope of wanting to name a stream in your noble alps after me!<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Haast named the Mueller glacier near Mt Cook, and also the nearby Hooker glacier, during his exploration of the area in early 1862.</p>
               </note> God knows, you are too kind! I have enjoyed many unmerited distinctions in my life; the greatest to me has been to possess an eternal monument in the snow-crowned alps of your excellent island,<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Haast had named Mt Mueller while exploring part of the Southern Alps of NZ in early 1860.</p>
               </note> and perhaps one day I may be able to listen to the sound of a stream, that is to preserve the memory of my name in a pure and inexhaustible flood.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In the midst of all my many duties my sketch maps of the mountain range where Mount Haast is situated<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">At the Macalister River, Vic; see also M to J. Haast, 12 May 1861 (in this edition as 61-05-12a). </p>
               </note> have not yet been completed. I intend, however, to spend about 2 weeks this summer exploring the mountains lying opposite to the west, which will help me to complete my triangulation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will find in Mr Katzenstein a reliable and kind friend, who will be happy to act as agent for our consignments.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
