<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>bot. gardens Melbourne ¶ 5. April 1855. ¶ Sir William ¶  ¶ Three letters ¶  of yours, which were received with much delight lay at present unanswered before me. The first of them came about a month ag...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1855/55-04-05-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 149*.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>55.04.05</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>bot. gardens Melbourne ¶ 5. April 1855. ¶ Sir William ¶  ¶ Three letters ¶  of yours, which were received with much delight lay at present unanswered before me. The first of them came about a month ag...</title>
               <date when="1855-04-05">1855-04-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1855/55-04-05-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Grevillea Latrobii var pubescens</term>
               <term>Orthrosanthus multiflorus</term>
               <term>Grevillea rosmarinifolia</term>
               <term>Muehlenbeckia parvifolia</term>
               <term>Caltha Novae Zealandiae</term>
               <term>Muehlenbeckia axillaris</term>
               <term>Polygonum lapathifolium</term>
               <term>Tetratheca baueraefolia</term>
               <term>Grevillea Dallachiana</term>
               <term>Polygonum glandulosum</term>
               <term>Banksia prionophylla</term>
               <term>Grevillea parviflora</term>
               <term>Grevillea tenuifolia</term>
               <term>Grevillea thyrsantha</term>
               <term>Grevillea triternata</term>
               <term>Microtis minutiflora</term>
               <term>Banksia Cunninghami</term>
               <term>Cucurbita micrantha</term>
               <term>Grevillea alpestris</term>
               <term>Grevillea Australis</term>
               <term>Grevillea micrantha</term>
               <term>Grevillea pubescens</term>
               <term>Microtis parviflora</term>
               <term>Polygonum lanigerum</term>
               <term>Drapetes Tasmanica</term>
               <term>Grevillea Stuartii</term>
               <term>Microtis pulchella</term>
               <term>Pimelea dichotoma</term>
               <term>Pimelea linifolia</term>
               <term>Polygonum elatius</term>
               <term>Aceratia connata</term>
               <term>Caladenia mollis</term>
               <term>Caltha sagittata</term>
               <term>Grevillea alpina</term>
               <term>Grevillea nutans</term>
               <term>Hakea leucoptera</term>
               <term>Diuris elongata</term>
               <term>Microtis media</term>
               <term>Pimelea cernua</term>
               <term>Pimelea nutans</term>
               <term>Hakea stricta</term>
               <term>Heuzenroedera</term>
               <term>Microtis rara</term>
               <term>Pimelea flava</term>
               <term>Thalamiflorae</term>
               <term>Atherosperma</term>
               <term>Picrophyta</term>
               <term>Polygoneae</term>
               <term>Proteaceae</term>
               <term>Dysphania</term>
               <term>Euphorbia</term>
               <term>Hydycarya</term>
               <term>Monolepis</term>
               <term>Orchideae</term>
               <term>Thymeleae</term>
               <term>Thymelea</term>
               <term>Anemone</term>
               <term>Würthia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">bot. gardens Melbourne ¶ 5. April 1855. ¶ Sir William ¶  ¶ Three letters ¶  of yours, which were received with much delight lay at present unanswered before me. The first of them came about a month ag...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">55.04.05</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 149*.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Part of this letter is misfiled immediately after the last page of letter no. 146, M to W. Hooker, 19 November 1854. The matching of the sheets is confirmed from the sequence of the excerpts of the letter published as B55.08.01 and B55 12.03. The changes in the printed version noted here are those that alter sense, or the spelling of plant and place names. Editorial additions follow the printed version.</p>
               </note>bot. gardens Melbourne</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">5. April 1855.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir William</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Three letters<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note> of yours, which were received with much delight lay at present unanswered before me. The first of them came about a month ago into my hands, but I hesitated to forward the already written answer, as I weekly expected to learn, wheather I had to remain in this colony or not. This is at last decided and I can joyfully say, to my favor.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">satisfaction <seg style="font-style: italic; ">for</seg> favor <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in the printed version</seg>
                     <seg style="">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By the papers you will have observed, that the once so florishing financial state of this colony which gave birth to so many useful institutions and [necssary] — now with difficulty to be followed up or carried out, — has for a time at least entirely changed, and the abolishment of the scientific institutions (excluding however the university) was decided upon, great retrenchments were made in every direction and were necessary, and amongst others my department was surely [none] of pressing necessity. The leg. council however took a different view and a petition was moved for by Dr. Greeves to be presented to his Excellency for putting an adequate sum on the estimates for this year, to enable me and several others to continue in office.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">At the Legislative Council session no. 73, 9 March 1855, 'Mr. Greeves moved, pursuant to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">amended</seg> notice, That this House resolve itself into a Committee of the whole for the purpose of considering the propriety of presenting an Address to His Excellency the Lieutenant Governor, praying that His Excellency will be pleased to place on the Estimates for the year 1855 the following sums, viz:— £1000 for the salary and expenses of the Government Botanist ... ' [sums for other scientific institutions follow]. See Victoria, Legislative Council (1855) <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Votes and proceedings</seg>, vol. 1, p. 291.</p>
               </note> As I trust to be able to say for my own honour, that no fault can be found with what I have done since being in the service, I can not doubt that the measure of the Leg. Council will receive his Excellency's sanction; — and I have to thank you now so much [more] for having evinced so much kind interest in my labours, as to adress Sir Charl Hotham in my behalf.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">W. Hooker recommended M to Governor Hotham, before the latter left England to take up his appointment, and Hotham replied that he considered 'it a public duty to contribute my official help to those who may stand in need of it' (C. Hotham to W. Hooker, 14 March 18[54], RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 78).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hooker also wrote to Hotham on 2 November 1854: 'Dr Mueller, respecting whom I took the liberty of writing to you, is, I am happy to say in frequent communication with me, &amp; not by letter only but he sends numerous specimens of plants, many quite new ones, &amp; of the whole he has drawn up, in Latin, most excellent &amp; scientific characters &amp; descriptions; &amp; this extensive mst. may be considered the foundation of a complete "Flora of Victoria." So sensible are the Botanists here &amp; myself of the value of these researches, that I have taken the great liberty of addressing to the Colonial Secretary at Melbourne a demi-official letter on this subject, hoping he may think it right to lay it before the Governor &amp; Council. It is true we do not expect your Excellency &amp; the Members of the Council should be Botanists: but we hope we may be allowed to consider you patrons of Botany, especially when you have so very able a person as Dr Mueller who holds the appointment of Botanist to the Colony, &amp; whose services must be in a measure lost, unless he his assisted in the publishing of the result of his researches. I have just sent out to Dr Mueller a considerable present of Botanical Books. But he writes to me to order a further supply from a Bookseller. I do not think any Bookseller would send out books to a stranger to be paid for on their arrival there: — &amp; indeed I am not without hope that the Colony will provide Books at the Botanic Garden, I presume, for the use of the Botanical &amp; Horticultural staff.' (No. 118, unit 1, VPRS 4021, Public Record Office, Victoria). See also W. Hooker to J. Foster, 2 November 1854 (in this edition as M54-11-02).The Assistant Colonial Secretary, J. Moore, replied to Hooker on behalf of Hotham, 24 January 1855: 'at the present moment it is impossible to accede to your suggestion — but should the next financial year find the Colony in a better state, His Exy will be happy to entertain your desire' (No. 167, unit 2, pp. 33-4, VPRS 2814, Public Record Office, Victoria).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Before entering upon the details of your letter to which I will refer point by point I beg to acknowledge most thankfully the transmission of the books and seeds which you, Sir William, had the favour of sending by Mr Burton.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">There are two letters from H. Burton to W. Hooker, 17 August 1854, announcing that he was returning to Melbourne near the end of August, and that he would 'be pleased to deliver anything to anyone' (RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letters 33 &amp; 34). F. Adamson to Hooker, 10 April 1855, reports that Adamson had informed M where Burton could be contacted in order to obtain Hooker's parcel (RBG Kew, Directors letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 4). Burton has not been further identified.</p>
               </note> The latter, a valuable acquisition are already in the ground, and the former, for which I will remit by Mr Archer,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">William Archer.</p>
               </note> have proved already useful to me in many ways. The Musci exotici<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">W. Hooker (1818-20)</p>
               </note> contains charming drawings, which must render muscology, to any botanist attractive. Your journal is always a pleasing recreation, and Dr. J. Hooker's Flora of New Zealand,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker (1853-5).</p>
               </note> will, to judge from the introductory number, be a guide to direct roads and correct directions through the labyrinth of systematic. It will open many of our best botanists, and directly to the continental ones, th[eir]<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — obscured by binding.</p>
               </note> eyes to see what are the real limits of species. This highly important work will be most instructive to me; I have already seen, that probably my first as <name key="Anemone">Anemone</name> mentioned plants (but I think I called it Caltha in my last letter) will be identical with C. N. Zealand[iae]<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — obscured by binding.</p>
               </note> certainly it approaches closely to <name key="Caltha%20sagittata">Caltha sagittata</name>. But thereon hereafter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have farther to express my thanks for the pain you have already taken in regard to a flora of this Colony, and for writing purposely to our Governor and Colonial Secretary. The exertions also of our noble old Governor will ever leave a deep impression on my mind and I will write to him<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> either by this vessel or by Mr Archer, the V. D. L.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Van Diemen's Land.</p>
               </note> Botanist, who goes for some years to England, bringing all his plants to you. He leaves in a few weeks, and I shall feel great pleasure in forwarding a set of alpine plants with him. I would have send already with this vessel, but they will only arrive from Gipps land at the very time when the "Lightning" leaves.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Greeves, member of the Leg. Council, and an ardent promoter of science in this colony, will upon my recommendation transmit to you a large quantity of <name key="Atherosperma">Atherosperma</name> bark. He praises it highly as a remedy in Bronchitis and I had myself an opportunity of becoming acquainted with its tonic properties. I have no doubt it contains an alkaloid of its own. Not only to see it subjected to a good quantitative chemical analysis but also to be examined by medical gentlemen attached to hospitals, we are very desirous, as it would perhaps form a precious article of export for at least four colonies.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Dr Greeves ... for at least four colonies. — <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is a marginal note in the MS. </seg>Its position here follows the printed version. See also M to J. von Liebig, 17 June 1859.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>From Dr Harvey I have heard a few days ago,<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. Harvey returned from Tasmania to Melbourne on 20 April 1855, and remained for about one month before arriving in Sydney on 25 May. See Ducker (1988), pp. 220-1.</p>
               </note> he is soon returning to this colony, so that I can enjoy again his instructions and company. He discovered on these shores no less than 4 new gen. of algae.<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bellotia (B. eriophorum)</seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Curdiea (C. laciniata)</seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gulsonia (G. annulata)</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Apjohnia (A. laetevirens)</seg>. See Harvey (1855).</p>
               </note> Is that not glorious? — This weeks Stuart, the V.D L collector, goes upon my expense to N. Zeel. I directed him to the Middle island, and it will give me much satisfaction to be able to increase thus your own stock of N. Z. plants. A few days ago I received also Dr Meissners remarks<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Meisner (1853a), Meisner (1853b) and Meisner (1853), respectively.</p>
               </note> on my collections of <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>, <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version has</seg> Thymelaeae.</p>
               </note> &amp; <name key="Polygoneae">Polygoneae</name> (going as far as 1852) I must candidly confess my regret, that this active and acute botanist not takes a more ample view of the precincts of special [diverty].<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's apparent spelling: <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version has </seg>and acute botanist not takes a more enlarged view of the variations of species.</p>
               </note> Our science becomes more and more encumbered with synonymy and in instances as in Grev. Austral.<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Grevillea</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">australis</seg>.</p>
               </note> &amp; G. tenuifolia, Dr Hookers opinions, based upon so much more ample material, ought not to have been disregarded.<note xml:id="ftn21" type="footnote" n="21">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Meisner (1853).</p>
               </note> It is a sad feeling to me also, to see against all my remonstrations,<note xml:id="ftn22" type="footnote" n="22">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version omits</seg> against all my remonstrations.</p>
               </note> nearly all of my old appellations now in print: most of these names have been <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">years ago</hi>
               </seg> replaced by more correct ones; they were originated mostly when I was very inexperienced here and much more in want of books than now and should only serve instead of numbers which by a slight inaccuracy lead at once into mistakes. I write by this mail also to Dr Sonder, to endeavour, that several errors of Meisner may not pass into DC pr.<note xml:id="ftn23" type="footnote" n="23">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version substitutes</seg> to make some observations that may be in time for De Candolle's Prodromus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">for</seg> to endeavour, that several errors of Meisner may not pass into DC pr.</p>
               </note> and to give him also more information on the extent of the species over the country. I may be permitted in this letter to make a few passing remarks on these points. What Prof Meisner mentions as G. triternata is my (not his) G. nutans. I really believe the sp. is good and I think the name might be altered now in<note xml:id="ftn24" type="footnote" n="24">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version substitutes</seg> to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">for</seg> in.</p>
               </note> thyrsantha. Grevill. pubescens (non Hook) is G. Latrobii var. pubescens. I doubt also the distinction of G. rosmarinifolia and G. Latrobii. G. Stuartii I think is a var of G. Australis. G. micrantha = G. parviflora first rep. p. 17<note xml:id="ftn25" type="footnote" n="25">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B53.10.01.</p>
               </note> and I think also of R Br <name key="Hakea%20stricta">Hakea stricta</name> = H. leucoptera sec. gen. rep<note xml:id="ftn26" type="footnote" n="26">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B54.10.01.</p>
               </note> and R.Br? — Muehlenbeckia<note xml:id="ftn27" type="footnote" n="27">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version has</seg> Mühlenbeckia.</p>
               </note> parvifolia = M. axillaris <name key="Banksia%20prionophylla">Banksia prionophylla</name> = B. Cunninghami? <name key="Pimelea%20dichotoma">Pimelea dichotoma</name> I received from Dr. Behr its discoverer; the flowers of it are, as you will observe in the specimens fowarded last year, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">white</hi>
               </seg>, and in 5 years observation of this plant I never saw them yellow, nor the bracts tinged yellow in the manner as those of <name key="Euphorbia">Euphorbia</name>s. Moreover P. dichotoma is a real scrub- and desert-plant, whilst P. flava is entirely absent from South Australia and makes only its appearance in the more southern latitudes of this colony where Tasmanian plants predominate.<note xml:id="ftn28" type="footnote" n="28">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Vol VII. 241 <seg style="font-style: italic; ">MS interline in an unknown hand.</seg> The reference is to the page of B55.08.01 where the printed extract of this letter appears.</p>
               </note> Pimel. nutans &amp; P. cernua are varieties of P. linifolia. <name key="Grevillea%20Dallachiana">Grevillea Dallachiana</name> will I trust retain its name, for neither the appellation <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alpina</hi>
               </seg> of Ldl.<note xml:id="ftn29" type="footnote" n="29">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">John Lindley.</p>
               </note> nor <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alpestris</hi>
               </seg> of Meisner can be admitted, as the beautiful shrub grows in the warmest parts of the ranges and even frequently in the scrub of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hot plains</hi>
               </seg>. If ever ascending to subalpine altitudes (and I am not aware of it) it will be like hundreds of other plants in a crippled state.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Microtis so common through South Austr, Victoria, and V. D. L. is over and over examined by myself in a living state; it is unquestionably M. media R. Br! Not much do M. rara and M. parviflora differ from it. But I cannot adopt Prof. Lindleys opinion, it should be M. pulchella.<note xml:id="ftn30" type="footnote" n="30">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lindley (1853).</p>
               </note> I examined <name key="Microtis%20minutiflora">Microtis minutiflora</name> in a living state and after having seen this plant now range as far as Gipps land I am inclined to take this for pulchella, notwithstanding it does not entirely concurr with R. Br diagnosis.<note xml:id="ftn31" type="footnote" n="31">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Microtis so common ... with R. Br diagnosis.<seg style="font-style: italic; "> is a marginal note on the second sheet of MS. </seg>Its position here follows the printed version.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Prof Lindley's remarks on my <name key="Orchideae">Orchideae</name> much remains to me doubtful.<note xml:id="ftn32" type="footnote" n="32">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lindley (1853).</p>
               </note> I am very anxious to learn, whether he had for his gen. &amp; sp. orch.<note xml:id="ftn33" type="footnote" n="33">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lindley (1830-40).</p>
               </note> R. Br's original specimens in hand. It is my intention to describe accurately all the species so as the [spring] will offer them, in the manner of <name key="Diuris%20elongata">Diuris elongata</name> &amp;c It appears to me so unprobable, that plants like his <name key="Caladenia%20mollis">Caladenia mollis</name>, which have such extensive range over the country should have exscaped R. Br.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With regard to my intended Flora of Victoria I think it best, that I should publish it here myself, I dare say in the Gov. printing office; i.e. in English. Before however I can make the beginning to this work several districts have yet to be visited, one of which will probably produce many Tasmanian forms. Others have yet to be examined in a different season. My desire was, under the difficulty of publishing all the manuscript, which I have send, to be favoured with a little space now and then for the new species, of which a stereotyp Latin diagnosis ought to be published after all. I should be so proud, if you would select what you, Sir William, thought correctly described of new plants for insertion into your journal. Mr. Kippist said once, that the Linnean society would give publicity to new plants if specimens were along with them. Perhaps he would accept a few natural orders thus, altho' a ful series of the corresponding specimens may be wanting, for I shall be happy to lay always some collection for the L. S. aside, and partly the L. S. must be already in possesion of them. My friend Prof. Fürnrohr would also be glad, I think, to receive through Dr. Sonder a small set of the manuscript now with you. The objects of such dispersion of the material in the present state would be, to acquaint the botanists with the new plants of this colony. By my next journey I think to complete the bot. survey of this colony and by the commencement of next year I hope to have to my delight and my instruction Dr. J. Hookers Tasmanian Flora in the first fascicle before me.<note xml:id="ftn34" type="footnote" n="34">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker (1860), the first fascicle of whch was issued in October 1855.</p>
               </note> I would venture then to follow with my own work, and I do not see material difficulty in bringing it out here, could I by that time become acqainted with the errors of the respective part to begin with, I mean <name key="Thalamiflorae">Thalamiflorae</name>. Highly I appreciate your kindful information this time <name key="Hydycarya">Hydycarya</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn35" type="footnote" n="35">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hedycarya</seg>?</p>
               </note> has yellow [acini], rather fleshy; <name key="Heuzenroedera">Heuzenroedera</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn36" type="footnote" n="36">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Heuzenroedera">Heuzenroedera</name>
                     </seg> was listed without description in B54.10.01, p. 14, but never formally described by M, although specimens collected along the Murray River (Vic) were distributed as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">H. dysphanoides. </seg>See M's labels on K898505, undated, and K898506, dated 'Dec 53'; Bentham (1863-78), vol. 5, p. 165 used the latter specimen in describing <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Dysphania">Dysphania</name> myriocephala</seg>. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Heuzenroedera">Heuzenroedera</name>
                     </seg> was presumably intended to honour Moritz and/or Heinrich Heuzenroeder, pharmacists whose dispensary in Adelaide, SA, had served as M's base during his time in that colony.</p>
               </note> appeared to me, when I analysed it some years back, rather nearer allied to <name key="Monolepis">Monolepis</name> than to <name key="Dysphania">Dysphania</name>; but I may be much in error, the flowering parts are very small and appear according to Moquin not correctly described by R Br., besides that I was at that time not in possession of such superior specimens of this plant, as I have since gathered.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You justly complain, Sir William, about the very indifferent state of many of my specimens and still I have always selected the best for you. I am under the great disadvantage here, that I have to collect the various species [most] from so remote localities. Compared with V. D L. there is here hardly anything to be found in the environs of the city; days journeys I have to go before I reach a interesting spot, whilst the botanists of V. D L. collect <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">most</hi>
               </seg> of their plants commodiously near their dwellings. — Particularly unfavourable was the season last year for scrub-plants, but I believed, I mentioned at that time,<note xml:id="ftn37" type="footnote" n="37">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M to W. Hooker, 28 April 1854.</p>
               </note> that I had at least been able to gather seeds of them, and so I see now many picked up in a miserable state as specimens grow in our garden; for instance the charming <name key="Aceratia%20connata">Aceratia connata</name>,<note xml:id="ftn38" type="footnote" n="38">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Aceratia%20connata">Aceratia connata</name>
                     </seg>not found (APNI, accessed 29 August 2019).</p>
               </note>
               <name key="Cucurbita%20micrantha">Cucurbita micrantha</name> etc. I hope Kew garden will be equally fortunate in the growth of the seeds collected here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am exceedingly annoyed that on my manuscripts a second postcharge has been made, as I paid for them to the postmaster-General here myself. By Mr Archer I will remit a sum for books and for a few dozend copies of such fascicles of your or other Journals as may contain descriptions of plants of mine. Your journal I shall be most happy to receive regularly; it is such a delightful and instructive recreation to read it. Much pleased I was yesterday to observe that Prof. de Vriese (according to your enumeration) has adopted the beautiful genus <name key="Picrophyta">Picrophyta</name>.<note xml:id="ftn39" type="footnote" n="39">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's genus (see B53.04.01, p. 421) is listed in an unsigned notice of de Vriese (1854), in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hooker's journal of botany and Kew Garden Miscellany</seg>, vol. 6, pp. 223-4.</p>
               </note> It was also pleasant to see that my observations on the Australian flora have been useful for Prof Balfours outlines.<note xml:id="ftn40" type="footnote" n="40">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Balfour (1854). On p. 138 (citing 'Müller') Balfour paraphrased M's statement in B53.03.01, p. 72 'that the cultivation of grain, which has so completely transformed one part of the wilderness of Australia, has already exercised so beneficial an influence on the increase of the rain'. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <name key="Drapetes%20Tasmanica">Drapetes Tasmanica</name> is an inhabitant of the Australian alps. I observe, that the character of <name key="Thymelea">Thymelea</name> as given by R Br. with regard to the insertion of the stamens must be altered according to this genus, what is neither done in Lin. Veg. Kingd. nor in Willkomms new work.<note xml:id="ftn41" type="footnote" n="41">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lindley (1847). <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Thymelea">Thymelea</name>
                     </seg> is treated on pp. 530-1 in all editions. Willkomm (1854), vol. 2, pp. 235ff. treats the ‘order’ <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name>.</p>
               </note> — Of <name key="Polygonum%20lapathifolium">Polygonum lapathifolium</name> I found here also the wooly form. It is R. Br's P. lanigerum[,]<note xml:id="ftn42" type="footnote" n="42">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — obscured by binding. All square brackets in the following have this meaning.</p>
               </note> nor do P. glandulosum &amp; P. elatius essentially differ from it. — <name key="W%C3%BCrthia">Würthia</name> Regel described in Prof. Fürnrohrs flora<note xml:id="ftn43" type="footnote" n="43">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Regel (1851). M was in error in referring to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora</seg>.</p>
               </note> = is identical with Orthrosanthus Sweet, nor appears the species to differ from O. multiflorus. Have you seen Schuchhardts Tremandreae.<note xml:id="ftn44" type="footnote" n="44">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Schuchardt (1853).</p>
               </note> It is a nice little pamphlet with a good deal [of] additional information, altho' much [of] uncertain characters has been mixed into the diagnosis[;] some of the general remarks require also a little alteration. A good chara[cter] for distinguishing Tetrathecae is offered also by the direction of the sepals in a fresh state; I adopted it in my own transmitted diagnosis of Tetrath. baueraefolia, but niether Steetz<note xml:id="ftn45" type="footnote" n="45">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Steetz (1853).</p>
               </note> nor Shuchhardt<note xml:id="ftn46" type="footnote" n="46">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Schuchardt (1853).</p>
               </note> could make use of it as they saw only dried specimens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With much pleasure I perused the article of Mr Drummonds exploration [of] the northern district of Western Australia.<note xml:id="ftn47" type="footnote" n="47">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Drummond (1853).</p>
               </note> Several plants from Lake Torrens I think I can identify from his notes. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope to be pardoned, Sir William, for my hasty writing this time. Let me conclude with my best wishes for your welfare. </p>
            <ab rend="valediction"
                style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                type="heading">Yours obediently </ab>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Most of the "pl. Muell" hitherto enumerated,<note xml:id="ftn48" type="footnote" n="48">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder (1852) and subsequent parts in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg>, vols 26, 28, 29.</p>
               </note> chiefly the rare new ones were obtained in South Australia and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> the specimens for the purpose of saving room (of which everyone is wanting here) were with exception of one, transmitted to Sonder.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I will however during this winter transmit fragments of as many as I possibly can, but I repeat with pleasure, that Dr. Hooker is quite wellkom indeed to select from my plants remaining [in] Sonders hand what he may require.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <ab rend="plant%20names"
                style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; font-style: italic; "
                type="heading">
               <name key="Aceratia%20connata">Aceratia connata</name>
            </ab>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anemone">Anemone</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Atherosperma">Atherosperma</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Banksia%20Cunninghami">Banksia Cunninghami</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Banksia%20prionophylla">Banksia prionophylla</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Caladenia%20mollis">Caladenia mollis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Caltha%20Novae%20Zealandiae">Caltha Novae Zealandiae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Caltha%20sagittata">Caltha sagittata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cucurbita%20micrantha">Cucurbita micrantha</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Diuris%20elongata">Diuris elongata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Drapetes%20Tasmanica">Drapetes Tasmanica</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dysphania">Dysphania</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Euphorbia">Euphorbia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20alpestris">Grevillea alpestris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20alpina">Grevillea alpina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20Australis">Grevillea Australis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20Dallachiana">Grevillea Dallachiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Grevillea Latrobii var. pubescens</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20micrantha">Grevillea micrantha</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20nutans">Grevillea nutans</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20parviflora">Grevillea parviflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20pubescens">Grevillea pubescens</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20rosmarinifolia">Grevillea rosmarinifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Grevillea%20Stuartii">Grevillea Stuartii</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20tenuifolia">Grevillea tenuifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20thyrsantha">Grevillea thyrsantha</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20triternata">Grevillea triternata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hakea%20leucoptera">Hakea leucoptera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hakea%20stricta">Hakea stricta</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Heuzenroedera">Heuzenroedera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hydycarya">Hydycarya</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Microtis%20media">Microtis media</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Microtis%20minutiflora">Microtis minutiflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Microtis%20parviflora">Microtis parviflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Microtis%20pulchella">Microtis pulchella</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Microtis%20rara">Microtis rara</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Monolepis">Monolepis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Muehlenbeckia%20axillaris">Muehlenbeckia axillaris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Muehlenbeckia%20parvifolia">Muehlenbeckia parvifolia</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Orchideae">Orchideae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Orthrosanthus%20multiflorus">Orthrosanthus multiflorus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Picrophyta">Picrophyta</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20cernua">Pimelea cernua</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20dichotoma">Pimelea dichotoma</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20flava">Pimelea flava</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20linifolia">Pimelea linifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20nutans">Pimelea nutans</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polygoneae">Polygoneae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polygonum%20elatius">Polygonum elatius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polygonum%20glandulosum">Polygonum glandulosum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polygonum%20lanigerum">Polygonum lanigerum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polygonum%20lapathifolium">Polygonum lapathifolium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Tetratheca%20baueraefolia">Tetratheca baueraefolia</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thalamiflorae">Thalamiflorae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thymelea">Thymelea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thymeleae">Thymeleae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="W%C3%BCrthia">Würthia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
