<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On Board the Monarch, ¶ 11th September, 1855. ¶ Dear ¶   ¶ Wilhelmi ¶ , — We are now approaching the Victoria River so closely, that I must think of closing my different letters. I will therefore not ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1855/55-09-11-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>55.09.11</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>On Board the Monarch, ¶ 11th September, 1855. ¶ Dear ¶   ¶ Wilhelmi ¶ , — We are now approaching the Victoria River so closely, that I must think of closing my different letters. I will therefore not ...</title>
               <date when="1855-09-11">1855-09-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1855/55-09-11-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl Wilhelmi</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">On Board the Monarch, ¶ 11th September, 1855. ¶ Dear ¶   ¶ Wilhelmi ¶ , — We are now approaching the Victoria River so closely, that I must think of closing my different letters. I will therefore not ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">55.09.11</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Carl Wilhelmi</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. M would have written in German. The text is an extract published in the Melbourne <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg>, 20 March 1856, p. 4 (B56.03.03), where it appeared under the heading 'The Australian Expedition', with the following introduction:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Much anxiety has been expressed that no tidings have yet come to hand of Dr Gregory's Expedition to Explore the Northern Parts of Australia. The subjoined correspondence, although communicating little as to the actual progress of the undertaking, will be acceptable as the first letter received from the expedition. The neglect complained of in Dr Becker's introductory letter will surely receive attention from some department of our Executive, if they are not quite indifferent to the reputation of the colony: —</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; font-style: italic; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To the Editor of the Herald.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>S<seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">ir</seg>, — It may perhaps be interesting to some of your readers to hear that a letter has been received from Dr Mueller, the Government Botanist of this colony. I beg to send you an extract of this letter, which was addressed to a friend of the doctor, Mr Wilhelmi. This young man was a companion of Dr Mueller in his former travels in Australia, and is, on account of his botanical acquirements, worthy of a better position than that of a mere labourer in the Botanical Gardens, where his wages, ten shillings a day twelve months ago, have been reduced to eight shillings. You will perceive from Dr Mueller's letter that he does not believe his position of Government Botanist a secure one; and it is to be lamented that this energetic man of science cannot think of a future quiet home in his dangerous travels through the Interior! As to Dr Mueller's remarks about the preservation of his valuable herbaria, which, he fears, are not safe, I may be allowed to add, that some unknown hand smashed the window of the small room in the cottage at the entrance of the Botanical Gardens in which these herbaria are preserved, then allowing the rain and dust to enter, until Mr Wilhelmi himself repaired the window, nobody else seeming to take the least interest in the matter.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>LUDWIG BECKER</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Melbourne, 18th March, 1856.</p>
               </note>On Board the Monarch,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">11th September, 1855.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Dear</seg>
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Wilhelmi</seg>, — We are now approaching the Victoria River so closely, that I must think of closing my different letters. I will therefore not allow this opportunity to pass by, without writing to you, previous to our penetrating into the Interior, or rather previous to our landing, for after that I shall have all hands full, and will not have time to write to any one. After considering for a long time I have at last determined to accompany the expedition. Perhaps I am doing wrong, but under present circumstances I am afraid it is the only thing I can do. Should it please God to let me return in safety, I should then be enabled to live and botanise independently; whilst otherwise I should, in a very few years, have spent my savings in New South Wales. I fear my position as Government Botanist is at an end, as I wrote to you already from Moreton Bay.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to C. Wilhelmi, 10 August 1855.</p>
               </note> …<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This and following ellipsis in source text.</p>
               </note> In my last letter I observed to you that I thought it the most advisable course for you to accept work of any kind in the Botanical Gardens at Melbourne, if only for a short time; you will thus have many opportunities to become acquainted with the botany of this country. … I am very anxious about my collection of plants since I received your last;<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> and I intreat you most urgently to see them removed to some place of safety, if you should leave the gardens. Perhaps we may at some future time have the pleasure of settling together at Mount Gambier, and I need not repeat that it will always afford me the greatest pleasure to assist you in any way in my power. Mr Gregory (the leader of the expedition) is very agreeable, and I think I shall also agree very well with the rest of our companions. The sea air has wonderfully improved my strength. We landed on four islands, and there and at Moreton Bay I collected a large box full of plants, which will be despatched to the English Government; but there are only a few new plants amongst the number. Please send 20 copies of my papers (printed in the transactions of the Philosophical Society)<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B55.09.02, B55.09.03, B54.13.06.</p>
               </note> to Sir William Hooker. At the end of next year I hope to find letters from you, care of Major Christie, in Sydney, in which you will be able to inform me of any matters that may have occurred during my absence, and by which my future movements may be influenced. Farewell, dear Wilhelmi, and be assured of my sincere interest in your welfare, and that I recollect with great pleasure the time when we were labouring and travelling together. — Yours, &amp;c.,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">(Signed) FERDINAND MUELLER.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
