<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melb. Botanic Gardens ¶ 14th May, 1880 ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ I have the honor to enclose herewith, copies of a Series of notices, and also extracts from various newspapers, concerning the "A.B.C. of Botany", re...</title>
            <author>William Guilfoyle</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1880-9/80-05-14Guilfoyle-Ramsay.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>80/16940, unit 516, VPRS 794 central inwards registered correspondence, VA 714 Education Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>80.05.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William Guilfoyle</author>
               <title>Melb. Botanic Gardens ¶ 14th May, 1880 ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ I have the honor to enclose herewith, copies of a Series of notices, and also extracts from various newspapers, concerning the "A.B.C. of Botany", re...</title>
               <date when="1880-05-14">1880-05-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1880-9/80-05-14Guilfoyle-Ramsay.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Robert Ramsay</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melb. Botanic Gardens ¶ 14th May, 1880 ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ I have the honor to enclose herewith, copies of a Series of notices, and also extracts from various newspapers, concerning the "A.B.C. of Botany", re...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">80.05.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">William Guilfoyle to Robert Ramsay</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">80/16940, unit 516, VPRS 794 central inwards registered correspondence, VA 714 Education Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 22 May 1880 Ramsay referred this letter to the Board of Examiners for their report, and sent a letter to Guilfoyle. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">[Gen 80/13404'</seg>. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">[...]: 'Returned 16.1180.'</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Melb. Botanic Gardens</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14th May, 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to enclose herewith, copies of a Series of notices, and also extracts from various newspapers, concerning the "A.B.C. of Botany", recently published for me by Mr Samuel Mullen, Bookseller Collins Street East.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It will be seen, that the reviews &amp;c, are in every instance of such a nature, as to lead to the opinion, that the work in question is calculated to supply a want in connection with both the elementary and practical teaching of the Science of Botany.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May I ask you therefore to be so good as to peruse the papers referred to, with the object of having the "A.B.C. of Botany" adopted as a Hand Book, in connection with the teaching of the Science in the State Schools of Victoria</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your Most Obedient Servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">W. R. Guilfoyle</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Honorable Robert Ramsay M.P.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Minister for Education</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Copy of Extracts from Various Newspapers Letters &amp;c, re <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">"ABC of Botany"</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Argus" February 8th 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"Mr Guilfoyle's ABC of Botany is just such a book as was wanted for the purposes of elementary teaching in the Science to which it relates. When that Science took its rise the Latin language was the medium of communication among the learned men in all parts of Europe, and thus a nomenclature borrowed from that language and from the Greek was adopted by all the botanists from Otto Brumfels to Linnaeus and Haller, and has proved a serious obstacle to the popularisation of the study of this otherwise fascinating branch of knowledge. Thousands have been repelled from it by what Grimward calls its "unqualifiable epithets" which symbolise nothing to the minds of 99 persons out of every hundred, and are only excusable when our copious mother tongue offers no expressive equivalent. To men who thought in Greek or Latin, and who wrote the latter language fluently the words monocotyledon, dicotyledon, and acotyledon, for example, conveyed the idea of one seed-lobe, two seed-lobe, and seed lobeless respectively, but to the average English, American, or Australian schoolboy or schoolgirl they are "crack-jam" phrases which have to be translated into the vernacular before the verbal symbol can be associated with the thing signified. Bearing this in mind, and remembering also that the natural sciences have ceased to be the property of a privileged few, and are being "vulgarised", as the French say for the instruction and enjoyment of the masses, Mr Guilfoyle has aimed at simplicity and intelligibility in his modest little manual for the use of schools. "My plan is" he observes in the preface, "to begin at the beginning, and to arrange each step of learning so that when once taken it shall not easily be forgotten." he traces the progress of a plant from its germination until it has accomplished the purpose of its existence by fructification, and relates the processes involved. He explains the meaning of each of the technical terms he has occasion to employ; and he illustrates the diversified forms and structures of roots and leaves by drawings exhibiting the shapes of each. In like manner he anatomises the garden fuchsia, in order to show the constituent elements which it possesses in common with all other flowers; and he dissects the misnamed indigenous "fuchsia" so as to exhibit its points of dissimilarity with its presumed relation. Seven chapters devoted to elementary instruction in relation to seeds, roots, stems, leaves, flowers, fruits, and cotyledons, are followed by a catalogue of the principal plants of economic value, systematically enumerated, and giving their common as well as their botanical names and their native countries. A copious index, which is also a glossary, like that attached to Mr Robert Brown's "manual of Botany" materially increases the utility of Mr Guilfoyle's serviceable little book, the form of which resembles that of the "Science Primers" which are being issued in England by Messrs MacMillan &amp; Co."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Daily Telegraph" January 31st 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"Mr W. R. Guilfoyle, F.L.S. director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens, has forwarded to us a very useful little work entitled the "ABC of Botany". The book is to some extent an introduction to Mr Guilfoyle's "First book of Australian Botany" published last year. The authors object in compiling so instructive a guide to Botany is fully set forth in the preface. He remarks: 'it is designed for the use of the youngest scholar, but is equally fitted for the maturer student. To botany like every other science, there is no royal road, but still it is possible to clear the path of botanical study from many a thorn of scientific nomenclature and many a tangle of needless technicality, and render it so easy and pleasant to youthful feet as to encourage them to keep in the upward and never-ending way of knowledge". After looking through the "ABC of Botany", we can safely say that Mr Guilfoyle has admirably succeeded in the pleasant task he undertook. The different subjects treated are explained by some well executed woodcuts. Mr S. Mullen is the publisher of the book"</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Evening "Herald" February 10th 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"We had recently to take exception to the publication of a work at the cost of the country on account of its incomprehensible erudition and the transparent egotism of the author. We have before us an unpretending book of quite another sort, published by a Government Servant at his own expense, showing that he has the welfare [...]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">line cut off on photocopy</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">giving in an easy and comprehensive form a vast deal of information on the subject of which he treats. We allude to Guilfoyle's ABC of Botany, published for that gentleman, who is director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens, by Mr S. Mullen. It is not only an A.B.C. easy of comprehension, and devoid of crack jaw terms, but it is an Alpha and Omega of the rudiments of Botany which mastered, enables those wishing to do so to comprehend all the important facts about a charming study. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">The price is 1/- only"</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Australasian" February 9th 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">"The ABC of Botany"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"In pursuit of the task commenced last year of endeavouring to popularise the Science of botany, Mr W. R. Guilfoyle, director of the Melbourne Botanic gardens, has prepared a little work bearing the above title. Mr Guilfoyle would appear to have discovered a necessity for some simple introductory work, for he concludes his prefatory remarks by intimating that The ABC of Botany may be usefully regarded as an introduction to his First Book of Australian Botany, published by him the previous year. Remarking that botany has hitherto been practically untaught in our schools, the author of the ABC explains the reason by saying that in no book yet published are the rudiments of botany rendered easy of grasp by the youthful understanding; those, also of riper years are said to have confessed that the ordinary botanical manuals demand a closer and more troublesome application than they care to give. Mr Guilfoyle, on these premises, says: With all this in view, and greatly prompted by my love of the subject, I have devoted myself to the preparation of this little work, which I, with some confidence, believe contains sound and full instruction in the rudiments of botany— [...]<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">words cut off photocopy</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>, the groundwork of the whole science - conveyed in language sufficiently clear and expressive as to strike home to the feeblest capacity,and in such a form as to readily reach not only the understanding but the memory. It is designed for the use of the youngest scholar, but is equally fitted for the maturer student. To botany like every other science, there is no royal road, but still it is possible to clear the path of botanical study of many a thorn of scientific nomenclature, and many a tangle of needless technicality, and render it so easy and pleasant to youthful feet as to encourage them to keep in the upward and never ending way of knowledge. I hope I have done good work in this direction. Of course however enticing the study is made, it must from the outset involve some technicalities, but I have striven to make them no stumbling-blocks. My plan is to begin at the beginning, and so arrange each step of learning that, when once taken it shall not easily be forgotten. To gain this end I have caused the main points the student has to bear in mind to appear in my book again and again, and as each technicality presents itself it is carefully explained. I assert that, under the strict rule of nothing be allowed to pass until it is understood, whoever goes through this manual to the end will establish a lasting foundation of botanical knowledge, and possess a valuable and ever-recurring help to the study of its <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">more advanced and intricate</hi>
               </seg> branches"</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Australasian Schoolmaster and Literary Review" February 17th 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"The ABC of Botany by W. R. Guilfoyle F.L.S., &amp;C</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In this unpretentious little work the curator of the Melbourne Botanical Gardens has embodied some elementary lessons of the Science of Botany. To those teachers who cannot find attraction in the more elaborate works of Balfour, Hooker, and Baron von Mueller, the book will prove of service. "No Science is more easy of acquisition than botany" says "Mr Guilfoyle" because none has a simpler foundation." From the common sward we tread, nor the green leaf rustling on the wayside tree, to the most brilliant blossom that ever rewarded the florists care - from the familiar grain of corn, or commonest fibre for textile fabric to the richest fruit or stateliest tree - the whole world of vegetation obeys the same immutable natural law, and the rudiments of that law once understood, the door is open to the mastery of the most complex and abstruse branch of the fascinating subject. Yet Botany has hitherto been practically untaught in our Schools. Why when so much pains are bestowed upon other points of knowledge, this, which is so well recognised, so plain, and so useful, should be neglected is hard to say." Possibly the reason may be found in the fact that the utilitarian character of this branch of science is not universally recognized; but more probably in the absence of Botany from the list of subjects for which the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">state pays "result money".</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Ballarat Star" January 28th 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"The ABC of Botany is the title of a very useful little book by W. R Guilfoyle director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens. The book contains a very clear explanation of the terms used in botany, and will form an admirable introduction to the study of that science. It is published by <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">S. Mullen Collins St Melbourne</hi>
               </seg>".</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Castlemaine Representative"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"We have received an excellent little manual of Botany under the title of the "A.B.C. of Botany" by W. R. Guilfoyle F.L.S. Director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens. The book may be regarded as an introduction to Mr Guilfoyle's First Book of Australian Botany which was published last year, and is a most valuable contribution to the primary literature of the country. In a brief preface the author points out that though no science is more easy of acquisition or interesting yet it remains practically untaught in our schools. This is probably because in no book are the rudiments of Botany rendered easy of grasp by the youthful understanding. The book in question is designed to supply and will supply the want referred to. It contains the whole groundwork of the science in clear and expressive language, all technicalities are avoided where possible and when used of necessity are fully explained. The main points to be impressed on the student appear in the book again and again and any one who acquires the information contained in the manual, will have gained a lasting foundation of botanical knowledge, enabling him to pursue the higher branches with pleasant ease. The book should be established at once in all state schools as the primary instructor in Botanical Science, which can be pursued healthfully and without capital, with advantage to the student and the community generally, for there are few earnest students who cannot contribute fresh facts and observations, which, especially in a comparatively unknown flora as this country contains, are valuable. Mr Guilfoyle is to be congratulated on the completion of the most valuable first book on botany which has come under our notice."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Belfast Gazette" February 5th 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"We have to acknowledge the receipt from the author, Mr Guilfoyle, the director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens, of a neat little brochure entitled the A.B.C. of Botany. The work may be regarded as an introduction to an earlier work by the same author, the first book Australian Botany. The work in question is divided into eight chapters, each chapter containing a digest of each separate department of the science. It also contains a list of much value of plants used as food, medicine, fibres, dyes, and timber trees of commerce. The work is written in a popular style, and is profusely illustrated by wood cuts, and is well calculated to assist the young as well as the more advanced student in acquiring a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">knowledge of the science</hi>
               </seg>".</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Warrnambool Standard February 3rd 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"The "A.B.C. of Botany" is the title of a useful hand book by Mr W. R. Guilfoyle, Director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens, published by Mr S. Mullen. It describes and names, with illustrations, the different kinds of seeds, roots, stems, leaves, flowers, and fruits, so that it furnishes the beginner with a complete elementary nomenclature. In the hands of a teacher who could find his illustrations in nature, it should prove of great service. It contains also a list of the principal plants of economic value, and an index which enhances its worth as a book of reference. The author states int he preface that the "A.B.C. of Botany" may be regarded as an introduction to his "First Book of Australian Botany", published in 1878. In point of fact, the former is to a great extent a reprint from the latter work."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Town &amp; Country Journal" Sydney February 14th 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">ABC of Botany</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"We are in receipt of a copy of a diminutive book under the [...]<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">cut off photocopy</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> title by the director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens Mr W. R. Guilfoyle. The main object of the little work is to help beginners, by making them conversant with the terms employed to distinguish the various forms of the more prominent and conspicuous organs of plants, as leaves, stems, flowers, fruits, &amp;c. To aid in this a few explanatory figures are added, as are also references to living plants, easily accessible, and illustrative of the forms described. The author regards the work as an introduction to his previously published "First Book of Australian Botany." The book consists of but one hundred small sized pages, and one half of these are occupied by lists of plants of economic value, and an index of thirty pages. The smallness of the work is, perhaps, its best recommendation; while it cannot fail to be of service to numbers of people who but for it, might never have an opportunity of commencing so delightful and useful a study. In the United States of America simple information of this kind is scattered broadcast in a thousand forms; but in Australia, Victoria alone has given attention to this and other kindred objects. There Baron Muellers "School Botany", published some two or three years since, may be mentioned as equal in educational value, as well as in other respects to anything of the kind to be met with in older countries, has been widely distributed. Besides this Mr Guilfoyle's work already referred to was published subsequently, so that school managers may choose from two rudimentary botanical works, each of which is specially designed for the students of Victorian Botany. Besides these various works of a more advance description and creditable to the colony have been issued from the Victorian Press. Although there is little to criticise to praise or blame in the work before us [...]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">cut off on photocopy</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> hail its appearance with pleasure, as an indication of a growing desire to promote the study of a science which occupies a place second to none amongst the sciences in promoting the best interests of the human family, and clearing the paths for the march onward to perfection."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Daily Telegraph" Sydney February 7th 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">"The A.B.C. of Botany</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Is a remarkably unpretentious little volume. Mr Guilfoyle, director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens, has written not only one of the best elementary works on the subject, but one of considerable use as a work of reference. Not only does he explain, and that most clearly and briefly in simple language, the base of botanical classification and the different and curious forms of vegetable life, but the book contains a most valuable index to trees and plants of economic value."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "South Australian Advertiser" February 17th 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"Mr W. R. Guilfoyle, F.L.S. the able and popular director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens, has usefully continued the work he began last year in the publication of his "First Book of Australian Botany" That volume was designed to meet the wants of students hailing from other parts of the world and the colonies, who possessing some elementary knowledge of the Science of botany might be desirous of studying the flora of Australia. Mr Guilfoyle, however, finding, that among the visitors to the gardens who were anxious to become more than mere lounging admirers of its floral beauties there were many to whom his book was practically sealed from the want of elementary knowledge, needing inf act instruction in the alphabet of botany, he determined if possible to supply the required means of education. The result of his thought has been the production of a small work entitled "The A.B.C. of Botany," a copy of which he has courteously forwarded to us. As an instruction book for the school pupil, and even as a manual to the maturer student, the work leaves little to be desired. While following a thoroughly scientific method, the author successfully disentangles intricacies, explains nomenclature, and metamorphoses the definitions of philosophers into language that may be understood by the least scientific of minds. Of course as Mr Guilfoyle points out, there is no royal road to botany, difficulties must be overcome by patience, and obstacles surmounted by perseverance in study in that as in every other science. Still the path of the student may be smoothed and his steps assisted, and assuredly Mr Guilfoyle's book is well calculated to render less rugged the path of any one aspiring to a knowledge of the interesting science he seeks to teach. Its not least important feature, so far as Australian students are concerned, is that as is fitting should be the case, the author is careful in illustrating the various scientific terms to refer to plants familiarly known in the colonies. It may be also noticed that a very useful synopsis is given of all the principal plants known throughout the work possessing an economic value, and indicating the various uses to which they can be applied. Mr Guilfoyle's work is published by Mr S. Mullen of Collins St Melbourne, and reflects great credit upon the printer."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The "Hobart Town Mercury" February 3rd 1880.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"Mr Guilfoyle director of the Melbourne Botanic Gardens has just prepared a very useful "A.B.C. of Botany" Which is published by S. Mullen of Melbourne. The book contains in all one hundred pages and is written specially for those both old and young, who wish to make themselves acquainted with the elements of a science, which the author complains is too much neglected in our schools. No science is more interesting to the general mind than Botany, and none is more easy of acquisition because one has a simpler foundation. In this little work Mr Guilfoyle has endeavoured to give sound and full instruction in the rudiments of the sciences — indeed the whole groundwork — in language sufficiently clear and expressive as to strike home to the feeblest capacity; and from a cursory glance at the contents we think he has accomplished the task most efficiently. The book deserves an extensive circulation."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">letter from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">H. N. Andrew Esq </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Principal Wesley College St Kilda</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"I regret that pressure of work has kept me from even looking at your "ABC of Botany" until now. I thank you for sending it; it seems to be a good and useful primer of Botany. Of its merits as a school book I cannot say without trying it and this must depend upon the report of Matriculation Scheme now being considered by the University Council"</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Letter from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">F. J. Gladman Esq</hi>
               </seg> B.A. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Superintendent of the Training Institution</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"I have to thank you for your little book A.B.C. of Botany. It appears to me to deal with the rudimentary facts and chief technical terms of the Science in such a way as to make it a useful introduction to the larger and more complete manuals, and it ought to be a useful text book, where the teacher can supply the needful amplifications, illustrations, and explanations."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Extract Letter <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from Sydney Gibbons Esq. </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">East Melbourne</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"I thank you for the interesting little book you have been kind enough to send me and for the compliment implied in your invitation of my criticism. I have read it through carefully and must admit that you have succeeded in putting a very large amount of useful information in very small compass and in language that all may understand. It ought to be found very useful. I much like the combination of index and glossary. The lists of officinal plants are very valuable and may well be supplemented in a future edition by some of the more familiar Australian plants and trees."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Letter from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">J. Lang Esq</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Seed Merchant &amp;c Melbourne.</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"Only to day have I received your presentation copy of the "ABC of Botany" and I thank you kindly for thus remembering me. I have gone over it all and am satisfied that it will be a most useful beginner's book"</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Extract Letter <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from Dr J. McMillan</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline"> Melbourne</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"I think your book will supply a want which has been long felt &amp; I am sure it only requires to be known, to be brought into general use"</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Letter from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">D Sullivan Esq</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">State School 1263 Moyston</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I thank you very much for your kindness in sending me your second book of Botany. I have read it through and consider it admirably suited for school classes. The style is simple yet it includes all the principal technical terms used by botanists placed before the student in such a manner that he cannot fail to have a clear idea of their meaning. The technicalities of a science cannot be dispensed with without the risk of making grave mistakes, but they may be placed before the mind in such a manner as not to create disgust at the very outset. I am pleased to see that your book is clear of all that is burdensome to the minds of beginners, and is made as attractive as any work dealing with so extensive a subject could be made. Those who study "A.B.C. of Botany" with care, and master all its details will find that they can afterwards continue the investigation of the higher departments of the science with comparative ease."</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Letter from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Hon. J. J. Casey</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline"> Melbourne</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">"many thanks for your very interesting work which does you infinite credit. When I tell you that I have taken an interest in reading it I am giving you the best evidence of my appreciation of your work"</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
