<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Brown's Camp ¶ 19/3/89. ¶ […] ¶  ¶ It will be satisfactory to you to learn that on the day you wrote (15th inst.) I was up on Tingiringi Mountain on purpose, if possible, to obtain the flowers of the ...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Bäuerlen</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1880-9/89-03-19Bäuerlen-Maiden.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MRS 203, Inwards correspondence — special bundles, 1886-1921 Item 1, 89/117, Archives of the Powerhouse Museum, Sydney.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>89.03.19</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Bäuerlen</author>
               <title>Brown's Camp ¶ 19/3/89. ¶ […] ¶  ¶ It will be satisfactory to you to learn that on the day you wrote (15th inst.) I was up on Tingiringi Mountain on purpose, if possible, to obtain the flowers of the ...</title>
               <date when="1889-03-19">1889-03-19</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1880-9/89-03-19Bäuerlen-Maiden.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>Standard</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Maiden</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Brown's Camp ¶ 19/3/89. ¶ […] ¶  ¶ It will be satisfactory to you to learn that on the day you wrote (15th inst.) I was up on Tingiringi Mountain on purpose, if possible, to obtain the flowers of the ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">89.03.19</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">Wilhelm Bäuerlen to Joseph Maiden</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">MRS 203, Inwards correspondence — special bundles, 1886-1921 Item 1, 89/117, Archives of the Powerhouse Museum, Sydney.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Transcribed 6 November 1992.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Brown's Camp</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">19/3/89.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[…]</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It will be satisfactory to you to learn that on the day you wrote (15th inst.) I was up on Tingiringi Mountain on purpose, if possible, to obtain the flowers of the supposed Euc. stricta growing there. That I have been successful in my search I have told you already in a letter, which went by yesterdays Mail. In that letter I have also given you more particulars about the species, to which particulars I have now</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">only to add (since you think the species stands near E. viminalis) that the flowers when fresh have a strong <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mannalike</hi>
               </seg> smell, only the smell is much coarser than that of manna and more stifling. This feature I have mentioned already in a letter I wrote to the Baron on the subject yesterday, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">before I recieved</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline"> your letter</hi>
               </seg>, so that the observation stands independent, and not in any way influenced by anything you said in your last letter. […]</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> As said already, I wrote a letter on the subject to Baron von Muller yesterday and at the same time forwarded a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">complete set of specimens</hi>
               </seg> to him. In my letter I stated, that two years ago he determined this species for me as E. stricta; that lately I sent a small quantity of Kino of it to you; that the results of your chemical investigations threw doubt upon the Kino coming from E. stricta, and that you naturally came to the conclusion that I may have made a mistake and obtained the Kino from another species, and that consequently you applied to me in the matter as pressing your doubts as to the species; that in reply I told you that I was sure that I obtained the Kino from the species, which he (Baron von Muller) two years ago determined for me as E. stricta, from the identical locality, and that at the same time I forwarded to you a specimen in fruit and one of the leaves in the young state, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">but no flowers</hi>
               </seg>, as at that time I could not find any, and that the result of all this was to puzzle you much, since according to your chemical results, this would be the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">only species</hi>
               </seg> of the Renanthera which in cold water gives a turbid solution owing to the presence of saponins. Under those circumstances I considered it my duty, apart from the interest I take in the matter, to try, if possible, to obtain the flowers of the species and have it investigated once more, and having now succeeded in obtaining flowering specimens, I forward a complete set of specimens (fruit, flowers, buds, and leaves in the growing state) with full particulars otherwise about the species.</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You may be sure Sir that I worded my letter to the Baron so, that he will take no offence, and I think he will be rather glad than otherwise to have an opportunity to correct an oversight in his work, (if such has been the case.) You yourself will allow that it would not be the right thing to take the matter entirely out of his hands, in fact your suggestion toward the end of your letter directly implies that it should remain in his hands.</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I for my part hope that your surmise regarding the species in question may likely prove new, will be correct, and I am quite sure that the Baron in that case would name it after you, especially in consideration that it would be owing to your chemical investigation of the kinos, [that] a new species would have been detected, which otherwise may have been overlooked by the highest authorities for many years to come. […]</p>
            <p rend="Standard"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I also forwarded a few small pieces of bark to you, which is, as I have also stated to Baron von Muller, comparatively rather thin, and the inner layers seem rather fibrous. […]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not relevant.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
