<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ When, two years ago, I got back from a trip to Australia I presented a collection of flora to this illustrious Athenaeum and you, benign and generous, gave me the most flattering proof of your acce...</title>
            <author>Francesco Rampinelli</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1880-9/M86-05-16-nonsf.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Archives, Ateneo di Brescia, Brescia.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M86.05.16</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Francesco Rampinelli</author>
               <title> ¶ When, two years ago, I got back from a trip to Australia I presented a collection of flora to this illustrious Athenaeum and you, benign and generous, gave me the most flattering proof of your acce...</title>
               <date when="1886-05-16">1886-05-16</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1880-9/M86-05-16-nonsf.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Ateneo di Brescia</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ When, two years ago, I got back from a trip to Australia I presented a collection of flora to this illustrious Athenaeum and you, benign and generous, gave me the most flattering proof of your acce...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M86.05.16</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Francesco Rampinelli to the Ateneo di Brescia</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Archives, Ateneo di Brescia, Brescia.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS is in a file marked ‘Ateneo di Brescia nella seduta del 16. Maggio 1886’ [<seg style="font-size: 8pt; ">Brescia Athenaeum in the session of 16 May 1886</seg>]. A modified version of the text was published in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Commentari dell’Ateneo di Brescia per l’anno 1886</seg> (Brescia, 1886), pp. 147-8.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Quando, or fan due anni, avendo io presentato a questo Illustr. Ateneo, recata da un mio viaggio all’Australia, una collezione di quella flora, voi benigni e generosi, voleste darmi il più lusinghiero attestato del vostro gradimento coll’accoglierme in cosi onorevole consesso, io mi tenni sin d’allora in debito e bramai, se mi fosse dato, di compiere il mio piccol dono, col procurarmi di colà anche un saggio di minerali, per offrirlo ugualmente a questo Decoro della mia patria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Varie peripezie ritardarono alquanto una tale offerta; l’indugio però venne compensato dall’essermi insieme pervenute circa 200 altre specie della flora australiana, da poter aggiungere alle 300 do me già presentate.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ed oggi ho la compiacenza de presentare al patrio Ateneo [anabe] le collezioni, e di pregare l’Illustre Presidenza e gli Onorevoli Soci di usarmi la solita indulgenze[.]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>La collezione di minerali mi fu spedita dal Sigr Coy, direttore del Museo mineralogico di Melbourne, la flora mi venne dall’Illustre Barone F de Mueller, professore di medicina, da lui con gràn curo raccolta e classificata; nella quale molte specie farono da lui stesso scoperte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ora abbandono la botanica e poichè vi ho nominato il barone Mueller mi parebbe di mancare al giusto omaggio verso la scienza e al sentimento di gratitudine, se non vi pregassi di lasciarmi dire brevi parole intorno ai meriti di questo Illustre cultore e propagatore della scienza, che fu con me tanto cortese, durate il mio soggiorno a que nostri antipode, ed alla cui potente autorità in tutta l’Australia io mi professe debitore, ve potei penetrare colà ogni dove, e vedere tante singolarità di quella regione, tanti lontana e si poco da noi conosciuta.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Il barone F. de Mueller, discendente da Illustri famiglia di Germania, </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">recossi in Australia un 40 anni fa, attrattovi non già dall’ingordigia dell’ore, ma sibbene dal grande trasporto ch’egli nutriva pei viaggi arditi, e dall’amore della scienza, sicuro che in quella terra avrebbe trovato un pascolo fecondo, e potuto dilatare ed accrescere vieppiù le sue vaste cognizioni. Stabilitosi in Melbourne, il suo sapere gli conciglio ben presto tante stima presso tutta quella cittadinanza, che si affido a lui l’incarico di tracciare i quartieri principali che si venivano costruendo, e così egli pote obbligare i proprietarii a tenere una certa regolarità nelle fabbrich[e] lasciando le vie spaziose, con tratto tratto giardini e parchi, in modo che egli ora sia la compiacenza di vedere le sua città primeggiere fra le più belle e salubri del mondo. Costrusse un giardino botanico di meravigliosa bellezza, ove egli lavoro assiduamente per anni ed anni, a fine di arrichirlo di tutte le piante indigene e delle più belle esotiche, tutte disposte nel miglior ordine, tutte classificate. Egli percorse l’interno del paese, penetrò nei luoghi più inesplorati, scoprendo mollissimi oggetti di storia naturale e di botanica, e scrisse pure un grosso volume sulla flora australiana, opera preziosa e frutto del più diligente lavoro. Ma non meno della mente, si dimostrò grande il cuore del barone de Mueller in più circostanze; mi limiterò a recarne per saggio ciò che egli fece per rintracciare il suo compatriota, l’ardito esploratore Leichthard, di cui non si aveva più notizia. Questi dopo aver fatto magnifici viaggi nell’interno, ove vide un continuo avvicendarsi di deserti, di ubertose pianure, di verdeggianti colline e di immense foreste, volle partire un’altra volta da Moreton Bay, per esplorare la parte Nord-Est.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Passarono diversi anni senza che si avesse notizia di Lui, e senza che si potesse seguirne le tracc[ia]: la sua stessa memoria quasi era caduta in dimenticanza. Ma il generoso barone Mueller non potè restare indifferente circa la sorte toccata al sua compatriota, e s’accinse a rintracciarlo.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Col mezzo dei giornali cominciò a commovere l’opinione pubblica, si che della somme considerevoli furono presto radunate a tale scopo, e stabilito di farne la più premurosa ricerca. Allora egli stesso, scortato da diversi coraggiosi, seguendo gli indizii che potè raccogliere fra i nativi, percorre senza tregua le regioni più selvaggie lunghesso il golfo di Carpentaria, a 1200 miglia da Melbourne, cercando con ardire dappertutto l’infelice compratiota, durando sovente sin 8 o 10 giorni senza trovar acqua, molte volte privo di provvigioni, e ad ogni tratto costretto a difendersi contro le tribù selvagg[..] che l’attaccavano colle loro frec[cie] avvelenate.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ed ogni qual volta gli parea di avere scoperto qualche traccia del passaggio di Leichthard, prendeva nuova lena per inoltrarsi; e sebbbene affrante dalle fatichete dai disag[...] di quei perigliosissimi viaggi, non cesso dalle ricerche se non quando per gli indizii raccolti pur troppo dovette persuadersi con tutta certezza che il suo caro amico era stato tracidato dai neri, per ingordigia di bottino.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Quanto intraprendente, altrettanto costante ne’ suo arditi propositi, il barone Mueller, ho incoraggiate e felicemente guidato lo spirito avventuroso delle giovine generazione australiana.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Egli anima i nuovi Squatter, dicende loro coll’entusiasmo di chi possiede la certezza di ciô che promette: Andate innanzi; dopo i deserti troverete praterie senza fine che alimenteranno migliaia e migliaia di mandre. E cosi avveniva di fatto.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ma il male dell’Australia è la mancaanza di acqua; ed ecco ei vuol rimediarvi: egli confacca a questo scopo tutto quanto ricava dal giardino botanico, e vi riesce. In che modo? Distribuisce in mezzo a quelle vaste praterie milioni d’arbusti; crescono questi; piccoli rivoli si formano presto nel folto de’novelli boschi, e così il bestiame trova di che dissetarsi. I risultati sono immensi; ai boschi si aggiungono fertili campi coltivati ad ogni sorta di prodotti.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ma ciò che eccitava qualche anno fa maggiormente l’entusiasmo, è che egli ha potuto mettersi alla testa d’un grande movimento, impegnare tutte le colonie australiane a costruir[...] a spese <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>comuni una ferrovia, che andra de Melbourne a Port Darwin, nel golfo di Carpentaria. Così si traversera l’Australia da un capo all’altro, sarà aperto tutto l’interno alla colonizzazione, sarà per la nuova strada quel continente reso meno lontano dall’Europa e dalla China.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Già la grandiosa impresa si avanza a gran passo, e non ne sentirà soltanto quel nuovo populo i beneficii, ma tutti gli altri ne saranno a parte. Già poi non solo tutti gli amatori delle scienze naturali onorano l’Illustre scienziato, ma tutti i populi benedicono lo scopritore della virtù dell’Eucalypto, come pianta febbrifug[...] Ne spedi egli dappertutto, e così molti e molti luoghi paludosi, inabitabili, vanno purgandosi dai miasmi e dalla malaria, mutandosi in campagne fertilie salubri.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Tutti i principali musei e giardini botanici del mondo devono a lui se posseggono cose dell’Australia, tutte le principali società scientifiche si onorano del suo nome, ond’egli è coperto di decorazioni.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>E qui pongo fine a questi brevi cenni, ringraziandovi, Onorevolis. Soci, di avermi dato mezzo di sciaglier in parte verso l’Illustre barone Ferd. de Mueller un debito sacro di gratitudine, coll’inviargli anche da Brescia, da questa sede nostra delle scienze e delle arti, un plauso sincero, un rispettoso saluto.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When, two years ago, I got back from a trip to Australia I presented a collection of flora to this illustrious Athenaeum and you, benign and generous, gave me the most flattering proof of your acceptance in welcoming me in such honourable assembly. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Since then I considered myself in debt and longed, if I was given the chance, to complete my small donation by getting a specimen of minerals from that continent and offering it to my homeland. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Various events prevented me from accomplishing this offer but the delay got compensated in getting 200 more species of Australian flora that got added to the other 300 samples I already submitted. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Today I have the pleasure to present this collection to this native Athenaeum and I ask the illustrious Presidency and the Honourable Members to grant me the usual indulgence. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The mineral collection was sent to me by Mr Coy,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I.e. Frederick McCoy.</p>
               </note> director of the mineralogical museum of Melbourne, the flora came to me from the illustrious Baron F von Mueller, professor of medicine, who took great care in the collecting and classifying, in the course of which he himself discovered many species. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I will now put aside botany and since I mentioned Baron Mueller, it would be lacking proper homage towards science and towards my feeling of gratitude if I omitted talking about the merits of this illustrious cultivator and propagator of science, who was so courteous to me during my trip to our antipodes, and to whose powerful authority throughout Australia I consider myself indebted, able to delve everywhere and discover many singularities of that country so remote and unknown to us.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Baron F Mueller, descendant of an illustrious German family, arrived in Australia 40 years ago not because he was attracted by greed for gold but for his love of adventure and science, convinced that in this land he would find fruitful ground and be able to widen and augment his vast knowledge. Settled in Melbourne, he soon gained so much respect from almost all the citizenry that he was entrusted with the task of delineating the principal neighbourhoods that were being constructed, thus enabling him to oblige proprietors to keep to a certain regularity in building, leaving open spaces with extensive parks and gardens so that he now has the satisfaction of seening his city become one of the most beautiful and salubrious in the world.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is no evidence of M's being involved in town planning of this kind.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>He built a botanic garden of marvellous beauty where he worked assiduously for many years to enrich it with all the indigenous plants and the more beautiful exotic ones, all arranged in the best order and classified. He travelled across the interior of country, penetrating into uncharted places and discovering most delicate objects <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of natural history and botany, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and writing a <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>large volume on the Australian flora, a precious work, the fruit of prodigious labour. But not less that a great mind, Baron von Mueller <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>has also shown a great heart in many ways. I <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>shall limit myself to telling as an example what he did to track down his compatriot the bold explorer Leichthard,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ludwig Leichhardt.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>from whom nothing has been heard. Leichthard had <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>made a magnificent journey into the interior and after crossing deserts, fertile plains, green hills and vast forests he decided to <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>depart once more from Moreton Bay to explore the North East.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On his final journey Leichhardt intended to explore the north-west of Australia, not the north-east.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Many years went by without any news of him, and without any trace being found: even the memory of him fell into oblivion. But the generous Baron Mueller could not <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>remain indifferent to the touching fate of his compatriot so he <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>set out to trace him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Through the newspapers he started to <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>arouse public <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>opinion and a considerable sum was quickly gathered for such a purpose and a most zealous search set in motion. Accompanied by other courageous men, Baron Mueller set off,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M never undertook such an expedition. Rampinelli’s account seems to conflate elements of the North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6, of which M was a member, and the 1865 Leichhardt Search Expedition, of which he was not but in the fundraising and planning for which he played a pivotal role. Several aspects of the account are, however, purely imaginary.</p>
               </note> following the few clues that could be collected from the natives, traversing without rest the wildest regions along the Gulf of Carpentaria, about 1200 miles from Melbourne, searching boldly everywhere for his unfortunate compatriot, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>often going 8 or 10 days without finding water, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>many times lacking provisions and always obliged to defend himself from the savage tribes that attacked him with poisonous arrows.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Every time he seemed to have discovered some trace of Leichthard’s passage, he found new energy to go on; and although exhausted from overcoming the difficulties of this most perilous journey, he did not stop searching until too many indications had been found and he had to accept that in all certainty his dear friend had been killed by blacks in search of booty. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>However enterprising, as much constant in his bold intentions, Baron Mueller has never failed to support and guide the adventurous spirit of the young Australian generations.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>He encouraged the new Squatters with the enthusiasm of someone who is certain and always keeps his promise: keep pushing ahead; beyond the deserts, you will find endless grassland that will feed thousands and thousands of herds. And this is what really happened. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But the lack of water is Australia’s main problem and he found a remedy, making the most of his botanic garden experience. What did he do? He distributed millions of shrubs on the endless grassland and when they grew little streams of water started to form among the new forests sustaining livestock with water to drink. The results are immense, to the forests have been added fertile cultivated fields with every sort of new products.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But what excited major enthusiasm a few years ago is that he headed the grand movement to engage all the Australian colonies in building at common expense a railway that will go from Melbourne to Port Darwin, in the Gulf of Carpentaria.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Darwin is a considerable distance from the Gulf of Carpentaria. No evidence of M’s promoting the building of such a railway has been found.</p>
               </note> This will cross Australia from end to end, opening the whole of the interior to colonization and by the new route making the continent less distant from Europe and from China.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Already the grandiose project is progressing at a great pace and it will be not only the new populace that feels the benefits, but everybody will. Already not only have lovers of natural science honoured the illustrious scientist, everybody blesses the discoverer of the virtue of the <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> as a <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>febrifuge. He sent it everywhere, and as a result many many swampy, uninhabitable places have been purged of miasmas and malaria, and changed into healthy fertile lands.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All the principal museums and botanical gardens around the world owe to him their possessing things from Australia, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>all the principal scientific societies, from which he is covered in decorations, are honoured with his name. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Here I finish this brief acknowledgment, thanking you, Honourable Members, for letting me express towards the illustrious Baron Mueller a sacred debt of gratitude and for sending him from Brescia, from this our centre of art and science, our sincere approval and respectful greetings. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
