<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>28/6/92. ¶  ¶ Through your last letter, ¶  highly esteemed Professor, it has become possible for me to explain the misplacement of the first part of the consignment of Hawaiian plants. Just as you exp...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-06-28a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>92.06.28a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>28/6/92. ¶  ¶ Through your last letter, ¶  highly esteemed Professor, it has become possible for me to explain the misplacement of the first part of the consignment of Hawaiian plants. Just as you exp...</title>
               <date when="1892-06-28">1892-06-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-06-28a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/c7b7118e-07f4-45a9-bad6-bbcaa21e203a">Dilleniaceae</term>
               <term>Myristiceae</term>
               <term>Andrastea </term>
               <term>Candollea</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/73ff9ddb-8eea-4734-86a6-b32984e34356">Hibbertia</term>
               <term>Huttia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="59">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="41">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Adolf Engler</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">28/6/92. ¶  ¶ Through your last letter, ¶  highly esteemed Professor, it has become possible for me to explain the misplacement of the first part of the consignment of Hawaiian plants. Just as you exp...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">92.06.28a</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">To Adolf Engler</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">28/6/92.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch Ihr letztes Schreiben, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, ist es mir möglich geworden, das Vermissen des ersten Theils der Sendung hawaianischer Pflanzen aufzuklären. Ganz wie Sie voraussahen, hat sich das Packet zwischen den Pflanzen Schlagintweit's nun gefunden, und thut es mir leid, Ihnen Sorge und Zeitverlust in dieser Angelegenheit verursacht zu haben. Ich selbst bin ziemlich schuldlos in der Sache nach mehrfachen Erfragen hier. Das Museum (resp. Herbarium) getrockneter Pflanzen besteht aus zwei hohen Hallen ohne Heizung, und ist nicht nahe meiner Bureau-Wohnung, wo in 7 Privat Zimmern ich meine Amtsarbeiten sehr verschiedener Art ausführe. Bei meinem ererbten Brustleiden, welches mich veranlasste in eine wärmere Zone auszuwandern, komme ich in den 5 kühlen u zuweilen selbst kalten Monaten des Jahres nur selten in die zwei Herbar-Saale, so dass das Auspacken und Eintragen in Bücher von erhaltenen Pflanzen-Sendungen einem Gehülfen obliegt, der in diesem Falle über sah, dass sich </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ein</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Packet, freilich ein grosses und werthvolles, von Hillebrand's Pflanzen bei denen Schlagintweit's befand, u. ich erinnere nicht, dass meine Aufmerksamkeit brieflich darauf gelenkt war. Dennoch wäre das Vorhandensein </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dieser</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Hawaia Pflanzen hier nicht unbekannt geblieben, wären solche in die grosse ausser-australische Abtheilung des Herbars inserirt worden, aber einige geographisch abgeschlossene Sammlungen sind hier separat aufbewahrt, so z. B. die Neu Seeländ, die Papuanisch, die Polynesien Pfl, so auch Cuming’s von der Philippinen, Beccari’s von den Sunda-Inseln u auch Schlagintweits von Ober Indien. Ich will nun aber doch lieber </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Alles</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> in das Hauptherbar inseriren lassen, was freilich bei den nun noch mehr verringerten Hülfskräften als Neben-Arbeit eine lange Zeit nehmen mag. Bedenken Sie, soweit das nun erledigte Übersehen mich persönlich angeht, dass ich ein alter Mann bin, dass meine Haupt-Obliegenheiten hier in der Orangen-Zone industriell (technologisch u rural) sein müssen, um die Colonisten zu befriedigen und Ihnen </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">thatsächlich</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> zu nützen, dass daher meine Herbarium-Studien hauptsächlich auf Sonntage u Festage angewiesen sind, obwohl ich täglich wohl ebensoviel Stunden arbeite als unser unvergesslicher Freund Regel. Bloss die Correspondenz erheischte von meiner eignen Hand etwa 3000 Briefe in jedem Jahre, seit 1857, wie ich von den 10-jährigen phytographischen und auch </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geograph.</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Endeckungs Reisen zurückkehrte. Durch viele Jahre habe ich an Sonntag Morgen jüngst angekommene Pfl. im Herbarium selbst ausgetheilt in Familien, aber das Material ist mir mechanischer Handhabung über den Kopf gewachsen, und die Zeit ist mir im Spätherbst meines Lebens sehr knapp geworden. Dies muss es auch entschuldigen, wenn nicht Alles so gut u so schnell ausgeführt wird für Austausch, als ich wohl wünschen möchte. Meine allgemeinen Reise-Diarien zu bearbeiten habe ich noch nie Musse gehabt. Ich will versuchen Ihrer Anstalt, so bald ich vermag, reciprocativ gerecht zu werden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Myristiceen gingen im Lauf dieses Monats an Sie ab, freilich nur in spärlicher Form. <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name> sollen nun bald hervorgesucht werden, aber im </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Haupt-Herbar giebt es keine eigentliche überzählige Ex.</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> und das Hinzugekommene letzterer Zeiten ist nicht immer critisch benannt, eben weil dies so Zeitraubend ist.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich werde für den Gebrauch der Dilleniaceen einige Notizen hinzufügen, damit der Monograph ersehe, mit welcher </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">reichlichen Erwägung</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> die Genera u Arten für den </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Census</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> begrenzt sind; und alles neue Material bestätigt nur, dass <name key="Candollea">Candollea</name>, <name key="Andrastea%20">Andrastea </name>u <name key="Huttia">Huttia</name> zu <name key="Hibbertia">Hibbertia</name> gehören, vielleicht aber nicht die Madagascar-Arten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">28/6/92.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Through your last letter,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> highly esteemed Professor, it has become possible for me to explain the misplacement of the first part of the consignment of Hawaiian plants. Just as you expected, the parcel has now turned up among Schlagintweit's plants and I am sorry to have caused you trouble and loss of time in this regard.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M enclosed with his letter a note to him from his herbarium assistant Gerhard Renner reporting that the parcel had been found; see G. Renner to M, 26 June 1892.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The consignment of Tibetan specimens collected by the Schlagintweit brothers had evidently been sent by Engler together with Hawaiian specimens collected by Hillebrand that Engler had promised M earlier, and about which M had become concerned; see M to A. Engler, 9 May 1890, and M to A. Engler, 11 May 1892. It is not known whether the Tibetan plants were a gift or had been bought by Engler on M's behalf. Sheets on which specmens are mounted are pre-printed, for example <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Delphinium schlagintweitii</seg> MEL 2407606, 'Herbarium Schlagintweit from India and High Asia. Tíbet. Province: Bálti. Locality: Environs of Skárdo. Height (engl. ft.) 6900-7500. Collected 6 August to 4 septbr. 1856'. At the bottom of the sheet details have been entered by hand against the pre-prnited 'Name of plant and remarks' and 'Gen. number of Catalogue'. No copy of the catalogue has been found, but see the advertisement for Schlagintweit plants for sale, placed in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Botanische Zeitung</seg>, vol. 44, p. 464, 2 July 1886 (and at least once more on 16 July) <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>by P. Hennings.</p>
               </note> I myself am rather innocent in the matter after numerous inquiries here. The Museum (or Herbarium) of dried plants consists of two high halls without heating and is not near my home-office, where I carry out my official work of very different kinds in 7 private rooms. In view of my hereditary chest complaints that caused me to emigrate to a warmer zone, in the 5 cool and occasionally even cold months of the year I only seldom come into the two herbarium rooms, so that the unpacking and entries into the books of plant consignments received is incumbent on my assistant, who in this case overlooked that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg> packet, admittedly a large and valuable one, of Hillebrand's plants was with that of Schlagintweit's, and I do not remember that my attention was directed to it by letter. Nevertheless the existence of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">these</hi>
               </seg> Hawaiian plants here would not have remained unknown, if they had been inserted in the large extra-Australian section of the Herbarium, but some geographically connected collections are separately stored here, thus for example the New Zealand, the Papuan, the Polynesian, thus also Cuming's from the Philippines, Beccari's from the Sunda Islands and also Schlagintweit's from upper India. However, I now prefer to have <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">everything</hi>
               </seg> inserted into the main herbarium, which of course may take a long time as additional work, with the work force now even more reduced. Consider as far as the now corrected oversight concerns me personally, that I am an old man, that my main obligations must be industrial (technical and rural) here in the orange zone<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. the warm temperate climate zone where orange trees would flourish? Cf. </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sydney morning herald</seg>, 26 November 1881, p. 7, and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Kew bulletin</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 9 (1895), p</seg>. 126.</p>
               </note> to satisfy the colonists and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">really</hi>
               </seg> be of use to them, that therefore my herbarium studies are mainly dependent on Sundays and holidays, although daily I probably work just as many hours as our unforgettable friend Regel. Just the correspondence has demanded from my own hand about 3000 letters in each year since 1857, when I returned from the 10-year phytographic and also <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geographic</hi>
               </seg> journeys of exploration. For many years on a Sunday morning I have myself distributed the recently arrived plants in the herbarium into families, but the material has got beyond my mechanical handling and time has become very scarce for me in the late autumn of my life. This must also excuse me, if not everything is undertaken as well and quickly for exchange as I would probably wish. I have never yet had the leisure to work up my travel diaries. I shall try, as soon as I can, to reciprocate to your institute properly.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the course of this month <name key="Myristiceae">Myristiceae</name> go off to you, of course only in scant form.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>O. Warburg was preparing a supplement to the treatment by Prantl (1891); see Warburg (1897).</p>
               </note>
               <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name> should now soon be looked out, but in the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">main herbarium there are no really surplus specimens</hi>
               </seg> and those coming in of late are not always critically named, just because it is so time-consuming.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I will include some notes for the use of <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name>, so that the monographer<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Notes not found; no internal evidence has been found that such notes were incorporated into Gilg (1895), printed in January 1893 according to the statement on p. 100 and issued in March 1893 (TL2). Gilg included <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Candollea">Candollea</name>
                     </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Huttia">Huttia</name>
                     </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Adastaea</seg> within <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Hibbertia">Hibbertia</name>
                     </seg>, as M had done in B89.12.03, this being among the works cited as the 'wichtigste Litteratur' [most important literature] for the revision of the <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name>. </p>
               </note> sees with what <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">abundant considerations</hi>
               </seg> the genera and species were delimited for the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Census</hi>
               </seg>;<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>B89.12.03.</p>
               </note> all new material confirms only that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Candollea">Candollea</name>
               </seg>,<seg style="font-style: italic; "> Andrastea</seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Adrastaea</seg>? </p>
                  </note>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Huttia">Huttia</name>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>belong to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hibbertia">Hibbertia</name>
               </seg>, but perhaps not the Madagascar species.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Andrastea%20">Andrastea </name>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Candollea">Candollea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hibbertia">Hibbertia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Huttia">Huttia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myristiceae">Myristiceae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
