<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ In the number of your fine journal that just arrived, noble friend, there is a short note derived from other public newspapers on a supposed resignation by me from the public service of the Colony ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-08-00f-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>92.08.00f</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ In the number of your fine journal that just arrived, noble friend, there is a short note derived from other public newspapers on a supposed resignation by me from the public service of the Colony ...</title>
               <date when="1892-08">1892-08</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-08-00f-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="56">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="44">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Günther von Beck</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ In the number of your fine journal that just arrived, noble friend, there is a short note derived from other public newspapers on a supposed resignation by me from the public service of the Colony ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">92.08.00f</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Günther von Beck</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="">Letter not found. For the extract given here, </seg>see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Wiener illustrirte Garten-Zeitung</seg>,<seg style=""> vol. 17, no. 10 (October 1892), p. 411 (B92.10.03). The item is dated to August 1892 as the latest likely date M’s letter could have been sent, to be received in time to be published in this issue. The text is introduced by: ‘Baron Ferdinand von Mueller. Aus einem Briefe dieses hochverdienten Forschers an Hrn. Dr. v. Beck entnehmen wir’ [Baron Ferdinand von Mueller. We draw from a letter of this researcher of great merit to Dr von Beck].</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In dem eben angelangten Heft Ihrer schönen Zeitschrift, edler Freund, findet sich eine kurze Notiz, aus anderen öffentlichen Blättern entlehnt, über einen vermeintlichen Rücktritt von mir aus dem Staatsdienst der Colonie Victoria. Diese Mittheilung ist aber auf ein Missverständniss begründet, denn das Ministerium hat mir in Anerkennung meiner vielseitigen und aufopferungsvollen Forschungen die besondere Begünstigung erwiesen, mein Amt fortzuführen, obgleich wie bei Ihnen dort, so auch hier, das Alter gesetzlich festgestellt ist, in welchem sich Beamte der Regierung zurückziehen. Es ist also eine Ehrerweisung für mich, dass eine Ausnahme in meinem Falle gemacht ist, und wie diese Angelegenheit im Ministerium zur Besprechung kam, war das Bedauern ausgedrückt, wie schwer es erschien, meine Stellung zu bewahren; wäre dies nach den hier bestehenden Verordnungen nicht möglich gewesen, so wäre die Anstalt als eine selbstständige aufgehoben worden. Aber bei dem gegenwärtigen bedrückten – gewiss nur temporären – Finanzstand auch dieser Colonie sind meine Betriebsmittel einstweilen sehr verringert, so dass die Wissenschaftsanstalten, mit denen ich in Verbindung stehe, nachsichtig sein müssen, wenn mein Verkehr mit denselben in Zukunft mehr beschränkt sein möchte. Ich selbst habe nicht gewünscht, dass meine Angelegenheit hier oder daheim Gegenstand öffentlicher Besprechung würde; im Gegentheil, ich hatte mein volles Vertrauen auf das Gerechtigkeitsgefühl meiner Oberen gesetzt, denen es wohl bekannt ist, dass ich mein ganzes Vermögen in meine Reisen, Studien, Sammlungen und Wissenschaftsverkehr gesenkt! Da auch meiner persönlichen Einkünfte gedacht ist in europäischen Blättern, bleibt mir zu bemerken, dass in einem Goldlande wie hier der Goldwerth ein ganz anderer ist als in den Heimländern, dass ich aus meinen persönlichen Emolumenten die extensive Bureau-Accomodation meines Departements liefere, grosse Privataufopferungen für meinen literarischen Verkehr mache und manche andere Zahlungen leiste, welche dem mir anvertrauten Dienst und somit der ganzen Colonie zugute kommen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der lhre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. v. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the number of your fine journal that just arrived, noble friend, there is a short note derived from other public newspapers on a supposed resignation by me from the public service of the Colony of Victoria.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the April issue of the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Wiener illustrirte Garten-Zeitung</seg>
                     <seg style="">, p. 175, the following report appeared:</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5118in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Baron Müller</seg>
                     <seg style="">. Die Regierung von Victoria hat unseren berühmten Landsmann, den verdienten Regierungsbotaniker Baron Müller, der die gesetzliche Altersgrenze von 60 Jahren überschritten hat, aufgefordert, um seine Entlassung einzukommen. Herr von Müller, d</seg>
                     <seg style="">er bisher 8000 fl. Gold Jahres</seg>
                     <seg style="">gehalt bezog, soll eine Pension von 5250 fl</seg>
                     <seg style="">. erhalten. Die bezügliche Auf</seg>
                     <seg style="">forderung soll in sehr schrof</seg>
                     <seg style="">f</seg>
                     <seg style="">er Form erfolgt sein.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5118in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">[Baron Mueller. The Government of Victoria has requested our famous fellow-countryman, the merited Government Botanist, Baron Mueller, who has exceeded the statutory age limit of 60 years, to apply for his retirement. Herr von Mueller, who until now received a yearly salary of 8000 florins gold, is to get a pension of 5250 florins. The relevant request is said to have taken place very abruptly.]</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> However, this information is founded on a misunderstanding, as the ministry, in recognition of my varied and self-sacrificing research, has bestowed on me the particular favour of continuing my office, although, as with you there, so also here, the age at which officers of the government retire is established by law. It is therefor a bestowal of honour for me that an exception is made in my case and when this matter was brought up for discussion in the ministry, regret was expressed, how difficult it seemed to retain my position. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Had this not been possible according to the existing regulations here, then the institution would have been done away with as an independent one. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>But with the present depressed – certainly only temporarily – financial position, even of this colony, my resources are for now much reduced, so that the scientific institutions with which I am connected must be tolerant if my communication with them might be more limited in future. I myself have not wished that my affairs would be a subject of public discussion here or at home, on the contrary I had put my complete trust in the feeling of justice of my superiors, by whom it is well known that I sank my whole fortune into my travels, studies, collections and scientific communications! As even my personal income is made mention of in European papers, it remains for me to remark that in a gold country like here the value of gold is quite another one than in the home countries, that I provide the extensive office accomodation of my department from my personal emolument, make great private sacrifices for my literary communication and make many other payments that benefit the office entrusted to me and thereby the whole colony.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
