<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>21/3/92. ¶  ¶ It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to write to you some weeks ago, mainly respecting the plants of the Hawaii Group intended for my institution. But I have waited until the ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-03-21-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>92.03.21</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>21/3/92. ¶  ¶ It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to write to you some weeks ago, mainly respecting the plants of the Hawaii Group intended for my institution. But I have waited until the ...</title>
               <date when="1892-03-21">1892-03-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-03-21-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Adolf Engler</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">21/3/92. ¶  ¶ It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to write to you some weeks ago, mainly respecting the plants of the Hawaii Group intended for my institution. But I have waited until the ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">92.03.21</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">To Adolf Engler</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">21/3/92.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es war meine Absicht, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, Ihnen schon vor einigen Wochen zu schreiben, namentlich in Bezug auf die Pflanzen der Hawaia-Gruppe als meiner Anstalt zugedacht. Ich habe aber gewartet bis zur Ankunft der dies-monatlichen deutschen Post, um zu sehen, ob die vor dem Ende des vorigen Jahres von Ihnen angekündigte zweite Hälfte diesmal mit dem deutschen Dampfschiff gekommen sein würde.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Obwohl nun zwei andere Sendungen mich mit dem jetzigen Dampfschiff aus Ihrer Kaiserstadt erreichten schnell u. sicher, kann ich nichts über die Hawaia-Pfl. ausfinden. </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ein Frachtbrief hat mich nicht erreicht</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, und ich habe auch keine Kunde, durch welche Agentur die Absendung ausgeführt ist. Es wäre ja immerhin möglich, aber es ist nicht wahrscheinlich, dass weitere Auskunft doch hier angelangt sei.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich war nämlich abwesend in Tasmanien während eines Theils von Januar, um den dortiger Gouverneur, Seine Excellenz Sir Robert Hamilton, als Präsidenten der Austral. Assoc. for Advancement of Science zu installiren; dann war ich auch in Südaustralien im Interesse von Baron Nordenskiolds beabsichtigter Südpolar Fahrt. Aber nach allen genauen Erkundigungen sowohl im Departement als im hiesige Bureau der deutschen Dampfschiffe kann ich nichts über die Hillebrand’s Pflanzen ermitteln. Leider kann ich auch noch nicht berichten, ob die erste Hälfte angekommen sei. Gesehen habe ich solche nicht. Es wäre aber möglich, dass im Herbarium Gebäude diese Sammlung verlegt sei. Ich war mehrmals </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sehr krank</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, so der Herbarium-Assistant, die Arbeitskräfte sind sehr gering in meinem Departement, u wenn ich auch Tag u Nacht, Werktag u Festtag arbeite, komme ich doch nie durch, da die officiellen Ansprüche an mich so vielseitig sind. Würden Sie gütig in den Geschäftsbüchern Ihres Herbariums nachschlagen lassen </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wenn</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> die beiden Sammlungen abgingen u auf </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">welchem</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Wege. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mein Herbarium füllt 2 Saale u enthalt etwa 800,000 Bogen. Es könnte ja leicht etwas an einen unrechte Stelle gebracht sein.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">21/3/92.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to write to you some weeks ago, mainly respecting the plants of the Hawaii Group intended for my institution. But I have waited until the arrival of this month's German mail to see whether the second half announced by you before the end of last year would have arrived this time with the German steamer.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Although now two other consignments from your imperial city reached me quickly and safely with the present steamer, I cannot find out anything about the Hawaii plants. </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">A consignment note has not reached me</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, and I also have no information by which agent the sending was carried out.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">One package of Hawaiian plants arrived some weeks later via the Smithsonian Institution, but M remained anxious about the other one; see M to A. Engler, 11 May 1892. Meanwhile, evidently in response to the present letter, Engler wrote to tell him where to look for it; see M to A. Engler, 28 June 1892 (in this edition as 92-06-28a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Nevertheless it would certainly be possible, but not probable, that further information has indeed arrived here.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You see, I was absent in Tasmania during part of January to instal the Governor of that place, His Excellency Sir Robert Hamilton, as President of the Austral. Assoc. for Advancement of Science; then I was also in South Australia in the interests of Baron Nordenskiold's proposed South Polar expedition. But after all painstaking enquiries both in the Department and in the local office of the German ships I cannot ascertain anything about Hillebrand's plants. Unfortunately I also cannot yet report whether the first half has arrived. I have not seen it. But it would be possible that this collection is mislaid in the Herbarium building. I was </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">very ill</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> several times, as was the Herbarium assistant, the workforce is very small in my department and even if I also work day and night, workdays and holidays, I really never come through because the official demands on me are so manifold. Would you be so kind as to have the office books of your herbarium consulted as to </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">when</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> both collections went off and in </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">which</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> way.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My herbarium fills 2 halls and contains about 800,000 folders. It could certainly easily have been put in an incorrect place.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
