<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>In various horticultural periodicals, there is a short note reproduced from public journals about a supposed retirement by me from the public service of the Colony of Victoria. This information is, ho...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-06-00b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>92.06.00b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>In various horticultural periodicals, there is a short note reproduced from public journals about a supposed retirement by me from the public service of the Colony of Victoria. This information is, ho...</title>
               <date when="1892-06">1892-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1892/92-06-00b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Gartenflora</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">In various horticultural periodicals, there is a short note reproduced from public journals about a supposed retirement by me from the public service of the Colony of Victoria. This information is, ho...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">92.06.00b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">To Gartenflora</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </seg>? <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Ferdinand von Müller bleibt im Amte' [Ferdinand von Müller remains in office], </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 41, p. 423. </seg>
                     <seg style="">It is introduced by 'Baron Ferdinand von Müller, seit langen Jahren korrespondierendes Mitglied des Vereins zur Beförderung des Garten-baues, der 1891 auch zum Ehrenmitgliede der deutschen botanischen Gesellschaft ernannt wurde, sendet uns folgendes Schreiben' [Baron Ferdinand von Müller, for many years a corresponding member of the Association for the Promotion of Horticulture, who in 1891 was also appointed an honorary member of the German Botanical Society, sends us the following letter].</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also Verein zur Beförderung des Gartenbaues in den Königlich Preussischen Staaten to M, 29 November 1876, and Deutsche Botanische Gesellschaft to M, 24 September 1891.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M's letter is dated to June 1892 as the latest likely date that it could have been sent to be published in the first August issue of the journal. (Although not dated, the journal issues have a standard structure: this is the 15th issue of 24 for the year.)</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In verschiedenen gärtnerischen Zeitschriften findet sich eine kurze Notiz, aus öffentlichen Blättern entlehnt, über einen vermeintlichen Rücktritt von mir aus dem Staatsdienst der Kolonie Victoria. Diese Mitteilung beruht aber auf einem Missverständnis, denn das Ministerium hat mir in Anerkennung meiner vielseitigen und aufopferungsvollen Forschungen die besondere Begünstigung erwiesen, mein Amt fortzuführen, obgleich, wie in manchen europäischen Staaten, so auch hier, das Alter gesetzlich festgestellt ist, in welchem sich Beamte der Regierung zurückziehen müssen. Es ist also eine Ehrerweisung für mich, dass eine Ausnahme in meinem Falle gemacht ist, und als diese Angelegenheit im Ministerium zur Besprechung kam, ward das Bedauern ausgedrückt, wie es schwer erschiene, meine Stellung zu bewahren; wäre dies nicht möglich gewesen nach den hier bestehenden Verordnungen, so wäre die Anstalt als eine selbständige aufgehoben worden. Aber bei dem gegenwärtigen gedrückten, doch gewiss nur temporären Finanz-Zustand auch dieser Kolonie sind meine Betriebsmittel einstweilen sehr verringert, so dass die wissenschaftlichen Anstalten, mit denen ich in Verbindung stehe, nachsichtig sein müssen, wenn mein Verkehr mit denselben in Zukunft mehr beschränkt sein möchte. Ich selbst habe nicht gewünscht, dass meine Angelegenheit hier oder daheim Gegenstand öffentlicher Besprechung würde; im Gegenteil, ich hatte mein volles Vertrauen auf das Gerechtigkeitsgefühl meiner Oberen gesetzt, denen es wohl bekannt ist, dass ich mein ganzes Vermögen in meine Reisen, Studien, Sammlungen und den wissenschaftlichen Verkehr gesteckt! Da auch meiner persönlichen Einkünfte in europäischen Blätter gedacht ist, bleibt mir zu bemerken, dass in einem Goldlande wie hier der Geldwert ein ganz anderer ist, als in Europa, dass ich aus meinen persönlichen Emolumenten die notwendigen Bureau-Ausgaben meines Departements bestreite, dass ich grosse Privatopfer für meinen litterarischen Verkehr bringe, und dass ich manche andere Zahlungen leiste, welche dem mir anvertrauten Dienste und somit der ganzen Kolonie zu gute kommen. </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In various horticultural periodicals, there is a short note reproduced from public journals about a supposed retirement by me from the public service of the Colony of Victoria. This information is, however, based on a misunderstanding, because the Ministry has conferred on me the particular privilege of continuing my office in recognition of my varied and sacrificial researches, even though, as in many European states, so also here, the age at which a government official must retire is fixed by law. Thus there is a bestowal of honour for me that an exception is made in my case, and when this matter came up for discussion in the Ministry regret was expressed, how difficult it seemed to retain my position. If this had not been possible according to the regulations existing here, then the institution as an independent one would be abolished. However, with the present depressed but certainly only temporary financial state of affairs also of this Colony, my resources are very reduced for now, so that the scientific institutions with which I stand in communication must be tolerant if my communication with them in the future may be more limited. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have not wished that my business would be an object of public discussion here or at home, on the contrary I had put my full trust in the sense of justice of my superiors, to whom it is well known that I have put my whole fortune into my journeys, studies, collections and scientific communication! Because even my personal finances are mentioned in European papers, it remains for me to remark that in a gold country such as here, the value of money is quite another thing than in Europe, that I defray the necessary office expenses from my personal emolument, that I make great sacrifices for my literary communication, and that I make many other payments that benefit the office entrusted to me and thereby the whole Colony.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
