<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>27 April 1864. ¶ Most esteemed patron and friend, ¶  ¶ I am not worthy of your great kindness and friendship, as I reply so rarely to your many amiable letters, and I should be ashamed to come before ...</title>
            <author>August Petermann</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-04-27a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv,SPA ARCHPGM328,Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.04.27a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>August Petermann</author>
               <title>27 April 1864. ¶ Most esteemed patron and friend, ¶  ¶ I am not worthy of your great kindness and friendship, as I reply so rarely to your many amiable letters, and I should be ashamed to come before ...</title>
               <date when="1864-04-27">1864-04-27</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-04-27a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">27 April 1864. ¶ Most esteemed patron and friend, ¶  ¶ I am not worthy of your great kindness and friendship, as I reply so rarely to your many amiable letters, and I should be ashamed to come before ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.04.27a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">SPA ARCH<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">PGM<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">328</seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; "/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a published version of this letter,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>see Voigt (1996),<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>pp. 52-5.</p>
               </note>27. April 64</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrtester Gönner und Freund,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin Ihrer grossen Güte und Freundschaft unwerth, da ich Ihnen auf Ihre vielen freundlichen Schreiben so selten erwidere, und ich würde mich schämen, mit Entschuldigungen vor Sie hinzutreten, wenn ich nicht im Voraus wüsste, wie nachsichtig Sie meine shortcomings ansehen werden und stets angesehen haben. Übrigens gewöhnt man sich als viel in Anspruch genommener Redakteur nolens volens daran, so wenig als möglich zu correspondiren, und so viel als möglich durch seine periodische Schrift zu seinen Correspondenten und Freunden zu reden, und man sucht darin gewissermassen eine Entschädigung und Erleichterung in den Sorgen und Mühen einer Redaktion. So mögen Sie denn auch aus den gelegentlichen gedruckten Kreuzbandsendungen erfahren haben, dass ich ein lässiger Briefschreiber bin, aber nichts desto weniger Ihrer sehr häufig denke, und mit inniger Dankbarkei und freundschaftlichster Ergebenheit danke.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die letzte Kreuzbandsendung, die ich Ihnen machte, geschah am 23. Nov. und bestand in Abhandlung und Karte über die<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Südpolar-Regionen</hi>
               </seg>, deren weitere Erforschung mich in höchstem Grade interessirt und mir in wissenschaftlicher Beziehung sehr wünschenswerth erscheint. Ich hatte mir in der Abhandlung erlaubt, auf Sie als den ersten [der]<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg>.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>wissenschaftlicher Männer hinzuweisen, der im Stande sein möchte, für diese Sache zu wirken.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Am 9. Dezember verpackte ich an Sie ein Paket mit 9 Exemplaren des Geologisch-topographischen Atlasses von Neuseeland, von Hochstetter und mir, für Sie und Ihre dortigen Freunde; allein bei der elenden Kommunikation eines kleinen Ortes in der Mitte Deutschlands mit einem überseeischen Erdtheile wie Australien, ist die Verschickung solcher Sachen stets schwierig und langwierig. Das Paket ging über Hamburg, ich fürchte aber, dass es viel zu lange zu seiner Reise gebrauchen wird.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine sehr grosse Freude haben Sie mir durch Übersendung Ihrer Photographie gemacht, die ich mit Stolz meiner ziemlich umfangreichen Sammlung von Photographien einreihte. Ich beehre mich, Ihnen anbei meine Photographie <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>zu Füssen zu legen. Den herzlichsten Dank bin ich Ihnen auch für Ihre letzten hochwichtigen Rimessen schuldig.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Sendungen von Karten und Druckschriften, die Sie so freundlich waren, per Monarch 9. Sept. an Dr Sonder und per Great Britain an Sir W.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>J. Hooker für mich abgehen zu lassen, sind beide bis dato noch nicht eingegangen; — ich habe bei Dr Sonder desswegen schon im Februar angefragt und thue es gleichzeitig noch einmal. Es gehen mir aus allen Weltgegenden Mittheilungen zu, allein die Ihrigen empfange ich immer mit doppelter Freude und Spannung, da sie mir die Freundschaft Ihres Gebers und Absenders bekunden, und stets so Interessantes enthalten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie waren so gütig, in einem Ihrer Schreiben zu fragen, ob ich die Originalkarten von McKinlay &amp; Stuart, Landsborough und Walker besässe, und dass Sie dieselben im Nichtfalle schicken wollten. Diejenigen von den beiden ersten Reisenden besitze ich, die von<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Landsborough</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>und<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Walker</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>aber nicht, und würden Sie mich daher ausserordentlich durch Übersendung verbinden; auch habe ich mich auf alle Weise vergeblich bisher um<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Walker’</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">s Journal</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>bemüht, welches mir sehr wichtig ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">pamphlet und Map of [Riv</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">erland]</hi>
               </seg>, das Grenzgebiet zwischen Victoria und S.Australia, welches freilich schon im J. 1862 oder gar 1861 erschienen sein muss, würde mich noch jetzt interessiren, wenn es Ihnen bekannt und leicht zu bekommen wäre.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wegen Proeschel’s Atlas habe ich mich direkt an den Verfasser gewandt. Darf ich Sie ersuchen, den inliegenden Brief an ihn und die anderen 6 gütigst franco befördern zu wollen? und den Betrag des Portos mir gut zu schreiben? Proeschels Wohnort ist mir unbekannt, obgleich ich Melbourne stark vermuthe, Sie wollen die Güthe haben, das Fehlende in der Adresse zu ergänzen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unter den 9 Ex.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Exemplaren.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>des Neu-Seeland. Atlas befindet sich ein unbeschriebenes Exemplar, welches ich Sie hatte bitten wollen, entweder Ihrer Royal Society oder Public Library in Melbourne zu übermachen. Ich ersuche Sie aber, dieses Exemplar gütigst an den A. Surv. Gen. Davidson in Sydney zu befördern. — Das Paket der Neu-Seeland-Atlanten wird Ihnen auch Porto-Unkosten verursachen, und muss ich Sie dringendst bitten, dieselben nebst den obigen zu notiren und mir mitzutheilen, damit ich nicht auch noch in dieser Beziehung in Ihrer Schuld bin.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre grossmüthigen und gütigen Gesinnungen liessen Sie in einem Ihrer Schreiben erwähnen, dass Sie es Sich zum Vergnügen machen würden, für das Gothaische Museum Ihre stets so freigebige Hand aufzuthun. Ich habe nun bei dem Chef desselben angefragt, und ist Ihnen derselbe im Voraus zum grössten Dank verpflichtet; er wünschte schon längst aus Australien ganz besonders Folgendes zu acquiriren :</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="de">1. Apteryx impennis<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(namentlich!),</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="de">2. Marsupialien,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="de">3. die grösseren australischen Vögel,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="de">4. Konchylien,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="de">5. Korallen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Durch irgend eine Sendung dieser Art, auch die kleinste, würden Sie das Herzogliche Museum und den Herzog zu [grossem] Dank verpflichten. Der Herzog hat schon häufig, indem ich mit ihm über Ihre hochherzigen deutschen Gesinnungen sprach, seinen Wunsch, Ihnen gefällig zu sein, ausgesprochen, und ich bin fest überzeugt, dass er im Geist Ihnen längst eine Dekoration zugedacht hat. Daher wundert mich nur, dass Sie dieselbe noch nicht erhielten. Eine Beschenkung seines Museums, wenn auch noch so klein, würde die Sache, die er — wie dies bei Hohen Herren der Fall ist — sehr wahrscheinlich vergessen hat, zur endlichen Realisation bringen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit innigster Verehrung und Dankbarkeit</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr treu ergebener<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Petermann.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">27 April 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Most esteemed patron and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am not worthy of your great kindness and friendship, as I reply so rarely to your many amiable letters, and I should be ashamed to come before you with excuses, did I not know in advance, with how much forebearance you will look and always have looked on my shortcomings. Besides, as a very busy publisher, whether one wants to or not, one gets used to corresponding<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as little as possible and to talking<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as much as possible to one's correspondents and friends through one's journal, seeking in that a kind<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>compensation and relief from the worries and troubles of a publisher. Thus you may also have realised from my periodic transmissions of printed<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>matter that I am a lazy letter-writer, but none-the-less<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>frequently think of you and thank you with sincere gratitude and very devoted friendship.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last consignment of printed matter I sent to you on 23rd November<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>consisted<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of an article and map on the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">South Polar regions</hi>
               </seg>, as their further exploration interests me in the highest degree and appears to me very desirable from a scientific point of view. I took the liberty in this article to point to you as one of the foremost men of science<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>who might be in a position to work in this cause.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Petermann (1863) p. 428 states: 'Ausser Dr. Neumayer aber zählt die Deutsche Wissenschaft zu ihren Vertretern bei unseren Antipoden einen hochverdienten Namen: Dr. F. Müller, Direktor des Botanischen Gartens in Melbourne...' [Apart from Dr Neumayer, German science counts amongst its representatives in the antipodes a highly meritorious name: Dr F. Mueller, Director of the Botanic Garden in Melbourne...].</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 9 December I packed a parcel for you with 9 copies of the Geologic-topographical atlas of New Zealand,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hochstetter &amp; Petermann (1863).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>by Hochstetter and me for you and your friends there; however, with the miserable communication between a small place in the centre of Germany and a continent overseas<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>like Australia,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the transmission of such things is always difficult and slow. The parcel went via Hamburg, but I fear that it will take far too long for its voyage.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You gave me very great pleasure by sending me your photograph, which I added with pride to my fairly extensive collection of photographs. I<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>have the honour to lay<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>my<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>enclosed photograph at your feet.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M had requested a photograph of Petermann more than once, for example in M to A. Petermann, 24 November 1863 (In this edition as 63-11-24a).<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>No image of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Petermann<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>has been identified at MEL, but see M to J. Haast, 29 July 1862 (in this edition as 62-07-29b) and notes thereto.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I also owe you my most sincere thanks for your last extremely important remittances.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to A. Petermann, 25 October 1863<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 63-10-25a),<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>M to A. Petermann,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>24 November 1863<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 63-11-24a)<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>M to A. Petermann,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>24 January 1864<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 64-01-24a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Neither of the consignments of maps and printed matter<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>you so kindly transmitted for me on 9 September to Dr Sonder per<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Monarch</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and to Sir William Hooker per<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>have arrived so far; I<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>already<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>inquired<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>about it<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of Dr Sonder in February<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and am doing so again now. I receive communications from all parts of the world, but yours I always welcome with twice the pleasure and anticipation, as they manifest to me the friendship of their donor and sender and always contain so much of interest.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You were so kind<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to ask me in your letter<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn7" n="8">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to A. Petermann, 25 July 1863<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 63-07-25a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>whether I have the original maps of McKinlay and Stuart, Landsborough and Walker, and that, if I do not, you would send them to me. I have those of the first two travellers,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn8" n="9">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See McKinlay (1863) and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">J.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">Stuart (1863).</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>but not those of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Landsborough</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn9" n="10">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Landsborough (1862).</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Walker</hi>
               </seg>,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn10" n="11">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No map was included in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">F.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">Walker (1862)</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">, but his route was included<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">with that of Landsborough</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on a map published by Vicoria’s Department of Lands and Survey in April 1862</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">, see<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <ref target="http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-231412875">
                           <seg rend="Hyperlink" style="color: #0070C0; ">http://nla.go</seg>
                           <seg rend="Hyperlink" style="color: #0070C0; ">v</seg>
                           <seg rend="Hyperlink" style="color: #0070C0; ">.au/nla.obj-2314</seg>
                           <seg rend="Hyperlink" style="color: #0070C0; ">1</seg>
                           <seg rend="Hyperlink" style="color: #0070C0; ">2875</seg>
                        </ref>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(accessed 31 October 2018).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>you would, therefore, greatly oblige me by their transmission. I have also tried every which way in vain to obtain<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Walker's journal</hi>
               </seg>, which is very important to me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">pamphlet and map of [Riv</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">erland]</hi>
               </seg>, the border area between Victoria and South Australia which, admittedly, must have been published already in 1862 or even 1861,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn11" n="12">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Not identified.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>would still interest me now, if it is known to you and easy to obtain.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Regarding Proeschel's atlas,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn12" n="13">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Proeschel (1863).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have addressed myself directly to the author. May I ask you kindly to forward the enclosed letter to him and the other 6<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>post free, and to put the amount for the postage on my account? I do not know where Proeschel lives, though I strongly suspect Melbourne. Be so good and complete the missing part of the address.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Among the 9 copies of the New Zealand atlas is one without inscription, and I had intended to ask you to donate this either to your Royal Society or to the Public Library in Melbourne. However, I now beg you to kindly forward this copy to the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>A. Surv. Gen.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn13" n="14">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Assistant Surveyor General.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Davidson in Sydney.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>— The parcel of the New Zealand atlases will also cause you expenditure with postage, and I must ask you most earnestly to note down these as well as the expenses mentioned above and to inform me of them, so that I will not be in your debt in this regard as well.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your magnanimous and kind disposition led you to mention in one of your letters, that you would consider it a pleasure to open your always so generous hand for the Gotha Museum. I have therefore enquired from its Director, and he feels under a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>grateful obligation to you in advance; he has wished for a long time to acquire from Australia the following:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="en">1.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Apteryx<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">impennis</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in particular!),</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="en">2. Marsupials,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="en">3. the larger Australian birds,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="en">4. shells,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="en">5. corals.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">You would greatly oblige the Ducal Museum and the Duke<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn14" n="15">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ernst II of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha. M sent some<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>specimens for the Duke's museum, shortly after receiving Petermann’s letter;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>see M to A. Petermann, 26 August<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1864.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>In response, M was awarded a Knight's Cross II. Class of the Ducal Saxon Ernestine House Order; see R. von Seebach to M, 5 January 1865.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>with any transmission of this kind, no matter how small. The Duke has frequently expressed his wish to do you a favour<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>when I spoke with him about your noble German character, and I am firmly convinced<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that in spirit he has bestowed a decoration on<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>you long ago. So I only wonder<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that you have not yet received it. A gift to his Museum, however small, would make the matter finally a reality, which he<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>— as tends to be the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>case with such noble gentlemen<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>— has most likely forgotten about.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With sincerest respect and gratitude</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">your truly devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Petermann.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
