<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 June 1864. ¶  ¶ It is my intention, noble Sir, to send you a number of plants for your herbarium by the ship  ¶ Suffolk ¶ , sailing from here next week, through the kin...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-06-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana II, A, 2, Handschriftenabteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.06.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 June 1864. ¶  ¶ It is my intention, noble Sir, to send you a number of plants for your herbarium by the ship  ¶ Suffolk ¶ , sailing from here next week, through the kin...</title>
               <date when="1864-06-25">1864-06-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-06-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Gingidium haastii</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d9d593f3-cf3a-4cd0-8346-da90200383ad">Xanthorrhoea</term>
               <term>Haastia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 June 1864. ¶  ¶ It is my intention, noble Sir, to send you a number of plants for your herbarium by the ship  ¶ Suffolk ¶ , sailing from here next week, through the kin...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.06.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Martiusiana II, A, 2, Handschriftenabteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ms annotation by Martius: 'b. 7 Sept. 1864' [replied 7 September 1864]. Letter not found.</p>
               </note>Melbourne im bot. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25. Juni 1864.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Es ist meine Absicht, edler Herr, Ihnen mit dem in nächster Woche von hier segelnden Schiffe Suffolk durch die freundliche Vermittlung des Herrn Dr W. Sonder in Hamburg eine Anzahl Pflanzen für Ihr Herbar zu senden, freilich nicht eine solche Menge als ich gern geliefert hätte, aber doch hinlänglich zu beweisen, dass ich Ihren Wunsch in dieser Beziehung nicht unbeachtet gelassen. Nehmen Sie denn auch die Versicherung hin, dass bald dieser Sendung eine andere folgen wird. Auch etwas <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name> Harz u.s.w. wird mitkommen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun habe ich zwei Bitten, nicht für mich aber für zwei Freunde und edle Menschen. Für mich werde ich nie wagen etwas von Ihnen zu erbitten und damit störend in die Ruhe Ihres schönen Lebensabends eingreifen; und wenn ich dies für Andere wage so ist es, weil kaum ein anderer Gelehrter in Deutschland sich mit Ihnen zu messen vermag in Einfluss auf Männer der Wissenschaft u in Verehrung die man Ihnen gerechtsam zollt. So wage ich es denn meine Wünsche auszusprechen, bittend jedoch selbige unbeachtet zu lassen, sollte Ihnen daraus Beschwerde entspringen. Der Geologe Haast, der soviel für die Erforschung der südlichen Alpen Neuseelands gethan, u. dem die Universität Erlangen die phil. Doctorwürde unlängst decretirte, ein deutscher Gelehrter u. Präsident des philos.Instituts von Canterbury u. Regierungs Geologe daselbst ist sehr vom Wunsch erregt in unsere grosse Carol. Leopold Academy aufgenommen zu werden. Möchten Sie ihn Ihrer Fürsprache würdig halten? Dr Julius Haast sammelt auch immerfort Pflanzen u. es war durch seine Vermittlung nach meiner Anregung, dass Mr. Travers seinen Sohn in diesem Jahr für mehrere Monate nach den Chatham Inseln sandte, um die bisher nur durch Dieffenbach sehr spärlich bekannte Vegetation (die sich jedoch der von Neu Seeland eng anschliesst) zu erforschen und mir für ein Werk über dieselbe, an dem ich jetzt beschäftigt bin, die Materialien zu liefern. Dr Haast (Julius Haast) hat auch bei seiner geographischen Erforschung der Alpen Neuseelands mehrere neue Pflanzen entdeckt, z. B. mein Gingidium Haastii u Dr Hooker´s <name key="Haastia">Haastia</name>. Er würde dankbar sein u. Pflanzen für Ihr Herbarium liefern sobald er weiss dass ich Ihre Fürbitte für ihn in Anspruch nahm. — Dann möchte ich auch Ihrer gütigen Erwägung überlassen, ob nicht durch einen Ihnen befreundeten Rector magnificus eine deutsche Universität dem ausgezeichneten G. H. K. Thwaites in Ceylon die philos. Doctorwürde ertheilen möchte. Ich habe das genaue Arbeiten dieses vortrefflichen Mannes seit Jahren beachtet, u habe seine Freundschaft seit Jahren genossen, u. kann so Bürge sein für seine Anwartschaft auf eine solche Belohnung durch die Wissenschaft, der er so lange u aufopfernd gediehnt.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>gedient.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> Ich bin überzeugt, dass wenn dieser Mann einen solchen Tribut der Anerkennung aus Deutschland erhalte, er bereitwillig mit seinem wohl bekannten Grossmuth aus der reichen Flora Ceilons</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ceylons.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> Ihnen wie mir längst die Pflanzenformen jener Insel zusenden würde, ohne bei einer solchen Gelegenheit auf die geringste Gegengabe Anspruch zu machen. Es ist wahrscheinlich, dass Mr Thwaites in diesem Jahr in jene ehrwürdige Gesellschaft von Gelehrten gewählt werden wird, in der einst Isaac Newton präsidirte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr Ferd Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Selbstverständlich erwarte ich kein Reciprocat für meine Pflanzensammlungen von Ihnen, denn nichts sollte mich mehr betrüben als Ihnen dadurch eine Bürde aufzuladen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 June 1864.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is my intention, noble Sir, to send you a number of plants for your herbarium by the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Suffolk</seg>, sailing from here next week, through the kind agency of Dr Sonder in Hamburg, admittedly not in such quantity as I should have liked to supply but enough to prove that I have not disregarded your wish in the respect. Accept then my assurance that another transmission will soon follow this one. Some <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
               </seg> resin etc. will also be included then.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I now have two requests, not for myself but for two friends and noble persons. I should never dare to ask you for anything for myself and so intrude disruptingly into the peace of the quiet evening of your life; if I dare to do so for others, it is because hardly another scientist in Germany can be compared to you in influence on men of science and in the veneration that is justly accorded you. Thus I dare to express my wishes, but beg you to disregard them should they cause you any inconvenience. The geologist Haast, who has done so much for the exploration of the southern alps of New Zealand, and on whom the University of Erlangen recently bestowed the doctor of philosophy degree,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Haast received an honorary PhD from the University of Tübingen—not from Erlangen—in October 1862; see H. F. von Haast (1948), p. 230. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>See also M to J. Haast, 1 April 1863 (in this edition as 63-04-01a).</p>
               </note> a German scientist and President of the Philosophical Institute of Canterbury and Government Geologist there, is greatly moved by the desire to be received into our great Carolino-Leopoldina Academy. Would you consider him worthy of your advocacy?<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also M to J. Haast, 20 June 1864.</p>
               </note> Dr Julius Haast is also constantly collecting plants and it was through his agency, on my suggestion, that Mr Travers sent his son to the Chatham Islands for several months this year to explore the vegetation, so far only very imperfectly known through Dieffenbach<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dieffenbach (1841).</p>
               </note> but that is very closely linked to that of New Zealand, and to supply me with the materials for a work on it on which I am presently engaged.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B64.13.02.</p>
               </note> Dr Haast (Julius Haast), during his exploration of the New Zealand alps, has also discovered several new plants, for instance my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Gingidium%20haastii">Gingidium haastii</name>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also M to J. Haast, 26 November 1860 and 23 February 1861.</p>
               </note> and Dr Hooker's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Haastia">Haastia</name>
               </seg>. He would be grateful and supply plants for your herbarium as soon as he finds out that I have requested <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> intercession for him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In addition I would also like to leave it to your kind consideration, if through the intercession of a Rector Magnificus who is a friend of yours, a German University would not bestow a doctor of philosophy degree on the excellent G. H. K. Thwaites in Ceylon.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thwaites was awarded an honorary PhD by the Imperial Leopoldo-Carolinian Academy later in 1864. He told William Hooker of the award in December of that year (Thwaites to W. Hooker, 8 December 1864 (in this edition as M64-12-08)), commenting that he did not want to be called 'Doctor' in Ceylon as there was already a Dr. Thwaites on the island.</p>
               </note> I have taken note of the conscientious work of this man for many years and have enjoyed his friendship for years, and so can be guarantor of his claims to such a reward by the science he has served for so long and with so many sacrifices. I am convinced that, were this man to receive such a tribute of acknowledgement from Germany, he would readily send you from the rich flora of Ceylon the plant forms of that island with his well known generosity, as he has done for me for a long time, without making the smallest demand for reciprocation on such an occasion. It is likely that Mr Thwaites will be elected this year to that venerable society of savants, over which Isaac Newton once presided.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Royal Society of London; Thwaites was elected a Fellow in 1865.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Naturally I do not expect from you any reciprocation for my plant collections, for nothing would distress me more than to place a burden on you by that.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gingidium%20haastii">Gingidium haastii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Haastia">Haastia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
