<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 February 1864. ¶ Revered Doctor, ¶  ¶ Since I wrote to you with the last mail, ¶  I have received the fruit of the plant, to which I gave the interim name of  ¶ Flueggea...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-02-24b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Bibliothèque, Conservatoire et Jardin botanique de la ville de Genève, Geneva.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.02.24b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 February 1864. ¶ Revered Doctor, ¶  ¶ Since I wrote to you with the last mail, ¶  I have received the fruit of the plant, to which I gave the interim name of  ¶ Flueggea...</title>
               <date when="1864-02-24">1864-02-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-02-24b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Phyllanthus subcrenulatus</term>
               <term>Pseudanthus nematophorus</term>
               <term>Pseudanthus occidentalis</term>
               <term>Chrysostemon virgatus</term>
               <term>Micrantheum hexandrum</term>
               <term>Flueggea buxifolia</term>
               <term>Euphorbiaceae</term>
               <term>Gynandropsis</term>
               <term>Cliftonella</term>
               <term>Lawrencella</term>
               <term>Lithoxylon</term>
               <term>Caletia</term>
               <term>Roepera</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jean Müller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 February 1864. ¶ Revered Doctor, ¶  ¶ Since I wrote to you with the last mail, ¶  I have received the fruit of the plant, to which I gave the interim name of  ¶ Flueggea...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.02.24b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Jean Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Bibliothèque, Conservatoire et Jardin botanique de la ville de Genève, Geneva.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation on lower margin of page in an unknown hand: 'Ecriture du Dr Ferd. Müller, à Melbourne. (Nov Holland.)'.</p>
               </note>Melbourne im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">24/2/64.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrter Herr Doctor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit letzter Post, mit welcher ich an Sie schrieb, gelangten die Früchte jener Pflanze, welche ich als Flueggea? buxifolia einstweilen bezeichnete, in meine Hände. Ich nehme jetzt recht wohl wahr, dass die Pflanze in ein entferntes Genus gehört u. möchte Ihnen beipflichten, dass sie in ein eignes Genus erhoben werden könne. Trotz dessen dass wir in <name key="Lawrencella">Lawrencella</name>, <name key="Cliftonella">Cliftonella</name> u. sw. Genera kennen, welche nach Eigennamen als Diminutive benannt sind, so scheint mir doch nach philosophischen Grundsätzen es kaum rathsam, diesem Beispiel anderer Gelehrter zu folgen u Diminutiv-Eigennahmen auf Gattungen zu verwenden. Wenn Sie es gutheissen, möchte ich dass wir voreins der Pflanze den Namen <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name> geben, um ein genus aufzustellen zum Andenken meines ehrwürdigen Freundes Prof Roeper in Rostock u. zwar in derjenigen Pflanzen Familie, in welcher dieser Botaniker vorzugsweise wirkte. Vielleicht haben Sie aber schon inzwischen die Flueggella in der Linnaea beschrieben, u dann möchten Sie vielleicht irgend ein anderes genus der Euphorbiaceen dem Professor meiner Geburtsstadt widmen, da Bentham (vielleicht nicht mit Recht) meine <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name> zu <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name> brachte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich wiederhole mein Anerbieten , Ihnen meine ganze Euphorbiaceen-Sammlung zur Durchsicht u Bearbeitung leihen zu wollen, falls Bentham diese Familie nicht in den 3. Band unserer Australisch. Flora, sondern erst unter die Monochlamydeen aufzunehmen gedenkt, worüber ich bald Nachricht haben werde. Ich knüpfe indessen an mein Versprechen die Bedingung, dass sie mir gütigst einen durchaus sichern Weg angeben, auf welchem ich diese höchst werthvolle Normal Sammlung, welche ich seit 16 Jahren hier zusammen brachte, nach Genf senden kann u. dass Sie die Sammlung nicht länger als 1 Jahr dort behalten. Ich würde inzwischen die Arten, welche der Flora v. Victoria angehören (etwa 1/6 des Ganzen) genau beschreiben, um im unglücklichen Falle eines Verlustes oder einer Beschädigung nicht das Material für mein grösseres Werk zu verlieren. Die Euphorbiaceen meines Herbars umfasssen 18 starke Fascicle u manche der Arten sind bisher nicht zu Ihnen gelangt, da ich nicht davon abgeben konnte. Wenn das vielleicht nur einige sind, so würde die Durchsicht einer solchen Sammlung doch für Sie belehrend sein, um die Formenkreise der Arten u die Verbreitung derselben zu ermitteln. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe kürzlich durch Vergleich eines Original Exemplares von Preiss mich überzeugt, dass mein <name key="Pseudanthus%20occidentalis">Pseudanthus occidentalis</name> u Klotzsch's <name key="Chrysostemon%20virgatus">Chrysostemon virgatus</name> eins sind. Zwar habe ich neuerdings diese Pflanze nicht wieder zergliedert, aber so kann ich mich noch nicht mit dem Gedanken vertraut machen, dass <name key="Micrantheum%20hexandrum">Micrantheum hexandrum</name> ein eigenes Genus bilde (<name key="Caletia">Caletia</name>) u wenn dies der Fall so scheint mir dennoch die Vereinigung meiner Pseudanthi mit <name key="Caletia">Caletia</name> nicht natürlich, sondern wenn es wirklich möglich ist diese Pflanze von dem typus Pseudanthi zu trennen, haben solche unter Chrysostemon sich einzureihen. Wie ich im vorigen Briefe schrieb, bin ich geneigt Synostemon aufrecht zu erhalten; wenigstens bildet es ein Subgenus mit eigenthümlicher Frucht u auffallend durch seine verwachsenen Antheren. <name key="Lithoxylon">Lithoxylon</name> möchte wohl ein eigenes Genus sein. Von <name key="Pseudanthus%20nematophorus">Pseudanthus nematophorus</name> habe ich die Frucht in meinen Fragm. phyt. Austr beschrieben; es scheint mir wirklich bloss ein Subgenus von Pseudanthus oder Chrysostemon, deren Arten alle einen leicht erkennbaren äussern Ausdruck besitzen. Von <name key="Phyllanthus%20subcrenulatus">Phyllanthus subcrenulatus</name> finden Sie eine Beschreibung im ersten Band meiner Fragmenta. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihnen nochmals für Ihre Auskunft u für Ihre grossmüthige Uneigennützigkeit dankend u bittend mich dem werthen Wohlwollen des Herrn Professors Alph de Candolle empfehlen zu wollen, bleibe ich Ihr Sie ehrender</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich werde die Beschreibung der Euphorbiaceen Victoria's in das demnächst erscheinende Heft meiner Fragmenta aufnehmen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wünscht die Société de Physique &amp; d'Hist. naturelle de Genève meine Schrift zu besitzen? Kann ich Ihrer wissenschaftlichen Anstalt dort sonst irgendwie nützlich sein?</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">24 February 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Revered Doctor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since I wrote to you with the last mail,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Müller, 25 January 1864 (in this edition as 64-01-25d).</p>
               </note> I have received the fruit of the plant, to which I gave the interim name of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Flueggea%20buxifolia">Flueggea buxifolia</name>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Flueggea%20buxifolia">Flueggea buxifolia</name>
                     </seg>not in APNI.</p>
               </note> I am now clearly aware, that the plant belongs to a quite distant genus, and I would agree with you, that it could be elevated to form its own genus. Even though we have genera such as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Lawrencella">Lawrencella</name>, <name key="Cliftonella">Cliftonella</name>
               </seg>,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Cliftonella">Cliftonella</name>
                     </seg> not in IPNI.</p>
               </note> etc., which have been formed from personal names in diminutive, it hardly seems advisable to me on philosophical principles to follow this example of other scientists of using diminutives of personal names as generic names. If you are agreeable, I would like to give the plant the name <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name>
               </seg> for the time being in commemoration of my venerable friend Professor Roeper in Rostock, particularly in this plant family, in which this botanist preferred to work. But perhaps you already have described the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flueggella</seg> in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg> in the meantime, and in that case you might perhaps dedicate some other genus in the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> to the Professor of the city of my birth, as Bentham (perhaps unjustly) has transferred my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name>
               </seg> to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">It would seem that J. Müller had proposed the name <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flueggella </seg>in a letter to M that has not been found; he did not publish the name. M's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Roeperia cleomoides</seg> (B57.13.01, p.15) was renamed by Bentham as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name> Muelleri </seg>in Bentham (1863-78), vol. 1, p. 91. J. Müller erected the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Neoroepera</seg>, from a specimen in de Candolle's herbarium, under the joint authorship of M and himself in J. Müller (1866), p. 488. See also M to G. Bentham, 15 July 1873 (in this edition as 73-07-15a).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I repeat my offer to loan you my complete collection of <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> for examination and revision, provided Bentham does not plan to include this family in the third volume of our Australian Flora,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham did not treat the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> In vol. 3 of Bentham (1863-78) but in vol. 6, published in 1873. M nevertheless did not send his <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> to J. Müller. However, he did later send them to Baillon; see M to J. Müller, 25 January 1864 (in this edition as 64-01-25d), n. 7.</p>
               </note> but rather to place it in the Monochlamydeae later on; I should receive word on this shortly. I do, however, attach the condition to my offer, that you will kindly provide me with an absolutely safe way by which I can send this extremely valuable collection to Geneva, which I have amassed here over the past 16 years, and that you will not retain it there for more than one year. In the meantime I would concisely describe the plants belonging to the Flora of Victoria (about 1/6 of the total), so as not to lose the material for my larger work in the unfortunate event of a loss or damage. The <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> of my herbarium comprise 18 thick folders and many species have not yet reached you to date, as I was not able to send any. Even though there may only be a few, the examination of such a collection would yet be informative for you in determining their range of forms and their distribution.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By comparison with an authentic specimen from Preiss I have recently been able to satisfy myself, that my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Pseudanthus%20occidentalis">Pseudanthus occidentalis</name>
               </seg> and Klotzsch's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Chrysostemon%20virgatus">Chrysostemon virgatus</name>
               </seg> are identical. Although I have not re-sectioned this plant recently, I can not yet get used to the idea, that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Micrantheum%20hexandrum">Micrantheum hexandrum</name>
               </seg> should form a separate genus (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Caletia">Caletia</name>
               </seg>), and if this is the case, the merging of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pseudanthi</seg> with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Caletia">Caletia</name>
               </seg> nonetheless does not seem natural to me, for if it were really possible to separate this plant from the type of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pseudanthus</seg>, it would have to be placed under <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Chrysostemon</seg>. As I wrote in my previous letter, I am inclined to retain <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Synostemon</seg>; it forms at the very least a subgenus with peculiar fruit, and is conspicuous by its coalescing anthers. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Lithoxylon">Lithoxylon</name>
               </seg> should probably form its own genus. I have described the fruit of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Pseudanthus%20nematophorus">Pseudanthus nematophorus</name>
               </seg> in my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg>;<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B60.02.02, p. 14.</p>
               </note> it truly seems to me to be but a subgenus of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pseudanthus</seg> or <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Chrysostemon</seg>, whose species all have an easily recognisable exterior character. You will find a description of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Phyllanthus%20subcrenulatus">Phyllanthus subcrenulatus</name>
               </seg> in the first volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B59.04.04, p. 108.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thanking you again for your information and for your kind generosity, and asking that you commend me to the esteemed goodwill of Professor Alphonse de Candolle, I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I shall include the descriptions of Victoria's <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> in the shortly to be published issue of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No such consolidated account was published in the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>
                     <seg style="">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Does the Société de Physique et d'Histoire naturelle de Genève wish to have my publications? Can I be of use to your scientific institute there in some other way?</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Caletia">Caletia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Chrysostemon%20virgatus">Chrysostemon virgatus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cliftonella">Cliftonella</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Flueggea%20buxifolia">Flueggea buxifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lawrencella">Lawrencella</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lithoxylon">Lithoxylon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Micrantheum%20hexandrum">Micrantheum hexandrum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Phyllanthus%20subcrenulatus">Phyllanthus subcrenulatus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pseudanthus%20nematophorus">Pseudanthus nematophorus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pseudanthus%20occidentalis">Pseudanthus occidentalis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
