<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 March 1864. ¶ Venerable Sir, ¶  ¶ Your affectionate letter of 12th of January ¶  has filled me with deep joy and emotion; with joy, because I can bask in the youthful ar...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-03-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.03.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 March 1864. ¶ Venerable Sir, ¶  ¶ Your affectionate letter of 12th of January ¶  has filled me with deep joy and emotion; with joy, because I can bask in the youthful ar...</title>
               <date when="1864-03-25">1864-03-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-03-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Livistona australis</term>
               <term>Seaforthia elegans</term>
               <term>Areca monostachya</term>
               <term>Calamus australis</term>
               <term>Cocos nucifera</term>
               <term>Caryota urens</term>
               <term>Eriocaulaceae</term>
               <term>Leguminosae</term>
               <term>Compositae</term>
               <term>Proteaceae</term>
               <term>Myrtaceae</term>
               <term>Cycas</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 March 1864. ¶ Venerable Sir, ¶  ¶ Your affectionate letter of 12th of January ¶  has filled me with deep joy and emotion; with joy, because I can bask in the youthful ar...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.03.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Martius: 'B. 18 May 64' [Replied 18 May 1864]. Letter not found.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This collection also contains an undated copy of M's letter in the hand of his assistant, Ernst Heyne, which has some minor changes and omissions of text while the middle part of the letter is missing.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im botan. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25. März 1864 </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ehrwürdiger Herr!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr liebevoller Brief v. 12 Januar hat mich mit tiefer Freude u Rührung erfüllt, mit Freude weil ich mich an der noch jugendlichen Gluth Ihres Geistes erwärmen kann, mit Rührung indem ich bemerke, dass Sie der geniale tiefsinnende weit umfassende Gelehrte auf mich, der ich Ihr nepos sein könnte, so gütig hinabblicken. Ihre Worte über das grosse Walten der Natur und die Gesetze, welche die Schöpfung der belebten Wesen lenken, fanden in mir einen hellen Widerklang; u. es schlägt mir froh das Herz, wenn ich wahrnehme, dass die gewichtige Erfahrung Ihres thatkräftigen Lebens von Seiten der reinen Naturphilosophie die unvergänglichen Lehren der Theologie freisinnig in Bezug auf unsere Schöpfungsgeschichte aufgefasst bewahrheiten. Welch´ ein unendlich mehr erhabenes Gefühl regt sich in dieser Anschauung, als wenn wir den Trugschlüssen Darwins folgend das untrennbar Vollständige u. Harmonische jedes belebten Naturkörpers nicht der göttlichen Allmacht sondern dem Zufall (accident) entsprungen wähnen. O! wie tief sinkt der herab, der verkennt, dass alle Formen der belebten Natur nach ewig unwandelbaren Gesetzen dem Cyclus ihrer Epoche durchleben, geschaffen sind von der Weisheit des Höchsten um als selbstständige Wesen ihren Zweck (their design) in dem grossen Naturleben zu erfüllen. Wir sehen es ja stets, dass wir keinen der fast endlosen Organismen der belebten Natur, etwas Wesentliches entziehen können ohne das schöne harmonisch vollendete Gebilde der Art zu zerstören. Offenbar ist es jedoch, dass wir zu häufig den Formenkreis der Arten und ihre Beugsamkeit zu Formen ändernden (aber nicht Species schaffenden) Verhältnissen verkannten. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dann theile ich, edler Herr, ganz Ihre Ansicht über die locale Ausdehnung der grossen Fluthen, u. bin mir keiner Bibelworte bewusst, welche eine solche Annahme verwerflich machen. Ebenso pflichte ich auch Ihrer Meinung bei in Bezug auf das Alter des australischen Welttheils. Wenigstens scheint es mir, soweit wir auf die Vorlagen der Palaeontologie bauen dürfen, dass die lebende Natur Australiens manche Typen aufzuweisen hat, die den Resten anderswo begrabener Organismen einer früheren Schöpfungs-Periode sich nähern, obwohl solche Typen als verschieden von den unserigen nur bedingungsweise massgebend für unsere Schlüsse sein können. Was Sie in Bezug auf die Formenreihen der von Ihnen so trefflich beleuchteten Eriocauleen Brasiliens bemerken, scheint mir anzudeuten, dass unter diesen Gattungsgenossen sich manche Mischlinge finden. Dies reisst aber keineswegs die Schranke nieder zwischen den Arten, wie ich mich beim Eindringen in den innern Bau dieser lieblichen Gewächse, soweit solche Australien angehören, überzeugte. (conf. Fragm. phyt. Austr. I, 91-96.). Dasselbe gilt von den Reihen der Proteaceen, Leguminosen, Myrtaceen, <name key="Compositae">Compositae</name> Australiens, auf welche Sie speciell hinweisen. Die schaffende Natur drückte dem Einzelwesen Ähnlichkeit und nur soweit Verwandtschaft auf, aber begabte die Arten mit einem Bildungsvermögen, nach welchem sie sich oft den verschiedensten Einflüssen anpassen, ja nach welchen sogar manche dem glacier clima sich ebensosehr als dem der sengenden Wüste fügen. Aber aus diesen Einflüssen entspringen nie bleibende Formen, und in demselben Grade wie die Dauer des Einflusses die abweichende Form befestigte, bedarf es einer längern oder kürzern Rückwirkung ehe diese Formen zu den normalen oder primitiven Ausdrucke zurückkehren.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mir erscheint das bunte Formenreich der Natur einzig als ein Complex von Species, in welchem jede Art eine vollständige unantastbare Unabhängigkeit behauptet, obgleich Ähnlichkeiten nur immer gewisse Arten in Annäherung bringen. Ehrhart's Idee nur jeder Art einen Namen zu geben ist streng genommen die einzig haltbare, aber mit ihrer Ausführung würde man die wichtigen Anhaltspunkte verlieren, an die sich namentlich das Gedächtniss lehnt, welche uns die künstliche und daher nie genau begrenzbare Aufstellung der Gattungen gewährt. Nachdem ich zur Ausdehnung von etwa 30,000 engl. Meilen die Welt als Phytologe durchzogen und wohl mehrere hundert Tausend Pflanzenindividuen zergliederte, hat sich mir diese Überzeugung stets aufgedrängt, obwohl ich es mir bewusst bin, selbst nur zu häufig aus mangelnder Kunde die Grenzen der Arten verkannt zu haben. Die einzigen vermittelnden Formen, durch welche im Pflanzenreiche Arten zusammenfliessen sind Mischlinge, die aber doch meistens unfruchtbar sind oder in den schwachen folgenden Generationen erlöschen; u. hier ist selbst zu beachten, dass manche der vermeintlichen Mischlinge nur die Übergänge von Varietäten, nicht aber von Arten darstellen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das isolirte Vorkommen von Pflanzen in Theilen der Erde entfernt von denen wo solche häufig sind, sowie die weite Verbreitung mancher Species (z.B. gewisser Hülsenpflanze durch die tropische Zone beider Hemisphären) ist, denke ich, oft dem Wirken der Zugvögel zuzuschreiben, während vielleicht ein unnachweisbarer Zufall menschlicher Thätigkeit die Verbreitung einzelner Arten in ferne Weltgegenden bedingt haben mag. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre Ansicht über die allerdings nicht absoluten Grenzen der Florengebiete nach natürlichen Basins, welche von Gebirgen umkettet sind, pflichte ich vollkommen bei. So scheidet die Bergreihe, welche die Gewässer der tropischen Ostküste Australiens von denjenigen des Carpentaria Golfes sondert, sehr viele Pflanzen, die nur einem dieser beiden Vertiefungen ausschliesslich angehören. Zum Theil habe ich diese Grenzlinien angedeutet in meinem Bericht über die botanischen Ergebnisse der Gregoryschen Expedition durch das tropische Australien (vide proceed. Linn. Soc. vol II, 137-163) u. in zwei kurzen Abhandlungen über die Geographie der Pflanzen Australiens, veröffentlicht im Jahr 1852 in Sir Will. Hookers Journal.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sehr gern würde ich Ihrem Wunsch entsprochen haben, für eine Abhandlung die ganze Phytogeographie Australiens umfassend meine Notizen zu ordnen, wäre die Arbeit nicht zu umfangsreich, um eilig vollendet zu werden. Ich muss mir eine solche für eine etwas spätere Zeit zur Mittheilung für Ihre ehrwürdige Akademie vorbehalten, u. hoffe inzwischen wichtige ergänzende Materialien von dem jetzt allgemach meinem Sammler zugänglichen Gebirgen u. Jungle-Schluchten Nord-Ost-Australiens zu gewinnen. Nicht unwahrscheinlich birgt auch jene Gegend noch unbekannte Palmen, die offenbar in Australien spärlich vertreten sind, obgleich diese edle Pflanzenordnung hier die südlichste Grenze erreicht in 37°30' südl. Breite. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wunderbar ist es, dass in dieser Breite die herrliche Livistona Australis ihren schlanken Stamm zu einer Höhe von 80' erhebt, u. zwar in den tiefen Waldschluchten des östlichen Gippsland. Die speciellen Grenzen der andern Livistona Arten Australiens sind bisher noch nicht genau ermittelt, u. daher ist auch die geographische Grenze der einzelnen Arten noch nicht zu umschreiben. Selbige ziehn sich indessen nur längs der waldigen Ost- u. Nordküste hin, mit Ausnahme einer erhabenen Art, denen der unglückliche Leichhardt sowohl als ich selbst in den offenen Ebenen oder Abhängen von Arnhems Land hin u. wieder begegnete. <name key="Areca%20monostachya">Areca monostachya</name> ist auf das subtropische Ost-Australien beschränkt. <name key="Cocos%20nucifera">Cocos nucifera</name> kommt in der einen oder andern kleinen Insel in der Torresstrait vor. <name key="Caryota%20urens">Caryota urens</name> findet sich im äussersten Nordosten Australiens. <name key="Seaforthia%20elegans">Seaforthia elegans</name> zieht sich am Illawarra längs der Ostküste unterbrochen hin, u. gehört auch vielleicht Nord-Australien an. Calamus Australis ist ziemlich weit durch den tropischen u subtropischen Osten des litoralen Australien verbreitet. Weder an der Westküste noch an der Südküste noch im fernen Innern Australiens zeigen sich Palmen, denn die Pflanze, deren der Reisende Stuart als einer Palme von Central-Australien gedenkt<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Heyne's copy has 'gedrückt' [pressed].</p>
               </note> ist eine Cycadea.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihrem Wunsche zu der grossartigen Sammlung von Pflanzen, die Sie besitzen u. entstehen liessen, beizusteuern hoffe ich wenigstens bis zu einem gewissen Grade zu genügen. In der That es liegt eine Anzahl von Pflanzen zur Absendung für Sie bereit.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Darf ich Sie bitten dem kleinen Bildnisse, das ich beizufügen wage, Ihre gütige Annahme nicht zu versagen und mich dadurch beglücken zu wollen, dass Sie mir erlauben u es veranlassen, Ihr Bild, gefeierter Mann, in die Reihe der mir befreundeten grossen Zeitgenossen aufnehmen zu können.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit meiner Huldigung zu Ihrer Jubelfeier u dem tiefen Wunsch, dass die Vorsehung Sie zur Zierde der Wissenschaft u Ihren Verehrern noch lange erhalte bleibe ich </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">ehrerbietigst der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 March 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Venerable Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your affectionate letter of 12th of January<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> has filled me with deep joy and emotion; with joy, because I can bask in the youthful ardour of your spirit, with emotion, when I realise that you, the genial, thoughtful, comprehensive scientist looks down so kindly on me, who could be your nephew. Your words on the great workings of nature and on the laws, which direct the creation of living things, found a strong echo within me, and it thrills my heart to perceive, that the important experiences of your active life from the point of view of pure natural philosophy subtly reflect the truths of the everlasting teachings of theology as concern our history of creation. What an infinitely more exalted emotion is aroused by this view, than if we followed Darwin's fallacious conclusions to ascribe the indivisible harmony and completeness of each living entity not to divine omnipotence, but as originating in mere chance. O, how low does a person sink, if he denies that all forms of animated nature are created by the wisdom of the Most High to live through the cycle of their lifespan according to eternal unchanging laws, so to fulfil their design as independent entities in the great scheme of nature. We can constantly observe, that we cannot remove anything essential from the almost innumerable organisms of living nature, without destroying this beautiful, harmoniously complete edifice. It is, however, evident that too often we failed to recognise the range of forms of species and the conditions that change their forms (but do not create species).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I also share your view, noble Sir, on the localised extent of the great floods,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The biblical great flood as described in Genesis, ch. 7-8.</p>
               </note> and I am not aware of any words in the Bible, that would condemn such an assumption. I also agree with your opinion concerning the age of the Australian continent. At least it seems to me, in as far as we can base it on the findings of palaeontology, that the living nature of Australia exhibits many types, which approach the remains of an earlier epoch of creation of organisms buried elsewhere, although such types, as differing from ours, can only be conditionally relevant to our conclusions. What you say concerning the series of forms in the <name key="Eriocaulaceae">Eriocaulaceae</name> of Brazil, so admirably illuminated by you,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius may have offered comments on Körnicke (1863).</p>
               </note> seems to me to indicate that there are many hybrids among these congeners. This, however, in no way tears down the barrier between the species, as I was able to convince myself, when penetrating the inner structure of these lovely plants, in as far as these are represented in Australia (cf. Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae, vol. 1, pp. 91-96).<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B59.02.03.</p>
               </note> The same applies to the series of the <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>, <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>, <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>, and <name key="Compositae">Compositae</name> of Australia, as you specifically point out. Creating nature imprints on the individual organisms similarities and only thus far a relationship, but gave to the species a developmental capability, according to which they often adapt to the most diverse influences, yes, according to which some even accommodate to a glacier climate just as much as to the scorching desert. But no constant forms ever arise from these influences, and in the same degree, in which the duration of the influence established the divergent form, it requires a longer or shorter reverse effect, before the forms return to their normal or primitive expression.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To me the colourful world of forms in nature appears solely as a complex of species, in which each species maintains a complete and unassailable independence, even though similarities will always place certain species in approximation to each other. Ehrhart's idea<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ehrhart (1753-62).</p>
               </note> to give a name only to each species is, strictly speaking, the only tenable one, but in its execution we would lose the important points of reference, which support particularly our memory, and that allows us the erection of the artificial and therefore never precisely definable genera. Having wandered through the world as a phytologist to the extent of about 30,000 English miles, and probably having dissected several hundred thousand individual plants, the conviction has always impressed itself on me that — even though I am aware of it — I myself have all too frequently failed to recognise the limits of species due to lack of knowledge. The only intermediate forms in the vegetable kingdom, in which species flow into each other, are the hybrids, which, however, are usually infertile or become extinguished in the following weak generations; it should be observed here, that so-called hybrids often represent only the transitions between varieties and not species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The isolated occurrence of plants in parts of the world distant from those where they are frequent, as well as the wide distribution of some species (for instance certain <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name> through the tropical zone of both hemispheres) is, I think, often to be ascribed to the action of migrating birds, while perhaps an untraceable accident of human intervention may have caused the distribution of individual species into far distant areas of the globe. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I agree completely with your view on the certainly not absolute limits of floristic zones according to natural basins, which are surrounded by mountain ranges. Thus the mountain range, that divides the waters of the tropical east coast of Australia from those of the Gulf of Carpentaria, segregates very many plants, which belong exclusively only to one of these two areas. I have in part indicated these dividing lines in my report on the botanical results of the Gregory expedition<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6. </p>
               </note> through tropical Australia (see Proceedings of the Linnean Society, vol. 2, pp. 137-163)<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B58.05.01.</p>
               </note> and in two short essays on the geography of plants in Australia, published in Sir William Hooker's journal in 1852.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B53.03.01, B53.04.02. M is in error on the year of publication.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I should have liked very much to accede to your wish to sort my notes for a paper covering the whole phytogeography of Australia, if the work were not too voluminous to be completed quickly. I must reserve such a work for a later date for a communication for your venerable academy,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Royal Bavarian Academy of Sciences (Königlich Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften), Munich.</p>
               </note> and in the meantime hope to acquire important supplementary material from the mountain ranges and jungle gorges of north-eastern Australia now accessible to my collector.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>John Dallachy.</p>
               </note> Very likely that area hides still unknown palms, which are evidently sparsely represented in Australia, even though this noble family of plants reaches its southern limit here at the southern latitude of 37°30'.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is wonderful, that in this latitude the glorious <name key="Livistona%20australis">Livistona australis</name> raises its slender trunks to a height of 80 feet in the deep forest ravines of eastern Gippsland. The particular limits of the other Australian Livistona species have so far not been precisely determined, and therefore the geographical limits of the individual species of this genus cannot yet be defined. They extend, however, only along the wooded east and north coasts, with the exception of one noble species, which the unhappy Leichhardt, as well as I personally met with occasionally in the open plains or on slopes of Arnhem Land. <name key="Areca%20monostachya">Areca monostachya</name> is restricted to subtropical eastern Australia. <name key="Cocos%20nucifera">Cocos nucifera</name> is found on one or another of the small islands of Torres Strait, and <name key="Caryota%20urens">Caryota urens</name> in far north-eastern Australia. <name key="Seaforthia%20elegans">Seaforthia elegans</name> extends intermittently from Illawarra along the east coast, and perhaps belongs also to North Australia. <name key="Calamus%20australis">Calamus australis</name> is distributed fairly widely through tropical and extra-tropical littoral eastern Australia. There is no evidence of palms, neither on the west nor on the south coast, nor in the distant interior of Australia, for the plant from Central Australia identified as a palm by the traveller Stuart<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>John Macdouall Stuart.</p>
               </note> is a <name key="Cycas">Cycas</name>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope to satisfy at least in part your wish, that I should contribute to the great collection of plants which you own and brought together. Indeed, a number of plants are prepared and ready for you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May I ask you not to refuse acceptance of the small photograph<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Photograph not found.</p>
               </note> I dare to enclose, and that you permit me, and bring it about, that I can add your picture, celebrated Sir, to those of friends of mine among great contemporaries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With my homage on the occasion of your jubilee<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius's 70th birthday was on 17 April 1864.</p>
               </note> and the deeply felt wish that Providence may long preserve you as an ornament to science and to your admirers, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain respectfully yours,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Areca%20monostachya">Areca monostachya</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Calamus%20australis">Calamus australis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Caryota%20urens">Caryota urens</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cocos%20nucifera">Cocos nucifera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Compositae">Compositae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cycas">Cycas</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eriocaulaceae">Eriocaulaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Livistona%20australis">Livistona australis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Proteaceae">Proteaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Seaforthia%20elegans">Seaforthia elegans</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
