<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 26 July 1864. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I have at long last dispatched to you a number of dried plants (about 1000) by the ship  ¶ Suffolk ¶  per address of Dr Sonder. ¶  You p...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-07-26-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Eduard Fenzl Nachlass, Archiv der Universität Wien, Vienna.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.07.26</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 26 July 1864. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I have at long last dispatched to you a number of dried plants (about 1000) by the ship  ¶ Suffolk ¶  per address of Dr Sonder. ¶  You p...</title>
               <date when="1864-07-26">1864-07-26</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-07-26-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Veronica angustifolia</term>
               <term>Epilobium tetragonum</term>
               <term>Veronica salicifolia</term>
               <term>Veronica decussata</term>
               <term>Veronica elliptica</term>
               <term>Veronica forsteri</term>
               <term>Fenzlia obtusa</term>
               <term>Veronica fonki</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard Fenzl</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 26 July 1864. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I have at long last dispatched to you a number of dried plants (about 1000) by the ship  ¶ Suffolk ¶  per address of Dr Sonder. ¶  You p...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.07.26</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Eduard Fenzl</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Eduard Fenzl Nachlass, Archiv der Universität Wien, Vienna.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 26. Juli 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Edler Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Am 2. d. Monats habe ich endlich eine Anzahl (etwa 1000) trockne Pflanzen mit dem Schiffe Suffolk unter der Adresse des Herrn Dr Sonder an Sie abgesandt. Es ist wahrscheinlich, dass Sie die Arten zum grossen Theil bereits von andern Gegenden Australiens besitzen; indessen wird doch dadurch die Formenreihe vergrössert werden, oder die Pflanzen werden Ihnen zum Weitergeben willkommen sein. Ich habe mehrfach daran gedacht, das ganze grosse Herbarium <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">australischer</hi>
               </seg> Pflanzen meiner Anstalt (meht denn 1000 starke Bündel umfassend) durchzugehen, um davon für Sie auszuwählen. Die Arbeit ist aber doch zu colossal, um selbige gerade jetzt, während ich von andern Obliegenheiten umringt bin, zu ergreifen. Da ich aber alljährlich einen Theil der Sammlung für Benthams Werk zur Benutzung herrichten muss, wird sich dann die Gelegenheit darbieten für Sie auszuwählen, sollte es nicht früher geschehen. Es kommen ausserdem von Zeit zu Zeit Dubletten-Sammlungen in meinen Besitz, aus denen ich ebenfalls mittheilen werde. Für Ihren Garten sende ich wiederum 253 Arten von Samen, freilich meistens dieselben, welche Sie vormals erhielten; leider hat unser Sammler in N. O. Australien fast gar keine Samen gesandt u daher ich nichts Neues zu bieten. Indessen denke ich, dass manche der Gärten Ihres Kaiserreichs doch gern solche Samen entgegen nehmen, sollte Ihre Anstalt derselben nicht bedürfen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit einigen Wochen bin ich mit einer kleinen Arbeit über die Pflanzen der Chatham-Inseln beschäftigt. Indem ich critisch in die Untersuchung der Arten eindrang u mich dabei auf ein sehr ansehnliches Herbarium Neu-Seeländischer Pflanzen stütze, bin ich veranlasst die Arten sehr einzuziehen. So fliessen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg> Epilobia durch eine vollständige Kette von Mittelformen in eine Art (<name key="Epilobium%20tetragonum">Epilobium tetragonum</name>) zusammen; ja, wenn nicht etwa eine südafrikanische Art verschieden ist, finde ich Alles was ich aus dieser Gattung in meiner grossen Sammlung ausseraustralischer Pflanzen besitze ebenfalls mit E. tetragonum vereinbar. Um ein anderes Beispiel zu geben bemerke ich, dass <name key="Veronica%20elliptica">Veronica elliptica</name> (V. decussata) nur die Alpenform oder die an der Felsküste dem Sturm ausgesetzte Form von V. salicifolia ist, während in typischem Zustand die letztere die Waldform repräsentirt. Dr Hooker hat freilich 14 Arten aus dieser Veronica (die ich nun collectiv V. Forsteri nenne) definirt u Ihr gehört auch V. Fonki<seg style="font-weight: bold; "> </seg>Philippi von Chonos an; aber die Übergänge in meiner lehrreichen Sammlung sind vollständig. Sollte nicht dies extensive Vorkommen der Wandelbarkeit der Arten Darwin u seine Anhänger zu ihrem unglücklichen Irrwahn verleitet haben? Lebte ich in Deutschland, ich würde de novo mit der Bearbeitung der dortigen Pflanzen beginnen u nach meinen Ansichten die Arten feststellen. So glaube ich nach meiner Sammlung annehmen zu dürfen, dass das ganze Genus Epilobium nicht mehr als etwa 4 oder 5 Arten umfasst[,]<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg>.</p>
               </note> die amerikanischen Arten eingeschlossen. Meine Schrift über diese Chatham Pflanzen wird vielleicht Ihnen nicht unwillkommen sein u solche kann Sie hoffentlich noch im Laufe dieses Jahres erreichen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit steter Verehrung u Dankbarkeit u Anhänglichkeit bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich weiss aus Erfahrung, dass <name key="Veronica%20elliptica">Veronica elliptica</name>, V. angustifolia &amp; V. salicifolia in Cultur standhaft sind. Dies beweist aber <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg> den Arten character, wie man oft irrig annehme</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Kürzlich habe ich eine merkwürdig kleinblättrige Varietät von <name key="Fenzlia%20obtusa">Fenzlia obtusa</name> von dem zwischen dem Burdekin u Thomson Fluss liegenden Gebirge erhalten</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">26 July 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Noble friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have at long last dispatched to you a number of dried plants (about 1000) by the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Suffolk</seg> per address of Dr Sonder.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to E. Fenzl, 26 June 1864 (in this edition as 64-06-26a).</p>
               </note> You probably already have many of the species from other parts of Australia; they will, however, expand the range of forms, or else the plants will be welcome for passing them on. I have repeatedly thought of going through the whole large herbarium of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Australian</hi>
               </seg> plants of my institute (consisting of more than 1000 thick folders) to select from it for you. But then the work is really too enormous for me to embark on just now, while I am surrounded by other obligations. However, as I have to prepare each year a part of the collections for the use of Bentham's work, this will then offer the opportunity to pick out plants for you, if it does not get done sooner. In addition, duplicate collections come into my hands periodically, from which I shall also communicate some. I am sending again seeds of 253 species, admittedly mostly the same as you received previously; our collector in north-eastern Australia<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">John Dallachy.</p>
               </note> has unfortunately sent hardly any seeds, so I do not have anything new to offer. But I imagine that many of the Gardens in your Empire would be pleased to accept such seeds, if your institute does not require them.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For several weeks I have been occupied with a small work on the plants of the Chatham Islands.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B64.13.02.</p>
               </note> During an intensely critical examination of the species, supported by a considerable herbarium of New Zealand plants, I find myself obliged to greatly reduce the species. Thus <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> epilobiums flow by a complete chain of intermediate forms together into one species (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Epilobium%20tetragonum">Epilobium tetragonum</name>
               </seg>); Yes, unless perhaps one South African species is different, I find that everything that I possess from this genus in my large collection of extra-Australian plants can also be united with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. tetragonum</seg>. To give another example, I noted that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Veronica%20elliptica">Veronica elliptica</name>
               </seg> (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. decussata</seg>) is simply the alpine form, or the form exposed to the storms on the rocky coast, of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. salicifolia</seg>, while the typical form of the latter is represented by the form from the forests. To be sure, Dr Hooker defined 14 species of this <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Veronica</seg> (which I call collectively <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. forsteri</seg>), and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. fonki</seg> Philippi from Chonos<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Archipielago de los Chonos, off the southern coast.of Chile.</p>
               </note> also belongs here; but the transitions are complete in my instructive collections.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to C. von Martius, 25 July 1864.</p>
               </note> Might not this extensive variability have misled Darwin and his followers into their unfortunate delusion? If I lived in Germany, I would start all over again from scratch on work on the plants there and fix the species according to my views. Thus I believe I can assume from my collections, that the whole of the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Epilobium</seg> does not contain more than about 4 or 5 species, including the American species. My publication on these Chatham plants may perhaps not be unwelcome to you, and I hope it will reach you still in the course of this year.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Always with respect and gratitude and devotion, I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I know from experience, that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Veronica%20elliptica">Veronica elliptica</name>, V. angustifolia</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. salicifolia</seg> are constant under cultivation. However, that does <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> prove the species character, as is often wrongly assumed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I recently obtained a peculiar small-leaved variety of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Fenzlia%20obtusa">Fenzlia obtusa</name>
               </seg> from the mountain range lying between the Burdekin and Thomson Rivers.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Qld.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Epilobium%20tetragonum">Epilobium tetragonum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Fenzlia%20obtusa">Fenzlia obtusa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Veronica%20angustifolia">Veronica angustifolia</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20decussata">Veronica decussata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20elliptica">Veronica elliptica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20fonki">Veronica fonki</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20forsteri">Veronica forsteri</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20salicifolia">Veronica salicifolia</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
