<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>25 August 1864. ¶ Dearest friend, ¶  ¶ How pleasantly surprised I was by the lines from your wife! ¶  How talented and diligent a lady she must be, and how happy you must be to possess her. I must not...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-08-25a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, folder 206, no. 547, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.08.25a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>25 August 1864. ¶ Dearest friend, ¶  ¶ How pleasantly surprised I was by the lines from your wife! ¶  How talented and diligent a lady she must be, and how happy you must be to possess her. I must not...</title>
               <date when="1864-08-25">1864-08-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-08-25a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/25eab479-d6c1-4a28-a7c5-0a0c11dc2d1d">Tetragonia implexicoma</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/1dfdd922-7fa3-4fc4-bb6e-96cfa112337a">Eucalyptus globulus</term>
               <term>Josephinia eugeniae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">25 August 1864. ¶ Dearest friend, ¶  ¶ How pleasantly surprised I was by the lines from your wife! ¶  How talented and diligent a lady she must be, and how happy you must be to possess her. I must not...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.08.25a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, folder 206, no. 547, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">25/8/64</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Theuerster Freund.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie freudig mich Ihrer Gemahlin Zeilen überraschten! Welch eine talentvolle u fleissige Dame sie sein muss, u wie beglückt Sie in ihrem Besitze leben müssen. Ich darf mir nicht die Freude versagen den Brief deutsch zu beantworten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist spät; so darf ich nicht schwärmen. Prof McCoy hat eine Vorlesung über Ihre Fossilien angekündigt, die am nächsten Montag in der Sitzung unserer königl Gesellschaft gehalten werden soll. Ich werde Ihnen berichten; doch da er mich in der Meteorit Angelegenheit gekränkt möchte ich keine Besprechung über Ihre Angelegenheit mit ihm anknüpfen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre wiederholte gütige Einladungen sind für mich ganz rührend. In den nächsten Monaten bin ich nicht frei; ob ich später für eine Weile mich dem Besuch zu Sir Geo Grey u Ihnen hingeben mag, denn auch Sr Excellenz hat mich wiederholt freundlich eingeladen, muss die Zukunft lehren. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe mich heute streng gegen Bentham in meinem Schreiben an ihn ausgesprochen, da mir manches in der Behandlung meiner Pflanzen nicht gefällt. Hoffentlich wird es aber nicht zum Bruch kommen, obgleich er mich ganz entmuthigt hat. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Chatham Pflanzen sind bis zum Beginn der Farnkräuter gedruckt. Die Abhandlung wird etwa 80 Seiten füllen u 7 Platten haben (die schon fertig liegen). Nur 7 Pflanzen sind neu, die Moose, Flechten u Algen werde ich nicht aufnehmen, theils weil die Bearbeit augenblicklich zu zeitraubend für mich sein würde, theils weil ich die Begrenzung der Cryptogame der Jetztzeit verwerfe, theils weil selbige früh genug für Hookers Specialisten da sind, theils weil mir die Sammlung als Illustration der Acotyledonen der Insel zu kärglich erscheint.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Können Sie mir gelgentlich einige Früchte der an Lyttleton Harbour vorkommenden <name key="Tetragonia%20implexicoma">Tetragonia implexicoma</name> senden? Es ist die fleischige Spinat-Schlingpflanze mit rothen Früchten (in J Hook. N. Z. Flora nicht enthalten)</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In der Vorrede der Chatham Flora, werde ich mit wenigen nicht anfeindenden Worten der Irrlehre Darwins entgegen treten. So hat es mein Freund, der grosse Italiener Parlatore gethan in einer philos. Abhandl. die er mir in diesen Tagen sandte. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit Mr Travers bin ich vortrefflich gestellt. Er handelt sehr edel u grossmüthig jetzt u ist mit meiner Arbeit befriedigt, hat mir jetzt wieder etwaige Pflanzen von der Antip. Ins. u.sw zugesagt. Das ist doch nobel. — Recht schade Sie hatten Reibungen, namentlich so kurz vor seinem Scheiden von N. Z. Hoffentlich gleicht sich Alles wieder freundlich aus. Übrigens halte Ihre Handlungsweise ganz gerechtfertigt. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie traurig dass der junge Travers auf Abwege gerieth. Hoffentlich sind solche nicht arger Art u ist nicht die Chatham Reise die Ursache des Umsturzes seiner Moral. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bitte versetzen Sie sich ja </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> in Unkosten für weiteres Sammeln in den Chatham Inseln. Ich dachte die Nachlese sollte von Hunt oder anderen geschehen, die dort wohnen. Hunt sollte sich hinlänglich dazu angetrieben fühlen durch die Benennung des baumartigen Senecio. </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihre</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Flora v. N. S. möchte mehr Neues liefern, als die der Chatham Inseln. Ist Buchanan von Kew besoldet? Er scheint ein reger Sammler. Dr Hector bitte ich zu grüssen; ich hätte gern von ihm gehört, doch zagte ich mit ihm zu correspondiren, um nicht Jos. Hookers Eifersucht zu erregen, obgleich Dr Hooker sich vor einiger Zeit um Pflanzen bittend an meinen Correspondent Stuart in Neu England wandte, der ihm aber rund seine Ansuche abschlug ohne mich zu consultiren, so dass ich nicht daran Schuld bin. Natürlich wandte sich Dr Hooker </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> durch mich an Stuart. </seg>Doch bleibe dies unter uns. Die Bearbeitung der Chath. <seg style="">Pflanzen kostet meinen Department wenigstens £100 so dass das Exemplar der Regierung auf etwa 4/6 zu stehen kommt. Etwas lösen wir natürlich wieder durch Verkauf. Ich werde Travers 20 Exempl. senden u Ihnen einge. Vor Ende September wird die Brochure nicht fertig sein.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Über die Wünsche welche Sie an Frankreich hegen will ich nachdenken. Ich wünsche Ihnen das Angedeutete aus tiefstem Herzen. Meine Beziehungen zu Graf Castelneau sind freilich cordial aber absolut wissenschaftlich. </seg>Wir wohnen zu entfernt um social nahe zu stehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Ich hatte vor nahe 10 Jahren das Glück die 2te Art der Gattung Josephinia zu entdecken u da damals Engl. u Franz. gegen Russland kämpften, hielt ich die Verknüpfung der beiden Kaiserinnen in meiner Pflanze als Josephinia Eugeniae nicht unpassend. Nicht durch meine Hand aber auf eine mir nicht bekannt gewordene Weise kam meine Abhandlung mit dem Bilde vor die Kaiserin. Dann pflanzte der Kaiser mit eigener Hand den riesigen Eucal Globul in Biaritz, nachdem ich selbige in Algier als Waldbaum u für künftiges Schiffbauholz weit verbreitet hatte. Noch andere Beziehungen zum Hofe des Kaisers machten mich dem Herrscher Frankreichs genauer bekannt u ganz </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unerwartet</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> ward mir die Ehre. Ich gebe Ihnen dies an als Freund mit Offenheit, damit Sie selbst vielleicht in ähnliche Beziehungen treten. Wie gesagt ich will über den Gegenstand nachdenken u wenn ich es Ihnen gegenüber thun kann ohne Sie zu compromittiren mit dem Grafen Rücksprache nehmen. Könnten nicht Maltebrun u Ihre andern Pariser Freunde die Sache für Sie einleiten? Ich werde sie freudig unterstützen. Sie sind übergütig gegen mich in Ihrem Wunsche dass ich nicht weiss wie ichs vergelten soll. Ich habe aber nicht die </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geringsten</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Ansprüche an die Huld des Königs von Preussen. Ich war nie dort u obgleich ich [mit]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg>.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> manchen Gelehrten des Königsthums in Verbindung stehe, ist solche eine absolut reciprocale. Nichts destoweniger erkenne ich Ihre Freundlichkeit tief an. Aber, Theuerster, was ist wohl ehrenvoller als zu der kleinen Schar Auserwählter zu gehören die die Medaille der geogr. Gesellsch. besitzen. War doch die Copleys'sche Medaille d. </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">R. S.</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Humboldt das Theuerste! — MacKinley &amp; Landsborough können sich nicht einmal des Besitzes der Medaille der R. G. S. rühmen, u doch war deren Leistung etwas Grossartiges. Aber auch Sie haben solche theuer erkämpft u können daher stolz sein über solche Leute den Sieg davon getragen zu haben. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An Martius habe ich zweimal so eindringlich geschrieben, dass Sie der Wahl in die Acad. gewiss sind, u ich werde nicht ruhn als bis ich Sie dort zum Collegen habe, denn kein Deutscher im Ausland verdient es mehr.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Da Hooker fil u Bentham beide sich zum Darwinismus bekennen, können wir natürlich nicht über die Grenzen der Species übereinstimmen. Ich überlasse mit Ruhe das Urtheil </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">künftigen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Generationen. Es ist gerade 12. So schliesse ich mit einem "Gute Nacht u guten Morgen" als</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Ihr treuer</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Besitzen Sie Dieffenbachs Abhandl. über die Geologie der Chatham Inseln? Wo nicht werde ich Ihnen selbige aus meiner Bibliothek leihen, falls Sie es wünschen </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich will gern ein kleines Herbar für Ihr Museum senden, aber Sie müssen mir ein wenig Frist geben, damit ich nicht durch Überarbeit erkranke.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 August 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dearest friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How pleasantly surprised I was by the lines from your wife!<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> How talented and diligent a lady she must be, and how happy you must be to possess her. I must not deny myself the pleasure of answering her in German. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is late, so I must not rave on. Professor McCoy has announced a lecture on your fossils to be held next Monday at the meeting of our Royal Society.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. Royal Society of Victoria. There is no reference to McCoy’s reading such a paper in the published proceedings of the meeting.</p>
               </note> I shall report to you on it, but as he offended me in the meteorite affair<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">See Lucas et al. (1994).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I do not wish to start a discussion with him regarding your concerns.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I find your repeated kind invitations really touching. I am not free in the next few months; whether I shall be able to give some time to visit Sir George Grey and you — for His Excellency also has kindly invited me repeatedly — only the future will tell. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have expressed myself quite severely in a letter to Bentham today, as there is much in his treatment of my plants I do not like.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">M to G. Bentham, 25 August 1864.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> But I hope it will not come to a break, although he has discouraged me completely.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Chatham plants are printed up to the beginning of the ferns. The paper will fill approximately 80 pages and include 7 plates (which are already completed).<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">B64.10.02.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Only 7 of the plants are new. I do not intend to include the mosses, lichens and algae, partly because their treatment would be too time-consuming for me, partly because I reject the modern arrangements of cryptogams, partly because they will be there in good time for Hooker's specialists, partly because the collection seems too paltry to illustrate the acotyledons of the Islands. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Could you send me fruit of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Tetragonia%20implexicoma">Tetragonia implexicoma</name>
               </seg> from the Lyttleton harbour when convenient? It is the fleshy spinach trailer with red fruit (not included in J. Hooker's New Zealand Flora<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker (1853-5).</p>
               </note>).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the introduction to the Chatham Flora I shall oppose Darwin's heresy in a few non-hostile words. That is what my friend, the great Italian Parlatore, has done in a philosophical paper, which he sent me a few days ago.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Parlatore (1863).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am in an excellent relationship with Mr Travers.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">W. T. L. Travers.</p>
               </note> He now acts very nobly and generously, is satisfied with my work, and has promised me possible plants from the Antip[odes] Islands. That is indeed noble. — What a pity that you had clashes with him, particularly so close before his departure from New Zealand. I hope everything will be smoothed over again in a friendly manner. By the way, I consider that your actions were completely justified.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How sad that young Travers was led astray. I hope the matter is not serious, and that the Chatham voyage was not the cause of his moral ruin.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Henry Hammersley Travers made the collection on the Chatham Islands upon which M based B64.10.02. It is not known to what M was alluding when he commented upon Travers being 'led astray'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Please do <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> involve yourself in any expenses for further collections from the Chatham Islands. I thought this further gleaning could be done by Hunt, or others who live there. Hunt should feel prompted to it by the naming of the tree-like <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Senecio</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M named <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Senecio huntii</seg> in B64.10.02, p. 23.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Your</hi>
               </seg> flora of New Zealand should provide more that is new than that of the Chatham Islands.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Is Buchanan paid by Kew? He seems to be an active collector.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">John Buchanan (1819-1898) was employed by James Hector as botanist and draughtsman on his survey of the province of Otago.</p>
               </note> Please give my regards to Dr Hector; I would like to hear from him, but have not dared to correspond with him so as not to arouse Joseph Hooker's jealousy, although Dr Hooker approached my correspondent Stuart in New England a while ago, asking him for plants. But he flatly refused this request without consulting me, so that it is not my fault. Of Course, Dr Hooker did <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> approach Stuart through me. But let that remain between us. The work on the Chatham plants is costing my Department at least £100, so that each copy costs the Government about 4/6. Of course we will get something back through the sales. I shall send 20 copies to Travers and some to you. But the pamphlets are unlikely to be ready before the end of September.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As regards the wishes you entertain concerning France, I shall think about it.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">See also M to J. Haast, 24 October 1864.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I wish for you what you have indicated from the bottom of my heart. My connections with Count Castelnau are, it is true, cordial but entirely scientific. We live too far apart for any close social contacts.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nearly 10 years ago I had the good fortune to discover the second species in the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Josephinia</seg>. As at that time the English and French were fighting against Russia,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In the Crimean War.</p>
               </note> I considered the conjoining of the two Empresses in my plant as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Josephinia%20eugeniae">Josephinia eugeniae</name>
               </seg> not unsuitable.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Empresses Josephine, wife of Napoléon I, and Eugénie, wife of Napoléon III.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>My paper with the picture came into the hands of the Empress, not through me but by means not known to me. Then the Emperor planted with his own hand the giant <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus%20globulus">Eucalyptus globulus</name>
               </seg> at Biarritz, after I had distributed it widely in Algeria as a forest tree and for future timber for ship-building. Other connections to the Imperial Court caused me to become better known to the French monarch, and the honour<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The award to M in 1863 of a Knight’s Cross in the Légion d'Honneur.</p>
               </note> came to me quite <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unexpectedly</hi>
               </seg>. I only tell you all this quite frankly as a friend, so that perhaps you can establish similar connections. As I said, I shall give the matter some thought, and if I can do it for you without compromising you, will discuss it with the Count. Could not Maltebrun and your other Paris friends set the matter in motion? I would happily support them. You are too kind towards me in your wishes and I do not know how to repay you. But I have not the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">least</hi>
               </seg> claims on the favours of the King of Prussia. I was never there and although I am in communication with several scientists of the kingdom, these are completely reciprocal. But I acknowledge your kindness nonetheless. However, dearest friend, what could be more honourable, than to belong to the small elect circle who have received the Medal of the Royal Geographical Society. Was not the Copley Medal of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">R. S.</hi>
               </seg> Humboldt's most precious honour?!<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Alexander von Humboldt was awarded the Royal Society’s Copley Medal in 1852.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> — MacKinley and Landsborough cannot even boast of possessing the Medal of the Royal Geographical Society, yet their achievements were magnificent. But then you, too, had to fight hard for it, and you can be proud to have succeeded over such men.<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Haast was not awarded the Royal Geographical Society’s gold medal until 1884.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have written twice to Martius so urgently, that you can be assured of election to the Academy,<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. the Leopoldina. See M to C. von Martius, 25 June 1864, and M to C. von Martius, 25 July 1864.</p>
               </note> and I shall not rest until I have you there as my colleague, because no German abroad merits it more.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As both Hooker fil. and Bentham believe in Darwinism, we of course cannot agree on the limits of species. I am happy to leave it to the judgment of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">future</hi>
               </seg> generations. It is just midnight, so I close with a 'Good night and good morning' as</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your faithful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Do you own Dieffenbach's publication on the geology of the Chatham Islands?<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Dieffenbach (1841).</p>
               </note> If not, I can loan you my copy from my library, if you wish it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am happy to send a small herbarium for your Museum, but you must give me a little time so that I do not get ill from overwork.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20globulus">Eucalyptus globulus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">Josephinia</seg>
               <seg style="">eugeniae</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Tetragonia%20implexicoma">Tetragonia implexicoma</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
