<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 July 1864. ¶ Noble Sir, ¶  ¶ There is for me an indescribably happy feeling in the knowledge of having participated, no matter how insignificantly, in the celebration o...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-07-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.07.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 July 1864. ¶ Noble Sir, ¶  ¶ There is for me an indescribably happy feeling in the knowledge of having participated, no matter how insignificantly, in the celebration o...</title>
               <date when="1864-07-25">1864-07-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-07-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Epilobium tetragonum</term>
               <term>Veronica salicifolia</term>
               <term>Veronica decussata</term>
               <term>Veronica elliptica</term>
               <term>Veronica forsteri</term>
               <term>Veronica Fonki </term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 July 1864. ¶ Noble Sir, ¶  ¶ There is for me an indescribably happy feeling in the knowledge of having participated, no matter how insignificantly, in the celebration o...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.07.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Martius: 'Erh. [Shlehd.] 23 Sept. [Received [...] 23 September].</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im bot. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25 Juli 64.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Edler Herr,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es liegt für mich ein unnennbar freudiges Gefühl in dem Bewusstsein, mich, wenn auch so gering, bei der Feier Ihres schönen Festes betheiligt zu haben. Es ist die Ehre meine, mich unter denen zählen zu dürfen, die Ihnen, Verehrtester, den glorreich errungenen Lorbeerkranz zum Schmuck Ihres ehrwürdigen Hauptes überbrachten. Wie herrlich wäre es für mich gewesen, hätte ich Ihnen früher näher stehen können im Leben, um mich von dem Licht Ihres weitdringenden Wissens erleuchten zu lassen und damit belebter u. kenntnisvoller auf meine Bahn gelenkt zu werden. So sei es mir wenigstens vergönnt mit Ihnen in für mich freudiger u. belehrender Verbindung zu bleiben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um wenistens bis zu einem gewissen Grade mein Versprechen zu lösen, habe ich mit dem Schiffe Suffolk im Beginn dieses Monats eben 1400 trockne Pflanzen an Sie abgesandt, solche der Obhut des Doctors Sonder vertrauend, um von Hamburg aus weitergesandt zu werden. Es ist freilich wohl die Mehrzahl der Arten bereits in Ihrer grossartigen Sammlung vertreten; indessen sind die jetzt gesandten Pflanzen doch wohl meistens von entlegenen Standorten oder zeigen andere Formen. Allgemach, wenn ich die Sammlungen für den Gebrauch Benthams zurichte, würde ich Anderes u Besseres nachliefern; und wenn Sie aus einer besonderen Gattung oder Familie, das was ich besitze zu erlangen wünschen, bitte ich Sie es mich wissen zu lassen, damit es gleich gesandt werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit einigen Wochen bin ich an einer kleinen Arbeit über die Pflanzen der Chatham Inseln beschäftigt. Critisch in die Untersuchung der Arten [eindringend], bin ich gezwungen selbige in manchen Fällen sehr zu verringern. So habe ich nicht nur alle Epilobien Neu Seelands (trotz dessen dass Dr Hooker dort allein 14 Arten aufstellt) auf eins (E. tetragonum ) zurückzuführen müssen, sondern auch alle übrigen Epilobien der südlichen Hemisphaere zu dieser Art bringen müssen. Meine Sammlung Neu-Seeländischer Pflanzen ist so gross, dass ich diese Reduction mit Sicherheit habe vornehmen können, u selbige stützt sich auf eine sorgfältige geduldige Zergliederung einer grossen Menge Pflanzen u zudem auf die vieljährige Beobachtung dieses Epilobium in freier Natur sowohl in den heissen Niederungen als in den Schneegürteln unserer Alpen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um ein anderes Beispiel hinzustellen bemerke ich, dass 14 in der Flora Neuseelands aufgestellte Veronica Arten, alle als Spielformen einer Art, die ich V. Forsteri nenne angesehen werden müssen. Von dieser bildet V. salicifolia die Waldform, V. decussata<seg style="color: #0000ff; "> </seg>(oder elliptica) die Alpenform oder diejenige varietät welche an der dem Sturm ausgesetzte Felsküste entspringt. Die Kette der Übergänge ist vollständig. Auch V. Fonki Philippi gehört zu dieser Art, wie die Pflanze am Chonos Archipel zeigt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In meinem letzten Briefe trat ich als Bittender vor Sie, edler Herr, hin, nicht für mich aber für 2 Freunde u wohlverdienende Männer der Wissenschaft. Ich bat um die Aufnahme des Herrn Dr Julius Haast, des Neuseeländischen Geologen, in die Akademie der Carol. Leop. u für Mr G. H. K. Thwaites, dem verdienstvollen Forscher der Diatomeen u. ausgezeichnete Untersucher der Pflanzen Ceylons um die phil. Doctorwürde. Könnte Beides durch Ihren gewaltigen Einfluss erreicht werden? Gewiss, wenn Sie diese Männer Ihrer Huld werth halten. — Beide würden dankbar sein u aus ihren Pflanzensammlungen viel Schönes Ihnen liefern können.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bevor ich für diesmal scheide, wage ich noch einmal die Frage aufzuwerfen: Hat nicht das fast allgemeine Vorkommen der Wandelbarkeit der Arten Darwins u seiner Anhänger zu dem unglücklichen Irrwahn geführt, dass es überhaupt in der Natur keine festen Schranken unter ihren Formen gäbe? — Ich finde wenn ich die Epilobien der Erde auf etwa 4 oder 5 zurückführe, dass die Grenzen bestimmt sind; jedenfalls giebt es in der ganzen südlichen Hemisphäre keine Übergänge von <name key="Epilobium%20tetragonum">Epilobium tetragonum</name> (in meinem Sinne angenommen) zu irgend einer anderen mir bekannten Pflanze. Lassen sich nicht aus solchen Thatsachen Schlüsse ziehen, die den verderblichen entmuthigenden Thesen der Transmutations Theory entgegen treten. Ich habe mit dem frommen geistreichen wackeren u selbstständig arbeitenden immer thätigen Sir Will. Denison diese inhaltsschwere Frage vielfach erwogen u wir beide theilen durchaus dieselbe Ansicht, der Gouverneur solche mehr vom Standpunkt der philosophischen Theologie, ich selbige [...]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An unknown amount of text missing.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 July 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Noble Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is for me an indescribably happy feeling in the knowledge of having participated, no matter how insignificantly, in the celebration of your beautiful feast day.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Martius celebrated the 50th anniversary of his doctorate on 30 March and his 70th birthday on 17 April 1864. M subscribed for both of the commemorative medals struck for the occasion.</p>
               </note> The honour is all mine, to have been permitted to be counted among those, who presented to you, revered Sir, the gloriously attained laurel wreath to decorate your venerable brow. How marvellous it would have been for me, could I but have been closer to you earlier in life, to be illuminated by the light of your comprehensive knowledge, and so have been directed in my path, more alert and knowledgeable through it. At least let it be granted to me, to remain in this communication with you that is so joyful and instructive for me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have dispatched 1400 dried herbarium specimens to you by the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Suffolk</seg> at the beginning of this month, in order to discharge my promise to you at least to some degree. I am entrusting them to the care of Dr Sonder to forward them from Hamburg. The majority of the species will probably be already represented in your magnificent collection; however the plants now sent are mostly from more distant localities or display different forms. Gradually, as I prepare the collections for Bentham's use,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg>.</p>
               </note> I will be able to send subsequently something different and better. If you wish to obtain something I have of a particular genus or family, I ask you to inform me and it will be sent immediately. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For the past few weeks I have been occupied with a small work on the vegetation of the Chatham Islands.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B64.10.02.</p>
               </note> Critically entering into the examination of the species I am forced in many cases to reduce them considerably. Thus I not only had to reduce <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Epilobium</seg> species of New Zealand to just <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg> (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. tetragonum</seg>) (in spite of Dr Hooker alone having erected 14 species there), but also had to bring all the other Epilobiums of the southern hemisphere under this species. My collection of New Zealand plants is so large, that I could undertake the reduction with certainty, and it is based on a careful and patient dissection of a large number of plants, and in addition on many years of observation of this <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Epilobium</seg> in the field, in hot plains as well as in the snow belts of our alps.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To demonstrate by another example, I want to remark that 14 species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Veronica</seg>, erected in the Flora Novae-Zelandiae,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. Hooker (1853-5).</p>
               </note> must all be considered forms of one species, which I call <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. forsteri.</seg> Of this <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. salicifolia</seg> represents the forest form, V. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">decussata</seg> (or <seg style="font-style: italic; ">elliptica</seg>) the alpine form or that variation that emerges on the rocky coasts exposed to storms. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">V. Fonki</seg> Philippi also belongs to this species, as is shown by the plant found in the Chonos Archipelago.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Archipielago de los Chonos, southern Chile.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In my last letter<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> See M to C. von Martius, 25 June 1864.</p>
               </note> I came before you as a supplicant, noble Sir, not for myself, but for two friends and deserving men of science. I asked for the election of Dr Julius Haast, the New Zealand geologist, into the Academy of the Carolinae-Leopoldina, and for a doctorate of philosophy for Mr G. H. K. Thwaites, the meritorious researcher of diatoms and excellent investigator of the vegetation of Ceylon. Could both be achieved through your enormous influence? I am sure of it, if you would consider these men worthy of your favour. — Both would be grateful and could supply many beautiful specimens to you from their collections.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Before I take my leave for today, I once more take the liberty to raise the question: Does not the almost general occurrence of the transmutation of species of Darwin and his followers lead to the unfortunate delusion, that in nature there exist no definite limits in its forms? — I find that, when I reduce the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Epilobium</seg> species of the world to about 4 or 5, the limits are definite; certainly there are no transitions in the whole of the southern hemisphere from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Epilobium%20tetragonum">Epilobium tetragonum</name>
               </seg> (taken in my sense) to any other plant known to me. From such facts, cannot conclusions be drawn that oppose the pernicious discouraging theses of the transmutation theory? I have frequently considered this significant question with the pious, talented, capable, and always independently working Sir William Denison, and we both share the same opinion, the Governor more from the point of view of philosophical theology, I from [...]<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An unknown amount of text missing.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Epilobium%20tetragonum">Epilobium tetragonum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20decussata">Veronica decussata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20elliptica">Veronica elliptica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20forsteri">Veronica forsteri</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20Fonki%20">Veronica Fonki </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20salicifolia">Veronica salicifolia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
