<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 January 1864. ¶ Dear Doctor, ¶  ¶ The last mail brought me your kind letter of 27 July 1863, ¶  enclosed with that from the revered Professor Dr [de] Candolle. ¶  I reg...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-01-25d-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Bibliothèque, Conservatoire et Jardin botanique de la ville de Genève.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.01.25d</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 January 1864. ¶ Dear Doctor, ¶  ¶ The last mail brought me your kind letter of 27 July 1863, ¶  enclosed with that from the revered Professor Dr [de] Candolle. ¶  I reg...</title>
               <date when="1864-01-25">1864-01-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-01-25d-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Phyllanthus novaehollandiae</term>
               <term>Phyllanthus glochidioides</term>
               <term>Phyllanthus albiflorus</term>
               <term>Monochlamydeae</term>
               <term>Capparidaceae</term>
               <term>Euphorbiaceae</term>
               <term>Calyciflorae</term>
               <term>Gynandropsis</term>
               <term>Zygophyllum</term>
               <term>Flueggella</term>
               <term>Synostemon</term>
               <term>Antidesma</term>
               <term>Adriana</term>
               <term>Roepera</term>
               <term>Bertya</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jean Müller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 January 1864. ¶ Dear Doctor, ¶  ¶ The last mail brought me your kind letter of 27 July 1863, ¶  enclosed with that from the revered Professor Dr [de] Candolle. ¶  I reg...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.01.25d</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Jean Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Bibliothèque, Conservatoire et Jardin botanique de la ville de Genève.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No addressee is indicated. However, comparing the references to <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> here and in M’s letter to A. de Candolle written on the same day (in this edition as 64-01-25a) makes it clear that the letter was addressed to Müller. </p>
               </note>Melbourne, im bot. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25. Jan 64.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Geehrter Herr Doctor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die letzte Post brachte mir Ihr freundliches Schreiben vom 27 Juli 1863, demjenigen des verehrten Herrn Professor Dr Candolle beigeschlossen. Ich bedaure Ihnen nicht gleich meine ganze Reihe Normal Exemplare der Euphorbiaceen zugesandt zu haben, was nicht geschah, da ich früher nicht die Ehre hatte mit Ihnen zu correspondiren u. weil Ihr Wohnort auch so von der Küste entlegen ist, dass das Darlehn einer so werthvollen u durch vieljährige Arbeit u Reisen zusammen gebrachten Sammlung wenigsten ohne sichere Vorbereitung mir zu gewagt erschien.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe mit heutiger Post Bentham befragt, ob er die Euphorbiaceen unter die <name key="Calyciflorae">Calyciflorae</name> unseres Werkes über die Pflanzen Australiens aufnehmen wolle oder selbige für die <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name> zurückhalten werde. Im letzten Falle bin ich bereit Ihnen die Original Fascicle dieser Ordnung aus meinem Staats-Herbarium zu leihen, wenn Sie mir einen durchaus sicheren Weg der Versendung angeben wollen u wenn Sie sich anheisich<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">anheischig.</p>
               </note> machen wollen die Sammlungen, welche ich hier stets mehr oder weniger entbehren werde, nicht länger als 1 Jahr in Genf zurückzuhalten. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eigentlich habe ich Baillon selbige versprochen; indessen da Sie doch einmal die Bearbeitung vornehmen für D.C. Werk ist es am Besten Ihnen diese Pflanzen zugänglich zu machen u Baillon kann dann erhalten was nach dem Erscheinen des prodromus in meine Hände kommen mag aus dieser seiner Lieblingsfamilie. Die analytischen Tafeln Baillons sind doch vortrefflich. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Beigefügt sende ich Ihnen einen Index der Euphorbicaeen welche ich selbst beschrieb. Da der 4 Band meiner Fragmenta erst halb gedruckt ist u daher nicht im Buchhandel zu erlangen sein wird, sende ich Ihnen das Blatt, auf welchem ich die 2 meiner Bertyen beschrieb.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Edinburgh phil journal von diesem oder vorigem Jahr oder im bot. Soc. Journal von Edinburgh ist eine Abhandlung von mir über Gregorys N W. Australische Pflanzen gedruckt, in welcher ich Dampiers Platte zu <name key="Adriana">Adriana</name> (Trachycaryon) zog u mich weiter über diese Gattung aussprach u nur 2 Arten (1 mit gegenüberstehenden, 1 mit alternirenden Blättern annehme) Bisher ist mir der Band nicht zugegangen, aber durch Hr Professor Balfour in Edinburgh könnten Sie ihn leicht beziehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sollte sich unter den Euphorbiaceen (wie ich überzeugt bin!) noch andere neue u <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sichere</hi>
               </seg> Genera finden in meiner Sammlung, so bitte ich Sie mir zu erlauben eins mit Ihnen vereint dem ehrwürdigen Professor Roeper in Rostock zu widmen. Da A. Jussieus <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name> nicht von <name key="Zygophyllum">Zygophyllum</name> zu trennen, u Sprengels Ricinocarpus ist u Bentham (vielleicht mit Unrecht) meine Capparideen Genus <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name> zu <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name> gebracht, so liegt es mir ob dem Professor meiner <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Vaterstadt</hi>
               </seg> ein neues zu creiren u dazu wäre doch eins aus der Familie, in welcher er so bedeutende Arbeit leistete, das Passendste.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich möchte Sie besonders bitten, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">keine</hi>
               </seg> meiner Manuscript Namen zu citiren, wenn selbige nicht durch Diagnosen fixirt sind. Dies ist die Regel welche in der beschreibenden Naturgeschichte obwalten sollte. Sie finden auf beigefügtem Blatte alles was ich selbst beschrieb; weitere Namen meiner Pflanzen sollten daher nicht in die Öffentlichkeit gehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leider war mir bisher das Material für critische Vergleiche trotz meiner grossen etwa 2000 fasc. umfassenden Sammlung so beschränkt, dass ich selbst nicht viel unter den Euphorbiaceen arbeitete, auch nicht vollständig die dahin gehörigen literarischen Hülfsmittel besitzend.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach den Erscheinen des prodromus wird die Arbeit in dieser Ordnung eine leichtere u sichere sein. Inzwischen ziehen mich auch vielseitige andere Berufsgeschäfte von Studien ab, die lange ununterbrochene Thätigkeit erfordern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mein Herbarium ausser australischer Pflanzen ist so gross, dass ich Ihnen vielleicht nützen kann, wenn ich auch dieses sende, trotz dessen dass Sie wohl in Kew u Paris alles finden was ich habe. Dasselbe möchte aber kaum von der colossalen Sammlung des Dr Sonder in Hamburg zu sagen sein, die ich Sie unbedingt zu benutzen anrathe. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe meine Verkennen von <name key="Antidesma">Antidesma</name> bemerkt u nun eine neue Art der Gattung vor mir.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Bände der königl Gesellsch. von Victoria würden durch Williams &amp; Norgate zugänglich sein. Wenn aber Hr Prof Dr Candolle officiell an mich schriebe, zweifle ich nicht dass der Rath der Gesellschaft selbige seiner Bibliothek zustellen würde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <name key="Phyllanthus%20albiflorus">Phyllanthus albiflorus</name> ist ein Manuscript Name. Ist wirklich der Genus <name key="Synostemon">Synostemon</name> unhaltbar? Der Unterschied der andern austral. Phyllanthi ist wirklich ein grosser u dazu gesellt sich noch bei <name key="Synostemon">Synostemon</name> eine eigenthümliche Frucht.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihnen für die gütige Auskunft dankend u ebenso für die grossmüthige Weise in welcher Sie die Autorität meiner Pflanzen behandelt</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">bleibe ich Ihr Sie ehrender</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Wenn Ihr Genus <name key="Flueggella">Flueggella</name>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sehr standhaft</hi>
               </seg> ist u noch nicht beschrieben, möchten Sie auf dies vielleicht Roepers Namen anwenden. Diminutive v. nominibus propriis suis kaum rathsam. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Den Namen Phyllanthus Novae Hollandiae würde ich rathen in P. glochidioides zu ändern, da es so viele der Species in Australien giebt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn Ihnen mein Normal Herbarium leihweise zugünstig[?] würde, dann bietet sich Ihnen die Gelegenheit grosse Formenreihen zu sehen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 January 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Doctor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last mail brought me your kind letter of 27 July 1863,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> enclosed with that from the revered Professor Dr [de] Candolle.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> I regret that I did not immediately send you the whole series of the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> from my general collections; this was not done, because I did not previously have the honour to correspond with you, and also because you live so far from the coast, that the loan of such a valuable collection, brought together through many years' work and travels, seemed to me to be too risky without at least prior arrangements for their safety.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have asked Bentham in today's mail,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M did not ask the question in either of the letters M to Bentham, 25 January 1864 (in this edition as 64-01-25e, 64-01-25f); but see M to G. Bentham, 12 December 1863. </p>
               </note> whether he intends to include the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> with the <name key="Calyciflorae">Calyciflorae</name> in our work on the plants of Australia, or whether he wants to hold them over for the <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name>. In the latter case I am prepared to loan to you the original folders of this family from my State Herbarium, if you can provide me with an absolutely safe way of transmitting them, and if you will give me your undertaking to retain the collections, which I shall always more or less miss here, for no longer than one year in Geneva.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M did not send his <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> to Geneva (see note 7 to M to W. Hooker, 24 February <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1864), but he did later send them to Baillon; see M to G. Bentham, January 1865 (in this edition as 65-01-00).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I had really promised them to Baillon, however, since you will work on their treatment for de Candolle's work,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Müller (1866).</p>
               </note> it will be best to make these plants available to you, and Baillon can get later what will come through my hands of this, his favourite family, after the publication of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus</seg>. Baillon's analytical plates really are excellent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Enclosed I send you a list of the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> I have described myself.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">List not found.</p>
               </note> As the 4th volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg> is only half printed and will therefore not be available in the book trade, I am sending you the page on which I described two of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Bertya">Bertya</name>e</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Bertya">Bertya</name> pomaderroides</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">B. rotundifolia</seg>, B63.10.01, p. 34.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Edinburgh Philosophical Journal</seg> of this or last year or in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh</seg> a paper by me is published on Gregory's North-West Australian plants, where I transferred Dampier's plate to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Adriana">Adriana</name>
               </seg>(<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Trachycaryon</seg>) and discoursed at length on this genus, in which I accept only 2 species (one with opposite leaves, and one with alternate leaves).<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's paper appeared in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transaction of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh; see </seg>B63.13.03.</p>
               </note> I have not yet received the volume, but you could easily obtain it through Professor Balfour in Edinburgh.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Should there be other new and indisputable genera among the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name> of my collections (I am convinced there are!), I ask that you permit me to dedicate, together with you, one to the venerable Professor Roeper in Rostock. As Jussieu's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name>
               </seg> can not be separated from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Zygophyllum">Zygophyllum</name>
               </seg>, and Sprengel's is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ricinocarpus</seg>, and Bentham (perhaps unjustly so) has transferred my <name key="Capparidaceae">Capparidaceae</name> genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name>
               </seg> to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name>
               </seg>, it devolves on me to create a new genus for the Professor of my home town,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">i.e. Rostock.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and for this purpose one in the family, in which he did such important work, would be most suitable.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Cf. Roeper (1824).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In particular I want to ask you, not to cite <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">any</hi>
               </seg> of my manuscript names, unless they are established by diagnoses.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also Lucas (1995).</p>
               </note> This rule should prevail in descriptive natural history. On the enclosed sheet you will find everything I myself have described;<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">List not found.</p>
               </note> additional names of my plants should therefore not be placed before the public.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unfortunately my material for critical comparisons, in spite of my large collection comprising about 2000 folders, has until now been so limited, that I have not done much work in the <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name>, nor do I own the complete relevant literature to this end.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Once the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus</seg> has been published, work in this family will be easier and more certain. In the meantime multifarious professional duties also keep me from any studies, that require long uninterrupted work.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My herbarium of extra-Australian plants is so large, that I may be able to be of use to you by sending them as well, although you will probably find everything I have also in Kew or Paris. The same can not be said, however, of the colossal collection of Dr Sonder in Hamburg, which I strongly advise you to use.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have realized my failure to recognise <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Antidesma">Antidesma</name>
               </seg>, and now have a new species of the genus before me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The volumes of the Royal Society of Victoria would be available through Williams &amp; Norgate.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Williams &amp; Norgate were very well-known booksellers in London.</p>
               </note> But if Professor de Candolle were to write to me in an official capacity, I do not doubt that the Council of the Society would forward them to his library.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Phyllanthus%20albiflorus">Phyllanthus albiflorus</name>
               </seg> is a manuscript name. Is the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Synostemon">Synostemon</name>
               </seg> really untenable? It really does differ greatly from the other Australian <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Phyllanthi</seg> and in addition <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Synostemon">Synostemon</name>
               </seg> has a peculiar fruit.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thanking you for your kind information and also for the generous way in which you treated the authorship of my plants, I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">If your genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Flueggella">Flueggella</name>
               </seg> is <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">very constant</hi>
               </seg> and has not yet been described, would you perhaps use Roeper's name for it? A diminutive of his proper name would hardly be advisable.<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to J. Müller, 24 February 1864 (in this edition as 64-02-24b). J. Müller did not describe either <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Flueggella">Flueggella</name>
                     </seg> or a genus based on Roeper’s name (IPNI, accessed 18 June 2020).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would advise to change the name <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Phyllanthus novae-hollandiae</seg> to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">P. glochidioides</seg>, as there are so many Australian species.<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Müller did not change the specific epithet; P. glochidiodes was used in 1911 by Elmer for a plant from the Philippines.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If my general herbarium were to be loaned in your favour, you would have the opportunity to see a large range of forms.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Adriana">Adriana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Antidesma">Antidesma</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Bertya">Bertya</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Calyciflorae">Calyciflorae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Capparidaceae">Capparidaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Euphorbiaceae">Euphorbiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Flueggella">Flueggella</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gynandropsis">Gynandropsis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Phyllanthus%20albiflorus">Phyllanthus albiflorus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Phyllanthus%20glochidioides">Phyllanthus glochidioides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">Phyllanthus novae-hollandiae</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Roepera">Roepera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Synostemon">Synostemon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Zygophyllum">Zygophyllum</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
