<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 January 1864. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ How can I thank you for the multifarious demonstrations of your kindness, of which the last mail brought me another proof in the bea...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-01-25c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Eduard Fenzl Nachlass, Archiv der Universität Wien, Vienna.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>64.01.25c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 January 1864. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ How can I thank you for the multifarious demonstrations of your kindness, of which the last mail brought me another proof in the bea...</title>
               <date when="1864-01-25">1864-01-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1864/64-01-25c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d9d593f3-cf3a-4cd0-8346-da90200383ad">Xanthorrhoea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard Fenzl</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 January 1864. ¶ Dear Professor, ¶  ¶ How can I thank you for the multifarious demonstrations of your kindness, of which the last mail brought me another proof in the bea...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">64.01.25c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Eduard Fenzl</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Eduard Fenzl Nachlass, Archiv der Universität Wien, Vienna.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im bot. Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25 Jan. 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Theuerer Herr Professor</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie soll ich Ihnen für die vielseitigen Beweise Ihrer Güte danken, von welcher mir die letzte Post wiederum einen Beweis brachte in dem schönen Diplom Ihrer Gartenbau Gesellschaft. Wahrlich ich bin Ihnen für Ihre unerschöpfliche Güte vielfach verpflichtet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wahrscheinlich werde ich in diesen Tagen ein wenig Rast haben, um Ihnen eine Kiste mit Sachen von hier zu füllen. Freilich hat eine entsetzliche Fluth, welche den untern Theil meines Gartens verödete, soviel mehr meine nachherige Aufmerksamkeit auf den Garten nöthig gemacht, dass ich noch nicht dazu gekommen bin, eine ordentliche Pflanzensammlung für Sie herzustellen; indessen liegen ein paar kleine Sammlungen bereit, die Ihnen zum Austausch willkommen sein möchten und zu denen ich etwa zwei Dutzend <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Holz-bücher</hi>
               </seg> (wenn ich mich so ausdrücken darf) hinzufügen werde. Diese sind Kästchen aus Holz in gross Octav Bücher darstellend u jeder Kasten ist aus einem andern Holze angefertigt. Man könnte so alle Baumarten der Erde in eine Art Bibliothek sammeln und geographisch oder botanisch ordnen. Der Kasten könnte dazu dienen, Rinde zu bewahren, Harze u andere Producte des Baumes u s w.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leider wird nicht Zeit dazu sein diese Kästen poliren zu lassen, was aussen geschehen sollte, während man innen einfach die gehobelten Flächen sieht. Es fehlt auch der Titel auf dem Rücken der Bücher, der in Buchbinder Manier den Namen u das Land des Baumes geben sollte. Doch dies sind Kleinigkeiten, welche Sie vielleicht, wenn Ihnen überhaupt die Dingerchen lieb sind, nach eigenem Geschmack anfertigen lassen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich werde auch eine gute Menge Harz von <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name> Australis mitsenden und einige Schriften.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Da unsere Samenerndte noch nicht vollendet ist, muss ich die Übersendung einer neuen Quantität der selben bis zur nächsten Sendung verschieben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wo möglich werde ich die Kiste mit dem Great Britain in dieser Woche absenden, wo selbige dann in Liverpool Ende März zu erwarten sein wird. Am Besten ist es dass ich meinen Agenten Messrs Betham &amp; Blackitt, Coxs Quay, die Spedition von London überlasse u vielleicht sind Sie so freundlich diesen Herrn die Ihnen wünschenswertheste Art der Weitersendung anzugeben. Leider weiss ich bei dem gänzlichen Mangel an directer Schiffsverbindung zwischen Australien u Deutschland (obgleich nicht Deutschland u Australien) nicht wie ich die Kiste weiter als bis London befördern kann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die engl. Post kam diesen Monat so verspätet an, dass alle Postgeschäfte sich auf 2 Tage concentriren. Dies muss Entschuldig<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Entschuldigung.</p>
               </note> für mein hastiges Schreiben sein.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Stets dankbar u verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 January 1864.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Professor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How can I thank you for the multifarious demonstrations of your kindness, of which the last mail brought me another proof in the beautiful certificate from your Horticultural Society.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See J. Beer to M, 13 March 1863.</p>
               </note> I am truly indebted over and over again for your inexhaustible benevolence.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall probably have a little leisure in the next few days to fill a case with materials from here for you. Certainly, a terrible flood, that laid waste the lower part of my Garden, has necessitated a lot more of my attention for the Garden afterwards, so that I have not yet found time to put together a proper collection of plants for you; nevertheless, a few small collections are lying in readiness, which you may find welcome for exchanges. I shall add to them about two dozen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">timber books</hi>
               </seg> (if I may call them that). They are boxes of wood in large octavo size, imitating books, and each box is made from a different timber. In this way it would be possible to gather all the trees of the world into a kind of library and arrange them in botanical or geographical order. The boxes could be used to store bark, resin and other products from the tree, etc.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unfortunately time is too short to get the boxes polished, this was to have been done on the outside, while the inside shows just the plain wooden surfaces. The titles for the backs of the books are still lacking as well, which are to give the name and country of origin of the tree in bookbinders' fashion. But these are minor things, and perhaps, if you like the little things at all, you will be able to get this done according to your own taste.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall also enclose a good quantity of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
               </seg> resin and a few publications.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As our seed harvesting has not yet been completed, I shall have to postpone sending new quantities of them until the next transmission.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If possible, I intend to send the case with the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg> during this week. It is expected to reach Liverpool about the end of March. It will be best if I leave the forwarding from London to my agents, Messrs Betham &amp; Blackitt,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">i.e. Blackith.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Cox's Quay, and perhaps you will be so kind as to inform these gentleman of your most preferred mode of further dispatch. With the complete lack of direct shipping connections between Australia and Germany (though not from Germany to Australia) I unfortunately do not know how I could expedite the transmission further than to London.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The English mail arrived so late this month, that all the mailing was concentrated on two days. That must serve as my excuse for my hurried letter. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Always with gratitude and veneration your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
