<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>At this season, when the flora of our colonies is in its native garb, it is particularly desirable to arouse the young Australians to a love of the flowers of their native country. When taught to obse...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1896/96-09-00g-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>96.09.00g</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>At this season, when the flora of our colonies is in its native garb, it is particularly desirable to arouse the young Australians to a love of the flowers of their native country. When taught to obse...</title>
               <date when="1896-09">1896-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1896/96-09-00g-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Church of England Messenger</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">At this season, when the flora of our colonies is in its native garb, it is particularly desirable to arouse the young Australians to a love of the flowers of their native country. When taught to obse...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">96.09.00g</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">To the Church of England Messenger</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Church of England messenger for Victoria and ecclesiastical gazette for the diocese of Melbourne</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 1 October 1896, pp. 131-2 (B96.10.03). It is dated to September as the latest date it could have been sent to have been included in this issue. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The text is introduced by </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">WITH an ardent love for the science which has won for him world wide fame, and a belief that its charm might add greatly to the interest of life in the country both for the families of our settlers and of the country clergy, Baron Sir Ferdinand von Mueller has kindly forwarded to us the following memo, which we hope may encourage many to comply with Charles Kingsley's advice to everyone to "collect something," and so get their eyes open to some of the wonders and beauties of the world they live in.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It will be seen that at whatever cost of labour to himself, the Baron offers to name all specimens of matured native plants that are sent to him : —</seg>
                  </p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At this season, when the flora of our colonies is in its native garb, it is particularly desirable to arouse the young Australians to a love of the flowers of their native country. When taught to observe the varied vegetation around their homes their faculties for observing are sharpened; their mind becomes more expanded; method, while the gatherings proceed, is instilled, and above all, religious feelings are heightened, because divine works in nature will lead to contemplations of godly admiration. If in wandering through natural flower fields plants are secured for close examination, sources of unexpected joy are suddenly opened up, and as collections increase they continually become enhanced in interest. There is an additional charm in these, recreative occupations throughout the interior regions of Australia particularly, as those distant regions are as yet imperfectly searched for plants, so that the enviable chances of discovering absolute floral novelties still exist. The task of collecting is one of the utmost facility, and equally easy in our dry clime is the process of pressing and drying specimens. Even if the species are not new, the material will serve for tracing still further the geographic distribution of many sorts of plants. For all this the amateur will get permanent credit in the works which emanate from such contributions. The </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">minutest</seg>
               <seg style=""> plants should not be missed, as they herald, as well as the most gorgeous, the wisdom of the Divine Creator! It will be among them that the largest number of novel forms remains to be discovered. If duplicate sets are prepared and numbered, the names of the systematic various species will be furnished. The transit of small parcels as samples by post is easy and inexpensive. If at each of the family homes on stations the local plants were collected, not only would an additional and highly intellectual display be gained for the drawingroom, but also original and truly valuable information elicited therefrom.</seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
