<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, ¶ 12 July 1889. ¶ His Royal Highness ¶ Grand Duke Friedrich Franz III ¶ of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c....</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-07-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Signatur: 4630, Grossherzogliches Kabinett III, Mecklenburgisches Landeshauptarchiv, Schwerin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>89.07.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, ¶ 12 July 1889. ¶ His Royal Highness ¶ Grand Duke Friedrich Franz III ¶ of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c....</title>
               <date when="1889-07-12">1889-07-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-07-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Franz III, Grand Duke of Mecklenburg-Schwerin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, ¶ 12 July 1889. ¶ His Royal Highness ¶ Grand Duke Friedrich Franz III ¶ of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c....</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">89.07.12</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">To Friedrich Franz III, Grand Duke of Mecklenburg-Schwerin</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Signatur: 4630, Grossherzogliches Kabinett III, Mecklenburgisches Landeshauptarchiv, Schwerin.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">MS annotated: 'Präs.: Jgdhs. [Präsentiert: Jagdhaus] Gelbensande, 26. </seg>August 1889' [Presented: Gelbensande Hunting Lodge, 26 August 1889].</p>
               </note>Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 12 July 1889.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Sr. Königlichen Hoheit </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">dem Grossherzoge Friedrich Franz III </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">von Mecklenburg-Schwerin &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist meine ehrenvolle Pflicht, Ew. Königlichen Hoheit gnädige Zuschrift vom 24 Mai anzuerkennen, durch welche mir tiefgerührt eben die Kunde wird, dass Ew. Königliche Hoheit in herablassendster Güte sich bewogen fühlten, die grossherzoglich-mecklenburgische Goldmedaille, — "den Künsten und Wissenschaften" gewidmet —, mir zu verleihen. In tiefster Dankbarkeit und sinnungsvollster Würdigung betrachte ich dies Ereignis als einen Glanzpunkt meines Lebens, — um so mehr als dadurch auch Ew. Königlichen Hoheit allergnädigstes Interesse an einen in weitester Ferne weilenden Sohn Ihres schönen Reiches bekundet wird; und es ist wahrhaft für mich erhebend, meine schwachen Bestrebungen, auch hier Glanz auf deutsche Wissenschaft zu werfen, von dem edlen Herrscher meines engeren Vaterlandes, meiner geliebten Heimat, in einer so hervorragenden Weise belohnt und ermuntert zu sehen! Besonders empfindungsvoll gedenke ich dabei auch des hohen Ahnen Ew. Königlichen Hoheit, welcher dies prächtige und bedeutungsvolle Ehrenzeichen stiftete, des Grossherzogs Friedrich Franz I, der meinen nach dem Gefecht bei Seestedt (1813) zurückkehrenden theueren aber früh dahingeschiedenen Vater, damals einem jungen Manne aus dem Kaufmanns Stande, der Übertragung der ersten Controlleur-Stelle in Rostock werth hielt, und ihn so aufs allergnädigste die Gelegenheit gab, sein häussliches Glück zu begründen, und später mir dort die erste Erziehung geben zu lassen und damit den Anstoss zu meiner künftigen Laufbahn. Dann ist es noch für mich eine besondere Erhöhung, dass selbst Ew. Königl. Hoheit in freudiger Huld davon Kenntnis nahmen, dass jene Gesellschaft, in welcher Newton einst präsidirte, mir eine so seltene Auszeichnung zu erkor, — so dass nun auch durch einen mecklenburgischen Namen eine Spange gebildet wird, in der Anteil derer der wenigen Sterblichen, welche während der letzten zwei Jahrhunderte durch die Gold-Medaille der Royal Society in unmittelbaren Contact gebracht sind innerhalb der Geschichte der Wissenschaften!</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Möge es mir gestattet sein an meine Worte unaussprechlichen Dankgefühls die innige Hoffnung zu knüpfen, dass die göttliche Vorsehung Ew. Königliche Hoheit und deren erhabenem Hause alles Erdenglück zu Theil werden lasse weit ins nächste Jahrhundert. So verharre ich als Ew. Königlichen Hoheit ehrerbietigster und unterthänigst Ergebenster</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">12 July 1889.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">His Royal Highness</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Grand Duke Friedrich Franz III</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>It is my honourable duty to acknowledge your Royal Highness's gracious communication of 24 May, by which I received the deeply touching news that Your Royal Highness in condescending graciousness felt inclined to bestow on me the Grand Duke of Mecklenburg's gold medal, dedicated to the 'Arts and Sciences'. In deepest gratitude and genuine appreciation I consider this event to be one of the highlights of my life, all the more so as it testifies to Your Royal Highness's most gracious interest in a son of your beautiful realm who lives in a most distant place. It is truly edifying for me to see my feeble efforts to reflect glory on German science here rewarded and encouraged by the noble monarch of my closer fatherland, my beloved homeland, in such an eminent way. On this occasion I remember also with particular sentiments the exalted forebear of Your Royal Highness, who founded this magnificent and significant medal, Grand Duke Friedrich Franz I, who considered my dear but early deceased father, then a young man of the merchant class returning from the battle of Seestedt (1813),<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sehestedt, Schleswig-Holstein, scene of a battle during the Napoleonic wars.</p>
               </note> worthy to be given the position of First Controller in Rostock,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's father was appointed a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Strandvoigt</seg> or customs officer in Rostock in 1818, responsible for controlling the flow of goods through several of the city's gates.</p>
               </note> thus enabling him to found his domestic happiness and later there to provide me with my first education and with that the starting point for my future career. Furthermore it is especially elevating for me that even Your Royal Highness took note with ready favour, when that Society, over which Newton once presided, bestowed on me such a rare distinction, so that now through a Mecklenburg name a tie is also formed with those select few mortals, who during the last two hundred years were brought into direct contact within the history of the sciences through the gold medal of the Royal Society.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In 1888 the Royal Society of London awarded M one of the two Royal Medals it bestowed each year.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May I be permitted to add to my words of inexpressible gratitude the sincere hope, that Divine Providence may grant Your Royal Highness and Your exalted House all earthly happiness well into the next century. I remain Your Royal Highness's most respectful and most obediently devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
