<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>29/5/89 ¶  ¶ Permit me, noble friend, to place before you a request, which you directly or through your excellent son, ¶  the medical officer, can easily grant. Dr Feoktistov of St Petersburg has made...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-05-29-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS 177, folio 21808, d. 76, op. 1, fond 335, Archives, Academy of Sciences, St Petersburg.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>89.05.29</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>29/5/89 ¶  ¶ Permit me, noble friend, to place before you a request, which you directly or through your excellent son, ¶  the medical officer, can easily grant. Dr Feoktistov of St Petersburg has made...</title>
               <date when="1889-05-29">1889-05-29</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-05-29-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard von Regel</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">29/5/89 ¶  ¶ Permit me, noble friend, to place before you a request, which you directly or through your excellent son, ¶  the medical officer, can easily grant. Dr Feoktistov of St Petersburg has made...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">89.05.29</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Eduard von Regel</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS 177, folio 21808, d. 76, op. 1, fond 335, Archives, Academy of Sciences, St Petersburg.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">29/5/89</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Erlauben Sie mir, edler Freund, Ihnen eine Bitte vorzutragen, die Sie direct oder durch Vermittlung Ihres ausgezeichneten Sohns, des Stabs-Arztes, leicht erfüllen können. Herr Dr Feoktistov in St. Petersburg hat zahlreiche Beobachtungen in letzter Zeit über das Ophidian Gift angestellt, und hat damit gewissermassen den Untersuchungen des Dr Aug. Mueller in Yakandandah weiteren Halt gegeben, da dieser Victorianische Arzt die Wirkung des Schlangen Giftes auf Paralysis der Motor-Nerven zurückführt, nicht auf eine Gewebe-Änderung sondern nur auf dynamische Action, obwohl wir freilich die etwa herbeigeführte Molekular-Alterationen noch nicht kennen. Einfach nach therapeutischen Grundsätzen wendet nun Hr Dr Aug. Mueller das Strychnin als Antidot (durch hypodermisch Injection) an u zwar in den wenigen unlängst beobachteten Fällen mit dem glänzendsten Erfolge. Ich habe diese seine Methode berührt in meiner Eröffnungs Rede der therapeutischen Section des Congresses austral Ärzte Jan. 1889, u auch eine Mittheilung darüber schon vorher an den mir befreundeten Geheimrath Virchow gemacht, welche in seiner Zeitschrift zur Veröffentlichung kam. Da nun Hr Dr Feoktistov in dieser Angelegenheit ein reges Interesse haben muss, möchte ich Sie oder Ihren geehrten Herrn Sohn bitten, die Methode Dr A. Muellers zu besprechen. Ich verfolge diese Sache einfach vom wissenschaftlichen Standpunkt, da mein Namens Genosse mir nicht verwandt ist, möchte aber doch von Ihrem gelehrten Mitbürger gern eine Notiz in dieser Hinsicht haben für die Präsidentur Rede in der austral Association for the Advancement of Science, welche im Jan. 1890 Ihre Versammlung in Melbourne halten wird, gerade wie die Versammlung deutscher Naturforscher u Ärzte alljährlich zusammen kommt, u mich 1846 mit vielen hervor ragenden Gelehrten in Contact brachte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was denkt der Herr Decan der medic. Facultät in Petersburg von meiner Idee, dass ein Rundschreiben an alle Universitäten ergehen solle, uns für den nächsten medicinischen Congress, der 1891 in Sydney gehalten werden soll, je einen Abgeordneten zu senden. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Ich weiss recht wohl, dass Sir Joseph Fayrer in Calcutta in seinen Strychnin Experimenten mit dem Gift der schrecklichen Naja negative Resultate in Bezug auf Strychnin erziehlte, aber er hatte nicht Gelegenheit die Wirkung an Menschen zu prüfen, u die Experimente mit Hunden sind auch gar nicht zahlreich gewesen</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">29/5/89</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Permit me, noble friend, to place before you a request, which you directly or through your excellent son,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">J. A. von Regel.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> the medical officer, can easily grant. Dr Feoktistov of St Petersburg has made numerous observations on snake poison in recent times<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Feoktistow (1889). </seg>No further biographical details found.</p>
               </note> and in so doing has, in a way, given further credence to the investigations of Dr August Mueller in Yackandandah.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Vic. See A. Mueller (1888); see also A. Mueller (1893) and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australian medical journal</seg>, new series, vol. 15 (1893), pp. 472-4.</p>
               </note> This Victorian doctor attributes the effects of snake poison to paralysis of the motor nerves, not to a change in the tissue but solely to dynamic action, though admittedly we are not yet aware of any possible molecular changes that may occur. Based on purely therapeutic principles Dr Aug. Mueller uses strychnine as antidote (by hypodermic injection), and did so in the few most recently observed cases with the most brilliant success. I touched on this method in my opening speech before the therapeutic section of the Congress of Australian doctors in January 1889,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not in the printed version, B89.13.16, but included in the report of his address in the weekly newspaper, the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leader </seg>(Melbourne), 19 January 1889, p. 15.</p>
               </note> and also sent a notice to my friend Privy Councillor Virchow prior to that, which was published in his journal.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Regel: 'nicht gefunden' [not found]. See A. Mueller to M, 14 February 1888 (in this edition as <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>88-02-14a), published in A. Mueller (1888a).</p>
               </note> As Dr Feoktistov evidently must have a keen interest in this matter, I would like to ask you or your learned son to discuss this method of Dr A. Mueller. I pursue this matter solely from a scientific point of view, as my name-sake is not related to me, but I would like to have a notice from your learned compatriot for my next presidential address before the Australasian Association for the Advancement of Science,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B90.13.01. M made no such reference in his presidential address.</p>
               </note> which will hold its meeting in Melbourne in January 1890, just as the congress of German naturalists and doctors meets annually and in 1846 brought me into contact with many eminent scientists.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What does the chairman of the medical faculty in St Petersburg think of my idea that a circular should be addressed to all universities, asking them to send us one delegate each to our next medical congress,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Regel: 'medisch. Academie senden' [send to medical Academy].</p>
               </note> to be held in Sydney in 1891?</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With my respects </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I know very well that Sir Joseph Fayrer in Calcutta obtained negative results with his strychnine experiments with the venom of the terrible Naja,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Indian cobra, a highly venomous snake. See Fayrer (1872) and, for strychnine experiments, pp. 74-6.</p>
               </note> but he did not have the opportunity to test its effects on humans and his experiments on dogs were not at all numerous.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
