<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Stuttgart 12 May 1889. ¶ Most honoured Baron and Friend! ¶  ¶ Today I take the liberty of consulting you concerning the "Statutes of the natural history travel grant endowed by Dr. Ferdinand von Muell...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Krauss</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-05-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>89.05.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Krauss</author>
               <title>Stuttgart 12 May 1889. ¶ Most honoured Baron and Friend! ¶  ¶ Today I take the liberty of consulting you concerning the "Statutes of the natural history travel grant endowed by Dr. Ferdinand von Muell...</title>
               <date when="1889-05-12">1889-05-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-05-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Stuttgart 12 May 1889. ¶ Most honoured Baron and Friend! ¶  ¶ Today I take the liberty of consulting you concerning the "Statutes of the natural history travel grant endowed by Dr. Ferdinand von Muell...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">89.05.12</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Ferdinand von Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Stuttgart 12. Mai 1889.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation: 'Abschrift des Briefes von Krauss an Freiherr Ferd. v. Müller' [Copy of the letter of Krauss to Baron Ferd. von Mueller]. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The file includes this letter and M's reply dated 22 June 1889, a copy of a memo to the Royal Administration, 17 October 1889, by Krauss and a copy of suggested changes to the regulations of the Mueller Foundation, dated 17 October 1889.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrtester Herr Baron u. Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Heute erlaube ich mir wegen das "Statuts für das von Dr Ferd. v. Müller in Melbourne gestiftete naturhistorische Reisestipendium v. 18. Mai 1869" mich an Sie zu wenden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie ich Ihnen schon einigemal schrieb, hat sich seither kein ernstlicher Bewerber um Ihr so reiches u. wohlwollendes Stipendium bewerben, obwohl es pflichtlich jedes Jahr am schwarzer Brett in Tübingen den Studirenden öffentlich bekannt gemacht werden ist u. jetzt rund 800 Mark jährlich beträgt. Dieser Mangel ist wohl hauptsächlich den Umstand zuzuschreiben, dass Studirende der Medicin, auf welche sich das Stipendium beschränkt, nach den neueren Vorschriften über ihren Studiengang ihr Studium nicht gern unterbrechen u. sobald als möglich ihren eignen Herd gründen wollen. Auch existirt eine "ersten medicin. Staatsprüfung" in früheren Sinne nicht mehr.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist desshalb in Erwägung gezogen worden, ob Ihnen nicht der Vorschlag gemacht werden soll, den Kreis der Berechtigten u. das Reiseziel zu erweitern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. Eimer, der gegenw. Prof. d. Zoologie u. Vorstand des zool. Instituts in Tübingen, hat nun in dieser Richtung vor<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geschlagen, das Stipendium "für naturwissenschaftliche Reisen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">uberhaupt</hi>
               </seg>" zu vergeben, wobei er namentlich die zoologische Station in Neapel in Auge hat, um seine Studenten mit Unterstützung dahin schicken zu können. Dieser Vorschlag geht nur aber offenbar zu weit, denn nach Ihrer sehr dankenswerthen Bestimmung wollen Sie durch Ihr Stipendium nicht allein dem Studierenden die Kosten für wissensch. Reisen ausserhalb Europas erleichteren, sondern was wir sehr hoch anschlagen, zugleich auch dem K. Nat. Kab. in St. durch solche Reisen naturhistorische Gegenstände aus ferner Ländern zu seiner Verwahrung zuwenden. Diese würde aber, wenn das Stipendium wie vorauszusetzen hauptsächlich für Neapel Verwendung fände, nicht erreicht, denn das K. N. Kab. hat seither von solchen, welche den würt. Sitz der Station von Neapel benutzen, noch nie eine nennenswerthen Gegenstand erhalten, auch können Mittelmeer-Objekte durch die Station selbst in vortrefflicher Zubereitung käuflich erworben werden. Auch bezüglich die Qualifikation der Bewerber müssen doch bestimmtere Voraussetzungen vorgeschrieben werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Direktion der wissensch. Sammlungen (Präsid. Dr. v. Silcher) hat nun in Uebereinstimmung mit mir Vorschläge zu einer Modification der Bestimmungen des Statuts Ihrer Stiftung entworfen, welche ich Ihnen im Auftrage des K. Kult-ministeriums im Anschlusse mitzutheilen mich beehre mit der Bitte, dieselben an der Hand des Statuts v. 1869 zu prüfen u. mir Ihren Entschluss bald gef. mittheilen zu wollen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach diesen Vorschlägen würde der bisherige Zweck Ihrer Stiftung in der Hauptsache beibehalten u. nur der Kreis der zuzulassenen Bewerber in so weit erweitert, dass auf eine regere Betheiligung an derselben zu hoffen wäre, nutz würde, wenn sich trotzdem kein Bewerber für aussereuropäische Reisen finden sollte, ausnahmsweise</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">u. mit Beschränkung auf ¼ des Jahresertrags das Stipendium auch für Reisen innerhalb Europas vergeben werden können, übrigens unter ausdrücklichen Berücksichtigung der Interessen des Natur. Kabinets.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meinen Brief v. 9. Mai mit der gewünschten Zusammenstellung der bisjetzt bekannten lebenden Arten der Thiere werden Sie nun in Händen haben.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit hochachtungsvollen Grüssen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr dankbar ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F Kr.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgart 12 May 1889.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Most honoured Baron and Friend!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Today I take the liberty of consulting you concerning the "Statutes of the natural history travel grant endowed by Dr. Ferdinand von Mueller in Melbourne of 18 May 1869".<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M69-05-18<seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>
                     <seg style="color: #000000; ">in this edition.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As I have written to you already several times, no serious applicant has applied since then for your so substantial and benevolent grant, although it has dutifully been made known publicly to the students each year on the notice board in Tübingen and now amounts to around 800 Marks annually. This shortcoming is probably mainly to be ascribed to the circumstance that students of medicine, to whom the grant is restricted, do not willingly interrupt their study following the new regulations concerning their course of studies and want to found their own home as soon as possible. Also a "first medical state examination" no longer exists in the previous sense.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We therefore have considered whether we should suggest to you that you enlarge the circle of those entitled and the purpose of travel.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Eimer, the present professor of zoology and chairman of the Zoological Institute in Tübingen, has now suggested that the award be granted "for <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">natural history travel generally</hi>
               </seg>", by which he especially has the Zoological Station in Naples in mind, to be able to send his students there with support. This suggestion, however, obviously goes too far, since according to your very commendable regulation you intended to alleviate the costs for scientific travel outside Europe not only for the student, but what we value very highly, at the same time also to obtain natural history objects from far lands for the Royal Natural History Cabinet in Stuttgart through such journeys for its keeping. However, this would not be achieved, if the grant as presupposed had use mainly for Naples, because the Royal Natural History Cabinet has never received an object worth naming from those who used the Württemburg seat at the Naples Station, also Mediterranean objects can be obtained by purchase through the Station itself in excellent preparation. Also respecting the qualification of the applicants more definite requirements must certainly be prescribed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Director of the Scientific Collections (President Dr von Silcher) has now in agreement with me drafted suggestions for a modification of the statutes of your Foundation,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Marginal annotation: 'Siehe Beil' [See enclosed].</p>
               </note> which I have the honour to communicate to you by instruction of the Royal Cultural Ministry in connection with the request to examine them with the Statutes of 1869 at hand and to kindly inform me of your decision soon. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>According to these suggestions the former purpose of your Foundation would be kept in the main and only the circle of the applicants to be admitted enlarged only so far that it would be hoped for a more lively participation in it, if nevertheless no applicant should be found for travel outside Europe, exceptionally and with restriction to ¼ of the annual proceeds the grant could also be awarded for travel within Europe, however, under the express consideration of the interests of the Natural History Cabinet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will now have in hand my letter of 9 May with the requested compilation of the living species of animals known to date.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found; but see M to F. von Krauss, 24 March 1889 in which M requested an estimate, that he could use in his forthcoming presidential address to the Australasian Association for the Advancement of Science (B90.13.01), of the number of living species of the different classes of animals.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With respectful greetings</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your grateful devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand Krauss</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
