<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir, — ¶  ¶ As in your highly valuable journal of yesterday and this day ¶  my name has been alluded to in reference to the giant trees of Australia, and as some of the remarks might imply that in my ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-05-23-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>89.05.23</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Sir, — ¶  ¶ As in your highly valuable journal of yesterday and this day ¶  my name has been alluded to in reference to the giant trees of Australia, and as some of the remarks might imply that in my ...</title>
               <date when="1889-05-23">1889-05-23</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1889/89-05-23-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eucalyptus amygdalina</term>
               <term>Pinus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of the Argus</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sir, — ¶  ¶ As in your highly valuable journal of yesterday and this day ¶  my name has been alluded to in reference to the giant trees of Australia, and as some of the remarks might imply that in my ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">89.05.23</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Editor of the Argus</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see ‘The Big Trees of Victoria’, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 25 May 1889, p. 12 (B89.05.01).</p>
               </note>Sir, —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As in your highly valuable journal of yesterday and this day<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'Our tall trees shortened' by 'Telemachus', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 22 May 1889, p. 6, and editorial comment, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 23 May 1889, p. 4. See also M to T. Wilson, 23 May 1889 (in this edition as 89-05-23a), and letters to the Editor: W. C Kernot, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 23 May 1889, p. 6; and William Macredie and John W Barker, both <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 28 May 1889, p.10.</p>
               </note> my name has been alluded to in reference to the giant trees of Australia, and as some of the remarks might imply that in my statements I was prone to exaggerations, I now beg, by permission of the Ministerial chief of my department, to offer a few observations on the points under discussion. When some months ago the public announcement appeared that a tree had been found at Neerim<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> estimated to be 520ft. high,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>David Boyle, 'The largest tree in the world', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 18 January 1889, p. 9.</p>
               </note> I promptly disclaimed any personal cognisance of such a tree, adding that I was, from autopsy, only aware of maximum heights approaching 400ft. Furthermore, on various occasions I pointed out that when travelling — often as a solitary wanderer, with only slender resources — through our primeval forests at the early time of Victorian colonisation, no such facilities as heavy survey parties now enjoy were at my command to cut base-lines through the jungle for tree measurements in any of the narrow glens in which only, and then exceptionally, the real giants of our woodlands were occurring. I further have always been particular to mention that in measuring eucalyptus trees <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in situ</seg> a further difficulty is encountered through the irregular growth of their ramifications in contrast to what can thus be done with straight-growing conifers, inasmuch as the last leading portion of an eucalypt would also be quite spreading. In every instance, also, when I published, as occasions arose, any observations on extraordinary heights of trees recorded by others, I have been explicitly careful in giving the names of the observers, without, however, making myself responsible for any over-calculations of theirs. Indeed, I would simply say, with an ancient classic author, "<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Relata refero</seg>."<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Approximately, 'I tell it how I was told' (referring to the disclaimer in Herodotus, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Histories</seg>, book 7, chap. 152). </p>
               </note> Thus the Dandenong tree, which, through public remarks of Mr. Boyle and Mr. Caire, excites just now so much interest, has never been seen by myself. Still it remains a very memorable object, well worthy of a visit, just as the enormously ample base of a hollow eucalypt, transferred to the Centennial Exhibition,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Centennial International Exhibition, Melbourne, 1888-9.</p>
               </note> attracted much attention. The stupendous height of 470ft. assigned to a particular eucalyptus tree (somewhere near the base of the Baw Baw Ranges by Mr. G. W. Robinson<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>G. W. Robinson to M, June 1878 (in this edition as 78-06-00a).</p>
               </note> was probably obtained at mere guess during a hurried exploration tour, but such a statement from him as a professional surveyor would carry with it great authority. Through the kind attention of our renowned fellow-colonist, Mr. A. W. Howitt, I received some time ago information of a tree of E. amygdalina, which grew on the southern slope of the Yarragon Ranges,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> where it was felled, according to Mr. T. Rollo, by a settler, Mr. Dickinson of name,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Not further identified.</p>
               </note> in clearing for his dwelling; the length measurement of this tree was 410ft., but unfortunately it was burnt off. Mr. C. Walter actually measured and re-measured, 1866, a fallen tree, also of E. amygdalina, about two miles north of Fernshaw,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> and found it to be 392ft. long; it was felled by a splitter, Hutchinson by name. But as the very oily foliage of this species, also chiefly used in Mr. Bosisto's extensive distillations, so easily ignites, and as the wood of this kind of tree on damp ground is so readily perishing, we are as a rule deprived of the chances of re-measuring fallen or felled trees, however much we may wish to satisfy scepticism in this respect. But we might just as well discredit the occurrence, certainly very rare, of trunks of todea-ferns over two tons in weight, notwithstanding a specimen heavier still, and weighed at a reliable weighbridge, being placed by me permanently in front of the Exhibition-building. For some other measurements of tree giants of ours reference may be made to the fifth decade of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptography</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eucalyptographia. B80.13.14, Decade 5, in the entry for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. amygdalina</seg> where M states: <seg style="font-style: italic; ">'it represents probably the tallest of all trees of the globe</seg>'.</p>
               </note> where also details of enormous stem diameters and stem circumferences are set forth, and where, likewise, are alluded to data about huge Tasmanian eucalypts, as locally furnished by the Rev. J. F. Ewing, and as rendered further known already through Professor Henfrey's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Botanic Gazette</seg>, as well as through Dr. M. T. Masters's early writings. Sir William Denison secured there also grand results in this respect nearly 40 years ago. When last year the question of "the tallest trees of the world" was anew discussed in connection with the Centennial Exhibition, I suggested specially to the Hon. John Forrest, the Minister of the Lands department of Western Australia, that the most gigantic of the karri trees might be accurately measured by the local surveyors, in confirmation of, or collateral to, the records left by the late Captain Pemberton Walcott, of Karridale,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>WA.</p>
               </note> who spoke of a tree of that species fully 400ft. high, and who related astounding basal widths; while another most trustworthy West Australian settler, Mr. T. Muir, of Lake Muir, found karri stems 300ft. long to the first branch, as reiterated in my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select Plants</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for example, entry for <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. diversicolor</seg>, B88.12.01, p. 149.</p>
               </note> I saw there myself, particularly towards the Gordon River,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>WA.</p>
               </note> karris of marvellous height in dense underwood. Here with us giant trees should be particularly sought for where the eucalyptus forests merge into those of the evergreen beech. What the recently discovered extensive sequoia forests in Southern California may yet reveal of colossal trees remains yet to be ascertained. Professor Brewer noted several species of pinus in the United States, exceptionally, as 300ft. high, but these proud individual trees went likely out of existence. Here I have, with others, repeatedly urged that tracks should be cut to any yet remaining or newly-discovered giant trees for easy approach of visitors to the spot, and that such wonders of the empire of plants should be retained as state property, duly protected by law, the ground to be cleared around, and to be fenced off, so that also the next generations may yet enjoy a view of these living wondrous structures of centuries' growth. As the Australian<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Australasian.</p>
               </note> Association for the Advancement of Science will hold its next annual meeting in Melbourne, let us fain hope that the new veritable giants of the forests at present known may come within convenient reach in time for the meeting — January, 1890, also to the members, their ladies and friends, many from the neighbouring colonies, and, as the railway by that time will be ready to Bright,<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> the association may, perhaps, avail us if extensively of the chance to visit the Australian Alps right up to the glaciers. — I am, &amp;c.,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">FERD. VON MUELLER.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">South Yarra, May 23.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20amygdalina">Eucalyptus amygdalina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus">Pinus</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
