<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>4/5/77 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ I thank you, best of friends, for your friendly letter and the kindly judgement of my small work, ¶  which would number 600 pages instead of 300, had not ignorance and envy upset...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1877/77-05-04-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, folder 210, no. 601,Hasst family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>77.05.04</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>4/5/77 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ I thank you, best of friends, for your friendly letter and the kindly judgement of my small work, ¶  which would number 600 pages instead of 300, had not ignorance and envy upset...</title>
               <date when="1877-05-04">1877-05-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1877/77-05-04-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius von Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">4/5/77 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ I thank you, best of friends, for your friendly letter and the kindly judgement of my small work, ¶  which would number 600 pages instead of 300, had not ignorance and envy upset...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">77.05.04</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius von Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, folder 210, no. 601,Hasst family papers, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">4/5/77</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Privat</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich danke Ihnen, bester Freund, für Ihr freundliches Schreiben u die gütige Beurtheilung meines kleinen Werkes, welches 600 Seiten anstatt 300 zählen würde, hätten Unwissenheit und Neid meine einst berühmte Anstalt nicht überstürzt. Die Ausgabe ist nicht gross, und wird für unsere Colonie nicht einmal ausreichen. Desshalb würde ich noch immer darauf dringen, dass eine Neu-Seeland Ausgabe erscheine, zumal da ich ja kein Honorar dafür verlangte, und man dort den Nachdruck schon vor mehreren Jahren versprach. Freilich wäre das Werk von Hooker erschienen, so würde es als bald dort auch neu erscheinen. Sind denn auch dort Eifersucht u Missgunst dem Deutschen entgegen? </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bester, machen Sie doch noch einen Versuch durch Ihren Vertreter im Parlament, dass das Werkchen dort erscheine. Es wäre zudem ein moralischen Support für mich, u eine Ehre des auch Ihnen theuere deutschen Namens. Sie sprechen von einer Häuslichkeit? Habe ja nicht einmal ein Obdach, und die Gage reicht nicht mal zu um der Werk des Departements vom Versinken zu schützen. Dess ungeachtet ehre ich Ihre u Ihrer Gemahlin Güte mich einzuladen; hätte gern einmal Ihre freie Bergluft geathmet. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin aber schon dadurch an den Ort gebannt, dass ich mich täglich gegen die aus meiner früheren Anstalt ausgestreueten Verläumdungen schützen muss. Von der Gemeinheit und Impudenz mancher Menschen hier können Sie sich gar keinen Begriff machen. So wie meine Anstalt wieder hergestellt ist, werde ich ein edles Wesen in mein Haus u an mein Herz ziehen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Können Sie nicht mit einigen Worten schriftlich an Stawell oder Andere appelliren. Bedenken Sie, wie Ihnen zu Muthe wäre, sähen Sie sich aus dem von Ihnen begründeten Museum verdrängt. Die Mittel sind 4 fach erhöht im Garten, seit ich verstossen wurde, u doch wird nichts mehr vertheilt en gros, u nichts für Wissenschaft gethan. Das Laboratorium, welches die Industrie des Landes berühmt machte, ist niedergerissen!</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">4/5/77</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Private</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I thank you, best of friends, for your friendly letter and the kindly judgement of my small work,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The first edition of M’s <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select plants</seg> (B76.13.03).</p>
               </note> which would number 600 pages instead of 300, had not ignorance and envy upset my once famous institution. The edition is not large and will not even suffice for our Colony. Therefore I would still urge that a New Zealand edition appear, especially since I will certainly claim no honorarium for it and the reprint there was already promised several years ago. Of course were the work by Hooker to appear, it would as soon also appear there new. Are then jealousy and envy against the Germans there as well?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Best of friends, do still make an attempt through your representative in Parliament that the little work appear there. It would moreover be a moral support for me and an honour even to your precious German name. You speak of domestic life? I have indeed not even a lodging, and the salary is not enough to protect the work of the department from sinking. In spite of that, I honour your and your wife's kindness in inviting me; I would like once to have breathed your free mountain air.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But I am already tied to the place, by having to protect myself daily against the slanders circulated from my former institution. You can have no idea at all of the vulgarity and impudence of some people here. But when my institution is re-established again, I shall draw a noble being into my house and to my heart.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Can you not appeal with a few words in writing to Stawell or others. Consider how you would feel, if you saw yourself supplanted from the museum established by you. The means are increased fourfold in the garden since I was turned out, and yet nothing more is distributed in bulk and nothing done for science. The laboratory that made the industry of the country famous is torn down!</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
