<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 1/2/72 ¶ Sir Henry ¶  ¶ The Roy. Geogr Society has always evinced such a vivid interest in the fate of the Explorer Leichhardt, that I deem it my duty to bring under the Societ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-02-01-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Royal Geographical Society, London, Archives, Journal MSS, Australia (Mueller, F von) 1872.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>72.02.01</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 1/2/72 ¶ Sir Henry ¶  ¶ The Roy. Geogr Society has always evinced such a vivid interest in the fate of the Explorer Leichhardt, that I deem it my duty to bring under the Societ...</title>
               <date when="1872-02-01">1872-02-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-02-01-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Henry Rawlinson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 1/2/72 ¶ Sir Henry ¶  ¶ The Roy. Geogr Society has always evinced such a vivid interest in the fate of the Explorer Leichhardt, that I deem it my duty to bring under the Societ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">72.02.01</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Henry Rawlinson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Royal Geographical Society, London, Archives, Journal MSS, Australia (Mueller, F von) 1872.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The MS was marked up for publication, but was not published.</p>
               </note>Melbourne bot. Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">1/2/72</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir Henry</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Roy. Geogr Society has always evinced such a vivid interest in the fate of the Explorer Leichhardt, that I deem it my duty to bring under the Societys notice the results of a new search after that Explorer and his party, which recently has been carried out by Mr Gilmore, Inspector of native police, under the direction of the Queensland Government. From the enclosed copy of Mr Gilmore's journal<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The copy of Gilmore's journal cannot be found at the RGS.</p>
               </note> you will perceive, that he advanced westerly as far as Eyres's Creek, a position not reached [again]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Text obscured by editor's marking-up deletion.</p>
               </note> by any explorer since Capt Sturt discovered it in 1845, unless that locality was visited by Leichhardt's party about 1848 or afterwards. The various remnants of clothing, equipment &amp;c of travellers, found near Eyres' Creek, render it certain, that Dr Leichhardt must have been in the vicinity. The sample of twisted goatskin, herewith forwarded,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The specimen is stored with the MS.</p>
               </note> is a portion of the ornamentation articles, found in the camps of the natives about Eyres Creek, and can only have originated from Leichhardts party. Remnants like these were not found at Wantata,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Wantata waterhole, 100 km NE of Birdsville, Qld.</p>
               </note> where Inspector Gilmore discovered human bones early last year. It requires therefore [just]<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Text obscured by editor's marking-up deletion.</p>
               </note> further confirmation of the assertion of some of the natives, that the brave party of missing explorers succumbed at that spot, since moreover no bones of their many oxen and horses have as yet been found, altho' remnants such as were found by Mr Gilmore might readily have been carried from tribe to tribe as far as the Eyres Creek and beyond it.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Eyre Creek is about 180-200 km NW of Wantata waterhole.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A new clue as regards Leichhardts movements having thus been obtained, I have solicited from the Government of South Australia,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to J. Hart, 15 January 1872.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> to cause enquiries to be made along their transcontinental telegraph line among the natives, whether Leichhardt advanced to that line anywhere, perhaps in 25° S. Should he not have penetrated so far, then further enquiries within Queensland territory is likely to clear early up the mystery of his fate. Strange and enigmatic remains the fact, that trees marked L and apparently indicating positions of Leichhardts were found on the upper parts of the Flinders River.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The upper reaches of the Flinders River, which runs into the Gulf of Carpentaria, lie between Julia Creek and Richmond, Qld., over 600 km NNE of Wantata waterhole.</p>
               </note> A favourable rainy season may have however induced that unfortunate traveller, to quit the more broken and difficult country towards Carpentaria and to steer for Eyres Creek, then known to him from Sturts map, with a view of gaining a flat country for easy travelling, particularly as that line would be the shortest in the contemplated direction of his march.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A small private party is just organised on my suggestion by Mr Ernest Giles, to advance from some central Australian position in the new telegraph line to the west coast, if possible to the sources of the River Murchison during the next cool season, for which enterprise the copious rains since 2 years in the interior augur well.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Giles, in his 1872 expedition, was unable to find a route across what he named the Gibson Desert to the west coast.</p>
               </note> If this object should be accomplished, a passable overland line from the inland stations of Queensland, NS Wales and South Australia to W. Australia will be gained, and thus Cattle and sheep can in masses be brought to pastures near shipping places of the W. coast; besides a line for exploratory observations would be gained in the great Western half of the Australian Continent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is also the intention of Mr Charles Harper to proceed during the next cool season from his station on the DeGray River to the East by Termination Lake;<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Termination Lake does not appear on modern maps, but M was referring to the furthest point inland reached by the Gregory expedition in 1856, now known as Lake Gregory. Harper did not undertake the expedition proposed here.</p>
               </note> and I deem it not improbable, that also the two young Explorers Mess John and Alexander Forrest, will endeavour to advance from Lake Barlee or some other inland position of W. Australia further easterly and try to reach the telegraph line, as this line gives such great facilities now for the continuation of geographic researches in the more Central portions of the Australian Continent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I remain, dear General Rawlinson, your very regardful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M.D.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Lt General, Sir Henry Rawlinson,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">K.C.B., D C L., FRS.,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">President of the Royal Geogr. Soc</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">All these expeditions may give us also further clues of Leichhardts fate.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
