<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot Garden ¶ 7/9/72 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ I regret, dear Dr Hooker, that still I have to write you a letter of lamentations, instead of my telling you, as I confidently thought, that the life with ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-09-07-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Kew correspondence, Australia, Mueller, 1871-81, ff. 59-62.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>72.09.07</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot Garden ¶ 7/9/72 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ I regret, dear Dr Hooker, that still I have to write you a letter of lamentations, instead of my telling you, as I confidently thought, that the life with ...</title>
               <date when="1872-09-07">1872-09-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-09-07-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot Garden ¶ 7/9/72 ¶ Private ¶  ¶ I regret, dear Dr Hooker, that still I have to write you a letter of lamentations, instead of my telling you, as I confidently thought, that the life with ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">72.09.07</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Joseph Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Kew correspondence, Australia, Mueller, 1871-81, ff. 59-62.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">7/9/72</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Private<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Each page of the MS is headed 'Private'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I regret, dear Dr Hooker, that still I have to write you a letter of lamentations, instead of my telling you, as I confidently thought, that the life with its hopes was once more before me. Through the shameless misrepresentations of the Argus Australasian and Leader (against which however I was defended by the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">whole</hi>
               </seg> of the country papers and the remaining portion of the city press,) my position is at present <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">broken up</hi>
               </seg> and my Department <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">completely ruined</hi>
               </seg>. Nearly half the Votes of the whole establishment have been withdrawn, behind my back, without the slightest consultation with me, to provide for excavations and other earth work in the area of the new Gov House, which has also been taken from me, and that very area where on barren rocky ground I succeeded to establish about 20,000 trees, chiefly the Himalaian &amp; Californian pines, and where I have laid out in years when our budget was better many miles of walks, is now to be withdrawn from my control and to be given over to what illogically is called a "landscape Gardener", though this magnificent Park, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">entirely created by me</hi>
               </seg>, is interjacent to the City &amp; the bot Garden proper!<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In accordance with recommendations made by Clement Hodgkinson (C. Hodgkinson to J. Casey, 19 August 1872 [in this edition as M72-08-19]), the responsibilities were divided in three: The Inspector of Forests was to be based at Macedon; the Government House Domain was to be separated off from the Botanic Gardens and placed under the control of a curator; Mueller was to be left with a little over 78 acres (62 acres of which were seen as 'garden ground'), with a vote of £1,990 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Victorian parliamentary debates</seg>, Assembly, 3 September 1872). See also the debate of 8 August, which resulted in a proposed vote of £1,020 being withdrawn, and of 4 September where the recommendation of the committee taken on September 3 was confirmed. See Cohn &amp; Maroske (1996).</p>
               </note> Badly as you have been treated, your treatment is a mere nothing compared to mine! Nevertheless I had no idea, that even a treatment, such as <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> experienced, you, an English man with the splendor of your own and your fathers name, could happen in Britain anno 1872!<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Acton Ayrton, First Commissioner of Works in Gladstone's administration, began a campaign to bring Kew under direct ministerial control, interfering in Hooker's management of the Gardens. Ultimately, after a campaign by Charles Darwin, Charles Lyell and other scientific colleagues, including Sir John Lubbock MP who laid the matter before Parliament, Hooker survived and Ayrton was transferred. See MacLeod (1974).</p>
               </note> — What will an admiring posterity say of the statesman ship of these days. Here the forest Inspector is again to be kept at present out of the forest, as (so <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">they</hi>
               </seg> contend!) the season for work had passed! The Argus applauds all these nonesenses<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Argus ... nonesenses <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is a marginal note with its intended position indicated by an asterisk.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and that in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">our</hi>
               </seg> clime of evergreen vegetation! I could not succeed, that the new estimates, laid before Parliament last week, were only withdrawn for a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">single day</hi>
               </seg>, in order that I might point out their <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ruinous</hi>
               </seg> effect on my Department, they being constructed by a hostile outsider, who knows nothing of my Department.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The estimates were prepared by Clement Hodgkinson.</p>
               </note> This was refused by the Ministry in Parliament, who even construed the request as an act on <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">insubordination</hi>
               </seg> of mine,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Casey, 4 September 1872, note 3.</p>
               </note> and yet the spirit of the Civil Service Regulation was not in the slightest observed towards myself. My greatest opponent in Parliament is a person, whom you see figured in the left hand corner of the byefollowing picture and who is particularly odious to Mess Wilson &amp; M’Kinnon.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See notes 16 and 18; image at note 19.</p>
               </note> That particular person is also the Head of the small clique of Conspirators, who for years worked on my ruin, and who have one or two powerful members as Writers on Mess Wilson &amp; M’Kinnons papers. I really think that Charles Darwin might extend his protection also to me, in as much as he is a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">near neighbour</hi>
               </seg> of Edw. Wilson.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Edward Wilson settled at Hayes, in Kent, in 1868 and died there in 1878. Hayes is about 6 km NNW of Downe, Darwin's village.</p>
               </note> As it is here, I have now less then <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">two thousand £</hi>
               </seg> for my whole Department (irrespective of my own starvation Salary, which is only ½ or ⅓ of that of most of my compeers and ruinously taxed both socially &amp; scientifically. Out of these £2000 I can no longer in this <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">expensive</hi>
               </seg> country support my laboratory, Museum, Library Branch, supply branch of Nursery &amp;c Indeed I shall have to close the forcing pits and perhaps even the Conservatories! My only clerk is struck off; so I have to write every account myself, copy every letter, nay — as my messenger can also no longer be paid I shall have to bring &amp; fetch myself my letters from town, clear the consignments; and so far as I can see the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">only</hi>
               </seg> horse &amp; cart, to which the Department through M'Cullock's enlightened wisdom was reduced since 3 years<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The reference is to James McCulloch's first period as Victorian Premier, from July 1868 to September 1869.</p>
               </note> has also to be given up. So you see, my generous &amp; dear friend, what can happen to a FRS in her Britannic Majesty's Colony Victoria! As yet no reaction has set in. If I agitate against these measures I shall be persecuted under the Civil Service Regulations</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Argus and Australasian rejoyce in their miserable triumph, altho' even the Leader feels ashamed of itself. Through the "dedication" my main enemy on the Leader has been there dismissed last week<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">my main enemy ... last week <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is a marginal note in the central margin f. 61, with the intended position indicated by an asterisk in the text</seg>.<seg style="font-style: italic; "> A second marginal note by M</seg>: Through the "dedication", <seg style="font-style: italic; ">appears in the right margin of f. 61 opposite this paragraph</seg>. See note 16 below.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Proprietors of the A &amp; A stand aloof in Europe. My appeals to them go for nothing As long as they can draw (I suppose) £12000 a year out of their papers, to enjoy themselves in Europe, they seem not to care what becomes of either friend or foe, of either the country or anything else. The idea is monstrous, that all three proprietors<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Edward Wilson, Lauchlan MacKinnon, Alan Spowers.</p>
               </note> should stay away for years &amp; leave the influence of their crushing papers to underlings.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Please use this information cautiously, for you have no idea, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">what</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>people <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">here</hi>
               </seg> are capable of! It is also possible that I may still succeed in turning affairs; but as it is, I am ruined at present. In the small colony of S. Australia even is given for the Adelaide Garden £3,300 with lower wages &amp; longer work hours, and without any scientific branches, while the area is only 40 acres! No distribution of plants there<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No distribution of plants there <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is a marginal note with its intended position indicated by an asterisk.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> — Our friend Moore<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Charles Moore, Director of the Botanic Garden, Sydney.</p>
               </note> has only 80 acres, largely under grass, no conservatory, no laboratory, no real Museum, no extensive distribution of plants to churches, cemeteries, schools, hospitals &amp;c yet he has annually £8000. How can I therefore in this more expensive colony maintain my institution for £2000 — I have long since <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sold off</hi>
               </seg> all private property (land bought as far back as 1847, town allotments (81 acres, in one township alone<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The land in Mount Gambier purchased by M in 1854? See Transfer of Title, 11 October 1865 (in this edition as 65-10-11b).</p>
               </note>) to defray the literary and social expenses of my department largely myself. I have <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>
               </seg> left except my position and I am to be robbed of that also now by a landscape Gardener, who is even to get the few hundred £ intended for enlarging my Museum, to which is not added in space for 12 years and where the collections are stand[ing] nailed down under the ceilings &amp; under the tables largely inaccessible, because these few hundred £ are to be devoted also to make new roads for the new Gov. House &amp;c. Yet in the face of this the framer of the estimates succeeded to get £6500 — (six thousand five hundred £) for excavating one single lagoon near the city! merely for a little pleasure boating!<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Albert Park Lagoon became a popular place in the early 1870s for sailing, but in summer became too shallow to use. In 1872 the government considered a proposal to dredge the lagoon and pump fresh water to it from the Yarra. The proposal was eventually struck off the Estimates in March 1873. See Lamb (1996).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The hostility to me arises largely because I am a foreigner! — Thank God! that I remained <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">unmarried</hi>
               </seg> and that I can go to ruin in good conscience. Had I been married I could not have done all my work here, with the miserable votes at my disposal, though the Argus calls them "fabulous", never sufficient even in years when sterling men like David Moore, Haines, Nicholson, OShanassy had the sway. The Ministry is misled and may yet retrace its steps towards me, but courts the support of the Argus As soon as the mail business is done, I will see what further measures I can adopt to protect myself, altho' in the [3] years struggle against the most vulgar intrusion, my very life is almost worried out of me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Masonry plaid a powerful part against me; the person in the Corner of the background of the picture being actually since years the Colonial <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Grand Master</hi>
               </seg>!! of the Irish Section.<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See image at note 19. J. T. Smith was the founding Provincial Grand Master Victoria under the Irish constitution, holding office until his death in 1879 (Lamonby (1906), p. 99). Smith spoke very disparagingly of M in the budget debates on the vote for the Botanic Gardens, describing him as 'behaving tyrannically to his subordinates' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Victorian Parliamentary Debates</seg>, vol 13, p. 981, 1871); and as having been permitted to 'receive pay here in order that he might gather honours elsewhere' (vol. 14, p. 1213, 1872).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Why do I trouble <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> with all this? Because I do not wish to stand before a honored colleague like you as the worthless individual, which the Argus &amp; Australasian (or rather 2 or 3 men thereon) make me to appear; and I wish also to show that if I sink to almost nothing for years as a scientific worker, it is because my time has been &amp; is still trifled away in mere defense of the integrity of my Department &amp; the honor of my professional &amp; administrative position.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Major Beddome has been here for a month, to recruit his health, but under the agonies of my troubles I could show him little attention and thus we could not go to the Giant Eucalypts.<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Beddome reported that he had spent many happy hours botanizing with M; see R. Beddome to J. Hooker, 21 November 1872, RBG Kew, Directors' Correspondence 157/36-37.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I never possessed a single Mining share or speculated in any way. I never yet in my life went to a single race or made a single bet — I worked Sun days &amp; Holidays included regularly 14 hours a day &amp; often much longer. So I could not have done more and have not even a family brought up. So little did I take advantage of the Votes of the Department, that in the 20 years during which Parliament voted me quarters I not even built a single private room!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Always your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Punch</hi>
               </seg>, September 1872<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Written on a page from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Melbourne</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Punch,</seg> RBG Kew, Miscellaneous reports, Melbourne, Mueller, 1853-96, p.139. (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Punch</seg> (Melbourne), September 5, 1872, p. 77.) Image at note 19.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dedicated to the person, who was the leading spirit of the Board of Enquiry concerning the Melb bot Garden. I understand he has now been dismissed from the 'Leader'. One or two of the persons of Mr Wilsons paper were cooperating with him against me.<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's MS paragraph is a sheet pinned to the page from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Melbourne Punch </seg>(5 September 1872, p. 77): 72-09-07_image01.jpg The text <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Punch</seg> printed below the caption is "The house which the prisoner rented, and which was used for the accommodation of the lowest class of women of the town, belongs to the Hon Henry Miller, who received £52 a year for the premises. A memorandum of agreement between Bonar (the negro) as a tenant for twelve months, and the Hon Henry Miller, was produced." Argus, August 31.' <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The quotation is from a report of the trial of Robart Bonar, convicted of keeping a house of ill fame, p. 5.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The person depicted in the background is J. T. Smith, MLA, a wealthy publican who was frequently attacked in print by MacKinnon and Wilson, and whom MacKinnon and others accused of making his money 'from sources even less pure than the sale of intoxicating liquors' [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">ADB</seg>]. See also note 16 above.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The central figure in the picture, Henry 'Money' Miller, was a wealthy property owner recently retired from politics. However, the ‘leading light’ to whom M refers was someone else, namely Josiah Mitchell; see M to J. Hooker, 31 January 1872. Mitchell chaired the Board of Enquiry and wrote for the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leader</seg>. Mitchell continued, however, to write for the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leader</seg> until 1873; see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>, 26 August 1881, p. 3. Mitchell and Smith were committee colleagues in a number of agricultural and horticultural organizations at this time.</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
