<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[1872. ¶ Most honoured Baron, ¶  ¶ I must not delay any longer to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of 25 January, 15 February, ¶  and 26 March, ¶  as well as of the various shipping transmissio...</title>
            <author>Jacob Agardh</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-07-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>72.07.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Jacob Agardh</author>
               <title>[1872. ¶ Most honoured Baron, ¶  ¶ I must not delay any longer to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of 25 January, 15 February, ¶  and 26 March, ¶  as well as of the various shipping transmissio...</title>
               <date when="1872-07">1872-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-07-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Sargassum peronii</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d9d593f3-cf3a-4cd0-8346-da90200383ad">Xanthorrhoea</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/26f088e5-c0e9-44d3-9684-57815342b778">Dicksonia</term>
               <term>Kingia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d50ddb57-69c1-4be7-b4fe-f1d8a1594f98">Todea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[1872. ¶ Most honoured Baron, ¶  ¶ I must not delay any longer to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of 25 January, 15 February, ¶  and 26 March, ¶  as well as of the various shipping transmissio...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">72.07.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Jacob Agardh</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. MS is a draft copy lacking a valediction. As mail between Sweden and Australia seemed to take around three months, and Agardh acknowledges M's letter of 26 March 1872 (in this edition as 72-03-26a), this letter was probably written about July 1872.</p>
               </note>1872</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrtester Herr Baron!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich darf es nicht länger unterlassen den Empfang Ihrer Schreiben von 25/1 15/2 26/3 so wie verschied. port-Versendungen mit Algen anzuerkennen, und Sie herzlichst zu danken für Ihre Bemühungen mich mit die Algen Neu Hollands bekannt zu machen. Nach einer 7-monathlichen aufenthalt in Stockholm bin ich jetzt wieder in Lund und eifrigst mit untersuchung der Verschiedenen Sendungen beschäftigt. In der grossen Kiste, welche ich vor meiner Abreise nur geöffnet hatte um mich zu überzeugen dass die Algen nicht irgend eine augenblichliche preparirung erforderten, habe ich jetzt mehrere pakete, die darin tiefer eingelegt waren, vorgefunden mit Schriften und Algen für welche ich alle Ihnen mich meinen besten Dank sage. Besonders enthielt das paket mit Algen von Edgecombe bay von Kilner gesammelt mehrere sehr interessante Sargassum formen, unter welchen die eine mir neu vorkommt (ich habe Sie noch nicht genau untersucht), die andere Sarg. Peronii eine der grossen Seltenheiten der Sammlungen bis jetzt war. Auch die Algen von Miss Goodwin sind mir jetzt erst zu gesicht gekommen; es sind auch darunter einige vielleicht neue formen. Die Algen aus Queenscliff habe ich nur so oberflächlich trocken klassificirt um das eine Genus nach dem andern vorzunehmen. Wahrscheinlich werde ich wenig neues darunter finden, aber es mag wohl seyn, dass irgend eine darunter fructificirend vorkäme, welche früher nicht mit Frucht gesehen wäre. — Auch von R. Gunn habe ich eine reiche Samlung von Tasmanischen Algen erhalten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bey meiner Rückkehr in Lund habe ich die <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name> Stämme alle in schönster entwicklung vorgefunden, einige mit 6 Fuss lange wedeln! Ich habe demnach 2 davon dem Prof. Lange in Kopenhagen anerbieten können, aber der Bot. Garten hat schon, durch Ihre Güte, 2 Ex. die jetzt in Entwicklung sind. Der Garten Verein in Stockholm, das einzige Institut dort, wo ein exemplar untergebracht werden kan, gewünscht ein ex. zu übernehmen. Nach Christiania und Upsala oder Gothenburg werde ich wahrscheinlich ein paar andere abgeben lassen. — Seitdem ich Ihnen letztens schrieb sind mir 3 <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">neue</hi>
               </seg> Farnbäume aus Neu Zeeland durch Ihre agenten in London zugekommen. 2 davon, die während der langen Reise Vollig ausgetrocknet schienen, werden wohl kaum angehen; das dritte exemplar (3 Fuss hoher Stamm mit ansitzende Wedelbasen die auswendig wohl mit Stackeln besetzt waren) steht jetzt schon mit schönen blättern. — Wir zweifeln ob es nicht richtig seyn wird die Stämme während der ganzen Jahres immerfort zu bewässern, oder ob es nicht richtiger seyn wird Sie während einige monate trocken zu halten um Ihnen eine ruhezeit zu gestatten. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sollten Stämme von der <name key="Kingia">Kingia</name>, <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name> etc. nicht ebenso wie die Farn Stämme behandelt werden können? — Wenn Sie gelegenheit finden wie Ihre Briefe voraussetzen scheinen uns eine "riesige <name key="Todea">Todea</name>" zu senden, so mögte ich mir auch ausbitten wenn Sie davon Vorrath haben museum exemplare (Stämme Fruchten etc) von solchen australischen formen die eigene Familien ausmachen oder weit mehr von gewohnten Sachen abweichend vorkommen die Gen. <name key="Kingia">Kingia</name>, <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name> etc.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich sende Ihnen heute ein kleines paket über Systematik der Florideen; und weil in derselb. verschiedenes über australische arten vorkomt, habe ich mich erlaubt einige dubl. ex. für Vertheilen anzuschliessen. Sobald ich mit bestimmen der gesandten austr. Algen fertig bin, werde ich Ihnen die Verlangten exemplare für Ihr Museum übersenden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">[1872.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Most honoured Baron,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I must not delay any longer to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of 25 January, 15 February,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">M to J. </seg>Agardh, 15 February 1872 (in<seg style=""> this edition as 72-02-15a).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and 26 March,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">M to J. </seg>Agardh,26 March 1872 (in this edition as 72-03-26a).</p>
               </note> as well as of the various shipping transmissions with algae, and to thank you sincerely for your efforts to familiarize me with the algae of New Holland. After a stay of seven months in Stockholm I have now returned to Lund and am busily occupied with the examination of the various transmissions. In the large case<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Agardh, 15 July (in this edition as 71-07-15a) and M to J. Agardh, 25 July 1871 (in this edition as <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>71-07-25a).</p>
               </note> which, prior to my departure, I had <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>opened only to assure myself that the algae did not require some sort of immediate attention, I have now found several packets, which had been placed deeper down in the case, containing publications and algae; for all of these I express my sincere gratitude. In particular the parcel of algae from Edgecombe Bay, collected by Kilner, contained several very interesting forms of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sargassum</seg>, one of these seems new to me (I have not yet examined them in detail), another, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Sargassum%20peronii">Sargassum peronii</name>
               </seg>, is one of the great rarities among the collections so far. I have also only just discovered the algae from Miss Goodwin, and there may be some new forms among these. I have only sorted the algae from Queenscliff superficially in dry state, so as to work through them genus by genus. I shall probably find little that is new among them, but it is possible that some of them may be fruiting, of which I have not previously seen any fruiting specimens. — I have also received a rich collection of Tasmanian algae from R. Gunn.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Agardh, 23 April 1870.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On my return to Lund I have found all the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>
               </seg> trunks<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M shipped seven <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name> antarctica</seg> trunks to Agardh in July 1871 by <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Anglesey</seg>.</p>
               </note> growing beautifully, some with 6 feet long fronds! Accordingly, I have been able to offer two of them to Professor Lange in Copenhagen, but the Botanic Garden there, through your generosity, already has two specimens growing. The Horticultural Society in Stockholm is the only institute there that could accommodate a specimen, and they wish to take one. I shall probably pass some on to Christiania<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Oslo.</p>
               </note> and Uppsala or Göteborg. — Since I last wrote to you, three <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">further</hi>
               </seg> treeferns from New Zealand have been furnished to me through your London agents. Two of them, which seem to have dried out completely during the long voyage, are very unlikely to grow; the third specimen (a trunk 3 feet tall, with adhering leaf bases that were probably covered with thorns on the outside)<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Agardh, 3 December 1871 (in this edition as <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>71-12-03a).</p>
               </note> is already growing beautiful fronds. — We wonder, if it is correct to water the trunks continuously the whole year through, or whether it would not be better to keep them dry for some months to give them a rest period.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Would it not be possible to treat trunks of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Kingia">Kingia</name>, <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
               </seg> etc. in the same way as treeferns? — Should you find the opportunity to send us a 'giant <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
               </seg>', an intention your letters seem to indicate, may I ask you, if you have them available, to also send us museum specimens (trunks, fruit, etc.) of such Australian plants as form their own families or differ greatly from the usual forms, such as the genera <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Kingia">Kingia</name>, <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
               </seg>, etc.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am sending you today a small packet with a publication on the systematics of the Florideae,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Agardh (1872).</p>
               </note> because in it several Australian species are mentioned, and I have taken the liberty to enclose some copies for distribution. As soon as I have completed the identification of the Australian algae you sent me, I shall return to you the requested specimens for your museum.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicksonia">Dicksonia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Kingia">Kingia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sargassum%20peronii">Sargassum peronii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
