<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden ¶ 23/12/72 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication, dated 20th Decbr, and crave permission in reply to draw respectfully your kind attenti...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-12-23-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>E72/27689, unit 750, VPRS 44/P inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>72.12.23</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden ¶ 23/12/72 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication, dated 20th Decbr, and crave permission in reply to draw respectfully your kind attenti...</title>
               <date when="1872-12-23">1872-12-23</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1872/72-12-23-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Casey</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden ¶ 23/12/72 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication, dated 20th Decbr, and crave permission in reply to draw respectfully your kind attenti...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">72.12.23</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Casey</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">E72/27689, unit 750, VPRS 44/P inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS written by Georg Luehmann and signed by M.</p>
               </note>Melbourne Botanic Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">23/12/72</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication, dated 20th Decbr, and crave permission in reply to draw respectfully your kind attention to the following facts:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1, That a division of votes according to mere acreage would be an impossibility in a department, where the expenditure on a single acre with its museum under proper and efficient working would be perhaps as great as for 100 acres of mere grassland, planted already with trees, and simply traversed by walks. Similar would be the comparison of a multitude of acres of mere parkland with single acres, on which conservatories stand, or on which forcing pits are placed, or on which nurseries are established, or on which scientific, literary work and office correspondence is transacted. Indeed, as I had the honor to point out in former communications, provision was made only on my own estimates during the last three years for the wages of one gardener in the extensive Govt. House Reserve after the great departmental reduction in 1870.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2, I may be permitted respectfully to draw your favorable attention to the circumstance, that the Honorable the Treasurer during the parliamentary discussions on the votes of the Botanic Garden expressed cheerfully the willingness of the Government to increase the votes left under my control, should it be found that the sums at the disposal of the Director (who was not consulted on the subject of the redistribution of the votes) would prove insufficient for the continuation of the service under his administration. Thus I hope, honorable Sir, that you will not leave me in the helpless state, in which I am placed at present.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3, May I ask to bring under your kind consideration, that the final redistribution of the votes and action thereon took place after nearly 4 months of the financial year had passed already. While I expected to have at least £100 per month for wages for the last eight months of the financial year (at the rate of £1200.- .- for the whole year) I have only £90 left at my disposal.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4, As regards the supply of stores, tools, timber, forage, coals &amp;c I respectfully submit, that the vote was previously reduced already to the lowest minimum for the efficient working of the Department; the Garden itself, as easily to be understood, being only a portion of an integral phytologic institution, just as the department of Kew in England has, irrespective of its scientific and ornamental garden, also its branches for literary publication, correspondence, information, researches, supply, phytographic museum collections, industrial vegetable articles, all closely connected and inseparable, if the welfare of departments of this kind is the object.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Only a very small sum was estimated for stores, tools &amp;c or use in the reserves, while now half the vote is withdrawn for them, while no Yan Yean water is available, and while water must be extensively carted to many valuable plants through insufficiency of engine supply, or carried by hand to the many thousands of valuable and important plants during the next three summer months. The supplies of stores, drawn during the first 6 months of the financial year, are within the limits of my original estimates, the final alteration of the votes having only taken place at the end of October; and it can be shown at any time that not a single article was ordered, which was not absolutely necessary.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5, Assuredly some misapprehensions must exist in reference to the nature of the service of the employees whom I retained here, as I have only <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one clerk</hi>
               </seg> in the whole department, and never had any more; and I may add that no Botanic Garden in the whole world is without one or even several clerks of special requisite knowledge. Although I have pointed this out before, I respectfully again submit the names and occupation of those people whom I kept under my control:<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Not all of the staff named have been identified. Those for whom details have been found have entries in the Biographical Register.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. G. Lühmann, Clerk and Accountant &amp;c</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>L. Rummel, Operator in Laboratory</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Neate, Messenger for town work, Storekeeper &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. Schlipalius, in charge of seeds-department &amp;c</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. Sullivan, Carter</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>S. Cottrell, Artizan, also in charge of gates and of birds &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. Richards, Museum Assistant.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>D. Coller, Gardener in charge of Forcing Pits, large Conservatory &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>G. Schneider, Gardener in charge of Nurseries, Victoria house, small Conservatory &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thos. Morrison, Gardener for outdoor-work only.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. Pitcher, Youth for general garden work.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>E. Soues, Enginedriver, (half time).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6, The sum of £1557.- for the whole financial year for wages, left at my disposal according to your communication, instead of £1618.- .-, as expected by me, has thrown me anew out of my calculation, because about £836.- were expended already for wages from July till the end of October, while the Forest Inspector had still control over all the outdoor men; and I now hope that you will kindly grant me at least an allowance of £100.- .- a month henceforth for wages, so as to make the reductions not in any way retrospective.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7, I find myself now in the position of being without forage for the only carthorse of the Garden (in the Sydney Garden and elsewhere several horses are kept) for the next six months, without coals for the Victoria house and forcing pits, where a constant temperature of about 80° F. must be maintained, without coals for the steamengine, without paper or pasteboards for the new museum collections, without material for technologic and phytochemic laboratory researches, without pots for the nurseries, without glass, tiles, timber, tallies &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>8, May I be permitted again to add that I continue unable to maintain a botanic collector in the field.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>9, To do my utmost for savingly carrying on the service with the utterly inadequate means left at my command, I ventured to ask that a transfer of £74.10/— might be made from the item of awards to garden boys to the Wages vote, so that the third gardener (left of ten) might be retained during the next six months for the extensive ground under spade culture, such transfers being of frequent occurrence, as the contingencies of a department can never be foreseen for many months even under ordinary circumstances. Moreover in this case, apparently by a clerical error outside of my office, the award vote was made £74.10/ larger than fixed in my own estimate which was £91.- .- for the whole area: if such is to be equally divided then £45:10/- instead of £120.- .- will be required; and under such circumstances I trust that this application will yet be open for your kind reconsideration, after the full explanation now afforded, and I may venture to say on this point, that during the twenty years, whilst I was the professional head of the Department here, none of my many successive honorable chiefs have ever refused any of the propositions of transfers made by me, so that a discontinuation of these favors would be to me not without humiliation and pain.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>10, To show you, Sir, that I have made the most strenuous efforts to carry on the service of my Department without unnecessary calls on the Government for monetary aid, I had since many weeks most of the messenger's work transacted through my private valet, (ever paid out of my private means), in order that the messenger could help to clear away weeds &amp;c. In a like manner I have since many weeks withdrawn the trained mechanical amanuensis of the museum to do garden work, a measure, which as a matter of course, brings the important museum work for the time to an utter standstill. The seedsman has likewise been employed since October almost exclusively in ordinary gardening, all with a view of doing the utmost of my falling in with the views of the Government; but all this is not sufficient to keep the Garden in a creditable state, although every fair and just visitor during the last two months has expressed himself highly pleased with the vast horticultural improvement latterly effected here, even under such disadvantages.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Direct. botan. Garden.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's letter was referred to the Secretary of Agriculture, A. Wallis on 10 January 1873 and returned to the Lands Department on 18 June 1873.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Honorable J. J. Casey</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Commissioner of Lands &amp; Survey.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
