<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Botanic Gardens ¶ Rockhampton ¶ My Dear Baron ¶  ¶ With reference to the Livistona's I dont think there is anything but one species indegenous to this district. The description given in the Flora Aust...</title>
            <author>James Edgar</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/undated/Edgar00-00-00.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M94, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>00.00.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>James Edgar</author>
               <title>Botanic Gardens ¶ Rockhampton ¶ My Dear Baron ¶  ¶ With reference to the Livistona's I dont think there is anything but one species indegenous to this district. The description given in the Flora Aust...</title>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/undated/Edgar00-00-00.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Botanic Gardens ¶ Rockhampton ¶ My Dear Baron ¶  ¶ With reference to the Livistona's I dont think there is anything but one species indegenous to this district. The description given in the Flora Aust...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">00.00.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From James Edgar</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RB MSS M94, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; text-transform: uppercase; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; font-weight: bold; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There are two Edgar letters - 86.09.23 and 92.07.05.</p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS found in a parcel of specimens of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Calamus</seg>. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">and marked: 'Correspondence re Palms forwarded for Dr Beccari's perusal. Please return when use is completed. A. J. Ewart 3/3/[19]09' - delete the last part?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Botanic Gardens</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="text-transform: uppercase; ">Rockhampton</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Qld. Address is stamped onto MS.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My Dear Baron</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With reference to the Livistona's I dont think there is anything but one species indegenous to this district. The description given in the Flora Australiensis is a very good one. Only in our largest cultivated plant the leaves are 6 ft in diameter. Some years ago I came across some very dwarf plants of Livistona and was under the impression that they must be a different species to the tall one found in the moist gorges in the Bersaken Ranges.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">the Bersaken Ranges </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; font-weight: bold; ">is underlined in pencil presumably by Ewart.</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>- delete?</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; font-weight: bold; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gazetteer shows Berserker Range, Qld.</p>
               </note> The seed could be found round or on any of the plants. some<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic? NOTE: he makes various errors which I have not marked with 'sic'.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> time after a selector informed me that on some sandy ridges near his place there were some very small cabbage tree palms. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I went and had a look at them they certainly were very small but further examination in moist rich soil soil<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic - repeated. he has inserted some and presumably the second 'soil' was meant to be 'some' and he forget to delete one 'soil'.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> some distance away a tree was found with a clear stem of 40 ft the birds had carried the seeds to the sandy country and during some excessively wet season some of them had germinated and had managed to exist for a number of years. This same thing has been done in our gardens excepting that I put down the seed instead of the birds, some seeds planted on the edge of a small gully eighteen years ago have produced plants having a crown of leaves about three feet hight without any appearance of a stem. Plants raised in pot from the same parcel of seed and planted out in well prepared ground have no[w] clear stems from 5 to 6 ft and and<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic - repeated.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> a large crown of leaves. There is a cultivated plant here of L Australis which came here from Sydney soon after the gardens were started which has a very different appearance. The plate of L Australis in Nicholsons Dictionary of Gardening is an exact representation of our plant and no doubt the photo had been taken from a plant in Kew Gardens which had been collected some where in New South Wales. When in Sydney a few months ago I went a<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">`<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">sic - word left out.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> trip to Kiama and we passed by a number of tall plants of Livistona but to me they appeared to be more slender stemmed and the crown foliage much smaller than with us. I am of opinion that there is only one species of Livistona on the Eastern coast and that there are several varieties produced by climatic influence. For instance there is a plant here which was kept in a pot five or six years. And out of curiosity about nine years ago I had it planted in the dryest parts of our grounds. The soil was not prepared in any way except digging a small hole in which to plant it and keeping it watered until it was established. that plant has grown very little larger since and from the ground to the tip of the longest leaf would not measure 2 ft yet the parent plant had a clear stem of at at least 60 ft. but it was growing in a moist mountain gorge any one meeting in the bush for the first time a dwarf plant such as I described and some time finding a clump of tall trees from 40 to 80 ft high would naturally take them for different species. I would not like to give an idea of the number of year required for providing my poor little plant with a 10 ft stem.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first seeds you sent me of M maria you mentioned as having been collected by the German Missionaries in Central Australia and that they required a very moist soil to grow in A second pkt came some time after some of each germinated and when strong enough for planting out were planted in the same piece of ground (a very wet place) and are growing well. you did not mention where the second pkt had been collected. there appears to be no difference in them except that the first ones being older are larger plants</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is a very marked difference between them and Australis very much more robust and upright in the foliage which is of a very rich bronzy colour. This may alter as the plant grow larger at present they are very interesting</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Many of the introduced palms will become naturalised in this district in a few years notably The Sabals, Phoenis &amp; Caryota sobilifere the birds carry away the fruit in quantities[.]<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I have found young plants some considerable distance away from the garden already</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">J S Edgar</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
