<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 28/9/91. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Under Secretary ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ In reply to your telegram, received this evening, ¶  I have the honor to report for the information of the hon. the Premier's Depa...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-09-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>P91/2930, unit 273, VPRS 1163/P1 inward Correrspondence, VA 672 Premier's Office, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>91.09.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 28/9/91. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Under Secretary ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ In reply to your telegram, received this evening, ¶  I have the honor to report for the information of the hon. the Premier's Depa...</title>
               <date when="1891-09-28">1891-09-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-09-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Thomas Wilson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 28/9/91. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Under Secretary ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ In reply to your telegram, received this evening, ¶  I have the honor to report for the information of the hon. the Premier's Depa...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">91.09.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Thomas Wilson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">P91/2930, unit 273, VPRS 1163/P1 inward Correrspondence, VA 672 Premier's Office, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">First registered as S91/8973 in the Chief Secretary's Department then referred to the Premier.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, 28/9/91.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">T. R. Wilson Esqr</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Under Secretary</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reply to your telegram, received this evening,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Telegram not found. However, it was undoubtedly related to a question on notice that was to be put in the Legislative Assembly: 'Mr L. L. Smith: To ask the Honorable the Chief Secretary whether he will cause to be distributed to every member of each branch of the Legislature a copy of Baron von Mueller's work, "Select Extra-tropical Plants for Industrial Culture or Naturalization in Victoria," and also cause one copy to be sent to every Free Library throughout the colony'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Under Secretary, T. Wilson, sent a copy of this question to E. Thomas, Secretary the Premier, on 25 September, saying that he presumed that the Premier would reply to it. Thomas in reply asked Wilson whether he knew of any objections to the proposed distribution of M's book, adding: 'The number required would be 463; and, with 100 free copies applied for by Baron von Mueller [see M to T. Wilson, 15 September 1891], would take up the major part of the new Edition of 1000 — leaving 437 copies for sale &amp; for future presentations Is it a work that is likely to have a sale? If so it would seem a pity to give away such a large number of copies. Please say what the cost is, of the new Edition &amp; what the proposed selling price' (P91/2929, unit 273, VPRS 1163/P1, Public Record Office, Victoria; first registered as S91/9022 in the Chief Secretary's Department, then referred to the Premier).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It was no doubt in response to a message from Thomas on 28 September that Wilson sent his telegram to M. He forwarded M's reply to Thomas on 30 September 1891, enclosing a memorandum of his own 'for the information of the Premier', James Munro. In the memorandum, Wilson stated that there 'is a very considerable sale for this work, 781 copies of the last (the 7th) Edition having been sold to the public at 4/- a copy'. He felt it likely that an equal demand would exist for the 8th edition, which was to be sold at 5/- a copy. As the 8th edition had a print run of 1000 copies, this would leave only about 200 copies for 'gratuitous distribution', of which he felt 150 should be set aside for distribution by the Trustees of the Public Library according to a list submitted by M: 'Of the 7th Edition 141 were distributed in this way'. If M's list were approved, that would leave only 50 copies and they 'would also, if available, be taken up by the public before a new edition appears. Moreover, I think that of those 50 there should be reserved say 20 to meet unexpected demands'. The type for the just-printed edition had already been broken up; the cost of printing was £252. He appended a summary of the disposal of the 7th Edition of 2000 copies, printed in 1888, 781 copies were sold, 350 went to the Agriculture Department, 550 were presented to members of the Intercolonial Medical Congress held in Melbourne in 1889, 141 went to the Public Library for distribution and 20 went to the Colonial Secretary, Sydney. The remaining copies were 'distributed to various institutions and persons on the authority of the Premier's Department'. At the beginning of September 1891, the Government Printer had 'borrowed 50 copies from the Agriculture Department which he now has in stock' (P91/2929, unit 273, VPRS 1163/P1, Public Record Office, Victoria).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The file also contains drafts of the Chief Secretary's reply to Smith's question, a typed version of which reads: 'This work has already been presented gratuitously to every Free Library that has applied for it [and can be given to all others that take the trouble to ask for it <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted</seg>] | There are not, however, enough copies left in stock to supply — as well —to Members of Parliament all round. Many members, no doubt, do not require it; but probably there are enough to supply to Members who do, and who may make application for it. The work has not been stereotyped, and another edition, therefore, would be costly.' Underneath is added in an unknown hand: 'A new Edition of 1000 of this work have just been printed &amp; the proposed free distribution would' [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">text breaks off</seg>].</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The question was put on 30 September 1891 and Hansard (vol. 57, p. 1660) recorded that the Premier 'stated that he had made enquiries with regard to the work referred to, and he found that it was being sold at 5s. per volume. The Government were quite willing to give copies to any Member of Parliament or to any free library who applied for it, but they did not think it wise to send copies of the book broadcast through the colony.'</p>
               </note> I have the honor to report for the information of the hon. the Premier's Department, that as the eight<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">sic</seg>.</p>
               </note> edition of the work on Select extratropic plants<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B91.09.01.</p>
               </note> has only quite recently appeared in 1000 copies, no arrangements are contemplated for an early future edition. Nevertheless it is very likely, that already in a years time the present edition will be exhausted, as a large sale exists for this book. I had the honor to report to you the completion of the print of the eighth edition lately,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M to T. Wilson, 15 September 1891.</p>
               </note> and forwarded to the hon. the Premier, the hon. the Chief Secretary and yourself each a copy. I may be here allowed to express an opinion, that this book will likely have a great future.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to be, Sir, your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gov. Botanist.</seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
