<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 24 May 1891. ¶ To the honorable Sir G. Grey, K.C.B., D.C.L., F.R.G.S., &amp;c. ¶ Member of the New Zealand Parliament. ¶  ¶ The generous sentiments of your valedictory letter, ¶  dear Sir Georg...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-05-24a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Auckland Central City Library, Grey Papers, GL M50(15) att.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>91.05.24a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 24 May 1891. ¶ To the honorable Sir G. Grey, K.C.B., D.C.L., F.R.G.S., &amp;c. ¶ Member of the New Zealand Parliament. ¶  ¶ The generous sentiments of your valedictory letter, ¶  dear Sir Georg...</title>
               <date when="1891-05-24">1891-05-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-05-24a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>Internet link</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>George Grey</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 24 May 1891. ¶ To the honorable Sir G. Grey, K.C.B., D.C.L., F.R.G.S., &amp;c. ¶ Member of the New Zealand Parliament. ¶  ¶ The generous sentiments of your valedictory letter, ¶  dear Sir Georg...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">91.05.24a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To George Grey</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Auckland Central City Library, Grey Papers, GL M50(15) att.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 24 May 1891.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To the honorable Sir G. Grey, K.C.B., D.C.L., F.R.G.S., &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Member of the New Zealand Parliament.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The generous sentiments of your valedictory letter,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. Grey was a member of the New Zealand delegation to the National Australasian Convention in Sydney, 2 March to 9 April 1891 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Official Report of the National Australasian Convention Debates. Sydney, 2 March to 9 April, 1891</seg>. Volume 1 (Sydney, George Stephen Chapman, Acting Government Printer, 1891), p. v) after which he toured ‘in Australia, advocating the principle of one man, one vote’ (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">The</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Times</seg> (London), 6 May 1891, p. 5, col. A). It is probable that the letter was written at the end of his visit to Melbourne or on his departure from Australia.</p>
               </note> dear Sir George, touched me much, particularly as coming from one of the two Nestors of Australian geographic Explorers, who moreover promoted always science-purposes by his own researches and by disinterested action during a long and distinguished career. Under these circumstances I feel all the more free, to approach you in regard to objects, in which New Zealand is so prominently interested, those of the new contemplated antarctic Expedition, and beg now to state, that I brought your kind offer, to bring the views of the Victorian Council of the Royal geographic Society of Australia under the favorable consideration of the N.Z. House of Representatives before my Colleagues, who requested me to express their grateful acknowledgement of your special friendliness in advocating thus publicly there the intended new enterprise. I am further desired on their behalf to enunciate the views, held by us here geographically on this highly promising subject; and if you should deem it necessary, the Council will submit through you a formal petition to the N.Z. Parliament, altho’ probably this communication may be sufficient. During the Christchurch-Meeting of the Austr. Assoc. for Adv. of Science<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The meeting was held in January 1891. </p>
               </note> the desirability for renewed south-polar exploration was discussed at considerable length when I brought up the progress-report of the antarctic committee<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The report was published, see B91.14.02.</p>
               </note> by his Lordship the Bishop of Otago,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">S. T. Nevill (1837–1921) (<ref target="https://teara.govt.nz/en/biographies/2n8/nevill-samuel-tarratt"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0000ff; ">
                        <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0000ff; ">https://teara.govt.nz/en/biographies/2n8/nevill-samuel-tarratt</seg>
                     </ref>, accessed 31 July 2018).</p>
               </note> Sir James Hector, Mr Chapman, Mr Thomson, Mr Parnell,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. C. W. Purnell of Ashburton, NZ, whose paper on Antarctic exploration was published in the proceedings of the Geography Section (see Purnell (1891)).</p>
               </note> Professor Kernot and others in the geographic Section, and the feeling, that the extension of south-polar researches should no longer be deferred, was unanimous. Mr Griffith’s presidential adress dealing also ably with antarctic prospects then.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Griffiths (1891).</p>
               </note> This could not be otherwise, as N.Z. by its geographic position is more than any other of these southern colonies interested in the furtherance of this undertaking.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3299in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3299in; "
                     xml:lang="en">undertaking <seg style="font-style: italic; ">above</seg> subject by the geographic position, which your islands with also their dependencies occupy <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> To yourself and the other statesmen of N.Z. as well as the general Legislature the advantages of renewing explorations now with Steam power in the remotest south of our planet, whether for Science-purposes or for commerce, industries and therefore <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">revenue</hi>
               </seg>, will be so apparent, that it seems hardly needful, to enter on these hopeful subjects at all; but it might here be called to recollection, that resources of the antarctic regions remained practically untouched up to the present time, as sailing whalers and sealers cannot with so much safety pass through the belt of drift-ice as steamers to reach the calmer inner oceanic zone pronounced so rich in whales by Sir James Ross.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. C. Ross (1847).</p>
               </note> If therefore the intended Swedish-Australian Expedition in one or two seasons reconnoitering disclose more particularly, what kinds of Whales and Seals are prevalent, what facilities for hunting these animals exist, what prospects of guano supplies occur, and what other mercantile and technologic commodities are accessible then all these colonies must be soon substantially benefitted, and particularly those stretching furthest south! Should financial pressure any where exist in these fair Australian Dominions, then one of the best remedies would be, to open up new resources, especially when they are within easy reach, and when the aid, solicited for initiating measures in this direction, is not amounting to very large sums. A flotilla of Steam-Whalers and Steam-Sealers, now largely unoccupied in the arctic regions, would after antarctic summer-chases necessarely<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This passage is heavily amended, but the final spelling is as shown.</p>
               </note> be wintering in Australian harbours to refit and replenish, and thus would actually spend large cash sums also in New Zealand, while what locally in these colonies cannot be worked up of raw material would go by ordinary freight ships to European, American and perhaps even other markets. To you, dear Sir George, I need not appeal in the cause of science, but we all can but ardently hope, that in the new enterprise of the illustrious discoverer of the eastern passage through the arctic sea,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">N. A. E. Nordenskiold.</p>
               </note> no colony should be left unrepresented in this part of the world, for participating in objects so grand as his even, even if it was for the advancement of knowledge alone. Very possibly after the proposed reconnoitering voyage (for which in polar latitudes first of all now also balloons will be employed particularly to complete the worlds-map,) — a great expedition on the scale of that of the Erebus and Terror<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The expedition led by Sir James Ross, 1839-43.</p>
               </note> may be forthcoming, but to justify the needful very large expenditure for that, some preliminary work ought to be carried out, such as is contemplated by the new Nordenskiold-voyage. What in this respect is required, to be brought under attention urgently now, is providing timely the means, so that also the season of 1892-1893 is not lost. The necessity of speedy action by Australasia, to carry out its share of monetary obligation, was pointed out some few months ago by Baron Oscar Dickson, a Nobleman of British descent resident in Stockholm, who during a late visit to London urged the Nordenskiold-cause in the “Times”.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See the news item in London <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Times</seg>, 13 February 1891, p. 14 col. E.</p>
               </note> It is easily understood that the present northern summer and coming autumn should not pass without fortifying the two selected ships, and that the equipment be carried out during the next northern winter, so that as early as the ice breaks next northern spring the voyage to the Australasian colonies can be commenced, the final purchases of provisions and other requisites here to be expected not later than June 1892, when also the two Australian Scientists can join the expedition,<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Under the proposed arrangements for the expedition, it would be under Swedish command but, in return for an Australian contribution to the financing, the party would include two Australian scientists.</p>
               </note> the depot to be established not later than August 1892 on Macquarie Island, now a possession of N.Z.,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Macquarie Island had been transferred to the jurisdiction of the Government of Tasmania in 1889!</p>
               </note> and kindly reserved free for that purpose by your Government. Baron Dickson gives £5000 —. —., the Royal Swedish Academy provides the costly Instruments to which Australia might add. The Governments of N.S.W. and of Qeensland<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Queensland?</p>
               </note> have generously placed £2000— and £1000 on the estimates of the new financial year respectively, though the latter great colony is the remotets<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">remotest?</p>
               </note> of all from the regions of action. Tasmania will vote according to the rate of its territory and population. The Victorian, South-Australian and West-Australian Ministries have the subject of providing subsidies at present under consideration with the most hopeful prospects for the enterprise thus far also. The private subscriptions amount to about £1500 now. Baron Dickson estimates the whole cost of the expedition £15000—.—. Everything therefore augurs well, and we can assuredly hope that New Zealand will through its Government countenance an enterprise, which will open the way to vast new industries of permanency<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. whaling and sealing.</p>
               </note> and which will be of special historic renown in science!<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The planned expedition did not take place. See Home <seg style="font-style: italic; ">et al</seg>. (1992) for the background to the Australasian involvement in promoting Antarctic exploration.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Let me remain, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>dear Sir George, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>most regardfully your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pres., R.G.S.A., Vict. Branch</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
