<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ In viewing the rural resources of the Australian alps a  ¶ double prospect is pressed on our attention ¶ , because not only could all the British culture-plants be reared there and some even to gre...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-07-19b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>A91/12316, unit 22, VPRS 619 Secretary's Correspondence Files, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>91.07.19b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ In viewing the rural resources of the Australian alps a  ¶ double prospect is pressed on our attention ¶ , because not only could all the British culture-plants be reared there and some even to gre...</title>
               <date when="1891-07-19">1891-07-19</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-07-19b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Belladonna</term>
               <term>Digitalis</term>
               <term>Valeriana</term>
               <term>Aconitum</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Stirling</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ In viewing the rural resources of the Australian alps a  ¶ double prospect is pressed on our attention ¶ , because not only could all the British culture-plants be reared there and some even to gre...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">91.07.19b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Stirling</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">A91/12316, unit 22, VPRS 619 Secretary's Correspondence Files, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>The document is undated. M composed it as an addendum to a report by James Stirling and sent it to Stirling on 19 July 1891; see M to J. Stirling, 19 July 1891 (in this edition as <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>91-07-19a). The document is not in M's hand but there are some alterations and minor additions by him.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In viewing the rural resources of the Australian alps a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">double prospect is pressed on our attention</hi>
               </seg>, because not only could all the British culture-plants be reared there and some even to greater advantage than in our low-lands, but also it will be only in the higher altitudinal zones, where many of the best vegetable treasures from other highlands of the world can find within our colonial area adapted homes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Pioneer-settlers in our snowy-mountains would necessarily resort in first instance to such cultural choices, as would produce profitable results already in the first or next season. Therefore with culture of ordinary kitchen-vegetables would be made a commencement, some of which cultivated even up to North-Cape,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Norway. The northernmost point in Europe.</p>
               </note> so it would be with rearing strawberries, raspberries, gooseberries, Red &amp; Black Currants, not to speak of many allied and highly valuable North-American and other fruits belonging exclusively to colder zones, for which no real facility of growing exists in Victoria, except in high mountain-regions, for instance the very palatable Billberrry or Blaeberry of British renown. Fruits in many instances as well as the culinary vegetables would improve in flavour, when grown in the cooler regions, when compared to what we are accustomed to getting ordinarily here in the market. Basket-willows and Hazel would along the hitherto unutilized rivulets establish themselves also quickly as a profitable vegetation spontaneously. For early cultural returns also many scent-plants and medicinal herbs would be eligible in or<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>our?</p>
               </note> subalpine country, where they moreover would often become enhanced as regards their qualities; for examples might be singled out Minth, Lavender, Gentian, <name key="Valeriana">Valeriana</name>, Rhubarb, <name key="Digitalis">Digitalis</name>, <name key="Aconitum">Aconitum</name>, <name key="Belladonna">Belladonna</name>, the straying of all these into pastures being easily prevented. Then all the best English grasses and fodder-herbs would particularly prosper in our Alps, and soon permanently enrich the by no means poor indigenous meadow-vegetation, such plants as the Buck-wheat and the Falkland-Island Tussock-Grass to be included, and they would gain a degree of a succulence and verdure not frequently to be met elsewhere here, especially under the refertilizing influence of easily applied or even natural irrigation. Of course each kind of the hardier Cereals would be turned likewise to immediate account. Orchard-trees of the ordinary English kind are bearing still in Middle Norway, even the Walnut-tree, though favored by the influence of the Gulf-Stream, therefore in a latitude considerably beyond that of the extremity of Scotland, and incidentially it might be mentioned, that the Rowan, of which a sweet-fruited variety exists, advances even beyond the arctic circle. If it should be an object in remoter time, to settle even in the highest parts of our alps, then it might be remembered, that Potatoes, Cabbages and Turnips can be produced even as far north as Iceland. For forestry our alps are especially inviting, where-ever for vehicles or for floating-carriage they can be rendered accessible.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Australian Alps should supply us largely with Pine-timber, such as that of the various larches, many kinds of spruces and firs, as all these delight in cold climes, collateral and easily obtained products being tar, turpentine and resin, but necessarily only after a series of years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">What just has been said concerning the coniferous trees, of which we have so little as indigenous in our forests for deals, masts, spars &amp;c applies also much to the other classes of hardy forest-trees of especial peculiarities as-or transatlantic, such as many kinds of Oaks, Elms, Maples, Birches, Alders, Ashes, Lindens, even from so far as Canada, Japan and the Himalaias, not to forget our own and the New Zealandian evergreen beaches.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>beeches?</p>
               </note> For further details respecting utilitarian plants of hardy constitution the volume on "Select plants for industrial culture", of which the eighth edition is just ready,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B91.09.01.</p>
               </note> might be consulted.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">It might be added yet, that never ceasing water supply prevails also through our Alps, that snow-fall gives the soil a periodic rest, that the region is free of locusts, and above all that Highlanders and other hardy colonists looking for new homes would likely prefer to settle in the bracing clime of the Alps as pioneers, sure to be soon followed by others to permanent habitations in all the lower levels of this wide tract of highland-country.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Summary of recommendations</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1, Selection of a site for test culture between Harrietville and Mt. Hotham, accessible from the track to Omeo, at an elevation of about 4000 feet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">2, Fencing of some acres, building of hut, providing tools and other requisites, and engagement of an experienced Gardener for a year, the whole expenditure not to exceed £120, if possible in time, to have full benefit of the coming spring and summer for the tests.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">3, Instructions to the Gardener, to furnish a full report on actual experiments in autumn, and to send samples of the produce fresh by railway to the Agricultural Department in Melbourne, where the enhanced market-value of these products, obtained so much later in the season, could be ascertained.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">4, Collaterally the test station to be used for ascertaining on a small scale the fitness of the region for getting dairy products, meat, wool, fowls, eggs &amp;c for disposal of these to local mining prospectors.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">5, Avoidance of descent to deep narrow vallies, into which cold air much ascends.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">6, Possibility of clearing scrub-country for extending the general pastural areas with simultaneous dissemination of the aptests<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>aptest?</p>
               </note> of grasses and fodder-herbs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">7, Probability if not certainty of vast increase of revenue from the alps through cultural and pastural settlements and the concomitant facilities afforded to the mining Industry.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 10 August the Secretary for Mines, A. Howitt, minuted his support for the idea of promoting settlement in the Alps and forwarded Stirling's report, with M's addendum, to the Secretary for Lands, who had a plan prepared showing 'the land still available'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 2 September 1891, the Secretary for Lands wrote to the Secretary of Agriculture asking 'that he will be good enough to state if he can by the use of any vote under his control see his way to further Baron Von Mueller's idea'. The response, on 8 September, was: 'No vote available'. M was informed of this on 14 September.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Much later, on 18 May 1893, R. A. P. Grieve of St Arnaud wrote to the Lands Department asking for a copy of Stirling's report or to be informed 'where the information could be had'. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>An attached minute states: 'According to information obtained from the Mining Department the report referred to has not been published'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Aconitum">Aconitum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Belladonna">Belladonna</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Digitalis">Digitalis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Valeriana">Valeriana</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
