<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ It has already become known through the  ¶ Geographische Mitteilungen ¶  that the magnanimous Sir Thomas Elder will send out an expedition into still unknown parts of Central Australia.  ¶  ¶ My pr...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-05-00b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>91.05.00b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ It has already become known through the  ¶ Geographische Mitteilungen ¶  that the magnanimous Sir Thomas Elder will send out an expedition into still unknown parts of Central Australia.  ¶  ¶ My pr...</title>
               <date when="1891-05">1891-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-05-00b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Alexander Supan</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ It has already become known through the  ¶ Geographische Mitteilungen ¶  that the magnanimous Sir Thomas Elder will send out an expedition into still unknown parts of Central Australia.  ¶  ¶ My pr...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">91.05.00b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Alexander Supan</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here see B91.07.03, published in Heft VII of the volume of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Petermann's geographische Mitteilungen</seg> for 1891, the closing date for which is given as 11 July 1891. Allowing a normal transit time of 6-7 weeks suggests that the letter would have been written in May of that year. The text is introduced by 'Über die neue Expedition zur Durchforschung der letzten grossen Lücke in Zentral-Australien und Untersuchung der neuesten Leichhardt-Spuren schreibt Baron <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ferd. v. Müller</seg>, der Nestor der deutschen Gelehrten in Australien:' [About the new expedition to explore the last great gap in Central Australia and to investigate the latest traces of Leichhardt, Baron Ferd. v. Müller, the Nestor of German scholars in Australia, writes:].</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Es ist bereits durch die 'Geogr. Mitteilungen' bekannt geworden, dass der grossmütige Sir Thomas Elder eine Expedition in noch unbekannte Teile Zentral-Australiens aussenden wird. Die Anregung zu diesem neuen Unternehmen gab meine Präsidentenrede bei der Eröffnung der Melbourne-Versammlung der 'Australian Association for the Advancement of Science' im Januar 1890, in der ich erwähnte, dass zwei Landstrecken — eine so gross wie England und Schottland zusammengenommen, und die andre noch grösser — bisher nie von zivilisierten Menschen betreten sei und der Erschliessung für Erdkunde harre. Freiwillig erbot sich dann Elder in einem Schreiben aus Schottland an mich, die ganzen Kosten dieser Reise zu tragen, und betraute mich mit den Vorbereitungen, die nun bei seiner eben erfolgten Rückkehr nach Süd-Australien und mit Hilfe der geographischen Vereine dieses Weltteils vollendet sind. Die Aufgabe der Karawane ist eine doppelte:</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1) die geographische Karte von Australien in ihren Hauptzügen zu vollenden;</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2) das Schicksal des seit 1848 verschollenen Dr. Leichhardt und seiner Gefährten zu ermitteln.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Beides wird bis zu einem gewissen Grade wohl gelöst werden, denn die Aussichten sind diesmal besonders ermutigend. Die Reisenden können zur Jetztzeit mit Eisenbahnen weit ins Innere gebracht werden, wo Dromedare, ohne bis dahin Lasten getragen zu haben, bereitstehen, so dass die Karawane schon im fernen Innern, und zwar im Beginn der kühlen Jahreszeit, frisch die Reise antritt, alles nach dem von mir entworfenen Plane. Der Kostenanschlag beläuft sich auf 5000 £, so dass Sir Thomas Elder eine ebenso grosse Summe opfert, wie der edle Baron Dickson in Stockholm für Baron Nordenskiölds Südpolar-Reise zur Verfügung stellt, mit gleichen Subsidien von Australien. Als Präsident der Victoria-Abteilung der Königl. Geogr. Gesellschaft von Australien habe ich die Wiederaufnahme der antarktischen Reisen auch hier seit sechs Jahren befürwortet, um neben den wissenschaftlichen Forschungen auch das südliche Polarmeer unter den entferntesten befahrbaren Breitengraden dem Walfischfang, Robbenschalg und andern Erwerbsquellen zu erschliessen. Zum ersten Befehlshaber der Elder-Expedition ist der Landmesser Lindsay in Adelaide ernannt. Alle Branchen der Wissenschaft werden vertreten sein. Auch ein Arzt ist angestellt: Dr. Elliott. Der Geolog und Mineralog Streich und der Zoolog Helms sind Deutsche. Ein halbzivilisierter Eingeborner wird auch mitgesandt. Aufsuchung von Weideland und Minenstellen sind nach meinem Wunsche zunächst ganz Nebensache. Es ist berechnet, dass die Partie gegen Ende des Jahres zurück sein wird. Voraussichtlich wird es aber grossentheils wasserloses Wüstenland sein, was die Reisenden zu durchziehen haben, aber dennoch sollen sie überall so weit wie möglich von Plätzen bleiben, die bereits auf den Landkarten verzeichnet sind. Die Expedition wird von der australischen transkontinentalen Telegraphenlinie abgehen, sich zwischen der Route von Giles im J. 1875 und dem Zug Gosses von 1873 und Forrests von 1874 westlich wenden, versuchen, den 122° Ö. L. v. Gr. zu erreichen, dann nördlich bis in die Nähe von Mt. Macpherson zu den Quellen des De Gray-Flusses vordringen, um den neuen bereitgehaltenen Proviant und andre Erfordernisse zu erhalten und über diesen ersten Teil der Expedition vorläufig zu berichten. In einem östlichen und etwas südlichen Kurs wird die Rückreise angetreten und in der Nähe des 125. Längengrades Halt gemacht, um durch Nachfragen unter den Eingebornen Auskunft zu suchen über die von Mc Phee erwähnten Gegenstände einer vor vielen Jahren verdursteten Partie, welche aus drei Europäern und einem Eingebornen bestand und mit Pferden von Osten gekommen war, so dass wahrscheinlich das Schicksal unsers berühmten, aber traurig verunglückten Landsmanns und seiner armen Begleiter erkundet werden wird. Die letzte Hauptausfüllung der zweiten grossen Landstrecke auf der Weltkarte würde unter glücklichen Umständen stattfinden können, ehe die grösste Sommerhitze zu Ende des Jahres eintritt, an einer Linie bedeutuend südlich von Warburtons Route im J. 1873. Mögen denn die grossen Hoffnungen, welche wir hier auf dies wichtige Unternehmen setzen — das letzte, für welche noch grosse Areale übrigblieben —, sich glänzend erfüllen! Ich selbst würde dann nach 44 jährigem Hiersein und auch nach geographischem Streben durch diese lange Zeit noch am späten Abend meines Lebens die Landkarte des fünften Erdteils vollendet sehen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>It has already become known through the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geographische Mitteilungen</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">i.e. </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Petermann's geographische Mitteilungen</seg>
                     <seg style="">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> that the magnanimous Sir Thomas Elder will send out an expedition into still unknown parts of Central Australia. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>My presidential address at the opening of the Melbourne meeting of the 'Australian<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Error for</seg> Australasian.</p>
               </note> Association for the Advancement of Science' in January 1890,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B90.13.01, a version of which had been printed in the press as B90.01.01.</p>
               </note> in which I mentioned that two stretches of land — one as large as England and Scotland together, and the other even larger — had never been walked on by civilised man and awaited disclosure for geography, gave the stimulation to this new undertaking. Then in a letter to me from Scotland,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">T. Elder to M, 2 July 1890.</p>
               </note> Elder voluntarily offered to bear the whole cost of this journey and entrusted me with the preparations that now are completed with his return just made to South Australia and with the assistance of the geographical societies of this part of the world. The task of the caravan is a double one:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1) to complete the geographical chart of Australia in its principal features;</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2) to ascertain the fate of Dr Leichhardt and his companions missing since 1848.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Both will probably be solved to a certain extent, because the prospects are particularly encouraging this time. The travellers can these days be brought by the railway far into the interior, where camels, without having to carry loads to there, are ready, so that the caravan already in the far interior and in fact at the beginning of the cool season begins the journey fresh, all according to the plan drafted by me. The estimate of costs amounts to £5000, so that Sir Thomas Elder sacrifices just as large a sum as the noble Baron Dickson in Stockholm has made available for Baron Nordenskiöld's south polar expedition with similar subsidies from Australia. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>As president of the Victorian branch of the Royal Geographical Society of Australia<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. Australasia.</p>
               </note> I have also supported the resumption of Antarctic voyages here for six years so as to open up the south polar seas below the farthermost navigable degree of latitude to whaling, sealing and other resources besides scientific research. The surveyor Lindsay in Adelaide is appointed as first commander of the Elder Expedition. All branches of science will be represented. Even a physician is on the staff: Dr Elliott. The geologist and mineralogist Streich and the zoologist Helms are German. A half-civilized Aborigine will also be sent along. Finding pasture land and mines are firstly quite minor matters according to my particular request. It is calculated that the party will be back about the end of the year. However, probably it will be for the large part a waterless desert that the travellers have to traverse, but still they should keep everywhere as far as possible from places that are already recorded on the maps. The expedition will depart from the Australian transcontinental telegraph line, turning westerly between the route of Giles in 1875 and the march of Gosse of 1873 and of Forrest of 1874, trying to reach 122° E. longitude from Greenwich, then advancing northerly up to the neighbourhood of Mt. Macpherson to the sources of the De Gray River so as to receive the newly prepared provisions and other necessities and to report provisionally about this first part of the expedition. The return journey will begin in an easterly and somewhat southerly course and stop in the neighbourhood of the 125th degree of longitude to seek information by questions among the Aborigines about the remains of a party, mentioned by McPhee, who died of thirst, that consisted of three Europeans and an Aborigine and had come from the east with horses, so that probably the fate of our celebrated but sadly unfortunate fellow countryman and his poor companions will be established. The last principal filling out of two large stretches of land on the world map would be able to take place under favourable circumstances before the greatest summer heat sets in at the end of the year, on a line significantly south of Warburton's route in 1873. May the great hopes that we place here on this important undertaking — the last for which large areas still remain —, be fulfilled brilliantly. I myself would then after 44 years' presence here and also after geographic efforts through this long time still see the map of the fifth continent completed at the late evening of my life.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
