<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne 14 Dec. 91. ¶ Melbourne, 14 Dec. 91 ¶  ¶ It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to answer your last letter ¶  already by the previous mail, but lack of time did not permit it; howev...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-12-14-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>91.12.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne 14 Dec. 91. ¶ Melbourne, 14 Dec. 91 ¶  ¶ It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to answer your last letter ¶  already by the previous mail, but lack of time did not permit it; howev...</title>
               <date when="1891-12-14">1891-12-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1891/91-12-14-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eleutheranthes</term>
               <term>Ceratopetalum</term>
               <term>Celastrinae</term>
               <term>Leguminosae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/f8213e05-e3b6-4888-a4fb-a9b29368b9b6">Scutellaria</term>
               <term>Hypsophila</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/b9c54c67-4dcc-4651-9897-eb29783e8622">Salicornia</term>
               <term>Quintinia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/7e16374d-05f2-436a-b962-0155162b09a2">Rubiaceae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>t-letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="60">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="40">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Adolf Engler</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne 14 Dec. 91. ¶ Melbourne, 14 Dec. 91 ¶  ¶ It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to answer your last letter ¶  already by the previous mail, but lack of time did not permit it; howev...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">91.12.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">To Adolf Engler</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <ab rend="letter"
                style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
                type="heading">Melbourne 14 Dec. 91.</ab>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es war meine Absicht, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, Ihren letzten Brief schon mit voriger Post zu beantworten, aber Zeit Mangel liess es nicht zu; doch sandte ich dann schon ein Extra-Exemplar des Second Census, um dort darin die in dem dortigen bot. Museum bereits vorhandenen austr. Arten zu notiren, falls es möglich sein sollte Solches von hier zu erweitern. Das Ex. müsste dann hierher zurückkommen. Dass dies nicht leicht u schnell ausführbar ist, werden Sie einräumen, wenn ich hinweise auf die sehr beschränkte Hülfe in meiner Anstalt, in welcher ¾ Millionen Bögen voll Pflanzen, welche ich seit 1840 zusammen brachte, freilich ⅓ durch Kauf der Sammlungen Sonder's, in Ordnung gehalten werden müssen, der neuen Einschaltungen nicht zu gedenken. Aus einer solchen umfangsvollen Sammlung besondere Exemplare herauszunehmen erfordert viel Zeit. Dann sind in den meisten Fällen auch nur die typischen Ex. conservirt u zurückbehalten, u wenn in diese eingegriffen würde, so gingen ja die Belege veloren, welche für alle Zeit hier für Charactere u Verbreitung nachsehbar sein sollten in Verbindung mit meinen Werken. Einiges liesse sich ja aber doch wohl herbeischaffen für Ihre Anstalt, selbst aus dem Surplus des Neu-Gesammelten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun liegt aber noch eine andere besondere Schwierigkeit in Bezug auf dort vor, nämlich die Wahrscheinlichkeit oder Möglichkeit, dass das von mir gelieferte Material zu Angriffen auf mich aus Ihrer Anstalt benutzt werden möchte. So z. B. hat der Bearbeiter der Rubiaceen in den Pflanzen-Familien, wenn ich recht erinnere, mein Genus <name key="Eleutheranthes">Eleutheranthes</name> angegriffen, als etymologisch unrichtig. Da dies das erste mal war, in welchem die Sinn eines für Pflanzen-Genera gewählten Wortes in dem Opus verwerfend besprochen wird, so geht deraus hervor, dass es die Absicht war, mir öffentlich etwas Unannehmliches zu sagen. Warum er </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mich</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> angreift, kann ich nicht anders denken; denn </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">D.C.</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> hat dreimal das Wort </seg>ἐλεύθερος<seg style=""> bei den Compositin genau in der Bedeutung angewandt, in welcher ich das Wort verwerthete, so anderweitig Poiteau, C. Koch, Klotzsch, Schlechtendal, Maximowicz, Wendland, gewiss ebenso gute Classiker als dieser Kriticker u mich treffen solche Bemerkungen um so empfindlicher, wenn sie von einem jungen Gelehrten einem Nestor gegenüber ausgesprochen werden. Quatrefages, Dumeril, Bonaparte, Fabricius, Gray, Rafinesque haben das Wort in gleichem Sinn für zoologische Genera gebraucht. Daher mache ich es zur </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Bedingung</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, dass Sie mir die </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Versicherung</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> geben, mich gegen ähnliche Unbill von Seiten Ihrer Untergebenen schützen zu wollen; sonst wird es vorzuziehen sein, dass sich der Austausch von hier auf </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ausser</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> australische Pflanzen meiner Sammlungen beschränkt.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es war mir recht erfreulich, dass meine Widmung des neuen <name key="Ceratopetalum">Ceratopetalum</name> für die Virchow-Feier so wohlwollend aufgenommen wurde. Ich habe es auch veranlasst, dass unsere seit mehr 40 Jahren bestehende ärztliche Gesellschaft auch eine Gratulations Adresse an den grossen Pathologen sandte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin nun mitten im Arbeiten an Neu Guineaische Pflanzen, inclusive Forbes's Material, und bearbeite Alles im Zusammenhang. Wir haben jetzt auch <name key="Quintinia">Quintinia</name>, <name key="Scutellaria">Scutellaria</name> u manche andere Genera, welche wir früher noch nicht als papuanisch kannten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie werden wohl bemerkt haben, dass Britten sich im Journal of Botany, wie ich hier eben sehe, sehr tadelnd über das ausprach, was im bot Central Blatt kürzlich erschien, bezüglich der Änderung der Namen einer langen Reihe von Leguminosen. Ich habe stets das Prinzip gehabt, Aublet's Namen denen Schrebers nicht vorzuziehen, wenn Jener aus einer Gattung 2 oder mehr machte, oder wenn auf einer Platte für ein Genus zwei Pflanzen stehen, von denen nur </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">eine</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> dazu gehört. Dann sollten wir auch an der Idee fest halten, welche seit dem Erscheinen von RBr's prodromus angenommen wurde, dass bei Umsetzung von Pflanzen in ein anderes Genus </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">die blosse Andeutung für alle bis dahin bekannte Arten gilt</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">. Also wenn Baillon ein Aublet's Genus restrictuirt, kommen </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ihm</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> sicher bekannte u gut begrenzte Arten zu für Autorität, selbst wenn er solche auch nicht neu merirte. Eine spätere Zeit wird irgend ein anderes Prinzip sicher verwerfen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich werde Ihnen in diesem Tage die 9te Decade der Salsolaceen für den Bearbeiter dieser Ordnung senden. Diese schliesst aber noch nicht <name key="Salicornia">Salicornia</name> ein mit den U</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nter</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">gattungen. Ich habe in toto nur 96 Arten, kann also die 10t Decade nicht erscheinen lassen, bis 4 mehr entdeckt sind, was viele Jahre dauern kann, wenn </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">je</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich werde aber Probeplatten der <name key="Salicornia">Salicornia</name>-Arten senden. Beigefügt erhalten Sie auch ein Fragment von <name key="Hypsophila">Hypsophila</name>, was der Bearbeiter der <name key="Celastrinae">Celastrinae</name> wünscht. Wurde der erste Doubletten Theil der Hawaia-Pfl meines Freundes Hillebrand über Amerika gesandt? Der schnellste und kürzeste Weg wäre doch wohl von dort über Bremen oder Hamburg. Ich wäre immer bereit die Fracht hier zu zahlen</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">In meinen eignen Schriften wird man meiner grammaticalische Genauigkeit beim Namen-Geben finden, mit gelegentlicher Abkürzung für Euphonie. Solche Adjective als ranunculoides, urticaefolius &amp;c, obwohl beibehalten von den besten neueren Phytographen kommen bei mir nicht vor.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> Ist keine Möglichkeit vorhanden, dass jemand dort ein Suppl zu Pritzel's Index iconum liefert? </seg>Es ist doch ein so nützliches Werk.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <ab rend="t-letter"
                style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
                type="heading">Melbourne, 14 Dec. 91</ab>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It was my intention, highly esteemed Professor, to answer your last letter<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> already by the previous mail, but lack of time did not permit it; however, I have then already sent an extra copy of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Second Census</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B89.12.03.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> to note in it there the Australian species already existing in the botanical museum there, in case it should be possible to extend such species from here. The copy must then come back here. That this is not easily or quickly practicable, you will admit, if I draw attention to the very restricted assistance in my institution, in which ¾ million folders of plants that I have brought together since 1840, of course ⅓ by purchase of Sonder's collection, must be kept in order, not thinking of the new insertions. To take out particular specimens from such an extensive collection requires much time. Then as well in most cases only the type specimens are conserved and retained and if these were encroached upon, then the vouchers would certainly be lost that should be examinable for all time here for characters and distribution in connection with my works. However, some can probably be provided for your institution even from the surplus of the newly-collected items. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But now there exists another particular difficulty relating to this, that is the possibility or probability that the material sent by me may be used for an attack on me from your institution. So for example the compiler of the <name key="Rubiaceae">Rubiaceae</name> in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pflanzen-Familien</seg> has, if I remember correctly, attacked my genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eleutheranthes">Eleutheranthes</name>
               </seg> as etymologically incorrect.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>K. Schumann (1891), p. 130: 'Anmerkung. Der Name </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutheranthus</seg>
                     <seg style=""> ist etymologisch fehlerhaft gebildet, da Eleutheria die Freiheit, nicht aber die Lösung, Trennung bedeutet; dem richtigen Sinne nach müsste die Gattung Choristanthus genannt werden. </seg>[Annotation. The name Eleutheranthus is etymologically erroneously constructed, since Eleutheria means freedom but not solution, separation; according to the correct meaning, the genus must be named Choristanthus]</p>
               </note> Since this was the first time in which the sense of a word chosen for a plant genus was discussed condemningly in the work, this shows that it was the intention to state something publicly unpleasant to me. Why he attacked <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">me</hi>
               </seg>, I cannot otherwise think; because <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">D. C.</hi>
               </seg> has used the word ἐλεύθερος<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>= free.</p>
               </note> in the Composites three times exactly in the meaning in which I utilized the word, as did in another way Poiteau, C. Koch, Klotzsch, Schlechtendal, Maximowicz, Wendland,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The works and names cited probably include Poiteau (1803), <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutheranthera</seg>; K. Koch (1842), <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutherospermum</seg>; Klotzsch (1838), <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutherostemon</seg>; Schlechtendal, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutherocarpum</seg>, listed in Lechler (1857); Maximowicz (1859), <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutherococcus</seg>; Wendland, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eleutheropetalum</seg>, in Örsted (1859).</p>
               </note> certainly just as good classicists as this critic, and such remarks hit me the more severely when they are expressed by a young savant against a nestor. Quatrefages, Duméril, Bonaparte, Fabricius, Gray, Rafinesque have used the word in the same sense for zoological genera. Therefore I make it a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">condition</hi>
               </seg> that you give me the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">assurance</hi>
               </seg> of intending to protect me against similar wrongs on the part of your subordinates, otherwise it will be preferable that the exchange from here be confined to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">extra</hi>
               </seg>-Australian plants of my collections. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I was very pleased that my dedication of the new <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Ceratopetalum">Ceratopetalum</name>
               </seg> for the Virchow Jubilee was received so kindly.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Ceratopetalum">Ceratopetalum</name> virchowii </seg>was described in B91.04.01, p. 181, the dedication reading: </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">This small tribute from the Australian floral world is gratulatorily offered to Professor Rudolph Virchow at the time of the public celebration of his 70th birthday, so that his illustrious name may be identified for ever also with the living creation of this part of our planet, where his great pathologic teachings have not less contributed to the advancement of medical science than in other parts of the globe, not to speak of his also to us here important anthropologic researches.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An account of the response to M's tribute to Virchow has not been found; it may have been mentioned in the letter to which M is responding.</p>
               </note> I have also arranged that our more than 40-years-old medical society send an address of congratulation to the great pathologist as well.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Victorian Branch of the British Medical Association resolved at its meeting on 18 March 1891 to send a congratulatory letter to Virchow (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 20 March 1881, p. 10); see also M to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australasian medical gazette</seg>, February 1891 (in this edition as 91-02-00b).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am now in the middle of working on New Guinea plants, including Forbes's material and working them up all in association.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The species from the galley proof of B91.13.01 are included in B92.11.02, where M states (p. 111) that the publication of the 10th part of his Papuan Plants was postponed.</p>
               </note> We have now also <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Quintinia">Quintinia</name>, <name key="Scutellaria">Scutellaria</name>
               </seg> and several other genera that we previously did not know as Papuan.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will probably have noticed that Britten in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of Botany</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See 'Book Notes, News, &amp;c.', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of botany</seg>, 29 (November 1891), p. 352, referring to Taubert (1891); the paragraph is unsigned, but James Britten was the editor.</p>
               </note> as I have just seen here, criticized what appeared recently in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bot. Centralblatt</seg> respecting the changing of names of a long series of <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>. I have always had the principle not to prefer Aublet's names to those of Schreber, if the former made two or more from a genus, or if two plants stand together on a plate for one genus of which only <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg> belonged to it. Because we should also hold fast to the idea, which has been accepted since the appearance of R Br's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus</seg>, that in the case of moving plants into another genus <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">the simple change applies for all species known to that time</hi>
               </seg>. Thus if Baillon restricts Aublet's genus, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> reliably-known and well-limited species come to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">him</hi>
               </seg> for authority, even if he does not merit such recently. A later time will certainly reject any other principle.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>One of these days I will send you the 9th Decade of the Salsolaceae for the compiler of this order.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Part of B91.13.24; it was evidently not published until 1892.</p>
               </note> However, this does not yet include <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Salicornia">Salicornia</name>
               </seg> with the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sub</hi>
               </seg>genera. I have in toto only 96 species, therefore the 10th Decade cannot appear until 4 more are discovered, which could be many years, if <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ever</hi>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No 10th Decade of this work was ever published.</p>
               </note> But I will send proof plates of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Salicornia">Salicornia</name>
               </seg> species.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A bound volume of assorted botanical illustrations in the library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne, covering <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ectrosia</seg> to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Zea</seg>, includes both original drawings and proofs of seven species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Salicornia">Salicornia</name>
                     </seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Enclosed you will also receive a fragment of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hypsophila">Hypsophila</name>
               </seg>, which the compiler of the <name key="Celastrinae">Celastrinae</name> wants.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See Lösener (1892) where, in a footnote to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hyposophila</seg> (p. 203), Lösener wrote:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Durch die Freundlichkeit des Herrn Baron F. v. Müller war es mir ermöglicht, diese Gattung sowie n. 7, welche bisher noch nicht im Berliner Herbar vertreten waren, selbst untersuchen zu können, wofür ich demselben auch hier meinen besten Dank ausspreche' </seg>[Through the friendliness of Baron F. v. Müller I was able myself to examine this genus and no. 7, which had not yet been represented in the Berlin herbarium, for which I would also like here to express my sincere thanks].</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'No. 7' was M's genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hedraianthera</seg>. </p>
               </note> Was the first part of the duplicates of Hawaiian plants of my friend Hillebrand sent via America? The quickest and shortest way would probably be from there via Bremen or Hamburg. I would always be prepared to pay the freight here.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In my own writings one will find my grammatical precision in name giving, with occasional abbreviation for euphony. Such adjectives as ranunculoides, urticaefolius &amp;c, although retained by the best recent phytologists, do not occur in my work.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: justify; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Is there any possibility that someone there will produce a supplement to Pritzel's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Index iconum</seg>? It is indeed such a useful work.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pritzel (1866).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Celastrinae">Celastrinae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ceratopetalum">Ceratopetalum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eleutheranthes">Eleutheranthes</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hypsophila">Hypsophila</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Quintinia">Quintinia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Rubiaceae">Rubiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Salicornia">Salicornia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Scutellaria">Scutellaria</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
