<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ The possession of an extensive tract of alpine country renders Victoria particularly adapted for the naturalisation of animals of the colder zones. Several of our lowland animals ascend moreover du...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/no date letters/00-00-00Alps-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Museum of Victoria, Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>00.00.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ The possession of an extensive tract of alpine country renders Victoria particularly adapted for the naturalisation of animals of the colder zones. Several of our lowland animals ascend moreover du...</title>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/no date letters/00-00-00Alps-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>[...]</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ The possession of an extensive tract of alpine country renders Victoria particularly adapted for the naturalisation of animals of the colder zones. Several of our lowland animals ascend moreover du...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">00.00.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To [...]</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Museum of Victoria, Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Trans 24.11.93. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof</seg>.</p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">full citation.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The possession of an extensive tract of alpine country renders Victoria particularly adapted for the naturalisation of animals of the colder zones. Several of our lowland animals ascend moreover during the summer season to the alpine plateaus and to the higher vallies of our Snowy mountains, and indicate how valuable for the purpose of naturalizing foreign animals the existence of an elevated back country will prove in many instances. Thus the Echidna ascends to fully 6000' and I noticed Emus, rearing their little young ones at elevations of at least 5000', where the Eucalyptus forest is reduced to diminutive trees or a scrubby brushwood, but where nevertheless the thick covering of perennial grasses and other rubaceous plants afford during the summer an abundance of sustenance and usually a quiet retreat.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the South-Western extremities of the alps, where the climate in consequence of the humidity of the surrounding ferntreegullies is much more moist than in any other part of the Snowy mountains, we find forests of Beechtrees irrigated by numerous mossy brooks to predominate, and there cannot be imagined more suitable spots for the liberation of the hardier species of deer and any other forest animals of the colder climate than these localities, whether we view them in regard to the pasture plants which they produce, or in regard to the climate or to the protection afforded by the density of the underwood of the adjacent ranges. Simultaneously there is every opportunity during the months of inclement weather afforded to the animals to descend into the lower vallies of the surrounding forest.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The lyrebird advances also occasionally to alpine elevations, altho' its favorite haunt exists in the ferntree ravines of the infraalpine ranges. Since these birds, which display but little agility in their flight, appear to enjoy in these deep forest retreats comparative safety against the [...], hawks and other indigenous adversaries it may be presumed that the much swifter English pheasant, which already abounds in some of the ferntreegullies of New Zealand, could be made a permanent denizen of these forest regions and with this bird many of the of the phasian tribe. Ferntree gullies extend with more or less interruptions through at least seven degrees of latitude of our territory.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During the summer months I found the temperature of the alps at hights from 4500 to 5500' ranging under ordinary circumstances from a minimum of 52° F. at sunrise to a maximum of 78° F during midday-hours. It is needless to explain, that occasionally for instance during snow-storms or during exceedingly hot weather the temperature may for limited periods range higher and lower than above indicated.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Already on some former occasions I have drawn attention to the mildness of the almost subtropical climate of Eastern Gipps Land; we have therefore to resort to this part of the colony, if we desire to attempt the naturalisation of any animals of the warmer zones in Victoria, such as the more tender species of Gazelles, many tropical birds &amp;c. It has often occurred to me, that the liberation of various species of goats in the many precipitous glens of our ranges might be attended with advantageous results, especially if the exstirpation of the Dingo could be gradually completed. For the former food exists there in abundance, now unused and not accessible to our domesticated herds &amp; flocks.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
