<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Permit me to express my warmest thanks to you for your kind letter ¶  and the endorsement contained in it of my treatment of snakebite. My discovery of strychnine as a reliable antidote for snakebi...</title>
            <author>Augustus Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1888/88-02-14a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>88.02.14a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Augustus Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ Permit me to express my warmest thanks to you for your kind letter ¶  and the endorsement contained in it of my treatment of snakebite. My discovery of strychnine as a reliable antidote for snakebi...</title>
               <date when="1888-02-14">1888-02-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1888/88-02-14a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Permit me to express my warmest thanks to you for your kind letter ¶  and the endorsement contained in it of my treatment of snakebite. My discovery of strychnine as a reliable antidote for snakebi...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">88.02.14a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">From Augustus Mueller</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see A. Mueller (1888a).The printed version is headed: ‘Ueber die Behandlung des Schlangenbisses durch Strychnin. <seg style="">| Von Dr. A. Müller zu Yackandandah (Nordwestliches Victoria, Australien). | Briefliche Mittheilung an Baron Ferd. v. Müller in Melbourne.’ </seg>[On the treatment of snakebite with strychnine. By Dr A. Müller at Yackandandah (Northwestern Victoria, Australia). Communicated in a letter to Baron Ferd. v. Müller in Melbourne.] Yackandandah is in northeastern Victoria.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Erlauben Sie mir, Ihnen meinen verbindlichsten Dank auszudrücken für Ihr freundliches Schreiben und die darin enthaltene Billigung meiner Behandlung des Schlangenbisses. Meine Entdeckung des Strychnins als eines zuverlässigen Gegengiftes bei Schlangenbiss war keine zufällige, sondern resultirte aus genauer Beobachtung des Vergiftungsprozesses, die mir die feste Ueberzeugung gab, dass das Gift eine specifische Wirkung auf alle die Muskelaction und Bewegung bewirkenden und regulirenden Centraltheile des Nervensystems habe. Da diese Wirkung keineswegs auf die willkürlichen Muskeln beschränkt ist, sondern sich auf alle contractilen Fasern zu erstrecken scheint, wie dieses sich unter Anderem in der Pupillenlähmung und der äusserst schwachen Herzaction zeigt, so bot sich das Strychnin als Gegengift vorzugsweise dar, da dasselbe in seiner wohlbekannten toxischen Wirkung einen direct entgegengestzten Einfluss auf das Muskelsystem zeigt. Hätte mich das Strychnin in Stiche gelassen, so würde ich sogar das Brucin versucht haben, so fest war ich von der Nothwendigkeit eines derartigen Mittels überzeugt. Das Strychnin ist indess dem Schlangengift vollständig gewachsen und wird sich gewiss auch in Indien als zuverlässig bewähren und dadurch eine Menge von Menschenleben alljährlich retten, während dem glücklichen Erfinder eine für seine alten Tage sehr willkommene pecuniäre Unabhängigkeit gesichert ist, verbunden mit dem beseligenden Bewusstsein, der Menschheit einen dauernden Dienst erwiesen zu haben. Ich werde mir erlauben, dem Herrn Dr. King eine kleine Abhandlung über den Gegenstand, die ich nächsten Monat vor der Medicinschen Gesellschaft in Melbourne zu lesen beabsichtige, zu übersenden und ihn gleichzeitig ersuchen, mir die von der Indischen Regierung ausgesetzte Belohnung zu sichern, falls sich das Mittel in Asien als ebenso zuverlässig bewährt, wie es in Australien ist. Nach den Symptomen zu urtheilen ist die Wirkung in Indien dieselbe, nur intensiver, und es wird deshalb dort wahrscheinlich grösserer Dosen des Antidotes bedürfen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">14. Februar 1888.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Permit me to express my warmest thanks to you for your kind letter<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> and the endorsement contained in it of my treatment of snakebite. My discovery of strychnine as a reliable antidote for snakebite was not accidental, but resulted from careful observation of the process of poisoning that gave me the strong conviction that the poison had a specific action on all the central parts of the nervous system producing and regulating muscle action and movement. Because this action is in no way restricted to the voluntary muscles but seems to extend to all contractile fibres, as is shown among other things in the paralysis of the pupils and the very weak action of the heart, strychnine offered itself particularly as an antidote, because it shows a directly opposing influence on the muscle system in its well-known toxic action. Had strychnine failed me, I would even have tried brucine, so strongly convinced was I of the necessity of a similar remedy. Strychnine, however, is completely a match for the snake poison and will undoubtedly prove itself reliable even in India and thereby save a host of people's lives annually, whilst a very welcome pecuniary independence for his old age is assured for the fortunate discover, coupled with the blessed knowledge of having rendered a lasting service to mankind. I will take the liberty of sending Dr King a small paper about the matter, which I intend to read before the Medical Society in Melbourne next month,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The report published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australian medical journal</seg>, 1888, pp. 103-10 of the next meeting of the Medical Society of Victoria, held on 7 March 1888, makes no mention of Mueller’s having presented a paper. It was read at the meeting of 2 May 1888 and published as A. Mueller (1888). See also M to A. Engler, 5 April 1888, and notes thereto.</p>
               </note> and at the same time ask him to secure me the reward offered by the Indian Government, if the remedy proves just as reliable in Asia as it is in Australia. To judge from the symptoms, the action in India is the same, only more intensive, and therefore it will probably need larger doses of the antidote.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">14 February 1888.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
