<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, ¶ 14 May 1888. ¶ T.R. Wilson Esqr, ¶ Undersecretary. ¶ Sir...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1888/88-05-14a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>K88/4831, unit 339, VPRS 3992/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>88.05.14a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, ¶ 14 May 1888. ¶ T.R. Wilson Esqr, ¶ Undersecretary. ¶ Sir...</title>
               <date when="1888-05-14">1888-05-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1888/88-05-14a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Thomas Wilson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, ¶ 14 May 1888. ¶ T.R. Wilson Esqr, ¶ Undersecretary. ¶ Sir...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">88.05.14a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Thomas Wilson<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">K88/4831, unit 339, VPRS 3992/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14 May 1888.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">T.R. Wilson Esqr,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Undersecretary.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reference to your communication of the 8th instant<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 8 May 1888, Wilson forwarded to M a letter from the Department of Agriculture to A. Deakin, Chief Secretary, dated 4 May: 'I have the honor to inform you that the Minister of Agriculture has decided that periodical reports shall be prepared and published by this Department. Mr Dow is of opinion that the Govt. Botanist might furnish papers for publication which would be of interest to agriculturists; and I am to ask you that you will be good enough to give instructions to Baron von Mueller to supply such papers to me, as, in his opinion, will be of an interesting and instructive character. It is desired that the choice of subject be left to the Baron's discretion.' Deakin approved this suggestion on 18 May (L88/4590, unit 339, VPRS 3992/P, Public Record Office, Victoria).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have the honor to state, that I shall not fail to comply with the request of the honorable the Chief Secretary and the honorable the Minister of Lands, to contribute occasionally a short treatise to the periodic publications of the Agricultural Department, to which indeed all along I forwarded a variety of information. I would beg however, that the request not be pressed for a few months, in as much, as the additional departmental duties for the Centennial Exhibition<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Centennial Exhibition, Melbourne, 1888-9.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>tax the energies of my establishment at present very much, and as it is also needful, that as early as ever possible the "Key to the system of Vict. plants"<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B88.11.02.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(now<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #000000; ">¾<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>printed) should be completed, and further the seventh Edition of the "select plants for industrial culture and naturalisation" should be in its enlarged form, (to be complete to the date of newest observations and discoveries), be speedily also brought out, so as not only to be available to ruralist, technologists and others, but also for the Jurors at the great forthcoming Exhibition.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B88.12.01.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Indeed I would respectfully submit for your favorable consideration the desirability, that the Agricultural Department should avail itself of the facility, which can be afforded, while the Gov. Botanists Department finds the monetary means, through your liberality, for setting up the typography of the "select plants," to have a supply of extra-copies rolled off at the Gov. Printing Office, so that this plain, handy and comprehensive volume may come more generally into the hands of ruralists (particularly in connection with your extensive system of irrigation), than other wise would be the case. Furthermore it seems to me advisable, that also the Educational Department seize on the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>present chance, to get for each state-school an impression provided, at a very much reduced expense, of the select plants for reference, as this work will be of real practical interest to every colonist and therefore also to each teacher and his disciples. I am however sure, that unless some extra- or special means be provided by the Agricult. and Educat. Dep. for the purchase of paper and the labor of rolling off, my own establishments interest will suffer by great retardation of the issue of the new Edition.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 18 May, Wilson forwarded M's letter to the Minister of Agriculture who replied on 29 May recommending 'that an extra number of Baron von Muellers work on Select plants be printed for distribution to Libraries Agricul[tura]l Societies, Clubs &amp;c.' Wilson then<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on 2 June forwarded M's letter to the Minister of Public Instruction 'with regard to the suggestion concerning the requirements of his Department'. His Under Secretary replied on 6 June saying that the 'question of supplying schools with the new edition of "Select Plants &amp;c" was lately considered by Professor Pearson at the instance of Baron von Mueller. As however the schools have been supplied with an earlier edition of the work, and we have still some 200 copies [on] hand, it was not deemed necessary to incur the expense of providing another copy for each school.' The file was forwarded to M for his information on 9 June. He replied on 21 June: 'Papers now returned, as matters are now finally arranged'.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be, Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gov. Botanist.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
