<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cooktown ¶ 10 December 1888.  ¶ Highly esteemed Baron ¶ My expedition in the interior of New Guinea has, thank goodness, been crowned with the uttmost success, thanks to the extensive help given to me...</title>
            <author>Hugo Zöller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1888/88-12-10b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>88.12.10b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Hugo Zöller</author>
               <title>Cooktown ¶ 10 December 1888.  ¶ Highly esteemed Baron ¶ My expedition in the interior of New Guinea has, thank goodness, been crowned with the uttmost success, thanks to the extensive help given to me...</title>
               <date when="1888-12-10">1888-12-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1888/88-12-10b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Cooktown ¶ 10 December 1888.  ¶ Highly esteemed Baron ¶ My expedition in the interior of New Guinea has, thank goodness, been crowned with the uttmost success, thanks to the extensive help given to me...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">88.12.10b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Hugo Zöller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="">‘</seg>Kaiser Wilhelms-Land’, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 26 December 1888, p. 2. <seg style="">The extract was introduced: </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">Dem Herrn Baron von Müller in Melbourne verdanken wir folgenden ihm zugesandten Bericht des bekannten und auch uns befreundeten vortrefflichen Berichterstatters der “Kölnischen Zeitung", Herrn Hugo Zöller, über eine neue Forschungsreise im deutschen Teil Neu-Guineas. Die geographischen Erfolgesind für die Wissenschaft sehr wichtig und wertvoll, und Herr Baron von Müller sagt in seinem liebenswürdigen Begleitschreiben an uns u. a.: “Ich bin ganz stolz darauf, die Anregung in einer längeren Unterredung mit dem ausgezeichneten Herrn Hugo Zöller gegeben zu haben, dass nun auch das Hochland im deutschen Gebiet erstiegen wurde." </seg>Herrn Zöller's Bericht lautet, wie folgt:’</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[We have to thank Baron von Mueller in Melbourne for the following report on a new expedition in the German part of New Guinea sent to him by the well-known and excellent reporter of the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Köllnischer Zeitung</seg>
                     <seg style="">,</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>
                     <seg style="">Mr Hugo Zöller, who is also a friend of ours. The geographical results are very important and valuable for science and Baron von Mueller said in his kind accompanying letter to us </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">[letter not found] </seg>
                     <seg style="">among other things: “I am quite proud of having given the stimulus in a long conversation with the excellent Mr Hugo Zöller that now the highland in the German region has been climbed.” Mr Zöller’s report runs as follows:].</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">Cooktown, 10. Dezember 1888.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter Herr Baron.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meine Expedition im Innern Neu-Guineas ist, Gott sei</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Dank, vom vollständigsten Erfolge gekrönt gewesen, Dank der</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">weitgehenden Hülfe, die mir seitens der Neu-Guinea Kompanie</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">zutheil geworden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Aufgebrochen bin ich von Constantin-Hafen mit 3 weissen</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Begleitern, 21 bewaffneten Neu-Britanniern (einem Teil der Polizeitruppe) und einer wechselnden Anzahl einheimischer Lastträger. In der ersten Zeit zählte die Expedition, die genau einen Monat in Anspruch nahm, gegen 100 Köpfe, später wegen Desertion viel weniger.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">In 15 Gewaltmärschen haben wir rund 230 Kilometer zurückgelegt, haben über ein Drittel (beinahe zwei Fünftel) der Breite von Kaiser Wilhelm's Land durchquert, und uns dann zur Küste zurück wendend den Kamm der höchsten Kette des Finisterre-Gebirges (wolverstanden</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg style="">wohlverstanden.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> nicht den höchsten Gipfel) in einer Höhe von 2660 Meter erreicht.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hätten wir noch ein halbes Dutzend Säcke Reis mehr gehabt, so hätten wir Mount Gladstone, der dicht vor uns lag (also einen der beiden höchsten Gipfel des Finisterre) unschwer erreichen können.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Fernblick landeinwärts war unbeschreiblich grossartig. Das Bismarck-Gebirge scheint das wahre und wirkliche Rückgrat von Neu-Guinea zu sein. Es zieht sich in ungeheurem Bogen, mit seinen Ausläufern die Westseite der Astrolabe-Bai berührend, ungefähr längs der englischen Grenze in der Richtung nach dem Hüon-Golfe hin. Zwischen Finisterre- und Bismarck-Gebirge sahen wir im Süden ein anderes gewaltiges jedenfalls über 10,000 Fuss hohes, aber doch noch von den dahinter sich weiterziehenden Gipfeln des Bismarck-Gebirges überragtes Bergsystem. Da es bisher unbekannt geblieben, wurde es nach dem derzeitigen Landeshauptmann Kraetke-Gebirge getauft. Den höchsten Gipfel des Bismarck-Gebirges, auf dem wir Schnee zu sehen glaubten, wollte der Landeshauptmann “Otto Berg" getauft wissen. Drei andere Gipfel sollen Marienberg, Wilhelmsberg und Herbertberg heissen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Finisterre-Gebirge tritt nicht, wie bisher fälschlich angenommen wurde, an die Küste heran. Küstengebirge und Flnisterre sind vielmehr durch ein gewaltiges Thal und niedriges Hügelgelände vollkommen getrennt.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Küstengebirge besteht aus Kalk. Sandstein und Conglomeraten. An drei Punkten fand ich Versteinerungen. Das Finisterre-Geblrge ist ganz vulkanisch, verdankt aber seine heutige Gestalt nicht der vulkanischen Thätigkeft sondern der Erosion.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finisterre ist furchtbar steil. Der letzte zweitägige Ansteig war das Lebensgefährlichste, was ich je durchgemacht. Wir Alle bluteten von Stürzen und Rissen. Unter den Schwarzen hatten wir 6 Fieberkranke und durch Wunden Erschöpfte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Oben in ungefähr 9000 Fuss Höhe zeigte das Thermometer nachts 8° und morgens zwischen 6 und 7 Uhr 10° Celsius.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Eingeborenen haben uns zweimal, wohl mehr, weil sie</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">erschreckt waren, als aus Feindseligkeit, in kindischer Weise angegriffen, ohne dass wir aber, da niemand verletzt wurde, von den Schiesswaffen Gebrauch gemacht hätten. Die Bewohner des Küstengebirges erwiesen sich als gänzlich unzuverlässige Führer, waren aber sonst freundlich. Hinter dem Küstengebirge kömmt ein gänzlich unbewohnter Landstrich. Dann folgen die Binnenlandsstämme, die wohl nie von Weissen gehört hatten. Das Land ist äusserst dünn bevölkert, und höher als 4200 Fuss</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">haben wir keinerlei Spuren der Eingeborenen (bis aufwärts 9000 Fuss) mehr gesehen. Es scheint also, dass auch der ganze höher gelegene Teil des Finisterre unbewohnt ist.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Grenze des Baumwuchses haben wir nicht erreicht. Dieselbe muss ausserordentlich hoch liegen, sehr viel höher als beispielsweise beim Kamerungebirge in West-Afrika. Denn den Mount Gladstone im Finisterre, dessen Höhe allerdings geringer ist als die englische Seekarte fie angiebt (wir schätzten ihn auf unter 10,000 engl. Fuss) sahen) sahen wir bis zum Gipfel hinauf mit Buschwald bedeckt. Blos an den steilen Gehängen des Finisterre ist die Vegetation verkrüppelt. Die Spitzen des Kraetke- und des Bismarck-Gebirges schienen, durch ein ausgezeichnetes Fernrohr betrachtet, vollkommen kahl zu sein. In 9000 Fuss Höhe waren die Rücken des Finisterre mit hochstämmigem moosbekleideten Laubwald bestanden, (Nadelhölzer sahen wir nicht); aber blos mit Jungholz, die alten Riesenstämme lagen modern am Boden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Etwas weiter unten wurde die Szenerie am meisten durch eine überaus häufig vorkommende Feigenart mit grünen Früchten von der Form und Grösse einer Apfelsine beeinflusst.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Jagd war trotz vieler Casuar-Spuren, je höher wir kamen, desto weniger ergiebig.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin zurückgerufen worden (im Begriffe stehend, eine zweite Expedition anzutreten) um mich, der dort ausgebrochenen Unruhen wegen, so schnell als möglich nach Ostafrika zu begeben. Bis zum 20. Dezember bleibe ich hier in Cooktown.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hugo Zöller.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Cooktown<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Qld.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">10 December 1888. </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">Highly esteemed Baron</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My expedition in the interior of New Guinea has, thank goodness, been crowned with the uttmost success, thanks to the extensive help given to me on the part of the New Guinea Company.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The commercial enterprise that spearheaded he establishment of a German protectorate over northeastern New Guinea and the New Britain archipelago.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I departed from Constantin Harbour with three white companions, 21 armed New Britains (a part of the police troup) and a changing number of native bearers. At first the expedition, which occupied exactly a month, numbererd about 100 head, later on account of desertion much fewer.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We covered around 230 kilometers in 15 forced marches, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>traversed over a third (nearly two fifths) of the width of Kaiser Wilhelms Land and then wending our way back to the coast reached the crest of the highest range of the Finisterre Range at a height of 2660 meters (mind you not the highest point).</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Had we had another half a dozen sacks of rice more, we could have easily reached Mount Gladstone, which lay close before us (therefore one of the two highest peaks of the Finisterre).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The distant view inland was indescribably magnificant. The Bismark Range seems to be the true and actual backbone of New Guinea. It stretches in a huge curve, with its foothills touching the west side of Astrolabe Bay, approximately along the British border in the direction of the Huon Gulf. In the south between the Finisterre and Bismark Ranges we saw another massive, at any rate over 10,000 foot high, mountain system, but yet still towered over by the peaks of the Bismark Range extending further behind them. Since it remained unknown until now, it was named after the present governor of the province Kraetke Range. The governor wanted to have the highest point of the Bismarck Range, on which we thought to see snow, named Mount Otto. Three other peaks were to be called Marienberg, Wilhelmsberg and Herbertberg.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Finisterre Range does not go up to the coast as was hitherto falsely assumed. Coastal range and Finisterre Range are rather completely separated by a vast valley and low hilly country.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The coastal range consists of limestone, sandstone and conglomerate. I found fossils at three points. The Finisterre Range is completely volcanic, but owes it present form not to volcanic activity but to erosion.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finisterre is awfully steep. The last two-day climb was the most life-threatening that I have ever experienced. We were all bleeding from falls and scratches. Among the Blacks we had six sick from fever and exhaustion from wounds.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Up at about 9000 feet the thermometer indicated 8° at night and 10° Celsius between 6 and 7 am.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The natives attacked us twice in a childlike manner, probably more because they were afraid than from hostility, but without us having to make use of the guns because no one was injured. The inhabitants of the coastal range turned out to be completely untrustworthy guides, but otherwise were friendly. Behind the coastal range comes a completely uninhabited tract of country. Then follow the inland tribes, who probably never have heard of white people. The country is very thinly populated and higher than 4200 feet we no longer saw any traces of the natives (up to 9000 feet). It seems therefore that the whole higher-situated part of the Finisterre is also uninhabited.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We did not reach the tree line. This must lie extraordinarily high, very much higher than for example the Kameroon Range in West Africa, as we saw Mount Gladstone in the Finisterre, the height of which admittedly is lower than the British marine chart shows it (we estimated it as under 10,000 English feet), clothed with brushwood up to the peak. The vegetation is stunted only on the steep slopes of the Finisterre.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The peaks of the Kraetke and Bismark Ranges, observed through an excellent telescope, seem to be completely bare. At 9000 feet the ridges of the Finisterre are covered with tall-trunked, moss-covered deciduous trees (we saw no conifers); but only young trees, the old giant trunks lay rotting on the ground.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Somewhat further down the scenery was influenced mostly by a species of fig with green fruits of the form and size of an orange occurring commonly everywhere.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The higher we came the less productive was the hunting in spite of many tracks of cassowaries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have been called back (on the point of starting a second expedition) to go to East Africa as quickly as possible on account of the unrest broken out there. I remain here in Cooktown up until 20 December.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With distingquished respect</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hugo Zöller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
