<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>14/12/94 ¶  ¶ This time, esteemed Mr Tepper, I am writing particularly to ask whether ¶  ¶ Atriplex semibaccatum ¶  ¶ is still common around Adelaide, in order to still get seeds of it, just as it was...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1894/94-12-14a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M198, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>94.12.14a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>14/12/94 ¶  ¶ This time, esteemed Mr Tepper, I am writing particularly to ask whether ¶  ¶ Atriplex semibaccatum ¶  ¶ is still common around Adelaide, in order to still get seeds of it, just as it was...</title>
               <date when="1894-12-14">1894-12-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1894/94-12-14a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plantnames</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Otto Tepper</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">14/12/94 ¶  ¶ This time, esteemed Mr Tepper, I am writing particularly to ask whether ¶  ¶ Atriplex semibaccatum ¶  ¶ is still common around Adelaide, in order to still get seeds of it, just as it was...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">94.12.14a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Otto Tepper</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M198, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style=""/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Tepper: 'Reply 19.12.94'. Letter not found.</p>
               </note>14/12/94</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Diesmal, geehrter Herr Tepper, schreibe ich besonders, um zu fragen, ob sich noch Atriplex semibaccatum häufig um Adelaide befindet, um Samen auch jetzt noch davon zu erlangen, wie es mir von 1847-1852 möglich war. Um Port Phillip ist die Pflanze durch die Ubermenge von Vieh fast ganz vernichtet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich zweifle an der Richtigkeit Ihrer Ansicht, dass der Pilz, auf welchem ein neues Genus gegründet wurde, für die Wissenschaft neu u auch nur das Genus standhaft sei. Es giebt nur einen Platz in der Welt, wo dies endgültig ermittelt werden kann, ob n.sp., u das ist Kew, wo sich eine vollstandige<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>vollständige.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Sammlung der Pilze, welche ich u Andere in Australien sammelten, befindet. Ob ein<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Genus</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>neu sei ist nur ein Wortspiel denn die Natur begründete nur Species nicht Genera. Begonia, Erica, Phyllanthus u viele andere genera wurden gelegentlich in eine Menge Genera getheilt, die alle wieder einginge. Ihre Erfahrungen in der Entomologie werden dieselben sein. Wenn man mit Kühnheit neue Genera u selbst neue Species aufstellt, ohne das vorhandene Material, wo immer es sich befindet, verglichen zu haben, fordert nicht die Wissenschaft. Vielleicht ist seitdem das neue Genus in Kew verglichen, etwa in der<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Grevillea</hi>
               </seg>, die ich nicht immer gleich bekomme.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun möchte ich im Vertrauen Sie als Deutscher noch um eine Gefälligkeit bitten, sollten Sie Ihren Weg klar sehen meinen Wunsch zu erfüllen. Vor einiger Zeit erschien in der Adel. deutsch. Zeitung eine Notiz über die jetzt bekannten Pflanzen Arten der ganzen Welt durch Berechnungen (einfach Aufzählungen nicht selbstständige Untersuchungen) des auch mir befreundeten Prof Saccardo in Padua, des universal Mycologen. Es ist begreiflich, dass eine genaue Aufzählung gar noch nicht gegeben werden kann, da wir selbst von vielen europäischen Arten die specifischen Grenzen nicht kennen, u täglich Neues in früher unerschlossenen Gegenden entdeckt wird. Dies Alles wissen Sie selbst, u practisch besonders aus der Insekt Kunde. Ich schrieb nach dem Lesen des Artikels eine kurze Notiz, wie sich die Zahlen stellten nach einer Durchstudirung von mir selbst für meine Präsidenten-Rede in der Melb. Meeting der Austral. Associat u veranlasse zoolog. Freunde mir auch eine Calculation für alle Thier-Klassen zu geben. Diese Notiz sandte ich in der freundlichsten Weise an die Redaction der deutchen Zeitung, aber<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>ich sah nichts erscheinen. Denn schrieb ich einen Brief an einen der Herausgeber. Auch dieser blieb unbeantwortet. Haben<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>meine Notiz im Druck gesehen? Ich mag solche bei den endlosen Arbeiten hier übersehen haben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seitdem ist mir der Gedanke gekommen, dass die Herren der dortigen Zeitung, trotz meiner bald 50 jährigen Freundschaft mit Dr. Mücke. Es mag sein, dass Ärger entstand, dass das Consular Jubileum hier gefeiert so ausführlich in der neuer deutsche Zeitung besprochen wurde. Das geschah einfach, weil aus eignene Antrieb die Sydney Zeitung einer deutschen Stenographen beim Fest hatte, der meine<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">freie</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>nicht geschriebene Rede in Zeichenschrift nieder schrieb u so dasjenige der anderen Sprecher. Sie sehen Hr Basedow doch ja zuweilen. Würden Sie gütig ihm dies erklären? Wenn ich aber ganz notizlos bleiben soll, wenn ich mich der Adelaider Zeitung nähere, ohne den geringsten Grund von meiner Seit, denn würde mich in Zukunft das Lesen der Zeitung nicht mehr erfreuen können, u stets unangenehme Gefühle hervorrufen, u ich wäre denn wohl am Besten, wenn ich die vieljährige ununterbrochen Subscription aufgebe.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend der Ihre u mit besten Festgruss</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14/12/94</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This time, esteemed Mr Tepper, I am writing particularly to ask whether<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Atriplex semibaccatum</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is still common around Adelaide, in order to still get seeds of it, just as it was possible for me from 1847-1852. Around Port Phillip<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>ie. Port Phillip Bay, Vic.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the plant is almost completely exterminated through the overcrowding of stock.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I doubt the correctness of your opinion that the fungus, on which a new genus was founded, is new to science and even if the genus is firm.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to O. Tepper, 7 November 1894.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>There is only one place in the world where this can be ascertained conclusively whether a new species and that is Kew, where there is a complete collection of fungi that I and others collected in Australia. Whether a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">genus</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is new is only a play on words since nature founded only species not genera.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Begonia</seg>,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Erica</seg>,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Phyllanthus</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and many other genera were occasionally divided into a large number of genera that all expired again. Your experiences in entomology will be the same. If one erects new genera and even new species with boldness, without having material to hand for comparison, wherever it is found, it does not support science. Perhaps the new genus has been compared since then in Kew, for instance in the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Grevillea</seg>,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The journal founded by M. C. Cooke and continued from 1892 by G. Massee.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that I do not always get immediately.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now in confidence I want to ask you as a German again for a favour, should you see your way clear to fulfil my wish. Some time ago a note appeared in the Adelaide<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>German newspaper about the plant species now known for the whole world through calculations (simply enumerations not independent investigations) of Professor Saccardo in Padua, the universal mycologist, who is also a friend of mine. It is understandable that an exact enumeration cannot yet be given at all, since we do not even know the specific boundaries of many European species, and daily new things are discovered in previously unexploited regions. All this you know yourself and practically especially from insect study. I wrote a short note after reading the article, how the numbers stood after a thorough study by myself for my presidential address in the Melbourne meeting of the Australasian Association<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B90.13.01.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and also arranged for zoological friends to give me a calculation for all classes of animals. I sent this note in the friendliest manner to the editor of the German newspaper, but I did not see anything published. Then I wrote a letter to one of the publishers. This also remained unanswered. Have<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>seen my note in print? I may have overlooked it with the endless work here.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">The letter was published in October. See M to editor of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>4 October 1894</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">, in this edition as 94-10-04a (B94.10.06)</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since then the thought has come to me that the gentlemen of the newspaper there, despite my soon 50-year friendship with Dr Mücke,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn7" n="8">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sentence incomplete.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>may be<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>annoyed<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that the Consular Jubilee celebrated here was discussed so thoroughly in the new German newspaper.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn8" n="9">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. W. Brahe<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>was presented with an illuminated address to celebrate his 25 years as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>German consul<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on 13 June 1894 (<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>14 June 1894, p. 6). M was one of among 'several hundred' who signed the address, and was one of the speakers. His address was published in the Sydney weekly<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Deutsch-Australische Post</seg>, 23 June 1894, p. 6 (B94.06.05).<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>M was one of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">organisers</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the occasion; see the advertisement in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(Melbourne)</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">, 17 February 1894, p. 11<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">(</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">in this edition as 94-02-00f</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">)</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(B94.012.06)</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>This simply occurred because the Sydney newspaper on its own initiative had a German stenographer at the celebration, who wrote down my<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">free</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>not written speech in shorthand, and also that of the other speakers. You certainly see Mr Basedow occasionally. Would you kindly explain this to him? However, if, without the slightest reason on my part,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I am to remain completely note-less<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>if I approach the Adelaide newspaper, then in future the reading of the newspaper would no longer please me and always call up unpleasant feelings, and it would then probably be best if I gave up the many years'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>unbroken subscription.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully and with best season's greetings</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Atriplex semibaccatum</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Begonia</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Erica</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Phyllanthus</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
