<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>25 June 1865. ¶  ¶ In keeping with my promise, noble friend, I take the liberty of informing you of the progress of the ladies' search for Leichhardt. These worthy representatives of this glorious ent...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-06-25e-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.06.25e</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>25 June 1865. ¶  ¶ In keeping with my promise, noble friend, I take the liberty of informing you of the progress of the ladies' search for Leichhardt. These worthy representatives of this glorious ent...</title>
               <date when="1865-06-25">1865-06-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-06-25e-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">25 June 1865. ¶  ¶ In keeping with my promise, noble friend, I take the liberty of informing you of the progress of the ladies' search for Leichhardt. These worthy representatives of this glorious ent...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">65.06.25e</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS letterhead: 'Ladies | Leichardt | Search | Committee'. MS annotation by Petermann: 'Erh. 23. Aug. 1865' [Received 23 August 1865]. The first part of the letter, ‘Gemäss meines Versprechens … grosser geographischer Entdeckung’, was published by Petermann; see B65.11.07. For a published version of the entire letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 69-72.</p>
               </note>25/6/65.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gemäss meines Versprechens, edler Freund, erlaube ich mir, Sie von den Fortschritten der Damen für Leichhardts Aufsuchung zu unterrichten. Die hehren Vertreterinnen dieser glorreichen Unternehmung haben unermüdlich gewirkt u. so bereits gegen £1000.-.- als Privatbeiträge für die Expedition gesammelt u durch ihre Vorstellungen von den Regierungen Südaustraliens, Queensland's u Victoria's das Versprechen der Mithülfe erwirkt. Obwohl nun der Fond für eine zweijährige Forschung noch nicht ganz gesichert, so haben sich doch die Damen des Committees hinlänglich unterstützt gefühlt, um die Parthie zu organisiren u den Befehlshaber zu erwählen. Auf Mr Duncan M'Intyre, den Mann der uns die neuen Anzeichen von Leichhardts Lagern brachte, fiel die Wahl, welche eine sehr glückliche zu nennen. Dr J. Murray, ein talentvoller Arzt, der auch als Naturforscher wirken wird u sich bereits in Howitts Reise auszeichnete, hat sich der Expedition angeschlossen. Die Parthie wird aus wenigstens 8 Leuten bestehen, von denen 2 Eingeborne sein werden. 14 Dromedare u eine bedeutende Anzahl Pferde bilden die Lastthiere. Die Caravane wird schon in nächster Woche aufbrechen u vom Darling Flusse aus nach dem Flinders River ziehen, wohin von einem Hafen der tropischen Ostküste Lebensmittel gesandt werden sollen. Ich zweifle nicht, dass M'Intyre seine Aufgabe ehrenvoll lösen wird. Dass von Leichhardts Begleitern irgend einer oder der Arme selbst noch am Leben sei kann ich kaum hoffen; dass aber durch sorgsame Nachfrage unter den Eingebornen das Schicksal der Verschollenen ermittelt werden <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">könne</hi>
               </seg> erliegt auch nicht den geringsten Zweifel. Vielleicht ist es den von den Damen Ausgesandten vorbehalten die Pläne Leichhardts, den grossen Westen Australiens zu durchdringen, bei dieser Suchung durchzuführen. Vielleicht wirft die Entdeckung von neuen Goldfeldern, reichen Kupferminen, ausgedehnten Weideländereien auf das Unternehmen einen erhöhten Glanz. Vielleicht wird es uns durch diese Forschungsreise zuerst völlig klar, durch welchen Theil Australiens die erste Telegraphlinie gezogen werden solle, um uns mit Europa in Contact zu bringen. Wir stehen hier noch immer am Vorabend grosser geographischer Entdeckungen; daher richtet sich unser Blick auch auf Sie zum Beistand, auf Sie einen der leuchtendsten u. gefeiertsten Geographen den je die Welt sah, auf einen Mann der reger für die Erdbeschreibung wirkte denn kaum irgend einer der lebt oder vor Ihnen lebte. Dass Sie uns Ihr helfenden u. rathendes Wort nicht entziehen werden, dessen sind wir gewiss; aber, edler Herr, Sie könnten <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mehr</hi>
               </seg> noch für uns thun. Sie haben es vielleicht noch in Ihrer Macht, den Damen, die sich so aufopfernd dieser heiligen Sache unterzogen, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">die Fürsprache der hohen Königin Englands</hi>
               </seg> zu erwirken! — Vielleicht erreichen diese Zeilen Sie gerade, während die verehrte Herrscherin das Denkmal ihres grossen zu früh dahingeschiedenen Gatten enthüllt in dessen Geburtsstadt, u. so möchte es Ihnen möglich sein, durch seine Hoheit den Herzog oder durch Ihre Hoheit die Herzogin, an welche sich die Damen bittend gewandt, von der Königin Victoria die Gnade zu erringen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mit einigen wenigen eigenhändigen ermunternden und beifälligen Worten</hi>
               </seg> diesem Suchungsunternehmen der Damen das höchste Patronat zuzuführen. Welch' eine Stütze würde dies für das Unternehmen sein! Ich wage dies direct auszusprechen u. zu erbitten, denn während wir alle das edelherzige Schalten u die erhabenen Gesinnungen Ihrer Majestät kennen, möchte es der Königin vielleicht unbekannt bleiben, wieviel Hülfe für mehrere Jahre der Suchung noch zuzuwenden sei u. wie durch ein freundliches Wort unserer Herrscherin die Apathie mancher unserer im Überfluss lebenden Colonisten gebrochen u reiche Hülfe den Damen wie durch einen Zauber-Schlag zugeführt werden würde! — Es ist ja noch ganz ungewiss, ob 2 Jahre zur Aufsuchung hinreichen: Falls Leichhardts Parthie im fernen westlichen Innern Australiens erlag, dann mag es 4-6 Jahre kosten, ehe wir seines Schicksals inne werden. Dann aber wird die Damen Expedition auch eine viel weiter leuchtende Helle auf das Innere werfen als eine schnell dahinziehende einfache Forschungs-Expedition. Der Vertreter Ihrer Majestät hat auch hier seine Huld dem Plane der Damen zugewandt, u so hat Sir Charles Darling mir aus freien Stücken vor wenigen Tagen £10.-.- für das Unternehmen begleitet von einem sehr freundlichen Briefe zugesandt. O! seien Sie gütig u rufen Sie die freundliche Hülfe des edlen Herzogs, der durch sein Wirken für Dr Vogel u durch seine Anregung der Expeditionen ins Innere Nordafrikas so glanzvoll in der Geschichte der Geographie dasteht, für uns an! Wir wollen ja das grosse Innere dieses mächtigen Welttheiles, der Englands grösstes Gut ist, der Civilisation erschliessen, damit die verhungernden u verfrierenden Armen Englands neue glückliche Heimathen finden! und dem Unternehmungsgeist u Talent des Mutterlandes u des jungen australischen Reiches neue Wirkungskreise eröffnet würden. Wir wollen ja dann auch künftigen Reisenden die erhebende Versicherung einflössen, dass wenn sie auf dem Felde der Forschung erliegen, man nicht rücksichtslos u ihrer uneingedenk bleiben werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Verehrungsvoll und dankbar der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">What follows is on a separate sheet and may not be part of this letter. The sheet is annotated by Petermann: 'Erh. 23. Aug. 1865.' [Received 23 August 1865.]</p>
               </note>Mit dem vor einigen Tagen absegelnden Schiffe, Sussex, habe ich in einer an Dr W Sonder in Hamburg beförderten Kiste, eine Anzahl statistischer Schriften, die ich mir von unserm Registrar General für Sie erbeten, abgesandt u den Gazetteer als eigene Gabe beigefügt. Diese Schriften werden Ihnen in etwa 3 Monat zugänglich sein. Ich habe seitdem den neuen Band der transact. of the phil Society of Victoria für Sie bereit liegen. Der 5. Band meiner Fragmenta, viel Neues u Merkwürdiges aus der Pflanzenwelt Nordaustraliens bringend wird wohl im Lauf dieses Jahres vollendet werden. Hoffentlich sind Ihnen der 4 Band u die Lithogramme über Paris zugegangen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass der prachtvolle Orden, mit dem Ihr königlicher Herr mich geziert hat, zwei Monat nach dem Decret der Ritterwürde angekommen theilte ich Ihnen mit voriger Post bereits mit.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 June 1865.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In keeping with my promise, noble friend, I take the liberty of informing you of the progress of the ladies' search for Leichhardt. These worthy representatives of this glorious enterprise have worked indefatigably and thus have already collected about £1000 as private contributions for the expedition, and through their representations have obtained the pledge of aid from the Governments of South Australia, Queensland, and Victoria. Although the funds for a two years' exploration are not yet completely secured, the ladies of the Committee have yet felt sufficiently supported to organize the party and elect the leader. The choice fell on Mr Duncan McIntyre, the man who brought us the new traces of Leichhardt's camp sites, it can be called a very happy choice. Dr J. Murray, a talented doctor who will also function as naturalist, and who already distinguished himself on Howitt's journey,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Alfred William Howitt (1830-1908) had been in charge of a relief party for the Burke &amp; Wills Exploring Expedition in 1861 and eventually brought their remains back to Melbourne.</p>
               </note> has joined the expedition. The party will consist of at least 8 men, two of them will be aborigines. 14 dromedaries and a considerable number of horses comprise the pack animals. The party is to depart already next week, and travel from the Darling River to the Flinders River;<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Darling River, NSW; Flinders River, Qld.</p>
               </note> the food supplies are to be transported there from a harbour on the tropical east coast. I have no doubt that McIntyre will discharge his task honourably. I can hardly hope, that one of Leichhardt's companions or the poor man himself may still be alive, but there is not the slightest doubt that the fate of the missing travellers <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">can</hi>
               </seg> be ascertained by careful enquiries among the natives. Perhaps it will be reserved to the ladies' emissaries to carry out Leichhardt's plans and penetrate the large western part of Australia in the course of their search. Perhaps the discovery of new gold fields, rich copper mines, extensive pasture lands, will give added lustre to the venture. Perhaps this exploring expedition will for the first time show us quite clearly through which part of Australia the first telegraph line is to be laid to bring us into contact with Europe. We still stand on the edge of great geographical discoveries here; therefore our eyes turn to you for assistance, to you, one of the most illustrious and most celebrated geographers the world has ever known, to a man who has worked more actively for geography than hardly anyone else living now or gone before you. We are certain that you will not deprive <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>us of your words of help and advice; but, noble Sir, you could do still <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">more</hi>
               </seg> for us. It lies, perhaps, in your power to obtain for the ladies who give themselves so unselfishly to this sacred task, the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">patronage of the august Queen of England</hi>
               </seg>. Perhaps these lines will reach you just at the time when the revered Sovereign unveils the memorial to her great much too soon departed late husband in his home town,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Albert of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, Prince Consort of Queen Victoria of England, who died on 14 December 1861.</p>
               </note> and you might then have an opportunity to obtain through His Highness the Duke, or through Her Highness, the Duchess,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Duke Ernst II of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, eldest brother of Prince Albert, and his wife, Duchess Alexandrine, née Princess of Baden. Petermann addressed the Duchess with a brief description of the search expedition, which had been brought to the attention of Queen Victoria by the Ladies' Committee, and then added: 'May I now for the same reasons and from my deepest conviction most warmly commend this matter to the gracious sympathy and support of Your Highness.' (Draft copy, Petermann to the Duchess Alexandrine of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, 29 August 1865; <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt).</p>
               </note> to whom the ladies have appealed, the favour from Queen Victoria of bestowing the grace of her most august patronage on the ladies' search expedition <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">with a few encouraging and approving words from her own hand</hi>
               </seg>. What a support that would be for the enterprise! I dare to express and ask this openly, for although we all know her high-minded rule and lofty sentiments, the Queen may perhaps not know how much has to be expended for several years of searching, and how through a favourable word from our Sovereign the apathy of many of our colonists, who live in abundance, would be shattered, and rich aid would flow to the ladies as if by the waving of a magic wand. After all, it is still quite uncertain whether two years will suffice for the search. If Leichhardt's party perished in the far western interior of Australia, it may take 4 to 6 years before we discover his fate. But in that case the Ladies' Expedition would afford a much greater illumination of the Australian interior than a fast-advancing ordinary exploring expedition. The representative of Her Majesty here has shown his graciousness towards the plan of the ladies, and thus Sir Charles Darling has voluntarily sent me £10 for the enterprise a few days ago, accompanied by a very kindly letter.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> Oh, be so kind and appeal to the noble Duke, who is such an illustrious figure in the history of geography through his activities for Dr Vogel and his encouragement of the expedition into the interior of North Africa,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Duke Ernst II was patron and keen supporter of the committee that administered the Heuglin Fund, instituted by Petermann to set up a German expedition to search for the missing Dr Eduard Vogel and explore the unknown regions in the interior of Africa.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to graciously help us! We want to open up the vast interior of this enormous continent that is England's greatest possession to civilisation, so that the starving and freezing poor of England can find new and happy homes, and that new fields of activity are opened up to the spirit of enterprise and the talents of the mother country and for the young Australian realm. And we also want to impart to future explorers the edifying assurance that, should they perish on the field of exploration, they will not be allowed to fade thoughtlessly from memory.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Respectfully and gratefully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sussex</seg>, that left a few days ago,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to E. Fenzl, 25 June 1865.</p>
               </note> I have sent you a few statistical publications that I requested from our Registrar General for you,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See W. H. Archer to M, 6 June 1865, sent by M as an enclosure with this letter.</p>
               </note> and added the gazetteer as my own gift, enclosed in a case dispatched to Dr Sonder in Hamburg. These publications should be available to you in about three months. I have since put aside for you the new volume of the Transactions of the Philosophical Society of Victoria.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">i.e. the Royal Society of Victoria.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The 5th volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>, containing much that is new and unusual from the plant world of northern Australia, should be completed in the course of this year. I hope the 4th volume and the lithograms<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B65.13.04.</p>
               </note> reached you over Paris.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to A. Petermann, 25 March 1865 (in this edition as 65-03-25a).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I already advised you by the last mail that the magnificent Order<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Knight's Cross II Class of the Ernestine House Order; see M to A. Petermann, 25 March 1865.</p>
               </note> with which your Sovereign Lord decorated me had arrived two months after the certificate of the Knighthood.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
