<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Editorial office of the Proceedings of Justus Perthes' Geographical Institute  ¶ Gotha. ¶ 25 March 1865. ¶ Esteemed Patron and friend, ¶  ¶ When these lines reach you, you will, I hope, have long ago ...</title>
            <author>August Petermann</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-03-25a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M1, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.03.25a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>August Petermann</author>
               <title>Editorial office of the Proceedings of Justus Perthes' Geographical Institute  ¶ Gotha. ¶ 25 March 1865. ¶ Esteemed Patron and friend, ¶  ¶ When these lines reach you, you will, I hope, have long ago ...</title>
               <date when="1865-03-25">1865-03-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-03-25a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
               <term>Times, Times</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>form text</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Editorial office of the Proceedings of Justus Perthes' Geographical Institute  ¶ Gotha. ¶ 25 March 1865. ¶ Esteemed Patron and friend, ¶  ¶ When these lines reach you, you will, I hope, have long ago ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">65.03.25a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M1, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">For a letterpress copy of this letter, see <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SP</seg>
                     <seg style="">A ARCH PGM 328, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt. For a published version of the letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 65-6.</p>
               </note>
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times, Times; ">Redaktion der Mittheilungen</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times, Times; ">aus Justus Perthes' Geographischer Anstalt.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times, Times; ">Gotha,</seg> 25. März <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times, Times; ">18</seg>65.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrtester Gönner und Freund, </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn diese Zeilen bei Ihnen eingehen, werden Sie längst wie ich hoffe, direkt durch den Staats-Minister von Seebach, den Orden für Kunst und Wissenschaft, die höchste Dekoration, über die unser Herzog für wissenschaftliches Verdienst zu verfügen hat, erhalten haben. Sofort beim Eingang Ihrer gütigen grossen Sendung für das Herzogliche Museum machte ich den Herzog mit Ihren neuen Spenden, Verdiensten und unbegrenztem Wohlwollen bekannt, bei welcher Gelegenheit es ihm eine innige Freude war, Ihnen dieses Zeichen seiner aufrichtigen Huld und freundschaftlichen Gesinnung gegen Sie zugehen zu lassen. Auch Ihre anregende und originelle Composition des Schiller'schen Gedichtes Cassandra hat ihn höchlichst interessirt, und wird ihn vielleicht veranlassen, Ihrem Wunsche in dieser Richtung weiter zu gehen, Folge zu leisten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Für Ihre grosse Güte gegen mich, mit der Sie mich unausgesetzt mit Sendungen von Schriften und Karten bereichern kann ich Ihnen meinen innigsten und verbindlichsten Dank nur in schwachen Worten lallen, verzeihen Sie mir nur, dass dieses nicht öfter geschieht, aber Sie wissen schon, was für ein schlechter und undankbarer Correspondent ich bin, und wie sehr auch in der That meine Zeit in Anspruch genommen ist. Jedoch Ihr letzter gütiger mit der heutigen Post angelangter Brief in Bezug auf die Spuren des edlen unglücklichen Leichhardt würde es wie ein Verbrechen erscheinen lassen, wenn ich Ihnen nicht mit umgehender Post sagte, wie glücklich ich mich schätze, Ihren Wunsch in dieser Angelegenheit zu erfüllen, und öffentlich mich in dem von Ihnen gewünschten Sinne auszusprechen. Ich lasse noch heute einen entsprechenden Artikel zum Druck gehen und hoffe Ihnen Abzug mit der nächsten Post zugehen lassen zu können. Da ich jedoch glaube, es wird Ihnen angenehm sein, wenn ich es nicht bei einem einzigen Artikel bewenden lasse, sondern möglichst bald einen zweiten folgen lasse, wo möglich mit illustrirender Karte, welche mehr als Worte zum Auge spricht, und desshalb sofort Eindruck macht,— so möchte ich Sie ergebenst bitten, mir ein Exemplar des <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">vollständigen</hi>
               </seg> Journals der so überaus wichtigen &amp; interessanten Reise des Herrn McIntyre zu verschaffen und schleunigst zusenden zu wollen, damit ich dasselbe als Grundlage weiterer Mittheilungen über diesen wichtigen Gegenstand machen kann. Vielleicht in Ihrer gewöhnlichen Voraussicht u. Güte haben Sie meinen Wunsch schon längst anticipirt, ehe diese Zeilen in Ihre Hände gelangen. Erscheint etwa von McIntyre´s Reise eine Originalkarte, so würde auch diese für mich von hohem Interesse sein.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit meinem innigsten Dank für Ihre grossmüthigen Sendungen darf ich nicht unerwähnt lassen, dass ich seit meinem Briefe vom 27. April 1864 deren drei erhielt, am 30. April, 5. &amp; 10. Dezember; diejenige vom 5. Dez. begriff die an das herzogl Museum in sich, — so dass ich, wie es scheint, derjenigen per Lincolnshire<seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>in der nächsten Zeit noch gewärtig sein kann. Drücken Sie gelegentlich den edlen Männern, die mich auf Ihren Wunsch, so liberal mit australischen Publikationen beglücken, meinen innigsten Dank aus, besonders auch dem Hrn Wadsworth; ich nahm Gelegenheit, in einem der beiden öffentlichen Arctic letters to Sir R. Murchison, von denen ich Ihnen unlängst ein Ex.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Exemplar.</p>
               </note> zugehen liess, mich über die grosse Wichtigkeit des von dem Victorian Government publicirten Prachtbandes des Flagstaff Observatory öffentlich auszusprechen, und werde es wiederholt thun.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auf Ihre direkte Anfrage wegen Ihres trefflichen Werkes Fragm. phyt. muss ich bemerken, dass ich den III. Bd. Ihrer Güte schulde, der I. &amp; II., sowie das neuere Werk über die Chatham Insel, auf welches ich sehr gespannt bin, gingen mir noch nicht zu.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wird Walker's Journal nicht vollständig im Druck erscheinen, und zu haben sein, — es ist eine im geographisch-topographischen Sinne so wichtige Reise.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit der Bitte, der gef<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">gefälligen.</p>
               </note> Beförderung der Einlagen und in der Hoffnung, dass Sie mir auch ferner das Glück Ihres mir so werthen Wohlwollens zu Theil werden lassen, bin ich in innigster Verehrung</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr treu ergebenster</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Petermann</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Editorial office of the Proceedings of Justus Perthes' Geographical Institute </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Gotha.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 March 1865.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Patron and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When these lines reach you, you will, I hope, have long ago received the Order for Art and Science<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Knight's Cross II. Class of the Ernestine House Order, bestowed on M on 5 January 1865. See R. von Seebach to M, 5 January 1865.</p>
               </note> directly through the Secretary of State von Seebach, the highest decoration for scientific merits our Duke<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Duke Ernst II of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha.</p>
               </note> has at his disposal. I acquainted the Duke with your latest donations, merits and limitless benevolence immediately on receiving your large kind consignment for the Ducal Museum, an occasion that made it a real pleasure for him to bestow on you this token of his sincere favour and friendly disposition. Your stimulating and ingenious composition of Schiller's poem Cassandra<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to A. Petermann, 26 August 1864. M's composition has not been found.</p>
               </note> has also been of great interest to him, and perhaps it will induce him to proceed in the direction you desire.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I can only stammer in inadequate words my sincerest and most courteous thanks for your great kindness towards me, with which you continuously enrich me by transmissions of publications and maps. Please forgive me that this does not happen more often, but you already know me for the bad and ungrateful correspondent that I am and also how many demands are indeed made on my time. However, your last kind letter, arrived by today's mail, regarding the traces of the noble and unfortunate Leichhardt, would make it a crime were I not to tell you by return mail how happy I am to fulfil your wish in this regard to speak up publicly in the vein suggested by you. Already today I have sent a relevant article to the printers and hope to be able to send you a copy with the next mail.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">'Neue Spuren der verschollenen Deutschen Reisenden Ludwig Liechhardt in Inneren von Australien', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen aus Justus Perthes' geographischer Austalt</seg>, March 1865, pp. 133-6.</p>
               </note> As I believe, however, that you would be pleased if I did not let the matter rest with just a single notice, but followed up as soon as possible with a second article, if possible with a map illustration that would attract the eye more than words and so would leave an immediate impression, I would sincerely ask you to obtain for me a copy of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">complete</hi>
               </seg> journal of the extremely important and interesting expedition of Mr McIntyre<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ladies' Leichhardt Search Expedition, 1865-6. M in due course did as requested and Petermann published a German-language narrative of the expedition, with a map, in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen aus Justus Perthes' geographischer Austalt</seg>, 1867, pp. 447-54; see M to A. Petermann, 24 November 1866. See also M to the Editor of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>, 22 November 1866.</p>
               </note> and speedily send it to me, so that I can make this the basis for further communications on this important subject. Perhaps you have already anticipated my wish with your usual foresight and kindness, even before these lines reach you. If an original map of McIntyre's travels is already being published, this would also be of the greatest interest to me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With my sincerest gratitude for your generous transmissions I must not omit to mention that since my letter of 27 April 1864 I have received three of them from you, on 30 April, 5 and 10 December—that on 5 December with an enclosure for the Ducal Museum so that, it seems, I must still expect that sent with the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Lincolnshire</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to A. Petermann, 24 January 1864 (in this edition as 64-01-24a), a packet with statistical documents and the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions of the Royal Society of Victoria</seg>, enclosed in a case to Sir William Hooker; M to A. Petermann, 25 July 1864 (in this edition as 64-07-25a), maps enclosed in a case to Sonder, sent by the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Suffolk</seg>; M to A. Petermann, 26 August 1864, a case sent by the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg> with the donation of zoological specimens for the Gotha Museum and miscellaneous other items for Petermann; M to A. Petermann, 26 November 1864, a parcel with publications enclosed in a case to Roeper, sent via Sonder by the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Lincolnshire</seg>.</p>
               </note> Please express, if the occasion arises, my sincerest gratitude to the noble gentlemen who so liberally supply me with Australian publications at your request, especially Mr Wadsworth. In one of the published Arctic letters to Sir Rod. Murchison<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen aus Justus Perthes’ Geographischer Anstalt</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 1865, pp. 99-104, 137-142</seg>. </p>
               </note> of which I recently sent you a copy, I used the opportunity to publicly voice my opinion, and shall do so repeatedly, of the great importance of the magnificent volume on the Flagstaff Observatory published by the Victorian Government.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Neumayer (1864).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On your direct enquiry regarding your excellent work <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg>, I must remark that I have the 3rd volume, thanks to your kindness, but the 1st and 2nd volumes, and also your recent work on the Chatham Islands<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B64.10.02.</p>
               </note> to which I am very much looking forward, have not yet arrived.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Is Walker's diary<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">F. Walker (1862).</p>
               </note> not going to appear in print complete? — it is such an important expedition from a geographic-topographical point of view.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With the request that you kindly forward the enclosures, and in the hope that you will allow me to enjoy the pleasure of your esteemed benevolence, I am with my deepest respect</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your most truly devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Petermann.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
