<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden ¶ 25 May 1865. ¶ Revered Baron, ¶  ¶ Your friend Madame Eliza King ¶  passed on to me recently your pleasing news about Dr Neumayer, and I was touched as pleasantly by the int...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-05-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Dokumentensammlung Darmstaedter 1921.26, Handschriftenabteilung, Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.05.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden ¶ 25 May 1865. ¶ Revered Baron, ¶  ¶ Your friend Madame Eliza King ¶  passed on to me recently your pleasing news about Dr Neumayer, and I was touched as pleasantly by the int...</title>
               <date when="1865-05-25">1865-05-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-05-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Uredo rubigo</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="56">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="44">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Justus von Liebig</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden ¶ 25 May 1865. ¶ Revered Baron, ¶  ¶ Your friend Madame Eliza King ¶  passed on to me recently your pleasing news about Dr Neumayer, and I was touched as pleasantly by the int...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">65.05.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Justus von Liebig</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Dokumentensammlung Darmstaedter 1921.26, Handschriftenabteilung, Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25 Mai 1865.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrter Herr Baron.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihre Freundin Madame Eliza King hat vor Kurzem mir Ihre erfreuliche Nachricht über Herrn Dr Neumayer mitgetheilt, welche mich ebenso angenehm berührte in der Wahrnehmung der Anerkennung dieses wissenschaftlich strebsamen Mannes als in der Freundlichkeit mit welcher Sie sich meiner erinnern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gewiss werden Sie das Unternehmen der Damen unseres Staates, den armen Leichhardt aufsuchen zu lassen, mit Theilnahme verfolgen. Innerhalb der nächsten Wochen werden £1000 für den Zweck gesammelt sein u mehrere der Regierungen Australiens haben bereits ihre Beihülfe zugesagt. Die freundliche Begutachtung von hochstehenden Männer der Wissenschaft in Europa ist für das Gelingen des Unternehmens von Wichtigkeit um unsere Colonisten zur thatsächlichen Unterstützung dieser schönen Sache anzuspornen. Die Damen nach eignem Erachten haben sich auch an die Königin Victoria, u an die Prinzessin von Wales gewandt Hülfe erbittend, auch an die Princessin von Preussen, da Leichhardt diesem Lande angehörte. Je grösser die Beiträge sind um so versprechender können die Mittel für dies Unternehmen gewählt und um so länger dasselbe ausgedehnt werden. Es ist keinem Zweifel unterworfen, dass das Schicksal Leichhardts erkundet werden wird durch diese Bewegung der hochherzigen Damen; es hängt aber von den Mahnungen hochstehender Männer und von den daraus erwachsenden Hülfsmitteln ab, ob die Such-Parthie, Duncan M'Intyre wird wahrscheinlich Führer sein alsbald ins Feld ziehn kann. Vermuthlich aber wird diese Expedition gerade das vollbringen, was der arme Verlorene beabsichtigte, nämlich das grosse Innere der westlichen Hälfte Australiens aufzuschliessen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In einer Vorlesung, die ich vor der Ackerbau-Gesellschaft von Bendigo über Uredo Rubigo hielt, erörterte ich, wieviel Vortheil daraus erwachsen würde, wenn hier in Melbourne eine Professur für technologische u Agricultur-Chemie begründet würde. Ich wies darauf hin, wie die Landbauer hier aller wissenschaftlichen Kunde bar einen Raubbau betreiben, wie fast alle fertilisirenden Substanzen vergeudet werden, u wie jeder über die Bestandtheile des Landes seines Landhofes im Dunkeln tappt. Ich deutete ferner an, wie in unsern ungeheuren <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> Wäldern Öle, Essige, Theer, Alkalien, usw in absolut unglaublichen Massen gewonnen werden könnten, u wie sehr es bedürfe, einen Mann hierher zu rufen, der dieser reichen Ertragsquelle seine <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">specielle</hi>
               </seg> Thätigkeit zuwenden könne, u dazu die nothwendigen neuesten Erfahrungen über Processe u Apparate mitbrächte. Ich sollte glauben, dass eine briefliche Demonstration von Ihnen, der über alle Autorität ausübt, eine solche Anstellung hervorrufen würde. Eine Auseinandersetzung von Ihnen über diesen Gegenstand hätte ich so gern dem Senat unserer Universität u unserm Ministerium vorgelegt. Vielleicht könnten Sie, Herr Baron, später, wenn die Stellung begründet, unter den jungen hervorragenden Talenten Europas den ausgezeichnetsten Mann für die<seg style="font-weight: bold; "> </seg>Professur erwählen. Ich denke dass ihm das Einkommen von £1000 fürs Jahr gesichert werden könne, theils von der Universität u theils vom Board of Agriculture, an dem ich einen Sitz habe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit innigstem Wunsche, dass Sie uns lange als Stolz der Wissenschaft erhalten bleiben mögen, bin ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Herrn Freiherrn Justus v. Liebig,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Commandeur u Ritter hoher Orden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>usw.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Wenn ein gedrängter Auszug aus Ihren vortrefflichen Letters of modern Agriculture, transl. by Dr Blyth veröffentlicht würde, so etwa dass die Kosten des Exemplars 2/ betrügen, Tausende von Tausenden von solchen könnten dann verkauft werden über die ganze Erde u welcher ausgedehnte Nutzen würde nicht dadurch entstehen!</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 May 1865.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Revered Baron,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your friend Madame Eliza King<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Eliza King and her husband, the Hunter Valley winemaker James King, visited Liebig in Munich in 1855, and she and Liebig continued to correspond after her husband’s death; see Rae &amp; Brock (2013).</p>
               </note> passed on to me recently your pleasing news about Dr Neumayer, and I was touched as pleasantly by the intelligence of the recognition received by this scientifically ambitious gentleman,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Shortly after returning to Germany in 1864, Neumayer launched a public campaign for a German scientific expedition to Antarctica that he hoped to lead. See <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Amtlicher Bericht über die erste Versammlung deutscher Meister und Freunde der Erdkunde in Frankfurt a. M…</seg> (1865) pp. 52-5.</p>
               </note> as by the kindliness with which you remembered me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will be sure to follow with interest the enterprise by the ladies of our State to search for poor Leichhardt. Within the next few weeks £1,000 will have been collected for this purpose, and several Australian Governments have already pledged their support. The sympathetic appraisal by eminent men of science in Europe is important for the success of the enterprise, to spur on our colonists to give real support to this fine endeavour. The ladies, by their own decision, have also approached Queen Victoria and the Princess of Wales with a request for help, also the Princess of Prussia, as Leichhardt was a native of that country.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">When first approached, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Queen Victoria felt unable to associate her name with the Committee, as none of the Colonial Legislatures had <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>expressed approval of the appeal. However, by the time it was raised again by Sir Roderick Murchison in January 1866, Colonial Government support had been given, and after seeking the approval of the Colonial Secretary, the Queen agreed to donate £100. However, the money was not paid until October 1866 (information supplied by the Deputy Registrar, The Royal Archives, Windsor Castle. See Keeper of the Privy Purse (Sir Charles Phipps) to Colonial Secretary (Edward Cardwell), 18 January 1866 (RA PP/VIC/1866/20810); Receipt in favour of Leichhardt Search Fund dated 27 October 1886 (RA PP/VIC/2/106/11309)).</p>
               </note> The larger the contributions, the more auspicious are the means that can be chosen for this undertaking, and the longer can be its duration. There is no doubt that Leichhardt's fate will be discovered by this movement of the high-minded ladies; but it depends on the exhortations of eminent men and the resulting resources, whether the search party — Duncan McIntyre will probably be its leader — will be able to depart soon. This expedition will probably succeed in precisely that which the poor lost man had intended to do: to unlock the vast interior of the western half of Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In a lecture I gave on <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Uredo%20rubigo">Uredo rubigo</name>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B65.04.05. </p>
               </note> before the Agricultural Society of Bendigo, I discussed how great a benefit would arise if a professorship for technological and agricultural chemistry were to be founded here in Melbourne. I indicated how the farmers here, completely lacking any scientific knowledge, despoil the land, how nearly all fertilizing materials are wasted, and how everybody is in ignorance about the constituents of the soil of his property. I pointed out further how our vast <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> forests could yield oils, vinegar, tars, alkaloids etc. in absolutely unbelievable quantities, and how necessary it would be to call a man here who could turn his <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">specialised</hi>
               </seg> ability towards this rich source of income, and in addition would bring with him the necessary experience on the latest processes and equipment. I should think that a written submission from you, the greatest authority, would result in the establishment of such a position. I should very much like to have an evaluation from you on this subject to place before the Senate of our University<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">University of Melbourne.</p>
               </note> and before the Ministry.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="color: #000000; ">See J. Liebig to M, 15 August 1865 (in this edition as 65-08-15a).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Perhaps later, dear Baron, when such a position has been founded, you could choose for the professorship the most distinguished man among the prominent young talents of Europe. I think that an income of £1,000 per annum could be secured for him, funded partly by the University and partly by the Board of Agriculture, of which I am a member.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's proposal did not proceed.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With most sincere wishes, that you may long be spared to us as the pride of science, I am </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Baron Justus von Liebig,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Commander and Knight of high Orders,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">etc.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">If a concise extract from your excellent <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Letters of modern agriculture</seg>, translated by Dr Blyth,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Liebig (1859).</p>
               </note> were to be published at an approximate cost of 2 shillings per copy, thousands upon thousands of them could be sold all over the world, and what outstanding benefits would not be achieved by that!</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Uredo%20rubigo">Uredo rubigo</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
