<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sydney, 218 Macquarie Street, ¶ June 20. ¶  ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ I trust you will excuse the liberty I am about to take in addressing you on a subject which has interested me much for some time past, and that ...</title>
            <author>A. Galbraith</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-06-20a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.06.20a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>A. Galbraith</author>
               <title>Sydney, 218 Macquarie Street, ¶ June 20. ¶  ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ I trust you will excuse the liberty I am about to take in addressing you on a subject which has interested me much for some time past, and that ...</title>
               <date when="1865-06-20">1865-06-20</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-06-20a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sydney, 218 Macquarie Street, ¶ June 20. ¶  ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ I trust you will excuse the liberty I am about to take in addressing you on a subject which has interested me much for some time past, and that ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.06.20a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From A. Galbraith</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australasian</seg>, 1 July 1865, p. 14, under the heading, Acclimatisation. The Victorian Society', where it is introduced as follows: 'Dr. Mueller laid before the Council the following letter, received from Mr. Galbraith, of Sydney'. The letter was also published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 29 June 1865, p. 5.</p>
               </note>Sydney, 218 Macquarie Street,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">June 20.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I trust you will excuse the liberty I am about to take in addressing you on a subject which has interested me much for some time past, and that is, the introduction of pure-bred Chinese sheep into Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I may preface my letter by informing you that I have been in the colonies of New South Wales and Queensland for the last twenty-three years, and have been constantly connected with sheep properties. In the latter colony I was managing partner in a station depasturing 60,000 sheep, and am, therefore, well qualified to give an opinion on matters connected with pastoral interests.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>About three years ago it was proposed to get up a company in Sydney by some of the merchants and stockholders to import a number of the pure-bred sheep from the north-western provinces of China, and locate them in a cold climate till such time as they should be acclimatized; but in consequence of the civil war then being waged in the Chinese provinces the matter was allowed to drop, and since then no further steps were taken in the matter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Latterly, I have made it my business to gain every information regarding the sheep in question, and have arrived at the conclusion that, by their introduction, the whole of the colonies will ultimately be greatly benefited.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When it was proposed to import them into this colony, I was to have gone and selected the sheep myself, not leaving it to agents in China, who would require to undertake a long and arduous journey of, likely, some four or five hundred miles from Pekin.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now that the Northern provinces are in a settled state, and every likelihood of getting assistance from British and French residents, I think that the time has now arrived when such an undertaking could be easily carried out, with the most splendid results to the individuals importing a flock.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>From representations made by an intelligent and wealthy Chinese merchant from Hong Kong, who has seen this peculiar breed, he says that there is as much difference between the Chinese sheep (that have been sent to Melbourne and Sydney, from Shanghai and neighbouring provinces, from those bred in Chinese Tartary) as there is between a Scotch terrier and a Newfoundland dog. This is using his own expression of comparison.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a few of the particulars regarding these sheep, I beg to inclose you an extract from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Empire</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Clipping not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> If I though[t] that there was any probability of getting the co-operation of some Victorian gentlemen, who would form themselves into a company, I should at once proceed to China, and do my best to select a flock that in a few years would be counted by tens of thousands.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall be glad to hear from you on this subject, what you think of it; and so thoroughly convinced am I of the probability of success, that I would invest largely in shares.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr. Wilcox, the naturalist, who accompanied my poor friend Ludwig Leichardt in his first journey,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No-one named Wilcox or with a name at all similar to this accompanied Leichhardt on either his first or his second expedition.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> would go as my companion, in case of accidents. He is most anxious to go with me, if the thing is carried out.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If I can get some inducement, I would at once proceed to Melbourne, and give all the information that I possess, so that the matter could be thoroughly discussed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After perusal of the enclosed extracts, will you kindly return them to me, as I have not copies. The prospectus was one of those made out some time ago, when the first company was started, but, in consequence of the war, was discontinued. I may mention that Mr. Wilcox and myself are married men, and would have our families in Melbourne till our return.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have taken a great liberty in writing you on this subject, but knowing the great interest you take in the progression of the colonies will be my only excuse.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I remain, Sir, your most obedient servant,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Galbraith, N.S.W.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dr. F. Mueller.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The report continues: 'After the reading of this, a conversation ensued, and the secretary was instructed to write for further particulars, and inquire at what expense one or two pairs of these sheep could be introduced, it being the general feeling that no large amount should be spent in making an experiment of this kind until at least some certainty of success was assured.'</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
