<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Since last meeting I have visited many parts of the country. My observations strengthen our former views ¶  as to the advantages of early sowing, and the necessity for ploughing up the land for a summ...</title>
            <author>Alexander Mackenzie</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-02-00g-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.02.00g</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Alexander Mackenzie</author>
               <title>Since last meeting I have visited many parts of the country. My observations strengthen our former views ¶  as to the advantages of early sowing, and the necessity for ploughing up the land for a summ...</title>
               <date when="1865-02">1865-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-02-00g-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Since last meeting I have visited many parts of the country. My observations strengthen our former views ¶  as to the advantages of early sowing, and the necessity for ploughing up the land for a summ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.02.00g</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Alexander Mackenzie</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is taken from the report of the meeting of the Council of the Board of Agriculture held on 1 March 1865 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>, 2 March 1865, p. 7). The text of the letter is introduced with 'A letter was laid on the table from Mr A. Mackenzie, addressed to Dr. <seg style="">Mueller</seg>, the chairman of the rust and blight committee, of which the following is the substance:—'</p>
               </note>Since last meeting I have visited many parts of the country. My observations strengthen our former views<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M and A. Mackenzie to Board of Agriculture, February 1865 (in this edition as 65.02.00).</p>
               </note> as to the advantages of early sowing, and the necessity for ploughing up the land for a summer fallow. I urged on the farmers the desirability of their varying their crops, and growing more roots, beans and peas, so as not wholly to depend on wheat, oats and potatoes. I found the Adelaide seed, in most cases, to have suffered most from rust, contrasting very unfavorably with our own colonial grown seed. Farmers should obtain their new seed from the colder parts of the colony — say, from Colac, Ballaarat,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now Ballarat, Vic. </p>
               </note> &amp;c., or from Tasmania. Adelaide seed should be avoided. I am strengthened in this belief by the fine sample of Ballaarat wheat which I now submit, which was grown alongside with rusty wheat from Adelaide seed. Sample No. 57 is from the farm of Mr J. Parsons, of Wabdallah.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Renamed Bannockburn in 1892; a rural township near Geelong, Vic.</p>
               </note> The soil is very good, with natural drainage, was twice ploughed, and sown in May, was attacked by rust in October, and, after threshing, yielded only two and a half bushels per acre. Sample No. 58 is from Mr A. Macadam, of Coolebarghurk, between Lethbridge and Meredith—was sown, the first week in June, with badly rusted Adelaide seed. The land is rich, lying high with a southern aspect. Sample No. 59 is from Mr L. Fynn's, in the same district, sown with Tartarian oats in May, so badly rusted that cattle refuse to eat the straw. The land is good and well drained. Sample No. 60 is from Mr W. Ellis, same parish, sown early in June, after a summer fallow, with his own good seed, and yielded ten bushels to the acre; the land is good. Sample No. 61 is from Mr H. Capron, same parish, sown at the end of June, partly with his own seed and partly with Ballaarat seed, the latter being much the best. The land is good, being on the top of a hill, with natural drainage, and was twice ploughed. Sample No. 62 is from Mr James M'Kay, same parish, new land; sown with Adelaide seed in May, and yielded five bushels per acre. Sample No. 63 is from Mr J. Parker's farm, Wabdallah; sown with Adelaide seed in May. The land is rich with a limestone subsoil, on a hillside; adequate drainage, and, although twice ploughed, the yield will be very short.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
