<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ It is most gratifying to observe how vivid an interest the leading gentlemen and ladies of your colony evince in the enterprise, and, above all, we owe a tribute of deep gratitude for the graceful ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-07-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.07.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ It is most gratifying to observe how vivid an interest the leading gentlemen and ladies of your colony evince in the enterprise, and, above all, we owe a tribute of deep gratitude for the graceful ...</title>
               <date when="1865-07">1865-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-07-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Landsborough</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ It is most gratifying to observe how vivid an interest the leading gentlemen and ladies of your colony evince in the enterprise, and, above all, we owe a tribute of deep gratitude for the graceful ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.07.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Landsborough</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is from the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Queensland daily guardian</seg>, 17 July 1865, p. 5 (B65.07.04). The letter is introduced as follows: 'Mr. W. Landsborough ... begs leave to offer the following extract from a letter which he has just received from Dr. F. Mueller, of Melbourne, for publication.... After some complimentary remarks, Dr. Mueller proceeds:–‘. <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter was also published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg> on the same day, p. 3 (B65.07.27), and in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Rockhampton bulletin and Central Queensland advertiser</seg>, 25 July 1865, p. 3 (B65.07.28).</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is most gratifying to observe how vivid an interest the leading gentlemen and ladies of your colony evince in the enterprise, and, above all, we owe a tribute of deep gratitude for the graceful patronage which his Excellency the Governor and Lady Bowen<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Diamantina Bowen.</p>
               </note> have extended towards this work of national philanthropy. Under such high auspices the brave little band sent out will be stimulated to the utmost exertions in fulfilling their mission.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Various records have been given successively of our proceedings here, and of the arrangements made by the ladies<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">leaders <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in the version printed in the Brisbane courier</seg>.</p>
               </note> for the speedy and efficient organisation of the party; and, in addition, the ladies of the Melbourne committee will have sent official progress reports to the Queensland ladies. You may not, however, be aware, that the great geographer, Professor Augustus Petermann, has risen as a champion of Leichhardt's cause in that unfortunate traveller's native country; and there can be no doubt that the universal attention of the intellectual world, from the throne to the cottage, will be directed to the ladies' enterprise, and that the sympathies of every feeling heart will follow this movement. To me, the ladies' cause has, beyond its philanthrophic tendency, still another deep meaning. We see for the first time in the world's history the ladies carrying on a national enterprise which will teach their high-minded sisters in other lands that the intelligence and zeal of the fair may be displayed beyond its usual sphere in administering local charities. And here I must affirm, that nothing could surpass the moral courage, the circumspect surveillance, and the active zeal which the ladies that form the Melbourne committee have displayed in carrying on the work against much discouragement and difficulties of many kinds. For it cannot be otherwise than that public opinion can only gradually be brought round to perceive the soundness of the views which led to a renewal of our exertions on Leichhardt's behalf. The ladies had to contend with the difficulty of vanquishing not only apathy but a strenuous opposition to embark in exploratory searches, which many fear would envolve endless expenditure and the sacrifice of human life.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Public fears have thus far been gradually allayed. The constitution of the party destined to carry out the ladies' object, is such as to inspire confidence. The members of the expedition seem fully conscious that while no <seg style="font-style: italic; ">impossibilities</seg> are expected from their exertions, and while they are not encouraged by us to incur useless risk and needless danger, that nevertheless it will be a point of honor to them not to leave the problem of Leichhardt's fate unsolved. Indeed, I anticipate absolute results from this enterprise; and in addition, though the search will be the primary and the only recognised object, there will be, I have no doubt, a vast augmentation of our knowledge of the geography of Australia, and a glorious expansion of our acquaintance with its natural resources. Indeed, exploration in itself, for its own sake, should be fostered. We now form a sufficiently populous community to afford getting the remainder of the Australian territory mapped; and before this is done, we can have no true appreciation of the riches we may possess in gold and copper mines and pastural lands. Nor can we form a true estimation of the most favorable means for connecting by telegraph lines the south with the north, and consequently with all parts of the globe. If it is desirable — and surely we applaud it — to traverse the polar region, or to penetrate in salubrious regions<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">penetrate the regions <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in the version printed in the Brisbane courier</seg>.</p>
               </note> of Dahomey or Waddi, where the terror of the most<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">worst <seg style="font-style: italic; ">in the version printed in the Brisbane courier</seg>.</p>
               </note> barbarism reigns, or if it has become an object of deep interest since Julius Caesar's time to advance to the sources of the Nile, or to ascend, as Baron von Decker has done, the mountains of the moon, or to penetrate into the gorilla country — localities too densely peopled by savages, or too injurious to health for extended exertions of a laboring population from Europe — then assuredly we ought fully to open the great Australian continent for settlement.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pray, give Mr. Sandeman my most friendly regards; and express to that gentleman my gratitude for his advocacy. Concerning the transit of (from Port Denison) flour, tea, and sugar to the Cormish Creek,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Cornish Creek, Qld.</p>
               </note> for the use of the expedition, we depend <seg style="font-style: italic; ">entirely</seg> on your arrangements, and gladly leave the details to your superior judgment. Should the supplies not arrive before Mr. M'Intyre, the expedition must either wait (which would be a great pity), or obtain a loan from the various neighboring stations, of what could be spared until the arrival of the drays; or, as the Hon. Mathew Hervey thinks, the Company's station could itself supply all that is wanted. I am thankful you have engaged in this somewhat anxious and responsible task of providing the expedition with supplies. Mr. M'Intyre will render payment in cash or by cheque, when he obtains his stores.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A final paragraph to the report has clearly been added by Landsborough, though this is not indicated:: 'I have written to Messrs Seaward, Marsh, and Co. of Bowen, to forward the supplies, and to Mr. Buchanan, of Cornish Creek, to kindly furnish Mr. M'Intyre, if possible, in case of need, with the requisite station stores. | Kangaroo Point, Brisbane, July 15, 1865'. In the versions of the letter published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg> and the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Rockhampton bulletin</seg>, which are identical even though the Rockhamption paper attributes its copy to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Guardian</seg>, this paragraph is printed as a footnote, without the address and date.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
