<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 February 1865. ¶  ¶ You in particular, revered Professor, as the greatest geographer of our time, must not remain uninformed about the new movement which is beginning t...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-02-24b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.02.24b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 February 1865. ¶  ¶ You in particular, revered Professor, as the greatest geographer of our time, must not remain uninformed about the new movement which is beginning t...</title>
               <date when="1865-02-24">1865-02-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-02-24b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 February 1865. ¶  ¶ You in particular, revered Professor, as the greatest geographer of our time, must not remain uninformed about the new movement which is beginning t...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">65.02.24b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Petermann: 'Erh. 21. April 1865' [Received 21 April 1865]. For a published version of this letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 62-3. Extracts were published by Petermann in his journal, namely the sections ‘Die Neuheit ... aufhellen wird’ and ‘Die 16 ... verweben’; see B65.06.22.</p>
               </note>Melbourne im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 24. Februar 1865.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie, hochverehrter Herr Professor, als der grösste Geograph unserer Zeit, dürfen doch nicht speciell ununterrichtet bleiben über die neue Bewegung, welche für Leichhardts Aufsuchung u vielleicht Rettung sich regt. Die Neuheit des — ich kann wohl sagen — romantischen Versuches, durch eine von Damen ausgesandte Expedition das Geschick des Unglücklichen zu erkunden, liess mich fürchten, dass das Vorhaben scheitern möchte. Die Vorbereitungen sind indessen von dem günstigsten Erfolge begleitet u vielleicht in wenig Monaten werden wir den Emissär der Damen Australiens im Felde sehen, u ein Unternehmen verfolgen, das die Aufmerksamkeit der ganzen intellectuellen Welt auf sich ziehen muss u neben Leichhardts Schicksal vielleicht auch die grosse westliche Hälfte Australiens aufhellen wird. Zur Förderung des hehren Unternehmens rufe ich nun Ihre Hülfe an. Möchten Sie nicht freundlichst in Ihrem Journal darauf hinlenken, dass Queensland zu all den neuen Expeditionen nicht mehr als £500 (fünfhundert Pfund) beigetragen, während Victoria allein vierzigtausend Pfund Sterling für geographische Entdeckungsreisen opferte. Dann hat ja Queensland fast ausschliesslich Vortheil gezogen von Leichhardts grossartigen ersten Forschungen u solange als die Aufsuchungsreisenden in der östlichen Hälfte des australischen Erdtheils wirken, wird auch wieder Queensland der grösste Antheil des geographisch. Gewinnes von dem Damen Unternehmen zufallen. Bei einer frühern Gelegenheit ist ein öffentlicher Anruf an jenes Land nutzlos verhallt! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Über Alles, was diese bedeutungsvolle Expedition bringen mag, werde ich Sie stets unterrichtet halten. Aber lassen Sie dann auch die Damen Ihres mächtigen Beistandes gewiss sein. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn einmal unter einem brillianten Führer die Expedition der Damen im Felde ist, wird selbige nie zurückgerufen werden bis Leichhardts Geschick enthüllt ist, sollte auch eine Decennie darüber verfliessen, so lange uns nur die grossen geographischen Autoritäten Europas in dem herrlichen Werk der Damen zur Seite stehen. Fehlt alle Privathülfe, so würden sicher vereint die Regierungen der australischen Colonien das Unternehmen unterstützen u unterhalten. Die 16 Damen haben eine seltene Gelegenheit Ihren Namen glanzvoll in die Geschichte Australiens zu verweben u Ihr Emissär wird die Namen derselben auf geographisch neue Positionen übertragen Ihnen ein mehr beständiges Denkmal bauen als irgend eins aus Erz oder Marmor sein wird.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meine Sammlungen für das Gothaische Museum sind wohl angelangt. Ich habe noch manches nachzuliefern. —</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll bleibe ich</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">24 February 1865.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You in particular, revered Professor, as the greatest geographer of our time, must not remain uninformed about the new movement which is beginning to stir, to search for and perhaps save Leichhardt.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M initiated a new search for Leichhardt with a speech at a public meeting in Melbourne on 9 February 1865 (see B65.02.01), and subsequently encouraged the forming of a committee of ladies to raise funds and organize what became known as 'The Ladies' Leichhardt Search expedition'.</p>
               </note> The novelty of this one might say romantic attempt to ascertain the fate of the unfortunate man through an expedition sent out by ladies caused me to fear that the enterprise might founder. However, the preparations are accompanied by the most auspicious success, and in perhaps a few months we shall see the emissary of Australia's ladies in the field and observe an enterprise that must attract the attention of the whole intellectual world, that besides revealing Leichhardt's fate will perhaps also unveil the western half of Australia. I now call on your help to promote this noble endeavour. Would you be so kind as to point out in your journal<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen aus Justus Perthes' geographischer Anstalt</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> that Queensland has contributed no more than £500 (five hundred pounds) to all the recent expeditions, while Victoria alone sacrificed forty thousand pounds sterling for journeys of geographical exploration. And Queensland has also received almost exclusively the benefits of Leichhardt's magnificent early explorations, and as long as the search expedition is travelling in the eastern half of the Australian continent, Queensland will again reap the greatest geographical advantages from the ladies' enterprise. A public appeal to that State on an earlier occasion remained without response.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall always keep you informed about everything that this significant expedition may produce. But in return give the ladies the assurance of your powerful support.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Once the ladies' expedition under a brilliant leader is in the field, it will never be recalled until Leichhardt's fate is revealed, even if ten years should pass, as long as the great geographic authorities in Europe stand behind the glorious labours of the ladies. If all private support were lacking, surely the combined Governments of the Australian Colonies would support the endeavour and sustain it. The 16 ladies have a rare opportunity to weave their illustrious names into the fabric of Australian history and their emissary will attach their names to new geographical features, thus setting them a more lasting memorial than one fashioned of bronze or marble.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My collections for the Museum in Gotha have probably arrived.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A case was dispatched by <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg>. See M to A. Petermann, 26 August 1864.</p>
               </note> I still have to send quite a few other things. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
