<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir,— Through the columns of your paper of this day, I am asked, in an uncharitable manner, strangely contrasting with your friendly and generous feelings hitherto evinced towards the promoters of the...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-07-10a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.07.10a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Sir,— Through the columns of your paper of this day, I am asked, in an uncharitable manner, strangely contrasting with your friendly and generous feelings hitherto evinced towards the promoters of the...</title>
               <date when="1865-07-10">1865-07-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-07-10a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of the Herald</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sir,— Through the columns of your paper of this day, I am asked, in an uncharitable manner, strangely contrasting with your friendly and generous feelings hitherto evinced towards the promoters of the...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.07.10a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Editor of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Herald</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>given<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>here,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>see <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'The<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Ladies’ Expedition for<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Leichhardt’s Search’,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg>
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(Melbourne), 11<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>July 1865, p. 2 (B65.07.24).<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  </p>
               </note>Sir,— Through the columns of your paper of this day, I am asked, in an uncharitable manner, strangely contrasting with your friendly and generous feelings hitherto evinced towards the promoters of the Leichhardt's search, what arrangements had<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>been entered into between the Ladies' Committee and the leader of their expedition.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on 10 July 1865, p. 2, wrote:</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.4722in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">The Leichhardt Search Expedition crossed the Murray on Friday and is now, we are informed, en route to Mount Murchison. It is high time that Dr. Mueller, who seems to have taken the entire management of the affair, should vouchsafe some information to the subscribers and to the general public. Of course the learned doctor is too anxious to obtain kudos from his fellow-countrymen in Europe to care anything for the interests of Victoria, whose only claim upon him is that she pays him a handsome salary, and allows him to make use of her resources in order to extend his scientific fame; but the Ladies’ Committee should take a different view of their responsibilities. The public and the Government have a right to know what agreement has been entered into by the committee with Mr. M’Intyre, Dr. Murray, and the subordinate members of the party; what instructions have been given to them as to the localities they are to search; and the amount of money likely to be required. Victoria has no direct interest in these hazardous ventures, and it will be too bad if, in our desire to solve the mystery in which the fate of the great explorer is involved, the colony should only expose itself to the risk of losing men and money in a fruitless expedition.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Allow me, then, on behalf of the lady delegates, to inform you that the preliminary arrangements have met with the full concurrence of Dr Wilkie and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Mr Ellery,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>who in a zealous and disinterested<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>manner have shown their wish to promote and facilitate the enterprise; and further that when the kindly-promised subsidies from the other colonies will have been assured, these arrangements for the expedition will receive their final confirmation, or perhaps slight alterations, according to the support experienced, and then what can be of general interest to the public will be rendered known. Meanwhile<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the party proceeds to its rendezvous at Mount Murchison.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Darling River, NSW.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>From time to time a general outline of the committee’s proceedings has been given by the courtesy of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>press.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>If any subscriber desires further information on subjects of special interest to himself, I have no doubt the Ladies' Committee will gladly afford it, though all contributions have been received unconditionally. With Mr M'lntyre solely is entered into a contract;<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The final agreement between M, on behalf of the Ladies' Committee of the Leichhardt Search Fund, and Duncan McIntrye was made on 20 July 1865 (in this edition as 65-07-20).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on him therefore the other members of the party are entirely depending, and while thus exercising an unlimited control, and an unrestricted<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>freedom of action, he has devolving on him commensurate responsibilities. I doubt whether<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>any man of ability<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and experience, any man deserving of confidence, would engage<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the task on other terms. As to the localities to be searched, I may state that the party intends to proceed to the farthest northern position attained by Leichhardt. Should the forlorn traveller have carried<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>out<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>his plan to penetrate<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>from thence towards the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>S. W.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>part of this continent, the interrogations will be extended<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>generally in that direction, as far as the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>physical<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>features of the country admit, which will<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>often<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>demand deviations. Should, however, Leichhardt's party, after calamities<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>have passed<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>southward in a retrograde movement from the Gulf of Carpentaria to the settlements, then his vestiges will be followed to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Bunderabulla<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bunderaballa watercourse where, according to one theory, Leichhardt and his party had been massacred by Aborigines.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>or wherever they<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>lead to. You will agree, Mr Editor, that it would be the height of imprudence to lay<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>down a route of operations whereby probably the object we all have so much at heart would be frustrated. The third question asked I regard extremely odd. Whom concerns it, except the legally<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>contracting parties, what precise sum will be required for the enterprise? Yet over<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and over it has been publicly stated that Mr M'Intyre had<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>offered to conduct the search<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>during two years for £3000, an<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>offer which reflected the more credit in the gentleman, and which we may regard the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>more a guarantee for his high-mindedness, as it<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>provided most inadequately personal reward. But fulfilling his mission the ladies are not likely to fail recognising his services in a substantial manner; but after two years' exertions the party may not<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>have followed Leichhardt further than to the centre of the Continent, though during its movement much more country will be mapped than along ordinary exploring lines, and it may need a second mission and a second outlay to resume the search from the last camps obtained. I entirely dissent from the idea enunciated in your columns that Victoria has no<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>direct interest in these explorative enterprises, for whatever tends to advance the geographical<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>knowledge of Australia will unavoidably promote settlement, and therewith the common trade and industry of our own community. The passage in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">T</seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">he H</seg>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">erald</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>evinces so much unjust and unprovoked hostility that I cannot, sir, for a moment regard its remarks as the exponent of your own enlightened and equitable views, but see in them the personal ill-feeling of one or the other of the few whose active<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>discouragement and reprehensible opposition have been encountered. Onslaughts of this kind are calculated to produce a disheartening effect<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>not only momentary, but on the furtherance of future objects of a kindred tendency, and they<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>this instance the more painful<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as they must wound the tender feelings of the fair who mustered courage to uphold Leichhardt's cause, and whose circumspect and clever actions on the poor traveller's behalf entitle them to the grateful<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>respect,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and the admiration of every one whose feelings are not closed to humanity and who can elevate himself to national pride.—<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I am, etc.,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden, 10th July.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
