<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>COPY ¶ Mr Duncan McIntyre ¶ and ¶ Ferdinand Mueller Esqu M.D. ¶ on behalf of the Ladies' Committee...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-07-20-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Royal Geographical Society, London, Archives, Journal MSS, Australia, 1867, Mueller, F. (1).</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.07.20</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>COPY ¶ Mr Duncan McIntyre ¶ and ¶ Ferdinand Mueller Esqu M.D. ¶ on behalf of the Ladies' Committee...</title>
               <date when="1865-07-20">1865-07-20</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-07-20-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Agreement with Duncan McIntyre</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">COPY ¶ Mr Duncan McIntyre ¶ and ¶ Ferdinand Mueller Esqu M.D. ¶ on behalf of the Ladies' Committee...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.07.20</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">Agreement with Duncan McIntyre</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Royal Geographical Society, London, Archives, Journal MSS, Australia, 1867, Mueller, F. (1).</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Another copy of this agreement is included with M to C. Darling, 20 April 1866.</p>
               </note>COPY<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The copyist mispelled Leichhardt's name with a single 'h' throughout.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Mr Duncan McIntyre</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">and</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferdinand Mueller Esqu M.D.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">on behalf of the Ladies' Committee</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">of the Leichardt Search Fund.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Agreement.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Articles of Agreement entered into the twentieth day of July one thousand eight hundred and sixty five by or on behalf of Duncan McIntyre of Glengower near Castlemaine, Gentleman of the one part and Ferdinand Mueller Esquire Doctor of Medicine, Director of the Botanic Garden of Melbourne on behalf of the Ladies' Committee of the Leichardt Search Expedition of the other part. The said Duncan McIntyre in consideration of the sum of one thousand pounds to be paid to him or his Agent by the said Ferdinand Mueller out of the above mentioned fund and not as a personal liability of the said Ferdinand Mueller on or before the first day of August one thousand eight hundred and sixty five and of the further sum of two thousand pounds to be paid to him or his executors or administrators or his or their agent at the times and in manner and under the conditions hereinafter mentioned, agrees with the said Ferdinand Mueller his executors or administrators in manner following.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1. First that the said Duncan McIntyre will proceed and conduct a party or expedition consisting of not less than eight men including one duly qualified Surgeon and one person competent to make surveying and astronomical observations and to take command of the party in the case of the death or of any accident happening to the said Duncan McIntyre to go in search of the party which under the leadership of Doctor Leichardt about the year one thousand eight hundred and forty seven started from Sydney New South Wales, with the intention of proceeding to Swan River and have not been heard of since one thousand eight hundred and forty eight.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. That the said Duncan McIntyre will provide the proper arms horses stores and provisions for the said party and pay all the expenses of whatever nature incurred by the said expedition and that neither he nor any of the said party shall have any claim beyond the above mentioned sums against the said Ferdinand Mueller or any other person or against any other than the said fund.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. That upon the return of the expedition the said Duncan McIntyre will bring or cause to be brought the Dromedaries which shall be lent to him by the Government of Victoria to such place as the said Government may direct.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4. That the said Duncan McIntyre shall engage and pay all the Officers and men and shall make such agreements with anyone or more of them as to taking command of the party in case of the said Duncan McIntyre from any cause ceasing to be the leader of the said party and as to the increase (if any) of the salary in such an event. And the said Duncan McIntyre shall alone be responsible to them for all monies due to their services and shall alone fix their respective salaries or rate of remuneration and shall obtain from such men and Officers an acknowledgement in writing that they have no claim for payment on any other person than the said Duncan McIntyre in respect of any services.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. That for the purpose of enabling the said Duncan McIntyre to prosecute such search and to pay the salaries of the Officers and men to be engaged by him and also the expenses of the said expedition the said Ferdinand Mueller agrees to pay to the said Duncan McIntyre his executors or administrators or his or their Agent the further sum of two thousand pounds at intervals of one month during the first year and in sums of not more than fifty pounds but subject to the conditions for the nonpayment or cessation of payment as hereinafter mentioned and subject as hereinafter mentioned the remainder of the sum shall be paid after the return of the expedition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6. The said Duncan McIntyre undertakes to proceed with all reasonable despatch to the Country where traces of Dr Leichardt's party are likely to be found and for no purpose other than the safety of his party to deviate from the duty—prescribed to him by the said Committee. And the said Duncan McIntyre promises so soon as in his judgement he has ascertained the fate of the said Dr Leichardt and his party and considers that any further search or delay will be useless to return to the settlement with all reasonable despatch.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7. That upon the return of the party the decision of Doctors Wilkie and Mueller shall be conclusive as to whether the evidence of the fate of Leichardt and his party upon which the said Duncan McIntyre may have relied is satisfactory or not for the purposes of the two following clauses.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>8. That if before the thirtieth July one thousand eight hundred and sixty seven it shall be determined that the evidence adduced by the said Duncan McIntyre is conclusive as to the fate of Leichardt and his party the said Duncan McIntyre will forthwith at the request of the said Committee sell and dispose of the horses and remaining stores and other articles of the expedition and pay the proceeds of such sale to such person as may be appointed by the said Committee and from that time all payments from the said search fund shall cease.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>9. That in case the expedition should return without having ascertained the fate of Leichardt and his party or in case the said Doctors Wilkie and Mueller do not deem the evidence conclusive as to such fate the said Duncan McIntyre will return the horses and remaining stores, arms and equipments at such place as the said Committee may direct and subject to the order and direction of the said Committee and all payments from the said search fund shall cease.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>10. The said Duncan McIntyre undertakes to keep a complete journal or diary of the proceedings of the expedition and as often as occasion offers to communicate with and report progress to the said Committee at Melbourne and upon his return that he will furnish the committee with a complete copy of his Diary or Journal and maps and the diaries and journals of any other member of the expedition and such Committee alone shall have the right to publish it and that any articles of Leichardt's party that may be found and any collections and records of objects of natural science that may be found be delivered over to the Committee.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>11 That the said Duncan McIntyre promises honestly and faithfully to devote himself to the object of the said Committee and to perform the stipulations and agreements herein before contained and not to deviate from the said object for any purpose whatever except from imperative necessity.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>12 That if the period occupied by the expedition be less than two years a deduction from the said sum of two thousand pounds shall be made at the rate of fifty pounds per month.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">sd/Fred<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Copyist's error.</p>
               </note> Mueller</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">sd/Duncan McIntyre</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
