<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Professor Fr Mueller in Victoria. ¶  ¶ The sad state of war ¶  that has been in existence for over a year has had a considerable effect on my correspondence, which in part has come to a complete stand...</title>
            <author>Johan Forchhammer</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-04-17-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Forchhammer Brev.-Copi-Bog no. 4 (1859-65), Geologisk Museum, Copenhagen.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.04.17</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Johan Forchhammer</author>
               <title>Professor Fr Mueller in Victoria. ¶  ¶ The sad state of war ¶  that has been in existence for over a year has had a considerable effect on my correspondence, which in part has come to a complete stand...</title>
               <date when="1865-04-17">1865-04-17</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-04-17-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Professor Fr Mueller in Victoria. ¶  ¶ The sad state of war ¶  that has been in existence for over a year has had a considerable effect on my correspondence, which in part has come to a complete stand...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">65.04.17</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Johan Forchhammer</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Forchhammer Brev.-Copi-Bog no. 4 (1859-65), Geologisk Museum, Copenhagen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is from a letter-book copy.</p>
               </note>Herr Professor Fr Müller in Victoria</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die traurigen Kriegsverhältnisse, welche seit über einem Jahre stattgefunden haben, haben einen wesentlichen Einfluss gehabt auf meine Correspondenz, die zum Theil ganz ins Stocken gerathen ist und ich habe wenigstens auf zwei Briefe von Ihnen zu antworten. Es war mir seht erfreulich in dem ersten dieser beiden Schreiben zu sehen, dass Sie desselben Weg in der derselben Stadt und demselben Hause beim Apotheker Becker in Husum durchgemacht haben und Ihr Brief hat mich in jene alte Zeiten des frischen Strebens und der unbegrenzten Erwartungen und Hoffnungen zurückgeführt und obgleich der Aufenthalt in der Apotheker in den 5 Jahren, welche ich da zubrachte keinesweges angenehm und befriedigend war, so ist das doch längst verwunden. Wenn meine Studien auf Sie einen anspornenden Eindruck gemacht haben, so ist das in hohem Grade erfreulich für mich und für die freundlichen Worte, die Sie mir davon sagen, danke ich Ihnen recht sehr. Sowie der Winter vorüber ist und die Häfen wieder offen werden, werde ich mir erlauben, durch das hiesige Handelshaus Melchior welches eine Comandite<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kommandite.</p>
               </note> in Victoria hatte und vielleicht noch hat, was ich noch von meinen <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Schriften vorräthig habe, zu übersenden; sie sind theils dänisch, theils deutsch, theils englisch. Sie haben die Güte gehabt in demselben Briefe anzubieten mir Seewasser von dem Südmeere zu verschaffen und ich würde Ihnen sehr verbunden sein, wenn Sie mir etwa durch einen Wallfischfänger Proben, namentlich von dem südlichsten Theil des Südmeeres aufnehmen lassen wollten. Besonders würde es mich interessiren wenn er auch Proben aus der Tiefe herauf bringen könnte, da ein Wallfischfänger schwerlich die Apparate hat um solche Proben sicher herauf zu bringen, an Bord hat, möchte ich folgende Vorrichtung vorschlagen: die Flasche wird offen, ohne Pfropf und mit dem Hals nach oben gewandt, hinabgesenkt und in der Tiefe wo sie bleiben soll 1/4 Stunde gehalten und dann so schnell als möglich heraufgezogen und verpfropft, doch so dass eine Luftblase zwischen dem unteren Theil des Pfropfens und der Oberfläche des Wassers bleibt. Mit einer Feile wird dann ein Feilstrich auf dem äussern Halse der Flasche gemacht um die Gränze<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Grenze.</p>
               </note> des Wassers im Halse zu bezeichnen und endlich die Flasche versiegelt. Da das Wasser in den tiefern Regionen des Meeres jedenfalls specifisch schwerer ist als in dem obern Theile, selbst wenn dieses grössere specifisches Gewicht durch die niedrige Temperatur veranlasst ist, so wird, wenn man nur etwas Zeit giebt das untere Wasser das Wasse ausgetreiben welches die Flasche von oben mit heruntergebracht hat, und aus demselben Grunde beim schnellen Heraufziehen nicht wieder aus der Flasche herausgetrieben werden. Es ist ein unsicheres Mittel, aber immer besser als gar keines. Der Feilstrich am Halse der Flasche zeigt mir an ob etwas von dem Wasser verdampft ist ehe es in meine Hände kömmte. Ich brauche nicht zu bemerken dass die Flaschen kurz vorher mit Salzwasser ausgespült werden müssen und dass die Korken rein und gut sein müssen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch Ihre Güte sind mir von Ihren schönen botanischen Arbeiten folgende zugekommen: Von Ihrer und Benthams Flora Australiensis 1 - 2</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Theil, Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae 3ter Theil und The plant indigenos to the colony of Victoria 1 Theil, wofür ich Ihnen meinen herzlichen Dank abstatte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich mögte gern durch Ihre Güte eine Erläuterung erhalten über das, was die Reisenden in Australien mit dem Namen Eisenstein (ironstone) bezeichnen, am liebsten ein paar Stücke von den verschiedenen Varietäten. Er scheint über grosse Strecken vorzukommen und fast als Gebirgsart aufzutreten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe mit dem Chef des Consulats Departementes wegen Ihres Wunsches etwas für […]<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An unknown amount of text missing.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">17 April 1865</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Professor Fr Mueller in Victoria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The sad state of war<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The German-Danish war over possession of Schleswig-Holstein, 1864-5.</p>
               </note> that has been in existence for over a year has had a considerable effect on my correspondence, which in part has come to a complete standstill, and I owe you a reply to at least two of your letters.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note> I was very pleased to see from the first of your two letters that you followed the same path in the same town and the same house with pharmacist Becker in Husum,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Both Forchhammer and M served their pharmaceutical apprenticeships at Becker's pharmacy in Husum. See Voigt &amp; Sinkora (1996).</p>
               </note> and your letter has taken me back to those old days of bright aspirations and limitless expectations and hopes; and even though my stay at the chemist's shop during the five years that I spent there was by no means pleasant and satisfying, I have got over all that long ago. I am exceedingly pleased, if my studies served as an influence to spur you on, and I thank you very much for the kind words you write to me about this. As soon as the winter is over and the harbours are open once more, I shall take the liberty of sending to you what I shall have available of my publications, partly in Danish, partly in German and partly in English,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">There are no works by Forchhammer at MEL.</p>
               </note> through the local trading house Melchior which had and perhaps still has a branch in Victoria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the same letter you have been so kind to make the offer of obtaining for me seawater from the southern oceans; and I should be much obliged to you if you could get samples collected, perhaps through a whaler, particularly from the most southern part of the Southern Ocean. I would be especially interested if he could also bring up samples from the deep, and as a whaler has hardly the necessary apparatus on board to take up such samples safely, I would suggest the following procedure: An open bottle is submerged without cork, neck uppermost, to the predetermined depth and held there for a quarter of an hour, and is then pulled up as quickly as possible and corked, but so that an air bubble remains between the bottom of the cork and the surface of the water. A mark is then cut with a file into the outside neck of the bottle to indicate the water level in it, and finally the bottle is sealed. As the water is no doubt specifically heavier in the deeper part of the ocean than in the upper parts, even when this greater specific weight is caused by the lower temperatures, given sufficient time the deeper water will force out the water that was brought down from above, and for the same reason will not be replaced again if the bottle is drawn up quickly. It is an uncertain procedure but always better than nothing. The filed mark on the neck of the bottle will indicate to me if any water has evaporated by the time it reaches my hands. I do not need to remark, that the bottle must be rinsed out with saltwater shortly before use, and that the corks must be clean and of good quality.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By your kindness the following of your fine botanical works have reached me: <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg>, vol. 1-2 by you and Bentham,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78), vols 1 &amp; 2.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae australiae</seg>, vol. 3,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The publication of the third volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta </seg>was completed in April 1863 with B63.04.01.</p>
               </note> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">The plants indigenous to the colony of Victoria</seg>, vol. 1,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B62.03.03.</p>
               </note> for which I sincerely thank you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I should like to receive through your kindness an elucidation about what travellers in Australia refer to under the name of ironstone, and preferable a few pieces of the different varieties. It appears to occur over large areas and to be found almost as a type of rock.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have [spoken] with the Head of the Consular Department about your wish [to do] something for […]<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An unknown amount of text missing. M had probably sought help from Forchhammer, as he did from others, in obtaining an honour for the long-serving Danish consul in Melbourne, J. B. Were; see <seg style="">M to C. Rafn, 25 May 1863 (in this edition as 63-05-25c); M to J. Agardh, 23 April 1870; M to J. Lange, 15 July 1871 and 1 December 1871 (in this edition as 71-12-01b).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
