<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ I would beg to advise you to have Lake Wendouree stocked with swans, as these animals pull up constantly the roots of water-weeds, together with their herbage for food. I think you might easily obt...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-12-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.12.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ I would beg to advise you to have Lake Wendouree stocked with swans, as these animals pull up constantly the roots of water-weeds, together with their herbage for food. I think you might easily obt...</title>
               <date when="1865-12">1865-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-12-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>a correspondent in Ballarat</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ I would beg to advise you to have Lake Wendouree stocked with swans, as these animals pull up constantly the roots of water-weeds, together with their herbage for food. I think you might easily obt...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.12.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To a correspondent in Ballarat</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ballarat star</seg>, 29 December 1865, p. 2. The correspondent is uncertain: the text is introduced by 'At the next meeting of the Council of Ballarat West, Cr Claxton will introduce to the notice of that body the subjects referred to in the following passage from a letter received from Dr Ferdinand Muller, Government Botanist, in reply to an enquiry made by Mr G. O. Rutter, formerly of Ballarat, but now of Melbourne:—’.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would beg to advise you to have Lake Wendouree stocked with swans, as these animals pull up constantly the roots of water-weeds, together with their herbage for food. I think you might easily obtain 50 black swans at Western Port, at this season, for 10s each. Taking off the upper joint of one wing, the animals could not leave the lake, would enliven the place, produce an abundance of young birds, and keep your water clear of weeds without recurrent expense. Of course some sort of protection ought to be afforded against dogs and shooting. I think I could easily procure the birds for you, having had them caught largely for my department last summer and the summer before. I think the birds would prefer the channels to the low portions of the swamp, for they are fond of deep water. If this proposition is found to be insufficient I should advise to excavate the desired spots at the dry season to some depth, unless you have facility of draining much water into the lake, so as to increase generally its depth to the submersion of the reeds.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the meeting of the Council held on 8 January 1866, M's letter was read, and Cr Claxton moved 'That fifty black swans be obtained at the cost of £25’. In a long discussion, doubt was expressed whether swans would be effective. The news item concluded: '<seg style="">'Cr Claxton stated he had moved in the matter, knowing the high repute in which the opinion of </seg>
                     <seg style="">Dr</seg>
                     <seg style=""> </seg>
                     <seg style="">Mueller</seg>
                     <seg style=""> was always held on many scientific subjects, but he had no wish to press the motion unnecessarily. The further consideration of the matter was then postponed for a month' (</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ballarat star</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 9 January 1866, p. 3). At the meeting of the Council held on 5 February 1865, when the item was reconsidered, ''Cr Claxton stated that the water in the lake having considerably fallen, while the reeds had grown very strong, he would ask the order of the day to be discharged. Agreed to. The town clerk was instructed to forward a letter of thanks to Dr Mueller for his suggestion' (</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ballarat</seg>
                     <seg style=""> </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">star</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 6 February 1866, p. 3). (Town clerk's letter to M not found).</seg>
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
