<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Garden, ¶ 30/11/65 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to draw your favorable consideration to the circumstance, that the time has arrived, when with advantage experiments on the culture of the...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-11-30-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>L65/11332, unit 110, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.11.30</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Garden, ¶ 30/11/65 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to draw your favorable consideration to the circumstance, that the time has arrived, when with advantage experiments on the culture of the...</title>
               <date when="1865-11-30">1865-11-30</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-11-30-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Cinchona</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James McCulloch</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Garden, ¶ 30/11/65 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to draw your favorable consideration to the circumstance, that the time has arrived, when with advantage experiments on the culture of the...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.11.30</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James McCulloch</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">L65/11332, unit 110, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot. Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">30/11/65</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to draw your favorable consideration to the circumstance, that the time has arrived, when with advantage experiments on the culture of the <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e (the plants yielding peruvian bark) may be instituted on a larger scale in this country. From my last annual report,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B65.10.01.</p>
               </note> presented to you, it will be apparent, that most likely the <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e would endure our climate in the mild humid air of the fern tree gullies. Should my anticipation be realized a most important and lucrative commodity will be added to our indigenous material of husbandry and to our articles of exportation. From a letter, received by last mail from H. E. Sir Will. Denison, the Governor of Madras, it appears, that in the <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name> plantations of the Neilgherri<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Nilgiri.</p>
               </note> hills, established four years ago, now annually 100 per cent will be realized on the capital spent in farming and maintaining the plantations. Allowing that our climate will not prove as genial to the <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e as the air of the mountains of the Madras Presidency and allowing also that the labour expense would compare unfavorably with that of India, it must still be admitted from the accurate data and calculations submitted by the Governor of Madras, that a large profit is likely to accrue from the yield of Peruvian bark in plantations formed in this country. I feel therefore justified to recommend my proposition, to establish a <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name> garden in one of the fern tree vallies, readily accessible from the city to your most favorable consideration. I should have urged the formation of such an establishment before, had the means presented themselves earlier than this moment to effect planting of <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e in Victoria extensively; but only this year the plants commenced ripening seeds in India and therefore only now facilities are afforded for obtaining enough of the <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e for entering practically upon their culture. I have however imported some years ago some living plants, have kept them under ordinary shelter in this garden, am encouraged by what I saw of their growth and have constructed pits for their multiplication. In wishing to give real effect to my proposition the difficulty presents itself to provide permanently for small experimental establishments, such as proposed, in the ranges. The botanic Garden is so much larger than those in other colonies as to involve a proportionately larger expenditure; it is moreover combined with a scientific branch, which though unexpensive compared with the results of its labors, and to the ordinary outlay of the garden; the garden furthermore is taxed with furnishing supplies for several hundred public institutions annually, thus supplying at an average 60,000 plants and 70,000 papers of seeds a year, and lastly the garden has out of its ordinary vote supported the pine plantations and those of the other timber trees, many thousands of which have formed (as will be noted on reference to the plan of my last report a permanent place in the extensive Gov. House reserve with a view of obtaining large masses of fresh seeds for future forest-culture. Next year the resources of the establishment under my charge will additionally be taxed by a series of experiments of a technological and chemical nature into the products and educts of timber, such as oils, naphtha, tar, alkalies, pyrolignous acid, paper material &amp;c. A laboratory for the purpose will be immediately constructed. Hence I find it impossible to carry on with the resources at my command the establishment of experimental plantations in country districts, especially as one single locality would not suffice for these trials, but as for <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>e a place is to be sought in the fern tree country, for cotton in the Murray-valley, for subtropical plants in the palmtree country of East Gippsland and for plants of the coldest inhabited zone in our snowy mountains. Each of these plantations for practical trials must be comparatively large; the ground requires to be fenced; a hut should be erected and an intelligent gardener or labourer be placed in charge of the place, not merely to prepare the ground &amp; place in it the plants, but also to protect the latter hereafter against native animals, thefts, overgrowth of weeds For the cinchona plantation I have selected sites on the Mount Macedon ranges; one of which could be occupied by plants of Chinese tea additionally. It appears not likely, that the proposed plantations can be connected advantageously with the industrial schools on account of the isolated sites of each plantation, the objects being to test the influences of the climatically most diversified conditions on eminently useful plants. I have in vain endeavoured to point out, how the proposed plan might be realized, if it meets with the approval of my honorable chiefs at all, unless by a special vote. If it is the intention to institute at once these experiments in the four different climatic regions indicated, not less than £200 for each spot or £800 altogether would be needed to carry out the objects for the first year and half the sum for a series of years subsequently, if fair prospects and ultimate success are to be gained. In the Madras Presidency the Government has spent on <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name> plantations alone during the last four years £21,270.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It would also be needful to learn from Government, whether these experimental Gardens could be most advantageously brought under the surveillance of my office or under the administration of any other department.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am most willing to select the land in the different spots and carry out in my department the arrangements and disburse the fund and attend to the superintendence, if the Government will entrust the whole to my care and my responsibility; or I shall gladly furnish advise to any other department, which you may deem more worthy to assume the new duties thus arising. If under a special vote these duties will devolve on myself, I beg that my manuscript schedules for the estimates of 1866 may be returned to me, that the needful additions may be made.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your most obedient</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The honorable the Chief Secretary</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">McCulloch initialled M's letter on 18 December 1865, but no funds were allocated to support the scheme proposed.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cinchona">Cinchona</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
