<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir ¶ ,— When reading the appalling accounts of the effects of the long-lasting drought in the desert districts of the interior, we are ever led to reflect by what measures the miseries thus from time...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-10-24c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.10.24c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Sir ¶ ,— When reading the appalling accounts of the effects of the long-lasting drought in the desert districts of the interior, we are ever led to reflect by what measures the miseries thus from time...</title>
               <date when="1865-10-24">1865-10-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-10-24c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Acacia mollissima</term>
               <term>Acacia lophantha</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Editor of the Australasian</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sir ¶ ,— When reading the appalling accounts of the effects of the long-lasting drought in the desert districts of the interior, we are ever led to reflect by what measures the miseries thus from time...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.10.24c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To the Editor of the Australasian</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The text given here is from 'The Prevention or Mitigation of Droughts', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australasian</seg>, 28 October 1865, p. 9 (B65.10.05). For reprints of the letter see Mueller's Bibliography. </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Sir</seg>,— When reading the appalling accounts of the effects of the long-lasting drought in the desert districts of the interior, we are ever led to reflect by what measures the miseries thus from time to time arising might be alleviated or obviated. On various occasions I have pointed out publicly that the wide dissemination of trees in the arid parts of the interior would exercise a marvellous effect on the increase of rain, on the retention of humidity, and on the mitigation of burning winds. For the purpose of raising timber in shadeless barren wastes, perhaps no country possesses greater facilities than Australia, inasmuch as some of our trees seemingly surpass those of any other country in celerity of growth, and in power to resist the dry heat of our summer season. I am satisfied that if over the extensive sheep-runs now visited by the drought such plants as the common so-called Cape wattle (the West Australian <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia%20lophantha">Acacia lophantha</name>
               </seg>), the ordinary wattle tree of Victoria (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia%20mollissima">Acacia mollissima</name>
               </seg>), and additionally <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalypti</seg> of quick growth, were raised, merely by scattering during the earlier part of the cool season large quantities of the seed over the ground, we should in due time no longer have to lament the destruction of vast flocks for want of fodder, and perhaps water, because the general climate of such districts would gradually become more humid, a tegument of herbage and grass would, under the shelter of timber vegetation, continue to cover the now generally naked soil even during summer, and from a heated bare surface of soils no longer that heat would emanate which now disperses every rain-cloud often for many a month, and which sweeps in currents of burning winds now widely over the continent. Moreover, the absorbing power of vegetation would prevent to a large extent the rain-water to flow away into temporary channels, and perhaps even the sudden and transient floods after thunderstorms would discontinue. Why the pastoral tenants in districts subject to drought do not cause the seeds of trees, especially such as mentioned, to be gathered and sown, with a view of establishing belts of timber, appears almost enigmatical. The seeds of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia%20lophantha">Acacia lophantha</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia%20mollissima">Acacia mollissima</name>
               </seg> might be gathered by tons for the most trifling expense, and sufficient seeds for 100,000 eucalypti might be obtained for the value of a few head of cattle. If merely the flocks were kept away for a season from the spots on which the acacia seedlings spring up, it would with the least care become an impossibility to annihilate the copses again, even by subsequent invasion of the pastoral animals, which indeed might to some extent browse on the young trees, and finally find in dry years even much additional food. Around Jerusalem, in Natal, in some of the South Sea Islands, in the dry high lands of India, and in Algeria, we have endeavoured by transmission of seeds from here to clothe the naked soil and ameliorate the climate. In Australia, however, almost no exertions are made in this direction. Not the least of the advantage of the measure which I urge anew on the pastoral settlers consists in the augmentation of the fertility of the land, by bringing, through the ever-active power of vegetation, the latent and dormant alkalies, and earths and acids needed for the nutrition of plants to the surface from strata below, into which the roots of trees will penetrate for food, to convey it to their foliage, and to leave these fertilisers with the decay of the leaves on the surface soil, not to be washed away, as was long erroneously supposed, but to be stored up for subsequent vegetation. But the remarks here offered apply as advice not to Australia alone. Who can cast a view over a North African landscape without reflecting what changes an extensive Australian acacia and eucalyptus vegetation would effect on the pictures of treeless desolation which mountains and plains, alike bare and waterless, there present? What amount of timber might not be realised on the desert ridges; what a cheerful image within a very few years be impressed on whole countries so near to the seats of ancient industry and learning; and what vast extension of means for human settlement, and activity, and support be afforded?</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Yours respectfully,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-variant: small-caps; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Gardens, Oct. 24.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Editor added: ‘If we remember rightly, our most highly esteemed correspondent once suggested, in conversation, distributing the seeds of the water-melon over the arid wastes of Riverina. His letter deserves, and will doubtless command, the greatest attention.’</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20lophantha">Acacia lophantha</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20mollissima">Acacia mollissima</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
