<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>16th Decbr 1865. ¶ Melbourne ¶ At your request I have the pleasure to forward you a short account of my late trip beyond the Great Australian Bight. ¶  ¶ The expedition which left Melbourne in Janry 1...</title>
            <author>Edmund Delisser</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-12-16-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Royal Geographical Society, London, Archives, JMS/13/159, 1866.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>65.12.16</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Edmund Delisser</author>
               <title>16th Decbr 1865. ¶ Melbourne ¶ At your request I have the pleasure to forward you a short account of my late trip beyond the Great Australian Bight. ¶  ¶ The expedition which left Melbourne in Janry 1...</title>
               <date when="1865-12-16">1865-12-16</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1865/65-12-16-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Pittosporum phillyroides</term>
               <term>Eremophila Scoparia</term>
               <term>Kochia sedifolia</term>
               <term>Grevillea</term>
               <term>Atriplex</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">16th Decbr 1865. ¶ Melbourne ¶ At your request I have the pleasure to forward you a short account of my late trip beyond the Great Australian Bight. ¶  ¶ The expedition which left Melbourne in Janry 1...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">65.12.16</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Edmund Delisser</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Royal Geographical Society, London, Archives, JMS/13/159, 1866.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter was published as Delisser (1865-6). The text given here follows the manuscript copy. The published version has several differences in punctuation and capitalization. To the MS there has been added in an unknown hand a title, and '(communicated by Dr. F. Mueller, F.R.G.S, Melbourne)'. The MS which was received at the RGS on 20 February 1866 was referred on 26 February to Sir Charles Nicholson whose report received on 9 March stated that 'No reliable observations or reckonings appear to have been made as to the precise positions of the points reached. … The route they traversed is nearly Coincident with that followed by Mr Eyre many years ago…[The] last portion of the Expedition seems to have been through a Country hitherto unvisited by any Traveller – and I think that if another Evening shall be devoted to Australian Geography a short abstract of this paper may be read and printed in the Proceedings.' <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The RGS cover folder records the decision made on 12 March as 'Short Abstract in Proceedings', but the complete letter was published. </p>
               </note>16th Decbr 1865.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">At your request I have the pleasure to forward you a short account of my late trip beyond the Great Australian Bight.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Delisser collected plants for M on this trip: see B66.04.01</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The expedition which left Melbourne in Janry 1865 under my command had a double object to effect – to explore the Country inland from the Bight, and to sink for fresh water on some claims taken by Messrs. Degraves &amp; Co. near to Fowler's Bay and the Head of the Bight. I started early in the year for the purpose of taking advantage of the earliest rains, but there was none untill the first week in April and although from that time until the first week of October we had sufficient rain along the coast, it did not penetrate into the interior beyond an average distance of 30 miles, but I don't think that this Country suffered more than other parts of the Continent from drought this year. While waiting for a general fall, I had wells sunk along the coast between Wahganyab and the Bight, and got good water at Coymbra in some sand-hills on the coast within 18 miles from the Bight, thus making the journey between Fowler's Bay and the Head of the Bight comparatively easy for packing up the provisions. Having waited untill June, I determined to take Mr. Hardwicke one of the party with me, and to lead out 3 pack horses, as far as they would go, in the event of being unsuccessful in finding water, and to return without them on our tracks, hiding water and flour at alternate camps going out.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leaving one man in charge of provisions and remaining horses at the Bight, I started with Mr. Hardwicke, on the 23rd of June, from a small limestone hole named Kŭtnã which I had found in 1862 and to which place I had packed out a few gallons of water. From here I went a course about N. 60<seg>°</seg> W. untill the 29th June when having entered scrubby country the evening before I turned north to get over some small hills covered with timber as myall, Sandalwood and Sheyaks.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sheyaks <seg style="font-style: italic; ">underlined, apparently by the editor</seg>. Sheoaks?</p>
               </note> The next day the horses not being able to go further and having exhausted our stock of water we were compelled to retrace our steps, the whole distance we had traversed without finding any surface-water. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The chief feature of the Country passed over as shown by the accompanying tracing<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The 'tracing' is not present in the file and is not published in the printed version, where the text has been amended to exclude reference to the tracing.</p>
               </note> is the immense plain which I have called the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Nūllarbor</hi>
               </seg> Plains from it's being destitute of any trees – which, commencing a few miles from the Coast extends such a long distance that we went 150 miles from the Head of the Bight before we entered a dissimilar Country. This plain, within 40 miles from the Coast, is in general well covered with the saltbushes, "<name key="Atriplex">Atriplex</name>" and "<name key="Kochia%20sedifolia">Kochia sedifolia</name>" which grew from 1 to 2 ft high, and in places is weIl grassed – the ground is undulating, and the higher portions generally covered with <name key="Eremophila%20Scoparia">Eremophila Scoparia</name>. Throughout the whole plain basins like clay-pans from a few feet to 2 or 3 acres occur in which, within 60 miles of the Coast Samphire grows, but after 100 miles on our tracks they were thickly covered with small trees <name key="Grevillea">Grevillea</name> and <name key="Pittosporum%20phillyroides">Pittosporum phillyroides</name>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The rock immediately under the surface is limestone and throughout a large portion of the Country we met numerous caves the air from which at daytime, especially in hot weather issues forth with great force – the noise from one we could hear 200 yards away and at the entrance the blast took our hats off. We remarked that at night the current of air is into the caves. From their number the portion marked in particular with "caves" seems to be composed of blocks of limestone enclosing large vacant places. No doubt water is in some of these caves but in the few we examined the numerous fissures prevented us from reaching the lowest levels. The appearance of the small basins clothed with timber have a pleasant effect; often these cannot be discerned untill quite close to the basins, in others they considerably relieve the monotony of the Plain. The soil from the commencement of these basins appears gradually to improve. Saltbush <name key="Atriplex">Atriplex</name> gives place to <name key="Kochia%20sedifolia">Kochia sedifolia</name> and the grass becomes thicker and greener the proximity of timber most probably being the cause. The soil on the timbered hills is a very red sand, and wherever any open patches were, the grass looked weIl; a few feet <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>below we found limestone. The Sheyaks were as fine any I have seen in South Australia and I believe from the number of Kangaroos, Parrots, and remains of Natives' fires we were not far from water when we were obliged to return. The latitude of 'Peelunibee' was taken by observation, but that of the termination of our trip is by calculation as in consequence of the almost certainty of having to leave extras behind I did not take my sextant out.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Yours truly, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>E. A Delisser</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I have not yet received the information promised me by Mr. Selwyn to whom I gave the few fossils I carried away – but the whole Country is a Iimestone formation – tertiary.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Granite was found about 30 feet at a well 2 miles from Pindubba,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pintumba, SA?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> or about 14 ms<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Printed version has</seg> 14', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">i.e. treating the contraction as 'minutes' not 'miles'. 'Miles' is correct.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> N.N.E. of Fowler's Bay.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Kŭ</seg>tnã is about 40' N.W. of Yeer Cumban Cowie, at the head of the Bight.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Final sentence is a footnote to the printed text. In the MS it is a marginal note alongside the mention of the place name.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Atriplex">Atriplex</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eremophila%20Scoparia">Eremophila Scoparia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea">Grevillea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Kochia%20sedifolia">Kochia sedifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pittosporum%20phillyroides">Pittosporum phillyroides</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
