<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MY EXCELLENT FRIEND— ¶  ¶ Nobody doubts your learning, your enthusiasm, your industry, your general goodness of heart, and your perfect sincerity both in the interests of science and the cause of Leic...</title>
            <author>the Melbourne Punch</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-01-25a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.01.25a </idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>the Melbourne Punch</author>
               <title>MY EXCELLENT FRIEND— ¶  ¶ Nobody doubts your learning, your enthusiasm, your industry, your general goodness of heart, and your perfect sincerity both in the interests of science and the cause of Leic...</title>
               <date when="1866-01-25">1866-01-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-01-25a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">MY EXCELLENT FRIEND— ¶  ¶ Nobody doubts your learning, your enthusiasm, your industry, your general goodness of heart, and your perfect sincerity both in the interests of science and the cause of Leic...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">66.01.25a </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From the Melbourne Punch</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For the text of this 'open letter', see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Melbourne punch</seg>, 25 January 1866, p. 36, under the headline 'Melbourne Punch to Dr. Ferdinand Mueller, F.R.S. &amp;c &amp;c.'</p>
               </note>MY EXCELLENT FRIEND—</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nobody doubts your learning, your enthusiasm, your industry, your general goodness of heart, and your perfect sincerity both in the interests of science and the cause of Leichardt; but a good many of us doubt your discretion. When, some months ago, you succeeded, after great exertion and much personal sacrifice, in organising an exepdition<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>expedition?</p>
               </note> in search of the deplored Leichardt, I kept silence. I could not approve of a scheme whose results were sure to be fruitless, and which might be disastrous; but out of the high regard I entertained for you, and the perfect conviction I had of your sincere belief in the necessity for the expedition, I forebore to fling upon it so much as a single drop of cold water, though, if almost anybody but yourself had originated the scheme, I should have been constrained to turn upon it a very strong jet. I could not but admire your ardent wish to recover traces of your lost compatriot, and the steady aid you received from the ladies would have made it a very ungracious task to offer absolute opposition. Indeed, between you and me, I knew that when the ladies took the matter up, opposition would, in accordance with a well-understood principle of moral force, have only helped on the project. Therefore, I naught spake; fearing much — but hoping a great deal, as becomes my sanguine temperament. And now I am not going to reproach you. I admire your enthusiasm as much as ever I did. Your generous devotion appears to me as beautiful as it always did; but —and I am serious now—don't get up any more expeditions in search of LEICHARDT. Let living men's lives be more precious than a dead man's memory, illustrious as this may be. The men whom you sent forth have barely escaped with existence.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>News of the travails of the Leichhardt Search Expedition in severe drought conditions near Cooper’s Creek reached Melbourne in January and the press carried brief accounts, for example, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australasian</seg>, 13 January 1866, p. 5: 'Dr. Murray … reports the whole party broken up, after narrowly escaping from drought at Coopers Creek'. See also D. McIntyre to M, 30 March 1866.</p>
               </note> Another hour or two and they would have been added to the long list of victims of whom I am every day reminded as I pass out of my door. There is no sadder episode in our history than that of BURKE and WILLS. Let their monument be the only one of its kind.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Punch </seg>office was at 77 Collins Street East, Melbourne, near the original site of the memorial<seg style=""> </seg>statue of Burke and Wills at the corner of Collins and Russell Streets, where it was unveiled in April 1865.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
