<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 28 May 1866. ¶  ¶ Just before the departure of the overland mail to Europe, noble Sir, I was pleasantly surprised by your kind letter of 15 February. ¶  ¶ As a luminary of ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-05-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Wachs, Nr 407, Akademiearchiv, Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.05.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 28 May 1866. ¶  ¶ Just before the departure of the overland mail to Europe, noble Sir, I was pleasantly surprised by your kind letter of 15 February. ¶  ¶ As a luminary of ...</title>
               <date when="1866-05-28">1866-05-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-05-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Wöhler</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 28 May 1866. ¶  ¶ Just before the departure of the overland mail to Europe, noble Sir, I was pleasantly surprised by your kind letter of 15 February. ¶  ¶ As a luminary of ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">66.05.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Friedrich Wöhler</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Sammlung Wachs, Nr 407, Akademiearchiv, Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Addressee inferred from other letters in the collection and from the contents of this letter.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 28. Mai 1866.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eben vor dem Abgange der nach Europa bestimmten Überlands-Post werde ich, edler Herr, durch Ihr liebevolles Schreiben vom 15. Februar freudig überrascht. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als Glanz der Wissenschaft, der auch ich eine Weile fast ausschliesslich Jünger war, standen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> oft in Gedanken vor mir. Kaum den Knabenjahren entwachsen benutzte ich das grosse Werk Berzelius's, dass durch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihr</hi>
               </seg> Genie eine Zierde der Literatur deutschen Wissens wurde. Unter allen Anregungen, die das Glück des Ungefährs oder die Güte der Menschen mir zuwandte, sind jene für mich die erhabensten gewesen, welche mich unmittelbar in Contact brachten mit Männern deren grosse Werke mein jugendlich beugsames Gemüth begeisterten und mich in die Bahn meines Lebens zogen. Mit filialer Pietät hänge ich diesen grossen Geistern an, und fühle mich so beglückt, wenn sie zu dem jüngern u wenig verdienten im entfernten Lande sich anregend herablassen. Meine armen Werke, Verehrtester, sind Ihres Lobes nicht werth. Da Sie aber solche so freundlich entgegen nahmen, werde ich 6 oder 7 andere Bände demnächst übersenden, welche hier unabhängig erschienen. Das Werk Benthams, an dem ich Helfer bin, u dessen 3 Band jetzt im Drucke sich befindet, ist aber nicht von hier aus zugänglich.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein junger Hannoveraner, namens Groener, der mehrere Jahre in meinem Departement beschäftigt war, nahm vor wenigen Monaten, ein paar Gegenstände für wissenschaftliche Anstalten Ihres Landes von mir mit. Wenn mich meine Erinnerung nicht missleitet, befand sich auch ein Stückchen (nur ein paar Unzen) des Cranbourner grossen Meteoriten unter diesen Kleinigkeiten. Dies ist alles was ich von dem grossen ja riesigen Exemplare zurück behielt, ehe es durch meine Vermittlung einen Ehrenplatz in Prof. Maskelynes Gallerie fand. Das kleinere Exemplar ist in unserm Staatsmuseum niedergelegt und unantastbar. Neue Auffindungen von andern Stücken sind seither nicht gemacht. Doch will ich das nächste Meteoreisen, das sich finden möchte, gerne Ihrer Sammlung zuwenden. Meine bleibenden Sammlungen haben sich hier auf Pflanzen beschränkt; doch will ich künftig Mineralien für Ihr berühmtes Cabinet aufsparen. Für das zoologische Museum steht bereits eine Sammlung von etwa 40 Arten Neuseeländischer Vögel bereit, fast die ganze ornithologische Fauna jener Inselgruppe umfassend. Diese Sammlung soll mit dem Schiffe Kent in nächster Woche bis London frachtfrei an meine Agenten Betham &amp; Blackitt, Coxs Quay, Lower Thames Street verschickt werden, u. wenn es irgend möglich ist sende ich ein Gebinde in Alcohol aufbewahrter Fische, die wohl alle Ihrer Anstalt neu sein werden, ebenfalls mit ab.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dem berühmten u vortrefflichen Professor Grisebach habe ich längst ein Versprechen auf Beisteuer von Pflanzen zu lösen. Doch muss ich diesen ausgezeichneten Gelehrten bitten, mit Nachsicht auf meine scheinbare Trägheit hinab zusehen. Meine 25000 Meilen Forschungsreisen in Australien habe<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">haben.</p>
               </note> durch endlose Entbehrungen u viel Leiden in dürren Wüsten und unter dem tropischen Himmel einen Körper geschwächt, der nie stark war u Phthisis als ein Erbtheil mit in die Welt brachte. Dann sind die Anforderungen in einem jungen Lande, das mit stürmischem Fortschritt dahin eilt, an eine Anstalt wie die meine colossal, u. doch ist ja selbst diese erst im Entstehen u eigentlich ganz meine Schöpfung. Mit einigem Stolz kann ich wohl sagen, dass als ein <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ganzes</hi>
               </seg> betrachtet, mein Institut nächst dem von Kew das grösste unter der britischen Krone ist. Wenn Ihr erhabener Freund nun gütig bedenkt, dass allein gegen 3000 Briefe im Jahre eigenhändig von mir geschrieben werden u dass manche Ehrenstellen mich officiell an ausser-amtliche Pflichten fesseln, so bleibt freilich die That u das Handeln oft nebem dem Willen u Wunsch zurück. Dennoch soll aber demnächst bei der grossen Vertheilung des überzähligen Pflanzen meines Museums dasjenige des Herrn Professors Grisebach nicht vergessen werden. Jedenfalls wird aber wieder eine Samensammlung für Goettingen u Herrenhausen mitfolgen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In tiefster Verehrung bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich schulde auch Ihnen, edler Mann, den Ausdruck meines tiefgefühlten Dankes, für die Güte sich bei der Unterstützung der Aufsuchung Leichhardts betheiligt zu haben. Ach, wenn doch der Arme noch lebend zu finden wäre (was wir nicht hoffen dürfen) um all seinen guten fühlenden Mitmenschen selbst Dank zu sagen. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Welch ein trauriger Tod des armen Barons v. d. Decken. Hätte der Arme doch nur seinen Pfad hierher genommen. Ich würde ihm haben zeigen können, wie mit seinen unabhängigen Mitteln, mit seinem regen Eifer, seinem trefflichen Talent u Kenntnissen ihm auf dem Felde der geographischen Forschung hier ein glänzender Weg offen stand! — Hier wo ihm die Ansiedler ruhig folgen konnten u Besitz nehmen konnten was er im Territorium der Königin für Niederlassung offen legte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eben bringt der Telegraph die Nachricht des Todes des jugendlichen Prinzen de Condé. Vor wenigen Wochen erst hatte ich eine längere Unterredung während der 2 Stunden die er hier war, da Sir Rod Murchison den talentvollen u gelehrten jungen Fürsten meiner Aufmerksamkeit empfahl. Sic transit gloria mundi!</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">28 May 1866.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Just before the departure of the overland mail to Europe, noble Sir, I was pleasantly surprised by your kind letter of 15 February.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As a luminary of the sciences of which I, too, was at one time an almost exclusive disciple, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> often stood before me in my thoughts. Barely past boyhood, I used the great work by Berzelius, that by your genius became an ornament of German scientific literature.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Berzelius (1825), Wöhler's translation.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Among all the stimuli which the luck of the draw or people's kindness brought my way, those have for me been the most edifying that brought me into immediate contact with men whose great works stirred my receptive youthful mind and directed me into my life's course. I remain attached to these great spirits with filial piety, and I feel so blessed when they condescend in a stimulating manner towards the younger and undeserving man in the far away country. My poor works, esteemed Sir, are not worthy of your praise. But as you were so kind to accept them, I shall shortly send 6 or 7 other volumes, that were independently published here. However, Bentham's work,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78).</p>
               </note> in which I assist and of which the third volume is now in print, is not obtainable from here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A young man from Hannover by name of Groener, who was employed in my department for several years, a few months ago took back with him a few articles from me for the scientific institutes of your country.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">During 1867, Groener, then in Hannover, served as intermediary in M's presenting to the Göttingen museum a complete skeleton of a Chinese man 'of undoubtedly unmixed blood' according to M's report, who, 'coming from Adelaide had died in the Grampians [Vic]' (Keferstein (1868), p. 11).</p>
               </note> There was also a small piece (just a few ounces) of the large Cranbourne meteorite<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Lucas et al. (1994).</p>
               </note> among these odds and ends, if my memory is not leading me astray. That is all I retained of the large, indeed, gigantic specimen, before it found a place of honour in Professor Maskelyne's gallery<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">At the British Museum.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> through my intervention. The smaller specimen has been deposited in our State Museum and cannot be touched. No new discoveries of further pieces have been made since then. But I should very much like to present the next meteorite iron that might be found to your collections. My remaining collections here are restricted to plants; but in future I shall put aside minerals for your famous museum.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The mineralogical museum at Göttingen. M sent 'a small case of Australian minerals' a few months later; see M to F. Wöhler, 14 September 1866 (in this edition as 66-09-14b).</p>
               </note> A collection of about 40 species of New Zealand birds is already in readiness for the zoological museum, comprising almost the complete ornithological fauna of that group of islands. This collection will be dispatched next week by the ship <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Kent</seg> free of charge as far as London to my agents, Betham &amp; Blackitt,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. Blackith.</p>
               </note> Cox's Quay, Lower Thames Street, and if it is at all possible, I shall also send a barrel of fish preserved in alcohol, which are all probably new to your institute.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am overdue in making good a promise of providing plants for the famous and excellent Professor Grisebach. But I must ask this eminent scientist to regard my apparent laziness with indulgence. My 25,000 miles on exploring expeditions in Australia have, by endless deprivations and great suffering in arid deserts and under tropical skies, weakened a body that has never been strong and that brought phthisis with it into the world as an inheritance. In addition, the demands that are made of an institute such as mine in a young country that rushes forward in tempestuous progress are colossal; yet this institute itself is still being formed and is really wholly my creation. With some pride I am able to say that, regarded as a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">whole</hi>
               </seg>, my institute is after Kew the greatest under the British Crown. If your eminent friend would be so kind to remember, that alone about 3,000 letters per year are written by me in my own hand, and that in addition many honorary positions tie me to extra-official duties, then deed and action do, I admit, often lag behind good will and desire. Nonetheless, in the shortly forthcoming large distribution of surplus plants from my museum, that of Professor Grisebach will not be forgotten. Certainly another collection of seed will be enclosed for Göttingen and Herrenhausen.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Herrenhausen near Hannover, the Royal Botanic Garden of the House of Hanover, was in the charge of three successive generations of Wendlands. M corresponded with the youngest, Hermann Wendland.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In deepest veneration I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I also owe you, noble Sir, an expression of my deeply felt gratitude for your kindness in having participated in the support of the search for Leichhardt.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably by a donation to the fund in support of the Ladies' Leichhardt Search Expedition, instituted by M in January 1865 (cf. M to A. Petermann, 24 February 1865 (in this edition as 65-02-24b), and M to A. Braun, 23 November 1865.)</p>
               </note> O, if only the poor man could still be found alive (what we can no longer hope) to personally thank all his good fellow-men!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What a sad death, that of the poor Baron von der Decken.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Karl Klaus von der Decken was killed in 1865 during an East African expedition.</p>
               </note> If only the poor man had made his way here instead! I could have shown him what a brilliant career in the field of geographical exploration would have been open to him here, with his independent means, his lively enthusiasm, and his admirable talents and knowledge! — Here, where settlers would have followed him quietly and taken possession of what he opened up to settlement in the Queen's territory.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The telegraph just brings the news of the death of the youthful Prince de Condé.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The young Prince de Condé died in Sydney in 1866 during a visit to Australia, aged 20.</p>
               </note> Only a few weeks ago I had a longer discussion with him during the 2 hours he spent here, as Sir Rod Murchison had commended this talented and knowledgeable young Prince to my attention. Sic transit gloria mundi!<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Thus passes the splendour of the world!</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
