<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 25/2/66 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to avail myself of the opportunity, at which the details of the expenditure for the services of the employees of the botanic Garden are brou...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-02-25a.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>O66/2150, unit 180, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.02.25a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 25/2/66 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to avail myself of the opportunity, at which the details of the expenditure for the services of the employees of the botanic Garden are brou...</title>
               <date when="1866-02-25">1866-02-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-02-25a.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James McCulloch</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 25/2/66 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to avail myself of the opportunity, at which the details of the expenditure for the services of the employees of the botanic Garden are brou...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">66.02.25a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James McCulloch</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">O66/2150, unit 180, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">footnotes to proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Melbourne bot. Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25/2/66</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to avail myself of the opportunity, at which the details of the expenditure for the services of the employees of the botanic Garden are brought before you, to recommend, that the office of the Assistant may be abolished at the end of 1866, and that then the present occupant of the Office may receive the highest recompensation, which the civil service act allows. To carry out the most rigorous economy combinable with an efficient working of the establishment has constantly be my aim; and since the apparently large expenditure at the botanic Garden has become repeatedly the object of public discussion, I feel the more bound to effect the saving of the item indicated. The appointment of the assistant was made during my absense in North Australia, and has been continued against my persuasion of its necessity; indeed it would have been abolished before, had it been one of daily wages instead of yearly salary. The functions of the assistantship are restricted to the botanical branch or nearly so; to extend them to a general assistant-office would be entirely impracticable and inexpedient.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During an occasional absense of the Director on journeys or otherwise the surveillance of the establishment can be well provided for without the appointment of a salaried permanent assistant. I have the honor to be, Sir, your most obedient and humble servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The honorable the Chief Secretary</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">&amp;c <space unit="chars" quantity="4"/>&amp;c <space unit="chars" quantity="4"/>&amp;c<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">McCulloch responded: 'I am much pleased to learn that the Director of the Botanical Gardens has resolved on reducing the expenditure connected with the Botanical Gardens and I assure Dr Mueller that I shall most willingly meet his wishes in economising the expenditure. Wilhelmi has been so long a servant of the Government and is placed under the operation of the Civil Service Act — it will be necessary to compensate him if his services are dispensed with and as the object that Dr Mueller has in view can be met by the dismissal of Heyne which can be done without any compensation if that course will be taken. There appears to be little difference between the salaries of the two servants. Dr Mueller will therefore have the goodness to give notice to Heyne that his services will no longer be required. I will thank Dr Mueller to say whether the number of men cannot be considerably reduced and I may say that I think the wages are too high.' M replied on 1 March 1866: 'The hon. the Chief Secretary being evidently very imperfectly informed of the value to be attached to Mr Heyne's as compared to Mr Wilhelmi's service, I beg leave to point out respectfully, that not only Mr Heyne's educational and professional knowledge far exceeds that of Mr Wilhelmi, but also that his services are at an average for <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">four hours</hi>
                     </seg> longer every day available to the Department. Thus Mr Heyne's remuneration is in reality <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">less than half</hi>
                     </seg> of that of Mr Wilhelmi. If the latter had to take the former's place, a measure which for many reasons would prove impracticable and very disadvantageous, an additional sum would have to be paid for extra assistant labor at the office. Mr Wilhelmi's services are comparatively of no value to the department except for manual work at the museum and this could be carried out at a much smaller rate of remuneration. I further have the honor to point out, that Mr Heyne has been in a superior position in the horticultural branch of the establishment eversince 1857, which Mr Wilhelmi acceded to an assistant position without my having had an opportunity to give an opinion on the creation of such, only one year before, his engagement from 1853-1856 having been temporary, interrupted and very subordinate. The compensation for the discontinuance of Mr Wilhelmi's office, I would beg leave to point out, might be saved by transferring his services to any other Department, for which his labours might prove valuable. To dispense with the services of Mr Heyne, who supports an aged mother, the Lady of of a physician, would be an act of much greater severity, than discontinuing the services of Mr Wilhelmi, the latter being entitled to a compensation, the former not. From my letter attached to my return of the employees, to which I beg to draw most respectfully the special attention of the honor. the Chief Secretary, the reasons will be apparent, why the number of the employees cannot be reduced without crippling same branch of the department. The only saving, which without serious injury to the establishment, could be effected, is that of the salary of the present assistant in the botanical branch. If the honorable the Chief Secretary desires it, the daily wages shall be reduced by from 6d to 1/1 though the rate of payment is <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">lower</hi>
                     </seg> than in most other departments of Government, at least if it is considered that no provision is made for ordinary illness, that to the system of eight hours work is not adhered, that for extra night duty and other work in extra hours no additional remuneration is offered and that only four holidays are kept.' McCulloch added on 2 March: 'I am of opinion that the servies of both may be despensed with without [...] to the department'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M replied on 5 March: 'In consonance with the desire expressed in the minute of the honorable the Chief Secretary dated 2/3/66 I have the honor to submit the following suggestions to effect a saving in the current expenses of the establishment without impairing materially its efficiency. That the Office of the Assistant be abolished at the end or the middle of the year 1866 or at any earlier period decided on by the hon. the Chief Secretary and that the occupant of the office may receive notification to that effect at an early day, in order that the sudden cessation of his appointment may not fall with too much severity on him. And further I would most respectfully solicit the favor of the hon. the Chief Secretary to confer on the Assistant hitherto here employed some other small appointment as may be or become vacant, such perhaps as that of a copying clerk or that of a station master on one of the smaller railway stations. To carry further out the wishes for economy expressed by the honorable the Chief Secretary I have reduced already the income of the horticultural officer (Mr Heyne) by two shillings a day, and the wages of many of the other employees by 6d a day.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also M to J. Mccuylloch, 7 March 1866.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
