<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>28 August 1866. ¶  ¶ The arrangements, esteemed Professor, that have been made for a renewed search for Leichhardt, are as follows: Mr Sloman, who had been appointed as second-in-command of the party ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-08-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.08.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>28 August 1866. ¶  ¶ The arrangements, esteemed Professor, that have been made for a renewed search for Leichhardt, are as follows: Mr Sloman, who had been appointed as second-in-command of the party ...</title>
               <date when="1866-08-28">1866-08-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-08-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="57">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="43">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">28 August 1866. ¶  ¶ The arrangements, esteemed Professor, that have been made for a renewed search for Leichhardt, are as follows: Mr Sloman, who had been appointed as second-in-command of the party ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">66.08.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Petermann: 'Erh. 22. Okt. 1866' [Received 22 October 1866]. For a published version of this letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 80-1.</p>
               </note>28/8/66.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Anordnungen, verehrter Herr Professor, welche für die Erneuung der Aufsuchung Leichhardts genommen sind, bestehen in Folgendem. Mr Sloman, der von dem armen M'Intyre als Unterbefehlshaber seiner Parthie ernannt war, ist instruirt, die Nachsuchung an den Golfflüssen fortzusetzen, und namentlich zu ermitteln, ob die Bastarde, welche sich unter den wilden Schaaren am Leichhardt- u. Flinders Flusse befinden, von der verlornen Parthie abstammen, oder wenn nicht ob Leichhardt mit seinen Gefährten das Golfland wohlbehalten überschritten habe. Diese Aufgabe zu lösen wird so viel Zeit erfordern als übrig bleibt, um den ursprüngliche Contra[c]t für eine zweijährige Suchungsexpedition durchzuführen, und somit erfüllt das Damen-Committee die gegen die Regierungen und die Privat Contribuenten unternommenen Verpflichtungen. Sollte nach dem Verlauf des 2ten Jahres es sich dann herausstellen, dass Leichhardt nicht an der Carpentaria Bucht umgekommen, dann werden vermuthlich die 4 oder 5 australischen Regierungen durch eine gemeinsame annuelle Subsidie das Unternehmen weiterführen, u dasselbe wird unter der Ägis der Damen bleiben, welche viel Scharfsinn und aufopfernden Fleiss dem Unternehmen zuwandten. Und selbst sollte das Dunkel, das Leichhardts Geschick verhüllt vorher aufgehellt werden, so werde ich darnach streben, dass die kleine Entdeckungscaravane mit ihren Dromedaren im Felde bleibe, um im Lauf der nächsten Jahre die Grundzüge einer </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">vollständigen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> geographischen Karte des Australcontinentes zu liefern.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sollte dieser Winter u Frühling in die Wüsten Regen gebracht haben, so werden vielleicht Warburtons Expedition die von Südaustralien aus sich nach Westen wandte, u. Hunts westaustralische Truppe, während sie nach Osten zieht, sich kreuzen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von all den traurigen Expeditionen ist doch die des Barons von Decken die traurigste! — In Central Afrika giebt es nur einen Weg des Vordringens. Es muss ein Einzelner sorglos den wilden Schwarzen unbewaffnet u ohne Habe entgegengehen u nicht eine Gegend müsste der Reisende verlassen bis er nicht durch freundliche Weise das Wohlwollen der Barbaren gewonnen u Fürsprecher für Weiterdringen erlangt habe. Ein paar Instrumente u Notizbücher ist alles was ein solcher Reisender führen darf, u es sollte ein Arzt sein, denn dessen Werth gestand selbst der grausame Herrscher von Dahomey ein.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets verehrungsvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sollte die Jahreszeit es günstig fügen, so wird Ihr geniales Project der Polfahrt sicher realisiert werden. Ich steuere £10 - - dazu bei, welche Sie vielleicht dem Hochstift zu senden wollen. Ich möchte Lebensmitglied der geographischen Gesellschaft werden, für die Sie ein Thaler Zuschüsse vorschlagen u möchte gern den Betrag ein für alle mal wissen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">28 August 1866.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The arrangements, esteemed Professor, that have been made for a renewed search for Leichhardt, are as follows: Mr Sloman, who had been appointed as second-in-command of the party by poor McIntyre,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Duncan McIntyre, leader of the Ladies' Leichhardt Search Expedition, died of fever during the course of the expedition.</p>
               </note> has been instructed to continue the search at the Gulf rivers<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. the rivers flowing into the Gulf of Carpentaria.</p>
               </note> and in particular to establish, whether the half-castes who live among the wild tribes at the Leichhardt and Flinders Rivers are descended from the lost party and, if not, whether Leichhardt and his companions travelled through the Gulf district safe and sound. To complete this task will require as much time as remains to carry out the original contract for a search expedition of two years' duration, and the Ladies' Committee will then have fulfilled its commitments to the Governments and the private contributors.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Governments of the various Australian colonies had provided subsidies and funds had been collected from private contributors in Australia and abroad to finance the expedition.</p>
               </note> Should it have been established at the end of the second year, that Leichhardt did not perish at the Gulf of Carpentaria, the four or five Australian Governments will probably continue to support the enterprise with a combined annual subsidy, and it will remain under the auspices of the ladies, who have devoted a great deal of acumen and hard work to it. But even if the darkness that veils Leichhardt's fate should be lifted sooner, I shall nonetheless strive to keep the small exploration party with their dromedaries in the field, so as to produce the fundamental features of a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">complete</hi>
               </seg> geographical map of the Australian continent in the course of the next few years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If this winter and spring have brought rains to the desert, Warburton's expedition,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The SA police commissioner Peter Warburton in 1866 led an expedition into the northern part of SA during which he discovered Lake Howitt and the Warburton River.</p>
               </note> which turned west from South Australia, and Hunt's Western Australian party travelling east<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In 1866 the surveyor Charles Hunt was exploring country some 300 miles east of York, WA, and deepening wells that he had sunk during an earlier expedition to the area.</p>
               </note> will cross paths.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of all the sad expeditions that of Baron von der Decken is the saddest!<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">The German explorer Karl Klaus von der Decken was killed in Somalia in 1865.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> — There is only one way in which to penetrate Central Africa. An individual person must confront the wild blacks care-free, unarmed, and without any belongings, and the traveller must not leave an area, until he has won the good will of the barbarians by friendly means and has obtained support for further advances. A few instruments and notebooks is all such a traveller may carry, and he should be a doctor, for even the cruel ruler of Dahomey<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kingdom at the Bight of Benin, West Africa, later a French colony.</p>
               </note> admitted to their value.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your ingenious project for a polar expedition is assured of success, if the season proves favourable. I contribute £10/-/- to it, perhaps you could forward it to the Hochstift.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Deutsches Hochstift in Frankfurt on Main, where Petermann in 1865 had called a meeting to promote a German North Pole expedition and instituted a fund for its financial support.</p>
               </note> I should like to become a life member of the Geographical Society,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M is probably referring to the Geographical Society [Gesellschaft für Erdkunde], Berlin, of which he had been elected a foreign member in November 1865.</p>
               </note> for which you suggest one Thaler subscription, and I would like to find out the correct amount once and for all.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
