<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>27 November 1866.  ¶  ¶ I cannot, venerated Sir, put your kind private letter, ¶  so rich in content, aside unanswered until the next mail. I would rather let my thoughts skip lightly from sentence to...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-11-27c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich. </msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>66.11.27c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>27 November 1866.  ¶  ¶ I cannot, venerated Sir, put your kind private letter, ¶  so rich in content, aside unanswered until the next mail. I would rather let my thoughts skip lightly from sentence to...</title>
               <date when="1866-11-27">1866-11-27</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1866/66-11-27c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Mesembryanthemum aequilaterale</term>
               <term>Cryptostemma calendulacea</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/cc8f5838-8fd9-4454-86da-4bd45da737d1">Nasturtium officinale</term>
               <term>Veronica salicifolia</term>
               <term>Erigeron linifolius</term>
               <term>Rumex acitosella</term>
               <term>Chrysosplenium</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/b0cab6bb-b1d5-4e4a-b9dd-1159e86e6555">Silene gallica</term>
               <term>Cyperus hydra</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/17e9cb40-f961-4155-8b1c-c954cdf09645">Loranthaceae</term>
               <term>Majanthemum</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/5dce4c74-5085-4f22-85aa-5ad5aadaff0b">Lysimachia</term>
               <term>Narthecium</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/4109dbbd-c83c-4bed-a695-fcd7e741206d">Sagittaria</term>
               <term>Stratiotes</term>
               <term>Hippuris</term>
               <term>Hottonia</term>
               <term>Butomus</term>
               <term>Circaea</term>
               <term>Glaux</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">27 November 1866.  ¶  ¶ I cannot, venerated Sir, put your kind private letter, ¶  so rich in content, aside unanswered until the next mail. I would rather let my thoughts skip lightly from sentence to...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">66.11.27c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotated by Martius 'praes. 12 Jan. 67' [Received 12 January 1867].</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2 pp. of MS attached to this letter, listing the genera first shown by M to occur in Australia, belong to letter M to Martius, 29 November 1866, as indicated in that letter. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>27/11/66</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr inhaltsvolles freundliches Privatschreiben, Verehrter, kann ich doch nicht bis zur nächsten Post unbeantwortet zur Seite legen. Ich will lieber in Gedanken leicht von Satz zu Satz hin hüpfen u hier u da einen laconischen Commentar liefern. In einem frühern Schreiben glaube ich meine Idee, an der ich seit der Jugend festhielt trotz alles Schwärmens für Deutschlands Einheit, hingestellt zu haben, dass nur in einem grossen Norden des deutschen Reiches u. einem grossen ebenso einmüthigen Süden Heil zu suchen sei. Beide grossen Staatenbunde mit ihren verschiedenen Interessen werden wieder für die Sicherheit Europas zu einem verbrüderten Doppelstaat vereint durch das Band der Sprache unserer Jugend!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mögen wir dankbar sein, dass im Bruderkampf Deutschlands Jugend nicht hinsank!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Doch nun zu den blumigen Feldern unserer Lieblingswissenschaft. Herrn v. Krempelhuber werde ich bereitwillig das wenige senden, was meine Flechten-Sammlung an überzähligen oder unbenannten Exemplaren enthält. Ich selbst bin gefesselt wie ein Gefangener an mein grosses Departement, das nur Kew nachsteht unter denen über welche England gebietet. Das dürre Flachland um die Stadt liefert keine Flechten, u. mein Sammler in Nordaustralien findet ebensowenig wie ich selbst früher selbst in den feuchten Tropenwäldern irgend eine erhebliche Zahl von Moosen u Flechten. Alle Bedingnisse des Vorhandenseins sind gegeben u danach sind diese grossen Pflanzengruppen so ärmlich vertreten. Sicher bedürfen manche Arten gewisser mineralischer Bestandtheile um überhaupt zu gedeihen u. in dieser Richtung haben wir noch viel zu forschen durch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg> Familien des Pflanzenreichs. Es ist sonderbar wie plötzlich gewisse Arten der Eucalypte mit eigenthümlichem Unterholze andern Arten weichen, wo immer sich die geologische Formation ändert. Geologie u. Phytologie müssen noch in einen viel näheren Einklang gebracht werden. Wäre es nicht am Besten eine grosse Kiste unpräparierter Algen zu senden? Die beschreibenden Bearbeiter der Polyzoa finden dann auch Material. Am wenigsten ist bisher die Pilzvegetation Australiens durchforscht; sie ist aber nicht reich, wenigstens nicht an den augenfälligen Arten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Name Dr. Eichlers erinnert mich wieder an das herrliche Geschenk der Flora Brasiliana das ich Ihrer Grossmuth schulde mit soviel andern Andenken an Ihre edle Freigebigkeit. Dr. Eichlers Arbeiten sind wunderbar tief, nur eins vermisse ich, eine Cursivschrift des Cardinalcharacters in jeder Diagnose. Das Auge wird so schnell angezogen durch eine solche gesonderte Schrift u das Aufsuchen der Arten so sehr erleichtert.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <name key="Hippuris">Hippuris</name> haben wir nicht in Australien nicht, aber h@tten wir ihn hier, es würde sich schnell verbreiten. <name key="Nasturtium%20officinale">Nasturtium officinale</name> verbreitet sich in Neuseeland so sehr, dass der Staat grosse Ausgaben hat um die Fahrt der Böte in den kleineren Flüssen möglich zu machen, u. ich habe schwarze Schwäne hingesandt um bei der Klärung zu helfen. Danach sehne ich mich nach den Lieblingen meiner Jugend. Ich hätte gern <name key="Stratiotes">Stratiotes</name>, <name key="Hottonia">Hottonia</name>, <name key="Butomus">Butomus</name>, <name key="Sagittaria">Sagittaria</name>, <name key="Lysimachia">Lysimachia</name> u.sw. in unsern Sümpfen u. Seen, u. <name key="Majanthemum">Majanthemum</name>, <name key="Narthecium">Narthecium</name>, <name key="Chrysosplenium">Chrysosplenium</name>, <name key="Circaea">Circaea</name> u.sw. in unsern Wäldern, u <name key="Glaux">Glaux</name> u andere Küstenpflanzen an unseren Strandwiesen. Nur die wirklich schädlich wuchernden Unkr@uter müssen wir entfernt halten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulacea">Cryptostemma calendulacea</name>, Rumex Acitosella, Cyperus Hydra, Silene Gallica, <name key="Erigeron%20linifolius">Erigeron linifolius</name>, u andere Pflanzen sind ein wahrer Schrecken des Landes geworden, denn hier ist in der winterlosen Zone der Wuchs der Unkräuter thätig durchs ganze Jahr.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Neuseelands Pflanzen kann ich viel aus meiner eigenen Sammlung liefern. Sobald die Wirren der Ausstellung vorüber sind, soll die Sammlung das Überzählige Ihnen bieten. Wie sonderbar, dass <name key="Mesembryanthemum%20aequilaterale">Mesembryanthemum aequilaterale</name> u <name key="Veronica%20salicifolia">Veronica salicifolia</name> auch in S. W. Amerika vorkommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Loranthaceen sind hier meist nicht eigensinnig in er Wahl der Bäume, deren Lebenssaft sie aufsaugen wollen, indessen doch auf eine Reihe von Gattungen, weniger auf Arten begrenzt, denen sie anhaften.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der edle gute Professor Fenzl muss eine rechte Trauerzeit durchlebt haben!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In dieser Woche hatten wir das Fest des Jahreswechsels in der Gesellschaft der Ärzte. Es fiel mir zu einen der Toaste zu bringen u ich konnte nicht umhin darauf die Aufmerksamkeit meiner Freunde zu lenken, dass die Medicin uns den Pass für Reisen durch ferne Weltgegenden liefern, dass aus ihr fast alle die grossen Träger der Naturwissenschaften hervorgingen, dass Medicin als die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">edelste</hi>
               </seg> Wissenschaft allen voranstehe u dass <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sie</hi>
               </seg> alle Disciplinen der Naturforschung vereine. Ich schloss mit den Worten: Like the maidens of honor gracefully surround their queen, like the satellites encircle the planet, so the great and noble science of medicine is surrounded by the natural sciences and brings them for the blessing of mankind in a most powerful contact! </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">27 November 1866. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I cannot, venerated Sir, put your kind private letter,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> so rich in content, aside unanswered until the next mail. I would rather let my thoughts skip lightly from sentence to sentence and make a brief comment here and there. I believe I put before you in a previous letter<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to C. von Martius, 26 September 1866. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> my view, to which I remained attached since my youth in spite of all my dreams of a united Germany, that safety can only be found in a large northern and a just as large united southern German state. Both large federations of states with their differing interests become united by the bond of the common language of our youth into a fraternal double-state for the security of Europe!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Let us be grateful, that Germany's youth did not die fighting brother against brother in a civil war!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But now to the flowering fields of our favourite science. I shall be happy to send to Mr von Krempelhuber the small amount of spare or unnamed specimens contained in my collection of lichens. I myself am chained like a prisoner to my large department, which is surpassed only by Kew among those ruled by England. The dry flat country around the city does not produce any lichens, and my collector in northern Australia<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>John Dallachy. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">finds just as few there as I had earlier on,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During the North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> there are no significant number of mosses or lichens even in the moist tropical forests. All the conditions for their existence are present, yet these large groups of plants are so poorly represented. I am sure many species require certain minerals to grow at all, and we still have much to research in this direction in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> the families of the vegetable kingdom. It is strange, how abruptly certain species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus</seg> and their particular undergrowth give way to different species, wherever the geological formations change. Geology and phytology must still be brought into much closer harmony. Would it not be best to send a large case of unprepared algae? That way the describing workers on Polyzoa find material as well. The fungal vegetation of Australia has so far been explored least of all, but it is not rich, at least not in conspicuous species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The name of Dr Eichler reminds me once more of the glorious gift of the Flora of Brazil,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. <seg style="">Martius (1840-1906).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> which I owe to your munificence, along with so many other mementos of your noble generosity. Dr Eichler's work has wonderful depth, I miss only one thing, a cursive print for the main character in each diagnosis. That way the eye is quickly drawn to such a different typeface and it facilitates the finding of the species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hippuris">Hippuris</name>
               </seg>is not found in Australia, but if it were here, it would spread very rapidly. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Nasturtium%20officinale">Nasturtium officinale</name>
               </seg> has spread so much in New Zealand, that the Government has to spend large sums to keep the smaller waterways open to enable the passage of boats. I have sent black swans there to help clear the waters. I do long for the favourites of my youth. I should love to have <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Stratiotes">Stratiotes</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hottonia">Hottonia</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Butomus">Butomus</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Sagittaria">Sagittaria</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Lysimachia">Lysimachia</name>
               </seg>, etc. in our swamps and lakes, and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Majanthemum">Majanthemum</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Narthecium">Narthecium</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Chrysosplenium">Chrysosplenium</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Circaea">Circaea</name>
               </seg>, etc. in our forests, and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Glaux">Glaux</name>
               </seg> and other coastal plants along our beaches. Only the truly harmful, rapidly spreading weeds must be kept away.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulacea">Cryptostemma calendulacea</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Rumex%20acitosella">Rumex acitosella</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cyperus%20hydra">Cyperus hydra</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Silene%20gallica">Silene gallica</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Erigeron%20linifolius">Erigeron linifolius</name>
               </seg>, and other plants have truly become a plague for the country, because in the winterless region here the weeds grow actively throughout the year. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I can send many New Zealand plants from my own collections. As soon as the bustle of the Exhibition<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Intercolonial Exhibition of Australasia, Melbourne, 1866-7. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> is over, spare specimens from the collection will be on offer to you. How strange, that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Mesembryanthemum%20aequilaterale">Mesembryanthemum aequilaterale</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Veronica%20salicifolia">Veronica salicifolia</name>
               </seg> occur also in S.-W. America.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <name key="Loranthaceae">Loranthaceae</name> here are usually not capricious in the choice of trees to which they attach themselves and whose vital juices they are trying to suck out, is spread over a number of genera, rather than being limited to some species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The good and noble Professor Fenzl must have lived through a real time of mourning.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This week we had our end of year celebration of the Medical Society. It fell to me to give the toast, and I could not help but draw the attention of my friends to this, that medicine provides us with the travel pass through distant parts of the world, that nearly all the great pillars of the natural sciences arose from her, that medicine as the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">most noble</hi>
               </seg> science stands above them all, and that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">she</hi>
               </seg> unites all the disciplines of natural science. I closed with the words: 'Like the maidens of honour gracefully surround their queen, like the satellites encircle the planet, so the great and noble science of medicine is surrounded by the natural sciences and brings them for the blessing of mankind in a most powerful contact!'</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Butomus">Butomus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Chrysosplenium">Chrysosplenium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Circaea">Circaea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulacea">Cryptostemma calendulacea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cyperus%20hydra">Cyperus hydra</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Erigeron%20linifolius">Erigeron linifolius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Glaux">Glaux</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hippuris">Hippuris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hottonia">Hottonia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Loranthaceae">Loranthaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lysimachia">Lysimachia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Majanthemum">Majanthemum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mesembryanthemum%20aequilaterale">Mesembryanthemum aequilaterale</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Narthecium">Narthecium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Nasturtium%20officinale">Nasturtium officinale</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Rumex%20acitosella">Rumex acitosella</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sagittaria">Sagittaria</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Silene%20gallica">Silene gallica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stratiotes">Stratiotes</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20salicifolia">Veronica salicifolia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
