<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ It concerns the discovery of a new symbiosis in the lichen kingdom that extends over many square miles and, in addition, information on the corresponding plant growth, therefore on life on a consid...</title>
            <author>Arthur Minks</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-03-00d-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.03.00d</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Arthur Minks</author>
               <title> ¶ It concerns the discovery of a new symbiosis in the lichen kingdom that extends over many square miles and, in addition, information on the corresponding plant growth, therefore on life on a consid...</title>
               <date when="1895-03">1895-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-03-00d-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ It concerns the discovery of a new symbiosis in the lichen kingdom that extends over many square miles and, in addition, information on the corresponding plant growth, therefore on life on a consid...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">95.03.00d</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Arthur Minks</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the extract from Minks's letter given here, see </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 15 May 1895, p. 5, where it is introduced by a letter from M to the Editor, 1 May 1895 (B95.05.07). Minks's letter is dated to March 1895 as the latest possible date it could have been sent in order to reach M by 1 May.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es handelt sich darin um die Aufdeckung einer neuen Lebensgemeinschaft im Flechtenreiche, die sich über viele Quadratmeilen Fläche erstreckt und damit um den Ausschluss über den entsprechenden Pflanzenwuchs; also über das Leben auf einem beträchtlichen Teile der Erdoberfläche. Um Ihnen in aller Kürze einen Einblick in diese neue Erscheinung zu verschaffen, lasse ich folgende Schilderung dienen, indem ich Sie auf die Arbeit selbst zur vollständigeren Aufklärung verweise. In Betreff der steinbewohnenden Flechten war die Meinung, dass sie alle ohne Unterschied auf der jungfräulichen Unterlage gedeihen können, ein Irrtum. Nur eine beschränkte Zahl häufiger und gemeiner Arten vermag dieses. Die anderen sind auf Vorbereitungen und Unterstützung von Seiten der ersten angewiesen. Bei der neuen Lebensgemeinschaft geht dieser soweit, dass solche unselbständigen Flechten mitten in lebenden anderen Lagern beginnen, diese letzten entsprechend ihrem Vorrücken ausnützen und damit verschwinden machen, um endlich selbst mit der unorganischen Unterlage in Verbindung zu treten und von Hause aus selbständige Flechten vorzutäuschen. Da hierbei die Gesetze der Harmonie beobachtet werden, und diese Vorgänge im dichtesten Gedränge des Flechtenlebens sich abspielen, vermag nur ein scharfblickendes und wohlgeschultes Auge sie zu erkennen. Als Beweis der grossen Abhängigkeit solcher Flechten dient die Thatsache, dass sie am Rande der wirtlichen Krusten angelangt, auf der nackten Unterlage nicht weiter entwickeln können. Ihr bisheriger Wuchs lebt in aller Selbständigkeit, wie jede höhere Flechte. Es ist schon deshalb in jener anfänglichen Unselbständigkeit kein Schmarotzertum, ja nicht einmal ein Ammenverhältnis zu finden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It concerns the discovery of a new symbiosis in the lichen kingdom that extends over many square miles and, in addition, information on the corresponding plant growth, therefore on life on a considerable part of the earth’s surface. In order to give you briefly an insight into this new phenomenon, I will let the following account serve, referring you to the work itself for a more complete explanation.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Minks appears to be summarizing his forthcoming work published early in the following year, i.e. Minks (1896).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> In reference to the rock-living lichens, the opinion was that they all without exception could flourish on the virgin substrate, an error. Only a limited number of widespread and common species are capable of doing this. The others are dependent on preparations and support on the part of the former. In the new symbiosis this goes so far that such dependent lichens begin in the middle of other living thalli, these latter accordingly exploit their advancer and thereby make them disappear to get in contact finally themselves with the inorganic substrate and pretend to be originally independent lichens. As in this connection the laws of harmony are observed and these occurrences take place in the densest crowding of lichen life, only a penetrating and well-trained eye is able to recognise them. The fact that having reached the edge of the host crusts they can no longer develop on the bare substrate serves as proof of the great dependency of such lichens. Their previous development exists in all independence, like every higher lichen. Therefore parasitism is not found in that initial dependency, indeed not even a nursing relationship.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
