<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>31/8/95 ¶  ¶ For some time, dear Sir Joseph, I owe you an answer to a most kind letter of yours, and now I am reminded specially of this by the arrival of an other friendly communication of yours. The...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-08-31-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Letters to Joseph Hooker, vol. 16, ff. 19-22.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.08.31</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>31/8/95 ¶  ¶ For some time, dear Sir Joseph, I owe you an answer to a most kind letter of yours, and now I am reminded specially of this by the arrival of an other friendly communication of yours. The...</title>
               <date when="1895-08-31">1895-08-31</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-08-31-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Gramineae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">31/8/95 ¶  ¶ For some time, dear Sir Joseph, I owe you an answer to a most kind letter of yours, and now I am reminded specially of this by the arrival of an other friendly communication of yours. The...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">95.08.31</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Joseph Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Letters to Joseph Hooker, vol. 16, ff. 19-22.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Annotated by Joseph Hooker: </seg>And Nov 17th with portraits of Brown &amp; WJH.</p>
               </note>31/8/95</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For some time, dear Sir Joseph, I owe you an answer to a most kind letter of yours, and now I am reminded specially of this by the arrival of an other friendly communication of yours. The work in the rural interests of the colony during the dire depression has been overwhelming and endless in the interests of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">breadwinning</hi>
               </seg> portion of the community and therewith for aiding also the revenue, that for the last 3 years I could give but little attention to anything beyond the local immediate requirements of the Department. The aid of Assistan[ts]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Obscured by binding. All square brackets in the text below have this meaning.</p>
               </note> in the establishmen[t] is very limited indeed, the whole annual grant for staff, working material of any kind, freight postage stationary museum material being only about £600 annuall[y.]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Office-rooms (7) I find in my private dwelling and I keep 3 Juniors on my private expense for the service. I mention this to you only in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">confidence</hi>
               </seg> and not with any discontentedness, contrarely I <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">cheerfully</hi>
               </seg> make all these sacrifices to keep up the dignity and efficiency of the branch of service, established by myself, but - of course - were I not alone in life or had to provide for relatives I could not act as I do. In mention this <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">privately</hi>
               </seg> to you, my only object is to make it clear to you, how difficult under these recuded<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">reduced?</p>
               </note> means it is for me, to keep up all communications in relation to our favorite science abroad, how difficult to maintain the interchanges and other obligations, which I have endeavoured still to do, and I may say heroically. If however short comings unintentionally arose on my side, it will be understood, how little I can diver[t] my attention from the requirements of my Office. In November and December, the annual examinations take place which I conduct as an <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hon.</hi>
               </seg> examiner for several Gov. Institutions here, which necessar[ily] takes up also much time.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I managed during the last 3 months, to see the 9th edit of the “Select Plants” through the press, brought up to recent date, as the 8th issue had been nearly exhausted by sale at the Gov. Printing Office.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B91.09.01; B95.08.04.</p>
               </note> In a winterless Colony the scope of culture is necessarily vast, and such a book is very much more in demand here than in colder countries and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">must</hi>
               </seg> be much under extension.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Knowing how very busy you are with the elucidation of the Indian <name key="Gramineae">Gramineae</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Indian grasses were published in late April and early December 1896 in Volume 7 of J. Hooker (1875-97); see TL2.</p>
               </note> and the finishing of the Nomina Plantarum,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">That is, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Index kewensis</seg>
                     <seg style=""> (B. Jackson (1895))</seg>.</p>
               </note> not to speak of the editing of the bot. Magazine, - all these large tasks simultaneously - I was reluctant to encroach with antarctic subjects on you, however significant the<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">they?</p>
               </note> would be above all to you, and no doubt you see Sir Henry Barkly, Mr Markham, Mr Keltie and others, who were kept informed of what we were doing here. The next two weekly mail-steamers ought to give us <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">full</hi>
               </seg> information of what you all decided on during the international Congress,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Very brief articles on the sixth International Geographical Congress, held in London, had appeared in the Australian press concerning a proposed expedition by C. E. Borchgrevink; for example, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 7 September 1895, p. 7, col. g. The full report was delayed (Keltie &amp; Mill (1896)).</p>
               </note> we having had here but very slight journalistic telegram[s] on that memorable gathering. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Two days ago in the geographic Council here I mentioned, that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>, the leader of antarctic thoughts, held also the view that it should be the British navy which ought to resume explorations in the south-polar regions on a scale adequate to the importance of the subject. The land-party need not be large for traversing any accessible ice-plateau and could be formed out of the British Marines there being also all or nearly all scientific staff available from Gov. Institutions to the Admiralty without extra-expenses[.] Some of the older Steamers of the R.N. now out of place for the modern requirements of war-fare (though God forbid we should have wars again), would still serve admirably for an expedition such as we all wish to send out and as the Australian Colonies are commencing to advance anew to prosparity<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">prosperity?</p>
               </note> through rising wheat-and-wool-prices the patriotism in these dominions and through their Legislatures might be called forth, so that a share of the extra-expenses to send supernumerary ships on such a glorious and useful errand, would surely be born by the Austra[l] colonies, none of the 7 refusing to contribute.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. including New Zealand as part of Australasia, as was common at the time. New Zealand sent delegates to the conferences held in 1890 and 1891 but not to the subsequent ones leading up to the federation of the other Australasian colonies in 1901. The Australian Constitution allows for the possibility of New Zealand becoming a State of the Federation (Preamble, section 6).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> While I am writing this, the British Association will be assembled and will doubtless in its geographic section further discuss the best means for resuming antarctic-work early and commensurately. I regard an <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">international</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">expedition</hi>
               </seg> unpractical, a Committee for such unworkable not only from jealousies sure to arise but also from the impossibility of often meeting. Belgium fits out already an antarctic expedition of its own, Norway is engaged in North-polar exploration so Austria already.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ever regardfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I lately wrote to your stately and accomplished daughter in law now at K G Sound.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sophie, Brian Hooker's wife, at King George Sound, WA.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <ab rend="letter"
                style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                type="heading">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If in your agrostologic researches you find that any [West]-Australia Grasses should change names in [...] [Census] [would] [you] kindly let me [know].</ab>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gramineae">Gramineae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
