<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 5/8/95 ¶ To the Permanent Secretaries ¶ of the Academy of Sciences. ¶  ¶ It was with the deepest sense of gratitude, dear and honoured Sirs, that I learnt I had been deemed worthy of being ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-08-05-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Mueller dossier, Archives de l'Académie des Sciences, Paris.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.08.05</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 5/8/95 ¶ To the Permanent Secretaries ¶ of the Academy of Sciences. ¶  ¶ It was with the deepest sense of gratitude, dear and honoured Sirs, that I learnt I had been deemed worthy of being ...</title>
               <date when="1895-08-05">1895-08-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-08-05-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="58">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="42">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Permanent Secretaries, Académie des Sciences, Paris</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 5/8/95 ¶ To the Permanent Secretaries ¶ of the Academy of Sciences. ¶  ¶ It was with the deepest sense of gratitude, dear and honoured Sirs, that I learnt I had been deemed worthy of being ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">95.08.05</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To the Permanent Secretaries, Académie des Sciences, Paris</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Mueller dossier, Archives de l'Académie des Sciences, Paris.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne, 5/8/95</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">A Messieurs les Secrétaires</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">perpétuels de l'Académie</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">des Sciences.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C'était avec la plus profonde émotion de gratitude, chers et honorés Messieurs, que j'appris d'avoir été considéré digne d'être élu Membre correspondant de l'Institut de France, une distinction à peine égalé par aucune autre dans le monde de science universelle, qui unit par contact individuel quatre siècles des recherches, - qui continuera d'allier les travailleurs sur les sentiers de savoir à l'avenir, - et qui sous les ailes de la France joindra en futur aussi bien, qu'elle la fait dans le passé les esprits les plus brillants pour le progrès la prospérité et le bonheur du genre humain!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pour moi-même la plus haute aspiration de ma vie a été atteinte en appartenant au nombre très limité d'élus, qui, alliés par les liens des sciences, exercent du siège de l'Institut une influence presque irrésistible sur l'opinion publique, les mésures des étâts partout où la voix humaine est ouie, où la force des idées recordées pénètre, où les rayons des découvertes illuminent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pour un humble contributeur aux pensées originales comme moi il doit être une source de fierté d'être le successeur du Savant illustre recemment décedé sur le champ dont il était un ornament et d'avoir l'honneur de remplir sa place.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J'essayerai pendant le court espace de temps, que je peux espérer encore vivre par la grace de providence, de me témoigner digne de la confiance reposée en moi, et d'aider les recherches surtout dans votre pays, d'où une si grande partie des acquets intellectuels est emanée et rependue.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">répandue.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Permettez-moi d'exprimer mon extrême reconnaissance au Président célèbre de l'Institut, aux Conseillers distingués et aux Membres honorés, et de reconnaître une fraternité, qui m'est ainsi accrûe avec le vénérable Nestor de la science botanique en France et avec ses Collègues speciaux.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Agréez, Messieurs, l'assurance de ma plus haute estime et de ma considération très dévouée.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 5/8/95</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To the Permanent Secretaries</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">of the Academy of Sciences.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It was with the deepest sense of gratitude, dear and honoured Sirs, that I learnt I had been deemed worthy of being elected a Corresponding Member of the Institute of France, a distinction scarcely equalled by any other in the world of science, that links through individual contact four centuries of research, that will continue to unite workers on the paths of knowledge in the future, and that under the wings of France will in future as well as it has done in the past bring together the most brilliant minds to advance the prosperity and happiness of the human race.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For myself, I have achieved my highest hopes in belonging to the very limited number of the elect who, united by the bonds of science, exert from the seat of the Institute an almost irresistible influence on public opinion and on the actions of states everywhere where the human voice is heard, where the force of recorded ideas penetrates, which are illuminated by discoveries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a humble contributor to original thought such as myself, it must be a source of pride to be successor to the illustrious Savant recently deceased in the field of which he was an ornament, and to have the honour of filling his place.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M succeeded to the place previously occupied by Nathanael Pringsheim (1823-1894), professor of botany at Berlin.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall try, during the short period during which I can through the grace of providence hope to live, to show myself worthy of the confidence placed in me, and to advance research above all in your country, from which such a large part of our intellectual acquisitions have originated and spread.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Allow me to express my extreme gratitude to the celebrated President of the Institute, its distinguished Councillors and honoured Members, and to acknowledge a fraternity which to me is thus enhanced with the venerable Nestor of botanical science in France and with his special colleagues.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Presumably M is referring to the Academy's senior botanist, C. Naudin, with whom he had earlier co-authored a French adaptation of his book <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select extratropical plants …</seg> (see B87.14.06).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Be assured, gentlemen, of my highest esteem and very devoted respect.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The dossier includes a note from M's correspondent Maxime Cornu, professor of horticulture at the Muséum d'Histoire Naturelle, to the President of the Academy: ' M. le B[ar]on de Müller, de Melbourne élu membre correspondant de l'Académie des Sciences, adresse, par dépèche, ses profonds remerciements au Président aux Rapporteurs et aux membres de l'Académie' [Baron von Müller of Melbourne, elected Corresponding Member of the Academy of Sciences, addresses, by telegram, his profound thanks to the President, the referees and the members of the Academy]. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
