<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Whoever has just the slightest knowledge of Arctic geography will know that the unfounded news that reached us recently ¶  is within the bounds of possibility and in Europe and America it was also ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-06-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.06.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ Whoever has just the slightest knowledge of Arctic geography will know that the unfounded news that reached us recently ¶  is within the bounds of possibility and in Europe and America it was also ...</title>
               <date when="1895-06">1895-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-06-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="58">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="42">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Krichauff</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Whoever has just the slightest knowledge of Arctic geography will know that the unfounded news that reached us recently ¶  is within the bounds of possibility and in Europe and America it was also ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">95.06.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Friedrich Krichauff</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Die Entdeckung des Nordpols’ [The discovery of the North Pole], <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 12 June 1895, p. 5 (B95.06.03). The quotation is introduced by 'Ueber diesen Gegenstand schreibt Herr Baron Dr. F. von Müller in einem uns freundlichst zur Verfügung gestellten Briefe an Herrn F. Krichauff J P., wie folgt’ [On this subject, Baron. F. von Müller writes in a letter to Mr. F. Krichauff J P., kindly provided to us, as follows].</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wer nur die geringste Kenntnis hat von arktischer Geographie wird wissen, dass die unbegründete Kunde, welche uns kürzlich erreichte, im</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Bereich der Möglichkeit lag, und in Europa und Amerika hat man es auch zuerst geglaubt. Die Wahrscheinlichkeit eines im Sommer offenen Nordpolar-Meeres habe ich mit Professor Petermann besprochen vor mehr wie 30 Jahren, wie er Kapitän Koldeway von Bremen nach dem nordöstlichen Grönland sandte, auch hatte ich mit Baron von Heuglin fast zur selben Zeit eine Korrespondenz darüber, wie er das Innere von Spitzbergen erforschte. Das Vorhandensein von Franz Joseph-Land, so gross wie Tasmanien, nachdem man Spitzbergen und Nova Zembla</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">ganz nahe 300 Jahre lang kannte, hätte noch vor 20 Jahren Jeder als ein Mährchen gehalten. Die Entfernung des Pols vom nördlichsten bekannten Teil von Franz Joseph Land ist nicht weiter als von Melbourne nach Adelaide. Wenn auf den arktischen und antarktischen Entdeckungsreisen kolossale Ballons in Gebrauch gezogen wären, so hätte viel mehr Chartographie durch Triangulation ausgeführt werden können! So viel ich weiss, war ich der erste, der Ballons für Recognoszierung anriet, und die Zukunft wird wohl lehren, dass die geographischen Karten der beiden Polar-Regionen grossenteils durch Ballon-Observationen ausgeführt werden müssen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Whoever has just the slightest knowledge of Arctic geography will know that the unfounded news that reached us recently<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>That a German expedition had reached the North Pole was reported in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Deutsche Australische Post</seg> (Sydney), on 18 May 1895. Convinced that the report was authentic, M prepared an English translation that was published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 23 May, p. 5, and elsewhere. Others were more sceptical, prompting M to seek confirmation from the editor of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Deutsche Australische Post</seg> (letter not found) who cabled Berlin and was informed that the story was a hoax. M’s admission that ‘for the first time in his life he ha[d] been cruelly deceived’, published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 29 May 1895, p. 5, was widely disseminated.</p>
               </note> is within the bounds of possibility and in Europe and America it was also believed at first. I discussed the likelihood of a north-polar sea open in the summer with Professor Petermann more than 30 years ago when he sent Captain Koldeway from Bremen to northeast Greenland.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to A. Petermann, 25 May 1865 (in this edition as 65-05-25c), and 26 November 1865 (in this edition as 65-11-26b).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> At almost the same time I also had correspondence with Baron von Heuglin about it<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Correspondence not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> when he explored the interior of Spitzbergen. Everyone would have regarded the existence of Franz Joseph Land, as large as Tasmania, as a fairy tale even 20 years ago, after knowing of Spitzbergen and Nova Zembla for nearly 300 years. The distance of the Pole from the northernmost known part of Franz Joseph Land is no further than from Melbourne to Adelaide. If colossal balloons were brought into use on Arctic and Antarctic voyages of discovery, much more cartography could have been carried out by triangulation! As far as I know, I was the first to recommend balloons for reconnaissance and the future will probably show that the geographical charts of both polar regions must be carried out for the most part by balloon observations.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
