<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sunday, 1 Dec. 1895. ¶  ¶ One of the most elevating letters, which I received in my whole life, dear Mrs Rowan, is yours written on the Colombus-Day, ¶  in which you convey the most cheering expressio...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-12-01a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS 2206 Ellis Rowan papers, National Library of Australia, Canberra.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.12.01a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Sunday, 1 Dec. 1895. ¶  ¶ One of the most elevating letters, which I received in my whole life, dear Mrs Rowan, is yours written on the Colombus-Day, ¶  in which you convey the most cheering expressio...</title>
               <date when="1895-12-01">1895-12-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-12-01a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ellis Rowan</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sunday, 1 Dec. 1895. ¶  ¶ One of the most elevating letters, which I received in my whole life, dear Mrs Rowan, is yours written on the Colombus-Day, ¶  in which you convey the most cheering expressio...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">95.12.01a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Ellis Rowan</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">MS 2206 Ellis Rowan papers, National Library of Australia, Canberra.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Sunday, 1 Dec. 1895.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>One of the most elevating letters, which I received in my whole life, dear Mrs Rowan, is yours written on the Colombus-Day,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> in which you convey the most cheering expressions, which our most gracious Queen condescended to bestow on my humble researches. Her Majesty is well known to evince a vivid interest also in all branches of art and thought, concerning even her remotest dominions, and our gifted Sovereign is cultivating Sciences and artistic application of them personally. Is it not remarkable that 3 Queens reign happily in Western Europe?<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Queen Wilhelmina of the Netherlands reigned 1890-1948 and Queen Maria Christina of Spain reigned as Regent for her young son, 1885-1902.</p>
               </note> May Victoria hold the scepter and wear the crown to initiate us far into the new century, and to witness the expansion and further flourishing of her empire, the largest of all, which it became under her reign!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Let me hope that your own splendid efforts under the highest auspices will gladden you on your own laborious path of life. It must be inspiring and sustaining to you also, that in the most exclusive science unions in the world and one which has passed already through centuries, the Institut de France has for its President a Musician and for its Secretary a painter,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">President: Ambroise Thomas; Secretary, Count Henri Delaborde. In 1895, the Bureau of the Institut was provided by the Académie des beaux-arts (Institut de France, </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Annuaire</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 1895).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> from both of whom I had some few months ago a letter of invitation,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> to attend as a corresponding member of this august Association the centenary jubilee, when I would have met personally some of the most brilliant spirits of our globe personally. But at a still continuing depression, to which a long protracted drought adds a distress, I could not leave my post, but wrote in French a dignified letter of felicitation.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> We are here grieved, I especially in our Roy. geogr Soc. of Austral., that the Admiralty cannot send out at present to the south-polar regions while the German Government is preparing one, and perhaps also a private one may be brought about in Europe, were especially for traversing the glacier-plateau towards the pole. I hope to see Lord Brassey in the course of the week, and when we presented in an inaugral adress at his Excellency's inauguration he received us in a spirit to lead us to think he will be a "Prince Henry the Navigator" to us. My name is known to the first Lord of the Admiralty, with whose family you are perhaps acquainted</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Many years ago the German firm of Frühling &amp; Goeschen transacted some cases of business for me in London</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now, dear Madam, can you with your intellectual power and Lady's grace give us also some help. Could you <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">soon</hi>
               </seg> see Lord Loch soon, to whom on my own inspiration I wrote when he was Governor of South-Africa, urging also aid from there in antarctic exploration, particularly so as great commercial advantages must arise also to H. M.'s S. Afr. Dominions by opening up for <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">steam</hi>
               </seg>-<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">whaling</hi>
               </seg> the almost unfurrowed sea under the African longitudes, Enderby Land being so near that Continent for a basis of operation. His Excellency <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">did</hi>
               </seg> bring the project before his Ministers, who were not unfavorable to the subject, especially as the revenue was good from the additional sources of the gold- and diamond fields. But it was a time of great politic agitation through complications with aboriginal population in interior states. Thus the whole remained in abeyance; but now is an opportune time to resume the consideration and give it practical effect. In the calmness of the Christmas- and Newyears festive days I intend to write the new Presidential Adress<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B96.14.01.</p>
               </note> when I will discuss the questions involved; but time fleetly passes on, and we like an Admiralty Expedition to operate during the summer 1896-97 already in the antarctic ocean, the waters near Enderby-Land having on one or two former occasions been formed open in or after mid summer. Of course Mr Goeschen would be reluctant to commit the Admiralty to an expenditure like that of the grand Expeditions through 3 years by Sir James Ross. But all we think requisite, while steam power is now available, would be, to devote for two seasons two of the older ships of the R. N.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Royal Navy.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> for this so promisingly glorious national service. Britain has possessions far south in Africa and America, and owns all Australia The additional expenditure to employ 2 ships in the new antarctic efforts can not be extraordinarily great so that the starting may perhaps not need to be delayed by waiting for subsidies &amp; be voted by the Legislatures of these possessions</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall look forward with great interest to an early answer of yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">With regardful remembrance</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir Jos. Hooker, Admirals Nares Richards Ommaney like Lord Loch would be sure to use their great influence that Britain is not altogether forestalled in antarctic new navigations</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
