<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 3rd December, 1895. ¶  ¶ You showed me, dear Sir Hercules, nearly forty years ago, the great consideration of consulting me with reference to arrangements for the formation of a Botanic Gar...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-12-03a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.12.03a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 3rd December, 1895. ¶  ¶ You showed me, dear Sir Hercules, nearly forty years ago, the great consideration of consulting me with reference to arrangements for the formation of a Botanic Gar...</title>
               <date when="1895-12-03">1895-12-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-12-03a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Acacia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Hercules Robinson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 3rd December, 1895. ¶  ¶ You showed me, dear Sir Hercules, nearly forty years ago, the great consideration of consulting me with reference to arrangements for the formation of a Botanic Gar...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">95.12.03a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Hercules Robinson</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'A botanical reserve-ground for the preservation of rare Cape plants', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Agricultural journal of the Cape of Good Hope</seg>
                     <seg style="">, </seg>vol. 9<seg style="">, p. 284 (</seg>B96.05.01).</p>
               </note>Melbourne, 3rd December, 1895.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You showed me, dear Sir Hercules, nearly forty years ago, the great consideration of consulting me with reference to arrangements for the formation of a Botanic Garden at Hong Kong;<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found; but see M to R. Heales, 3 August 1861 (in this edition as 61-08-03a). </p>
               </note> and I had the honour of communications of like kind when your Excellency represented Her Majesty in other portions of Her Dominions.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letters not found.</p>
               </note> Hence, in approaching you I feel somewhat more free than otherwise would be the case, and now would plead for two distinct causes, in which your powerful influence might realize hopes which as a scientist I entertain, and both of which affect the interests of the great South African possessions of Great Britain.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Robinson was at this time Governor of the Cape Colony, South Africa.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first of these regards the Flora of the Cape. The vegetation of South Africa is the richest in the world, not only as to number of species, but also as containing an astounding variety of plants of special and peculiar type, aggregated chiefly in the south-western provinces and occurring nowhere else. Hundreds of these are quite local and restricted to very circumscribed areas. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">They are sure to be swept out of existence altogether, unless special provision is made for their preservation.</seg> It is true that many of these are cultivated in the conservatories of botanic gardens. But necessarily such representatives are small and juvenile seedlings. Nor can they, in most instances, receive the precise climatic requirements, or natural soil-food, which they require. At the best these green-house representatives are certain in no long time to succumb, and to be lost to cultivation. Hence it follows that in future centuries hundreds of these beautiful and remarkable plants will be unknown save by the dried specimens preserved in State Herbaria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It may seem strange, or perhaps even intrusive, for me, a stranger who has never set foot on South African soil, to intercede for the protection of the primeval vegetation of the Cape. But I do not feel a stranger. In my orphan boyhood, that is, some sixty years ago, I used to take delight in examining along with our Australian <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>e</seg>, the vast number of South African Heaths, and many other charming Cape plants which then were the glory of European conservatories, although now largely superseded by mere horticultural productions of little merit and secondary interest. Is it not an endless pity that these most wonderful creations, on which the men of coming centuries would wish to gaze are doomed to absolute extinction unless a protecting hand is extended before it is too late? Once lost, there is no possible process of evolution competent to give them back to the world. Taking the matter on the lower line of profit and loss, it would be a recommendable measure to maintain some sequestered nooks or reserve-areas where rare native plants might be encouraged under conditions natural to them and favourable to their perpetuation. As in other parts of the world, the export of seed and plants of interest will never cease, and such commerce from the Cape might be much greater than it is. So far as bulbs are concerned no country in the world, not even the most favoured regions of Asia, could compete with the Cape.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The reserve-areas, necessarily set out upon Government land, would require location on many spots of varied character, because the plants constituting the indigenous flora are varied in their requirements. To some limited extent, certainly, plants could be reproduced and fostered outside the limits of purposely enclosed areas. Doubtless there would be found throughout the Dominion administered by Your Excellency many retired pensioners, past active service, who at trifling extra expense might become custodians and perhaps collectors for these varied asylums. I have great hope that your Excellency and not less the many enlightened statesmen administering under you, will not pass by a plea for their native denizens of Cape soil whose dumb appeal for a little of their own land, to save them from extinction, I am taking the liberty to voice in this letter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[…]<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Agricultural journal</seg> notes: 'The second portion of Sir Ferdinand's letter, omitted here, refers to proposals for a united Australian and Cape effort for Antarctic exploration.' On this, see also M to A. Macdonald, 1 April 1896. For M's involvement in Antarctic exploration, see Home et al. (1992).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I feel sure that this approach will be received in the generous spirit which has ever characterised your Government.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Regardfully yours,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand von Mueller<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Agricultural journal</seg> added a supporting comment from Professor MacOwan, drawing attention to the geological history of the Cape that explained the uniqueness of the flora. An extract of M's letter and McOwan's comments were printed in 'Horticutural notes’, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leader</seg> (Melbourne), 11 July 1896, p. 13 (B96.07.03). MacOwan lamented the necessity forced on botanic gardens in the Cape 'to grovel down into a nursery garden on commercial lines, in order to get money enough to keep it presentable for the daily stroller.' He went on to say: 'The public … care nothing for the special prehistoric flora of the land they live in, compared with the newest hideous abortion in chrysanthemums. For just such attempted making the Melbourne gardens truly "botanic," as opposed to being merely ornamentally floral, my dear friend Von Mueller endured the greatest disappointment of his scientific life.'</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
