<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>During my stay in Port Moresby the details about the unsuccessful German New Guinea expedition came to my knowledge. They went out from Mr Kowald the Government Agent for the Mekeo District. On 24 Oct...</title>
            <author>William Fitzgerald</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-11-00f-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>95.11.00f</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William Fitzgerald</author>
               <title>During my stay in Port Moresby the details about the unsuccessful German New Guinea expedition came to my knowledge. They went out from Mr Kowald the Government Agent for the Mekeo District. On 24 Oct...</title>
               <date when="1895-11">1895-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1895/95-11-00f-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">During my stay in Port Moresby the details about the unsuccessful German New Guinea expedition came to my knowledge. They went out from Mr Kowald the Government Agent for the Mekeo District. On 24 Oct...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">95.11.00f</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From William Fitzgerald</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 18 December 1895, p.6. The letter was introduced as 'Eingesandte Ergänzung des in letzter Nummer gebrachten Berichts über die verunglückte deutsche Neu Guinea Expedition' [Submitted addition to the report on the unsuccessful German New Guinea expedition published in the last number], and preceded by M to the Editor of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung,</seg> 11 December 1895. The letter is dated to November as the latest possible date on which it could have been sent, to reach M by 11 December.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Während meines Aufenthalts in Port Moresby kamen mir die Einzelnheiten über die missglückte deutsche Neu Guinea Expedition zu Ohren. Sie gingen von Herrn Kowald, dem Regierungsagenten für den Mekeo Distrikt, aus. Am 24. Oktober kamen 21 Konstabler und Träger in Motu Motu als die einzigen Ueberlebenden des ursprünglich 46 Mann starken Zuges an. Beide Führer des Unternehmens, die Herren Behring und Ehlers, hatten ihren Tod gefunden, als sie einen der Nebenflüsse des Motu Motu oder Williams River zu befahren versuchten und ihnen das Floss zu Stücken ging. Die Szene des traurigen Vorfalls dürfte etwa 70 oder 80 Meilen inland zu suchen sein. Man hatte grosse Entbehrungen auszustehen; so gingen z. B. die Nahrungsmittel aus und dazu kam hässlich kaltes Wetter in dem sehr gebirgigen Distrikt. Mehrere der</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Leute starben infolge des Genusses giftiger Beeren ; diebische</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Eingeborene halten sich mit dem grössten Teil der Nahrungsmittel in die Berge geflüchtet, so dass die beiden Weissen, nach Angabe der zurückgekommenen Träger, hätten "Gras essen" müssen. Herr Behring war, soweit sich hat ermitteln lassen, Chef der Polizeitruppe und hatte schwer an geschwollenen Beinen und Ausschlag zu leiden ; sein Gefährte, Herr Ehlers, hatte die Führung der Expedition übertragen bekommen, war ein bekannter Gelehrter und erst kürzlich in Neuguinea angelangt. Mit dem Floss gingen natürlich auch alle Sammlungen und Auszeichnungen zu Grunde, so dass der Zug fast gar keinen wissenschaftlichen Wert hat. Unter den Trägern befanden sich keine Eingeborene von Neuguinea, sie kamen vielmehr aus Neubritannien, den Solomons Inseln oder Neuirland. Sie verstehen etwas englisch und sind von prächtigem Körperbau. Ihre Bewaffnung bestand in Mausergewehren. Bei ihrer Rückkehr nach Motu Motu waren sie sämtlich aufs äusserste abgemattet und hatten den Körper voll Schwellungen und Hautwunden; mehrere von ihnen starben, als sie bereits Pflege erhalten konnten. Hauptursache des Fehlschlages dieser Expedition scheint mangelhafte Ausrüstung mit <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Lebensmitteln gewesen zu sein. Nach Aussage der Träger hat man nur wenige Eingeborene zu Gesicht bekommen und ist von ihnen nicht ernsthaft behelligt worden. Die durchzogene Gegend soll sehr gebirgig kalt und unbewohnt sein. Wo jetzt die Deutschen (fährt der englische Schreiber fort) den Anfang gemacht haben, wäre es auch wohl an der Zeit, dass die Kolonien etwas für die Erforschung der grossen Insel thäten. Eine Reise ganz hindurch würde zwar etwas kostspielig sein ; man müsste mindestens acht mit dem Gebrauch von Feuerwaffen betraute Eingeborene dazu anwerben, ausser den Trägern. Auch würde man, ausser sonstigen Ausrüstungsgegenständen, mindestens für drei Monate Proviant anzuschaffen haben. Für Tauschzwecke würden allerlei europäische Waaren, die den Eingeborenen noch neu sind, wie billige Messer, grellfarbige Kattune, Tabak geringster Sorte, denaturierter Spiritus, Perlen &amp;c. zu kaufen sein. Der Schreiber glaubt, dass eine solche Expedition sich auch ganz gut bezahlt machen werde, nämlich durch die gesammelten Kuriositäten &amp;c. Die Kosten für die neuliche Expedition der Herren Armit und Guise seien z. B. durch den Verkauf der Bälge neuer Vogelarten mehr wie gedeckt worden und die Insel biete dem Forscher und Sammler ein ebenso grosses wie reiches Arbeitsfeld.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During my stay in Port Moresby the details about the unsuccessful German New Guinea expedition came to my knowledge. They went out from Mr Kowald the Government Agent for the Mekeo District. On 24 October 21 constables and bearers arrived in Motu Motu as the only survivors of the original 46-man-strong troop. Both leaders of the undertaking, Messrs Behring and Ehlers, met their deaths when they tried to navigate one of the tributaries of the Motu Motu or Williams River and their raft went to pieces. The scene of the sad incident could be searched for about 70 or 80 miles inland. They had to endure great hardships, so for example the provisions ran out and in addition beastly cold weather came in the very mountainous district. Several of the people died in consequence of eating poisonous berries. Thievish natives had fled into the mountains with the largest part of the provisions, so that both the Whites, according to the statements of the bearers who returned, had to 'eat grass'. Mr Behring, as far as it can be ascertained, was chief of the troop of police and had to suffer from severely swollen legs and rashes. His companion Mr Ehlers had taken over command of the expedition, was a well-known scholar and only recently arrived in New Guinea. Of course all collections and sketches also sank with the raft, so that the expedition has almost no scientific value at all. There were no natives of New Guinea among the bearers, rather they came from New Britain, the Solomon Islands or New Ireland. They understood some English and are of splendid physique. Their weapons consisted of Mauser rifles. On their return to Motu Motu they were all extremely fatigued and their bodies were full of swellings and skin wounds. Several of them died when they were already able to receive care. The main cause of the failure of this expedition seems to have been insufficient supply of provisions. According to the account of the bearers, only few natives were seen and they were not seriously bothered by them. The area traversed is said to be very mountainous, cold and uninhabited. Where now the Germans (the English writer continues) have made a beginning, it would probably also now be high time that the colonies did something for the exploration of the large island. A journey from one side to the other would certainly be somewhat costly. At least one must be careful enlisting natives entrusted with the use of firearms for it, besides the bearers. Also besides the other items of equipment, provisions at least for three months would have to be provided. For bartering, all kinds of European wares that are still new to the natives such as cheap knives, strong coloured cotton cloth, tobacco of the most trifling kind, denatured spirits, pearls &amp;c would have to be purchased. The writer believes that such an expedition will even pay for itself quite well, especially through the curiosities collected &amp;c. The costs for the recent expedition of Messrs Armit and Guise</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, ﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽﷽; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A party led by R. E. Guise, with W. E. Armit as second in command, climbed Mt Damon in 1894 and made 'a valuable collection of the flora and fauna'; see </seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sydney morning herald</seg>
                        <seg style="">, 8 May 1894, p. 6.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> have been more than covered for example by the sale of skins of new species of birds and the island offers the explorer and collector a both large and rich field of action.</seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
