<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>19/5/84 ¶  ¶ For a very long time, dear friend, I have not put pen to paper with such great delight as today, to congratulate you most sincerely for the high and well-deserved honour that was bestowed...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-05-19b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, folder 212, no. 618, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.05.19b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>19/5/84 ¶  ¶ For a very long time, dear friend, I have not put pen to paper with such great delight as today, to congratulate you most sincerely for the high and well-deserved honour that was bestowed...</title>
               <date when="1884-05-19">1884-05-19</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-05-19b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius von Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">19/5/84 ¶  ¶ For a very long time, dear friend, I have not put pen to paper with such great delight as today, to congratulate you most sincerely for the high and well-deserved honour that was bestowed...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">84.05.19b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius von Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, folder 212, no. 618, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">19/5/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit sehr langer Zeit, theuerer Freund, habe ich nicht mit so grosser Wonne die Schreibfeder ergriffen als heute, um Ihnen meinen innigsten Glückwunsch zu erstatten für die hohe und wohlverdiente Ehre, welche Ihnen zu Theil wurde von der R.G.S.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist doch nur eine ganz geringe Zahl Sterblicher, welche sich dieses hohen wissenschaftlichen Lohnes erfreuen können, und mit gerechtem Stolz werden Sie Ihren Namen unter denen, welchen die Medaille zu Theil wurde, eingereiht sehen. Dass nach den grossen Beschwerden u endlosen Gefahren Ihren Entdeckungs Reisen Ihnen nicht längst diese Auszeichnung zu Theil wurde, hatte gewiss nur darin seinen Grund, dass die R.G.S. doch nur 2 Medaillen jährlich vertheilen kann, und — wie Prof. Huxley neulich Sir Henry Barkly mittheilte — die Colonialen in ihren gerechten wissenschaftlichen Ansprechen leicht über sehen werden, während die heimischen Gelehrten, wenn solche von Entdeckungs Reisen zurückkehren, sich in den unmittelbaren Kreisen der engl. wissenschaftlichen Gesellschaften bewegen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist aber nicht nur, dass ich mich aus strengen Fach Rücksichten auf Ihre hohen Verdienste bei dieser Auszeichnung freue, sondern auch aus den wärmsten privat Gefühlen. Sie waren mir stets ein grossmüthiger u uneigennütziger Freund; Sie ehrten mich in hervorregender Weise in der Geographie der Alpen Neu-Seelands. Sie standen immer muthig für meine wissenschaftliche Stellung auf, und geben mir endlose Beweise Ihrer Güte. Für Alles dies habe ich mich nur schwach als dankbar beweisen können, u fühle ich um so inniger nun für Sie.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich denke noch immer mit Gerührtheit an Ihre neuliche Einladung u an die vor 20 Jahren; u vielleicht begrüsse ich Sie doch noch einmal in Ihrer Häuslichkeit und in Ihrer grossartigen Natur-Umgebungen, ehe ich aus dem Leben scheide. Sollte diese Freude dort bei Ihnen zu weilen mir aber doch versagt bleiben (denn ich leide noch schwer am Pulmonar Erkrankung), so halten Sie sich meiner treuen Dankbarkeit bis zum Ende meiner Tage gewiss!</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihnen u den Ihrigen recht Frohe Jahre der Zukunft wünschend im Genuss aller Ihrer Errungenschaften und Triumphe, bleibe ich verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">19/5/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a very long time, dear friend, I have not put pen to paper with such great delight as today, to congratulate you most sincerely for the high and well-deserved honour that was bestowed on you by the Royal Geographical Society.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Haast received the Patron's Gold Medal of the Royal Geographical Society, London, in May 1884.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is really only a quite small number of mortals who can enjoy this high scientific reward, and with just pride you will see your name ranked among those on whom the medal was bestowed. That, after the great hardships and endless dangers of your expeditions of discovery, this distinction was not bestowed long ago had certainly only its basis in that the Royal Geographical Society can only allot 2 medals annually, and — as Professor Huxley recently informed Sir Henry Barkly — the colonials are easily overlooked in their just scientific claims whilst the home savants, when they return from expeditions of discovery, move in the immediate circles of the English scientific societies.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But it is not only that I rejoice at your high merit in this distinction from strict specialist considerations, but also from the warmest private feelings. You were always a magnanimous and unselfish friend to me; you honoured me in an outstanding way in the geography of the New Zealand Alps.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Haast had named both Mt Mueller and the Mueller Glacier in M's honour.</p>
               </note> You always courageously stood up for my scientific position, and gave me endless proofs of your kindness. For all this I am able only poorly to prove myself grateful, and I feel so much more deeply for you now.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I still think with emotion of your recent invitation and of that 20 years ago; and perhaps I will greet you again in your household and in your wonderful natural surroundings before I depart this life. However, should this pleasure to stay there with you be denied me (since I suffer still heavily from pulmonary illness), you certainly will hold my true gratitude until the the end of my days!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wishing you and yours very happy years in the future in the enjoyment of all your achievements and triumphs, I remain respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
