<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>2 April 84 ¶ Memo No. 1098 ¶  ¶ Referring to previous correspondence respecting the presentation of the giant todea fern to the Botanical Gardens at St Petersburgh I beg to request the Government Bota...</title>
            <author>Thomas Wilson</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-04-02-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>P84/759, unit 22, VPRS 1163/P1 inward correspondence, VA 1123 Premier, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.04.02</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Wilson</author>
               <title>2 April 84 ¶ Memo No. 1098 ¶  ¶ Referring to previous correspondence respecting the presentation of the giant todea fern to the Botanical Gardens at St Petersburgh I beg to request the Government Bota...</title>
               <date when="1884-04-02">1884-04-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-04-02-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Todea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">2 April 84 ¶ Memo No. 1098 ¶  ¶ Referring to previous correspondence respecting the presentation of the giant todea fern to the Botanical Gardens at St Petersburgh I beg to request the Government Bota...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">84.04.02</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Thomas Wilson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">P84/759, unit 22, VPRS 1163/P1 inward correspondence, VA 1123 Premier, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This letter was first registered as B84/2968 in the Chief Secretary's Department, then referred to the Premier. See also M to T. Wilson, 18 March 1884 (in this edition as 84-03-18a), and M to T. Wilson, 3 April 1884.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 28 March 1884, E. Thomas, Secretary to the Premier, summarized the matter of the transit of the giant fern for the Premier, J. Service: 'In this case the Government Botanist, without authority or any kind of communication with the Government, made arrangements for transmitting and presenting to the Russian Government a very unique and handsome Giant Fern for the International Horticultural Exhibition of last year. The Account for the freight of the Fern to London was sent in, and Mr Berry immediately pointed out that the authority should have been obtained before the outlay was incurred, and he remarked, in a minute which has been communicated to the Government Botanist, that the proceeding was very irregular. We now get through the Secretary of State a despatch from the Foreign Office communicating the thanks of the Russian Government to the Government of Victoria for defraying <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">part</hi>
                     </seg> of <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">the cost of the conveyance of</hi>
                     </seg> "a Giant Fern <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">presented by</hi>
                     </seg> Baron von Mueller." I have enquired, as it seemed to me that it should appear on the papers, whether the mutuality of this arrangement had been sanctioned by the Government, and what the relative burdens were of the expense borne by the Government and the Baron respectively. I find that nothing whatever was known officially of the presentation, and that the expense to the Government was £32.15.0 to the Baron £15.8.6. The Hon. Mr Berry has already pointed out to the Government Botanist that that the expense should not have been incurred without authority. There are further points now brought out by the correspondence: 1. It seems to me that the Government should not be made a party to a mutual arrangement of this kind without its consent. Indeed, it may possibly be considered hardly dignified for the Government of Victoria to be in the position of contributing part of the cost of transport of an article presented to Russia by the Baron. Of course, if he likes to present anything to anyone wholly at his own cost, no one can say him "nay" but, if the Government are brought into the matter, it certainly should not be in a subordinate position to the Baron, or, at all events, not without its consent. 2. But this Fern, which was <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">really Government property</hi>
                     </seg> and purchased with Government funds, is acknowledged in the Despatch as the <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">present</hi>
                     </seg> of <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Baron von Mueller</hi>
                     </seg>, and this, <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">not as an officer of the Government</hi>
                     </seg>, because the Correspondence distinguishes in its thanks the Government and the Baron as two distinct parties. I think we should call upon the Government Botanist to exhibit a copy of the letter under which he made the presentation, so as to see whether he is responsible for this or whether it is a mere misapprehension. Our circular requiring all presentations to be made with the Premier's sanction will prevent this for the future. As an officer of this Colony the Government Botanist should not have communicated with another Government, excepting through the Head of his own Government.' Service consented to M being asked for his letter of presentation by initialling the paragraph in which Thomas made the suggestion.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 31 March Thomas wrote to Wilson: 'It appears that the cost of this Fern was defrayed out of the Vote for the Purchase of Plants: but in the Despatch [see footnotes T. Wilson to M, 3 March 1884] it is acknowledged as <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">the present of Baron von Mueller</hi>
                     </seg>. In order to see whether or not this is a misapprehension, Mr Service directs me to ask that the Govt Botanist may be asked to supply a copy of the letter under which the presentation was made, and of the acknowledgement.'</p>
               </note>2 April 84</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Memo No. 1098</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Referring to previous correspondence respecting the presentation of the giant todea fern to the Botanical Gardens at St Petersburgh I beg to request the Government Botanist will be good enough to furnish me with a copy of his letter under which the presentation was made, and of the letter received by him in acknowledgement.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Govt Botanist</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
