<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private ¶ A tick in purple pencil has been added to the MS to the left ofPrivate. ¶ 11/3/84. ¶  ¶ How sorrowful, dear Sir Joseph, that the great Bentham should not be able to enjoy the late evening of...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-03-11-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Kew Correspondence, Australia, Mueller, 1882-90, ff. 85-88.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.03.11</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Private ¶ A tick in purple pencil has been added to the MS to the left ofPrivate. ¶ 11/3/84. ¶  ¶ How sorrowful, dear Sir Joseph, that the great Bentham should not be able to enjoy the late evening of...</title>
               <date when="1884-03-11">1884-03-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-03-11-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plantnames</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Private ¶ A tick in purple pencil has been added to the MS to the left ofPrivate. ¶ 11/3/84. ¶  ¶ How sorrowful, dear Sir Joseph, that the great Bentham should not be able to enjoy the late evening of...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">84.03.11</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Joseph Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Kew Correspondence, Australia, Mueller, 1882-90, ff. 85-88.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">A tick in purple pencil has been added to the MS to the left of</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">Private.</hi>
                        </seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">11/3/84.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How sorrowful, dear Sir Joseph, that the great Bentham should not be able to enjoy the late evening of his life in genuine happiness, watching and directing the progress of others and living in daily interest and fruits of his labours. His case seems so much sadder still, as he has no<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>descendents; and he must feel thus<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>inexpressively<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>lonely and forlorn; though it must be a real consolation and comfort for him, to have<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>so near to him. This very absense of family-ties<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">I</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>can understand, thus I deeply feel for him; and when in late years I became oft melancholic, it was largely because through endless persecutions and undeserved adversities I gradually became too aged and so poor, that I could not build up a domestic home!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When I realized, that his feebleness was not a transient one, I have tried to do a trifle to cheer him; and he became lately elected on my suggestion a hon. member of the L.S. of Sydney. - Did I know, what might give him some little pleasure, possible to be done by me, I would at once carry it out. Your letter is from the middle of Jan; so the worst part of the winter will then soon have passed there, and perhaps he will rally in the spring. Kindly express to him my deep sympathy, and assure him, that I should always treasure my litterary auxiliary connection with him, as among the greatest of the achievements of my poor life.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And now, while thanking you for your solicitude about my health, let me say, that it is somewhat improved. To prevent progress of pulmonary disease is already a great gain. I am fitted up for correspondence, routine-officework &amp;c in a forestral region of Gippsland<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Near Drouin, Vic; see M to J. Hooker, 2 March 1884.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for the sake of the pure air, antiseptic Eucalyptus-vapour and tranquillity, so that I need not speak almost every day from morn til eve as in my Office, and my lungs get some rest; still this summer season has been unusually wet and cool; warm days we had few; I am compelled to work here in a room without fireplace, and am very weak, and my cough is only to some extent subdued, while the cold season is approaching again. To go on a lengthened tour to the tropics is impossible since the intrusion on my Department and its disruption took place; and I could not well trust myself away, without<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>giving up the rest of my position, [or] finding myself so impaired on my return, that my difficulties would be still more augmented. If a pension should be perhaps<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">forced</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on me, it would be extremely small, and I should be obliged to give up also the Herbarium and Library. So I might just as well perish here, as linger on in a miserable existence. Of course I may have too gloomy anticipations; but in letters from the Government here I am only<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>"the Gov Botanist", and all seems so cold, not to speak of daily jealousies.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You speak of a scientific expedition to New Guinea from Australia! I do not think it likely that any means were forthcoming for that in these colonies except just for emissaries of newspapers unless the great Papuan Island in its eastern half was annexed to Australia. Personally, I could not share any more in rough exploration-work. I am beyond the age for that, if even my pulmonary sufferings could be subdued; and half my salary would during any absense of mine be required for my Office-place still in a small private cottage in Melbourne, where there is so little working space, that whatever I do is retarded and often beset with the greatest difficulty. If you were only here for an hour you would realize all this. My position is in such a way taxed, that I cannot add to the dwelling, unless I throw myself into debt. As however<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the most jealous and powerful adversaries of mine lately passed away,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. G. Francis. See comment about Francis in M to J. Hooker, 25 December 1875, in this edition as 75-12-25a.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I shall make again an effort, to get back again half the ground and half the Garden vote; but while the man, who usurpates my place<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>William Guilfoyle.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>has an absolute sinecure by nepotism and has any amount of time to misguide people in reference to me and my wretched position I have no leisure to go out to plead my cause, polititians and indeed almost no one comes near me, unless a few of my medical friends in long intervalles, and they have quite enough to do in active practice, to give me that strenuous and continuous support needed for the resuscitation of my Department. Such can easily and quickly be destroyed, just like an exploring expedition may at any moment be disbandend; but it is very difficult and often impossible to reorganize it again. I trust, that when influential Australians come to Kew, that you and your Assistants will impress on them, that to be a Gov. Botanist without a Garden is an impossibility. Bentham[s] case is quite different; he is rich, had never had any official obligations to the state, and even<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">he</hi>
               </seg>, what could he have done without Kew, and what would the Kew-herbarium have been without the Garden? As regards my using the garden, you must kindly remember, that when I ceded before rude power, I did so under<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>protest; so far as a Gov. Officer can protest that I should break by going to my garden, though I am there in my thoughts in day-hours and in my dreams at night, - then with such a person as Curator, as the individual, who with the greatest audacity continues to style himself Director, is an impossibility; there aught to be also some<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>"point d'honneur"<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to one's professional brethern abroad. - And if I even live, and go yet through some years toil, to form a new garden, will it not be all altered into lawns, common flower-plots &amp;c so soon as I am dead?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Field work alone, even if I abandoned my position, does not work up any flora.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Here even this very day I shall do lots of things for the Melbourne-Exhibition soon to be opened. But where is the laboratory now? Where the apparatus? Where the raw material, where the manual working power. Last mail brought me letters from two University-Professors, who after years of efforts and solicitation<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">did succeed to get a garden</hi>
               </seg>, because even as mere teachers they found, that they could not do without a garden, Prof Just in Carlsruhe and Prof. Gubler in Rostock.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letters not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Had I remained in my garden, and had continued in a fairly roomy and at all events healthy dwelling, I should not have become so susceptible to colds, as I have been in later years, when I relapsed to my early<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>phthisic<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>disposition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have instructed my assistant in Melbourne, to send you by this post a copy of an article, I wrote from here, prior to the receipt of your letter, for the Melbourne Chemist<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B84.03.01.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in reference to priority-claims; these remarks originating through Asa Gray's<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>discussion of Alphonse de Candolle's last publication.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">A.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">Gray (1883).</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>When D.C. sent me his,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn7" n="8">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">A. de<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">Candolle</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(1883).</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I at once stood up for the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">right</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">genera</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>plantarum,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn8" n="9">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bentham &amp; Hooker (1862-83).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and wrote an appeal to the Bot. Centralblatt, which must since have appeared.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn9" n="10">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B84.04.05; the date of composition given at the foot of the article is<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'November 1883'. See M to J. Hooker, 24 June 1884.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have now followed it up; and as I am doubtless regarded in my far and disconnected position in the field of Botany as a sort of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>"<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">free-lance</hi>
               </seg>", I can speak with perfect independence and under no influence whatever.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What I said on both occasion may perhaps have some little weight with the Committee, which will deal with this priority-question<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in England. For my own part, I adhere to views, emanating from the purest<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">feeling of justice</hi>
               </seg>, which should overrule all considerations of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">form and usage</hi>
               </seg>. No doubt Darwin's endowment for a new bot nomenclator (is that really the best name? it savoures too much of former works)<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn10" n="11">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The nomenclator when it appeared<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>B.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Jackson (1895)<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>was titled<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Index kewensis</seg>.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is most munificent; but we should count it according to fortune; so I suppose, if Dr Fr Darwin sent<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn11" n="12">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">There is a vertical red pencil line in the central margin of the MS to left of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>Rev. B. Scortechini . . . Weld is sure,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">and to the right of</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>it savoures too much of former . . . Dr. Fr. Darwin sent.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="2"/>£3000 to the widow and daughters of poor<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Hermann Mueller,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn12" n="13">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Heinrich Ludwig Hermann Müller (1829–83).</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>it would be proportionately not so much as the poor £3 - - forwarded to day by me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What glorious prospects for new material at Kew!<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Some years ago I had some correspondence with Sir John Kirk about a journey of mine contemplated to the alpine mountains west of Zanzibar.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn13" n="14">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letters not found.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Sir John acted most kindly; the Sultan promised protection; but finally I had not in or out of the Department the requisite<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">money</hi>
               </seg>!<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Then there was Perak; my friend and to some extent disciple (so far as correspondence is concerned) the Rev. B.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Scortechini<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is gone there. He is still young, and as a Catholic priest without domestic ties; he has a keen eye for observation, and his coreligionist Governor Weld is sure<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn14" n="15">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See note 12<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>above.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to give him every possible aid and protection. Weld however has also shown some friendly feelings to me formerly.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn15" n="16">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M had corresponded with Weld when he was Governor of Tasmania (24 July 1878) and claimed (M to M. Fraser, 7 August 1876) that Weld, when Governor of Western Australia, had suggested that M might take up some land in that Colony, and had written to tell him of appointments made there (M to J. Haast, 30 April 1870).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The region here is the most unproductive for plants; I am too early for fungs and mosses; and as regards the general vegetation, I explored it at the risk of my life 31 years ago, being on the occasion once 5 days without food, had just about here a ride from 5 a.m. til 11 p.m without a settlement, and was nearly drowned in crossing one of the swollen water courses,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn16" n="17">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See Darragh (2003), p. 6 for an account of the incident by Bishop Goold, who was with M for this part of his 1853 journey; see also M to L. Haynald, 22 November 1882.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and subsequently narrowly escaped falling into the hands of cannibal-natives!<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Now</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>there are railroads, vast wealth is accumulating from the territory, and - of course - the early explorers are forgotten, and men come to the front now, then either unborn, or in their boyhood or in obscurity!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>One of the Senecios here puzzles me; but I can deal with it only after my return to Melbourne. I will then also reexamine<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Wittsteinia</hi>
               </seg>,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as I have some idea, that it belongs to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Gesneriaceae</hi>
               </seg>, though anomalous in that order also.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hardly ever get now a new plant to work out; Australia unless some of the forest-mountains of the far N.E. is almost exhausted as regards actual novelties of decided characteristics.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Pray, thank Mr Dyer for sending me the print on Sand-binding plants of India.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn17" n="18">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Gardeners</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">'</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">chronicle</seg>, vol. 21 (24 May 1884), p. 685.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I will use the information for the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>"select plants", so far as that is possible, as only some of the plants would be hardy beyond the tropics. I am sure, to pick up some notes from the new Kew-Report<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn18" n="19">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Presumably<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Report on the progress and condition of the Royal Gardens at Kew during the year</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1883</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(London, 1884).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and Mr Dyers Guide<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn19" n="20">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew (1883); this work appears not to have been issued until early 1884, and is favourably<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>discussed as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'recently issued'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Gardeners</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">'</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">c</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">hronicle</seg>, 29 March 1884, pp. 407-8. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Publication in late January or February is consistent with M's<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>receiving a copy in time to comment upon it in M to J. Hooker, 23 March 1884.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>also.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Very regardfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have written a few notes for the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Sydney Medical Gazette, reviewing Zopfs new work on Bacterian organisms (Spalt-Pilze);<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn20" n="21">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See B84.03.04, reviewing Zopf<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(1883).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the connection of them with numerous diseases, into which we now get more and more insight, is marvellous!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How grateful you must be to providence, to grant you unimpaired health and strength, without which you could not carry on your glorious labors! I suppose you see Sir Henry Barkly sometimes; give him my kind regards</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A new Civil service bill comes here in force now. Our Chief Rulers are now three permanent Commissioners; still much will yet depend on the individual Minister of the Department also henceforth.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn21" n="22">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Victoria's Public Service Board of three persons was created by the Public Service Act 1883.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>- What not happens perhaps to many mortals occurred to me lately; I<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">declined three Presidencies</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>within a few weeks, just before my illness; that of the new-formed Geographic Society of Sydney, that of the large Melbourne Turn-Verein and that of the Melbourne or rather Victorian Field Naturalists Club. The latter was offered me for several years in succession. You see, that most of my fellow-colonists wish me well! I shall also relinquish the Vice-Presidency of the Liedertafel; as I work under so much official disadvantage, and have therefore so little leisure now, besides all these positions involve extra expenses.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You speak, my dear Sir Joseph, of your florishing family;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">investments</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>in bringing them up are the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">best in life</hi>
               </seg>, and you will live through them into futurity.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Gesneriaceae</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Senecio</p>
            <p rend="plantnames"
               style="font-style: italic; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Wittsteinia</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
