<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>7/7/84 ¶  ¶ It does not require my assurance, highly esteemed Professor, that I was highly pleased when I heard of the acquisition of the special gold medal of His Excellency the Minister of Domains, ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-07-07b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.07.07b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>7/7/84 ¶  ¶ It does not require my assurance, highly esteemed Professor, that I was highly pleased when I heard of the acquisition of the special gold medal of His Excellency the Minister of Domains, ...</title>
               <date when="1884-07-07">1884-07-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-07-07b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Dicksonia billardierii</term>
               <term>Cibotium billardierii</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d50ddb57-69c1-4be7-b4fe-f1d8a1594f98">Todea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>[Gustav Reichenbach] </name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">7/7/84 ¶  ¶ It does not require my assurance, highly esteemed Professor, that I was highly pleased when I heard of the acquisition of the special gold medal of His Excellency the Minister of Domains, ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">84.07.07b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">To [Gustav Reichenbach] </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</seg>
               <seg style=""/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Reichenbach is identified as addressee since he was director of the Hamburg botanic garden, and M writes about shipping a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
                     </seg> to Hamburg. Reichenbach is known to have attended the International Exhibition of Horticulture at St Petersburg (see n. 3) to which M refers in the letter, and to have played an active role in the exhibition and associated International Congress of Botany and Horticulture as one of the official German delegates; see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin du Congrès international de botanique et d'horticulture, réuni à St.-Pétérsbourg, le 5-15 mai 1884</seg>, p. xiii.</p>
               </note>7/7/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es bedarf nicht meiner Versicherung, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, dass ich aufs Höchste erfreuet wurde, wie ich von dem Erwerbe des speciellen Goldmedaille S. Exc. des Ministers der Domainen hörte, als von den Preisrichtern dem von mir gesandten Riesen-Exemplar der <name key="Todea">Todea</name> ertheilt. </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihnen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> ganz besonders fühle ich mich verpflichtet für diese hohe Errungenschaft bei der letzten grossen Wettkampf in der Garten-Welt. Wenn Sie in Ihrem schönen Garten noch nicht diese Art vertreten haben in einem ansehnlichen Exemplar, so bin ich bereit, Ihnen eins zu senden, freilich würde der Stamm wohl nicht viel über 1000 lb wiegen, denn solche Exemplare sind schon sehr selten. In Süd Afrika soll das grösste bisher erlangte nur 150 lb gewogen haben!</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um mir aber die Sendung etwas zu erleichtern, möchte ich Sie bitten, einen Agenten in London zu wählen, der das Exemplar entgegen nähme, sollte nicht gerade ein deutsches Dampfschiff direct nach Hamburg von hier fahren.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Februar wäre die beste Zeit, die <name key="Todea">Todea</name> hier zu erlangen, da dann im Spätsommer die tiefen Waldthäler für Gespanne am ehesten zugänglich sind, denn käme die Pflanze bei Ihnen auch gleich nach der frostigen Jahrseszeit an. Das Herbeischaffen hier, u. die Verpackung u. die Fracht bis London würde ich hier bezahlen, so dass Ihnen nur die Kosten zwischen London u Hamburg erwachsen würden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich könnte Ihnen auch einen </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">grossen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Stamm von Dicksonia Billardierii (Cibotium Billardierii, sie ist nirgends antarctisch senden),</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M has placed the closing bracket in the wrong place; it should come after 'antarctisch'.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> falls Sie noch nicht mit einem hohen Ex. dort versehen sind.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Sammlungen trockner Pflanzen des verstorbenen Herrn Dr Sonder sind einstweilen bloss ausgepackt. Die Pflanzen aus Indien von Hooker's &amp; Thomson's eignen Reisen herrührend scheinen inserirt zu sein; doch da ich aus Bronchial Entzündung ein Erbleiden, welches mich nach Australien brachte, monatlang habe das Krankenzimmer nicht verlassen können, bin ich noch nicht völlig über diese indischen Pflanzen unterrichtet, hoffe aber bei herannahenden Frühlings Wetter bald die genauere Durchsicht vornehmen zu können. Wenn wirklich der grössern Theil separat gehalten ist, so wäre es leichter </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihnen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> (was ich ausserordentlich gern thäte, wäre es Privat-Eigenthum) die H &amp; T. Pflanzen zuzuwenden; es ist aber noch möglich, dass in dem grossen Weltaustellungs Gebäude hier, wo jüngst unter meiner Obhut ein specielles phytologisch technisches Museum begonnen ist, auch die Sonder-Sammlung ihren bleibenden Platz finden wird, weil dies grosse Gebäude central </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> der Stadt liegt, während der Bot. Garten, in dessen Reserve mein grosses Departements Herbar sich befindet, zu entfernt von der Stadt ist, um dem Studien leicht zugänglich zu sein.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sie ehrend und Ihnen Alles Gute wünschend</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Die grosse Gold-Medaille aus Petersburg wird neben anderen, die ich im Departement früher erwarb, in dem Kunst-Museum Melbourne's deponirt werden, da dies hohe Ehrenzeichen als der Colonie Victora zuertheilt doch betrachtet werden muss.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, der grosse und erfahrene Kenner, müssen in Hochgenüsse geschwelgt haben, wie Sie sich unter den grossartigen Pflanzen-Schätzen in der russischen Kaiserstadt befanden während der Welt-Ausstellung im Verein mit so viele Freunden. So ist also der ausgezeichnete Freund Goeppert nun auch dahin.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">7/7/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It does not require my assurance, highly esteemed Professor, that I was highly pleased when I heard of the acquisition of the special gold medal of His Excellency the Minister of Domains, as awarded by the judges for the giant specimen of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
               </seg> sent by me.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Imperatorskoe Rossiiskoe Obschestvo Sadovodstva to M, 30 May 1884, and M to G. Berry, 2 July 1884. At the International Exhibition of Horticulture held in St Petersburg, a gold medal was awarded to the Government of Victoria for the giant <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
                     </seg> that M had sent as Victoria's contribution to the Exhibition.</p>
               </note> I feel quite particularly indebted to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> for this high achievement in the last great competition in the garden world. If you do not yet have this species represented in your beautiful garden in a sizable specimen, I am prepared to send you one, admittedly the trunk would probably not weigh much over 1000 lb because such specimens are already very rare. In South Africa the largest obtained up until now is said to have weighed only 150 lb!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>However, in order to make the consignment somewhat easier for me, I should like to ask you to choose an agent in London who could take receipt of the specimen, should a German steamer just not sail direct to Hamburg from here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In February would be the best time to get the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
               </seg> here, because then in late summer the deep forest valleys are accessible with least delay for horse and cart, then the plant would also arrive at your place just after the frosty season. I would pay for the collecting here and the packing and the freight to London, so that only the costs between London and Hamburg would accrue to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I could also send you a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">large</hi>
               </seg> trunk of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Dicksonia%20billardierii">Dicksonia billardierii</name>
               </seg> (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cibotium%20billardierii">Cibotium billardierii</name>
               </seg>, it is nowhere Antarctica),<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had previously argued that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia antarctica</seg> is not an appropriate name and that the epithet should thus be substituted with one honouring the first person to describe the species [i.e. Labillardière] (B74.04.01, p. 175); he cited that source for the combination <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia billardieri</seg> in B83.03.04, p. 137. Because the combination was not explicitly made in B74.04.01, it is considered an illegal name under the International Code of Nomenclature.</p>
               </note> if you are not yet provided with a tall specimen there.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The collections of dried plants of the late Dr Sonder are in the meantime barely unpacked. The plants from India stemming from Hooker and Thomson's own journeys<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In M to J. Hooker, 28 November 1878, M accepted the offer of a set of duplicate specimens of the Indian collections at Kew. It is not certain when they arrived in Melbourne, but it was evidently some time before this letter was written.</p>
               </note> seem to be inserted; but because I have not been able to leave my sick room for months on account of bronchial inflammation, an hereditary disease which brought me to Australia, I am not yet fully informed about these Indian plants, but hope with the approaching spring weather soon to be able to carry out a closer inspection. If the largest part is really kept separate, it would be easier to let <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> have the H and T. plants (something I should very much like to do, were it my private property); but it is still possible that in the large Exhibition building here, where recently a special phytological technical museum has begun under my care,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">See M to the Exhibition Trustees, Melbourne, March 1884 (in this edition as 84-03-00a).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> the Sonder collection also will find its permanent place, because this large building stands centrally <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
               </seg> the city, whereas the Botanical Garden, in whose reserve my large departmental herbarium is situated, is too far from the city to be easily accessible for study.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully and wishing you every good thing</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The large gold medal from Petersburg will be deposited, together with others that I acquired in the department previously, in the art gallery of Melbourne, because this high award must indeed be regarded as awarded to the Colony of Victoria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">You</hi>
               </seg>, the great and experienced specialist, must have indulged in a great treat when you were among the wonderful plant treasures in the Russian imperial city during the International Exhibition in association with so many friends. Thus the excellent friend Goeppert is now also there.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cibotium%20billardierii">Cibotium billardierii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicksonia%20billardierii">Dicksonia billardierii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
