<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>19/5/84 ¶  ¶ A few days ago, Dear Sir Joseph, I received from one of the missionaries of New Guinea ¶  a small parcel of plants, collected in the  ¶ upper ¶  regions of Mt Owen Stanley's Range, not re...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-05-19a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Archives, Miscellaneous correspondence.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.05.19a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>19/5/84 ¶  ¶ A few days ago, Dear Sir Joseph, I received from one of the missionaries of New Guinea ¶  a small parcel of plants, collected in the  ¶ upper ¶  regions of Mt Owen Stanley's Range, not re...</title>
               <date when="1884-05-19">1884-05-19</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-05-19a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Chalmersia Papuana</term>
               <term>Gesneraceae </term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">19/5/84 ¶  ¶ A few days ago, Dear Sir Joseph, I received from one of the missionaries of New Guinea ¶  a small parcel of plants, collected in the  ¶ upper ¶  regions of Mt Owen Stanley's Range, not re...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">84.05.19a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Joseph Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Archives, Miscellaneous correspondence.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Annotated</seg>: This might go to [Linn Soc] if I had it by Thursday <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>W. T. T. D <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>30/6/84 <seg style="font-style: italic; ">and</seg> Ansd | 17/8/84. <seg style="color: #000000; font-style: italic; ">Letter not found, but see J. Hooker to M, 31 August 1884 (in this edition as 84-08-31a).</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Found with specimen K831965, which bears one of M's labels: '<name key="Chalmersia%20Papuana">Chalmersia Papuana</name>, | F.v.M | In the higher regions of Mt. Owen Stanley's Range. Rev Jam Chalmers | 1884'.</p>
               </note>19/5/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A few days ago, Dear Sir Joseph, I received from one of the missionaries of New Guinea<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">James B. Chalmers.</p>
               </note> a small parcel of plants, collected in the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">upper</hi>
               </seg> regions of Mt Owen Stanley's Range, not reached by them before. Among these few plants is one of remarkable showiness, so that I wrote a description of it at once, although unfortunately the fruit is wanting. It is evidently gesneraceous; but I find nothing like it figured by Mr Clarke<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Probably C. B. Clarke (1874).</p>
               </note> As however meanwhile Dr Beccari's <name key="Gesneraceae%20">Gesneraceae </name>may have become published,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Gesneriaceae? M was probably referring to plants collected by Beccari but to be described by other authors. For example the Gesneriaceae described in C. B. Clarke (1883) contained many specimens from Beccari's herbarium, acknowledged by Clarke as 'beautifully collected; <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>which has supplied far more novelties than any other collection' (p. 9). The volume had arrived during M's illness and he had not noticed that the supposed new genus was a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dichrotrichum</seg>, see M to J. Hooker, 27 May 1884.</p>
               </note> and as moreover some other publications concerning that order may have very recently emanated in Europe and remained unknown to me, I deem it best, to send the description to you,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See below.</p>
               </note> accompanying it by the best half of the foliage specimen, I possess. Unfortunately the fruit was not obtained</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Will you kindly spare the little time, it will take you, to cheque<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">check?</p>
               </note> any shortcomings on mine, as I have written the description away from my office at Dr Buettner's hospitable house,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had been staying at the home of his physician, Dr Alexander Büttner, in East Melbourne, in an attempt to overcome the persistent cough that had been troubling him for months.</p>
               </note> where I have but few books. Though I shall leave it quite to you where these notes may be published, if at all you approve of them, — I would venture to suggest, that Mr Britten might get them, because he repeatedly asked me for a contribution, and I have become quite faithless to his Journal<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of botany.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> for years. The local journals, which recently arose here, demand from me frequently litterary data; and you can understand that as a Colonist I cannot well refuse their request based on what is considered prior claims of the colony. Should I have failed to recognize this genus as known, and should still the species be unrecorded, then I would suggest that the finder's name should become that of the species, so that the valiant Mr Chalmers, who is a splendid “Bushman” (as we say in Australia) gets this little botanic reward for what must have been a most toilsome ascent of the Mt Owen Stanley's Range that far.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am so glad to hear, that Mr Bentham regains some strenght; and trust, that he will still further improve in his health this summer. Thus my long held anticipations, that he will outlive me, are almost sure to be realized. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Regardfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In the parcel brought from this tour by Mr Chalmers, is only one other plant of some importance, which I will pass through the press here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Buettner is a leading practitioner here. He studied 4 years in Berlin, where he took his degree, and then spent £3000- additionally to hear all the great specialists for several years in Paris, Vienne, Leipzig, Italy and also in Britain,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Britain <seg style="font-style: italic; ">over </seg>England <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> taking out <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">three</hi>
               </seg> scottish degrees. His Lady is highly accomplished in music, languages &amp;c, and as the whole family is german I feel not only, that I am under the best of treatment, but also that I have special sympathies, altho my English friends here express themselves also most kindly. Still I am very weak yet, so much so, that I again fainted last night, the violent paroxism of cough wearing out my strength and allowing me little sleep at any time</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have also now the best of the two trusses of flowers, got by the Rev Mr Chalmers.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">You have ... Chalmers. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Marginal note on back of first sheet of MS.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Chalmersia</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The description begins on a separate sheet..</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Calyx divided to near the middle into five semielliptical almost equal lobes. Corolla several times longer than the calyx; its tube gradually widened upwards, slightly curved; limb about three times shorter than the tube; upper lip slightly longer than the lower, bifid, its lobes roundish-blunt, nearly as broad as long; lobes of the lower tripartite lip nearly twice as long as broad, blunt. Fertile stamens four; the two longer of these slightly extended beyond the corolla, the two shorter stamens not quite reaching to the end of the lobes; filaments free from near the middle of the corolla-tubes, filiform, not appendiculated; anthers cohering in pairs at their apiculated summits, affixed above the base, bursting longitudinally, expanding elliptically; their cells parallel and connate. Sterile stamen rudimentary, capillary, adnate, much abbreviated. Pistil filiform, not much extended beyond the corolla; style thin, much shorter than the ovary; stigma divided into two semielliptic lobes. Ovary glabrous, stipitated, not twisted; ovules numerous. Disk entire, cupular. Fruit unknown.–– A Papuan herb, with procumbent, probably short stem, with scattered thin ovate-lanceolar irregularly serrated leaves, with elongated peduncle bearing a rich fascicle of large flowers.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A new genus of gesneraceous plants, belonging to the tribe of Didymocarpeae, differing from all other known genera of the order in the conjoint characteristics of scattered leaves, parallel connate anther-cells and filiform ovary.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Chalmersia%20Papuana">Chalmersia Papuana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the higher regions of Mount Owen Stanley's range; Rev James Chalmers. Stem rooting; densely hairy. Leaves 3 – 4 inches long, flat, appressed-hairy, gradually attenuated into a petiole of about one inch length, hardly paler beneath. Flower-stalk nearly a foot long, appressed-hairy. Flowers on the summit of the stalk numerously crowded. Stalklets a few lines long. Bracts spatular, about ⅛ inch long. Calyces measuring 3 – 4 lines in length, scabrous-hairy outside; the sinuosities open in bud. Corolla about 1½ inch long, dark-red in dried state, minutely rough-dotted all over, bract with very short hair outside, glabrous inside except towards the base, where scattered short hair occur. Anthers glabrous, about one line long, dark-colored, their slits anterior. Style roughly short-hairy. Lobes of stigma plan-convex, about ⅔ line long. Disk glabrous.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M withdrew the description and the genus was not erected; see M to J. Hooker, 27 May 1884. However, Moore (1889), p. 174 quoted Chalmersia papuana from 'Baron von Mueller's type at Kew'. The plant was subsequently described by M as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dichrotrichum chalmersii</seg>, published in B84.06.02, p. 14.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gesneraceae%20">Gesneraceae </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Chalmersia%20Papuana">Chalmersia Papuana</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
