<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>13/6/84 ¶  ¶ For several months I have been suffering from chest complaints, my parents died prematurely from phthisis and I had to emigrate to a warmer climate myself, dear Mr Möller, and I became so...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-06-13-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Biblioteca do Departamento de Botânica, Universidade de Coimbra, Coimbra, Portugal.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.06.13</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>13/6/84 ¶  ¶ For several months I have been suffering from chest complaints, my parents died prematurely from phthisis and I had to emigrate to a warmer climate myself, dear Mr Möller, and I became so...</title>
               <date when="1884-06-13">1884-06-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-06-13-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Adolpho Möller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">13/6/84 ¶  ¶ For several months I have been suffering from chest complaints, my parents died prematurely from phthisis and I had to emigrate to a warmer climate myself, dear Mr Möller, and I became so...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">84.06.13</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Adolpho Möller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Biblioteca do Departamento de Botânica, Universidade de Coimbra, Coimbra, Portugal.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">13/6/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit mehreren Monaten bin ich brustkrank gewesen, meine Eltern starben früh an Phthisis u ich selbst musste in ein warmeres Clima auswandern, lieber Herr Möller, u. ich wurde so schwach, dass ich der Correspondenz nicht völlig gerecht werden konnte. So weiss ich jetzt nicht mehr, ob ich Ihren letzten Brief beantwortete, oder ob es bei dem Entschluss blieb.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Da ich nun etwas mich erholt habe, so versuche ich, das Versäumte nachzuholen, u möchte Ihnen danken für das Interesse, welches Sie für das Erscheinen einer portugiesischen Ausgabe meiner "select plants" gezeigt haben. Wie steht es jetzt mit der Sache? Ist Aussicht vorhanden, dass sich ein Verleger in Portugal findet oder vielleicht in Brasilien? Wie ich früher bemerkte, war ich Willens £25 für das Übersetzen durch Sie und Ihren Freund zu zahlen, </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wenn</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> ein Verleger dann den Druck auf eigne Kosten übernehmen u mir einige Frei-Exemplare senden würde. Ich bin nicht reich, nicht einmal wohlhabend, u es ist mir nicht möglich, auch noch für den Druck zu zahlen. Ich habe den Wissenschaften im Lauf meines Lebens bereits überschwere Opfer gebracht.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Falls nicht Unternehmungsgeist genug unter den Buchhändlern Portugals existirt, um eine solche Übersetzung in Verlag zu nehmen, so möchte ich Ihnen rathen an Hr Dr Glaziou, den Director des bot Gartens in Rio de Janeiro zu schreiben, der vielleicht bei seinem grossen Einfluss in Brasilien doch Mittel u. Wege finden würde, um Ihre Übersetzung dort durch die Presse zu bringen. Es wäre doch recht schade, wenn Ihr Vorsatz aus Mangel an Druckmittel nicht ausgeführt werden könnte, um mein Werk in portugiesischer Sprache erscheinen zu lassen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Kann ich Ihnen etwas von hier senden? es soll recht gern geschehen, soweit mir dies möglich ist.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend und Ihnen alles Gute wünschend</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">13/6/84</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For several months I have been suffering from chest complaints, my parents died prematurely from phthisis and I had to emigrate to a warmer climate myself, dear Mr Möller, and I became so weak that I could not completely do justice to the correspondence. So I now no longer know whether I answered your last letter<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> or whether it remained a resolution.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since I have now somewhat recovered I am trying to make up for what was missed and I should like to thank you for the interest that you have shown in the publication of a Portuguese edition of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select plants</seg>. How does the matter stand now? Does a possibility exist that a publisher is to be found in Portugal or perhaps Brazil? As I remarked previously, I was willing to pay £25 for the translation through you and your friend, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">if</hi>
               </seg> a publisher takes on the printing at his own cost and would send me some free copies. I am not rich, not even prosperous, and it is not possible for me to pay for the printing as well. I have already made too-heavy sacrifices for science in the course of my life.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If not enough spirit of enterprise exists among the book dealers of Portugal to take on publication of such a translation, I should like to advise you to write to Dr Glaziou, the Director of the botanical gardens in Rio de Janeiro, who perhaps would yet find ways and means through his great influence in Brazil to bring your translation through the press there. It would really be a great shame if your intention to have my work published in the Portuguese language could not be carried out from lack of printing funds.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No Portuguese translation of M's book was published until 1905 (B05.13.01).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Can I send you something from here? It shall happen very willingly as far as this is possible for me.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully and wishing you every good thing</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
