<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>14 December 1884. ¶  ¶ My best thanks for your kind letter, noble friend, and for all the good wishes you harbour for me. Your retirement from your leading position in  ¶ Gartenflora  ¶ is a great los...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-12-14-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS 159, folio 21808, d. 76, op. 1, fond 335, Archives Department, Russian Academy of Sciences, St Petersburg.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>84.12.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>14 December 1884. ¶  ¶ My best thanks for your kind letter, noble friend, and for all the good wishes you harbour for me. Your retirement from your leading position in  ¶ Gartenflora  ¶ is a great los...</title>
               <date when="1884-12-14">1884-12-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1884/84-12-14-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="57">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="43">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard von Regel</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">14 December 1884. ¶  ¶ My best thanks for your kind letter, noble friend, and for all the good wishes you harbour for me. Your retirement from your leading position in  ¶ Gartenflora  ¶ is a great los...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">84.12.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Eduard von Regel</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS 159, folio 21808, d. 76, op. 1, fond 335, Archives Department, Russian Academy of Sciences, St Petersburg.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">14/12/84</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Besten Dank für Ihren gütigen Brief, edler Freund, und für all die guten Wünsche, welche Sie für mich hegen. Dass Sie von der Gartenflora als leitende Persönlichkeit zurücktreten, ist ein grosser Verlust für den Gartenbau, obwohl Sie durch den ausgezeichneten Prof Engler ersetzt werden, der eine so ausserordentliche Arbeitskraft entwickelt, wie Sie selbst. Mag er dabei die kernige feste Gesundheit bewahren, daran Sie sich erfreuen, denn nur der kräftigsten Constitution genügt ein stündiger Schlaf. Ich selbst leide mehr u mehr an "Insomnia", die eigentlich bei mir schon constitutionell wurde in den Reise-Jahren meines jüngeren Lebens, während ich mich meistens nur zum Ruhen nicht zum Schlafen niederlegen konnte, theils wegen der Feindseligkeiten der Eingeborenen, theils wegen des Benehmens der Pferde, der gänzlichen Unbequemlichkeit gar nicht zu gedenken, wenn das Bett aus einer Wolldecke und das Kopfkissen aus dem Sattel besteht, meist ohne Beschirmung durch ein Zelt. Seit ich durch die aus Neid u Nepotismus hervorgegangenenen Entfernung aus dem Garten </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">gar keine </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">regelmässige Bewegung mehr habe, ist die Schlaflosigkeit so unerträglich geworden, dass ich dabei fast aufgerieben werde.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin ganz gerührt über Ihre Mittheilung von der Absicht eines grossen Geschenkes; ich erwartete es in keiner Weise, da ich ja schon von dort höchsten Ortes so sehr beschenkt bin, u fühle keine Ansprüche an eine so übergrosse Güte zu haben! Es würde aber ungeziemend sein, wollte ich Höchster Huld nicht dankbar entgegenkommen; dann müsste ich Sie aber als theuren Freund bitten, die Sendung </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> gerade gleich u nicht auf einem officiellen Wege sondern durch Watson &amp; Scull, Lower Thames Street später zu veranstalten. Dass die Blumen-Bilder der Frau Capitainin Rowan sicher zurückkamen, und dass wir auch durch Ihre Freundlichkeit die Medaillen hier richtig erhielten, habe ich Ihnen bereits mitgetheilt im letzten Briefe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In der gerade beginnenden Woche habe ich hier in der </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geographischen Gesellschaft zu präsidiren</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> und nach der Sitzung wird ein mehrtägiger geogr. Congress stattfinden, für welchen Sir Edward Strickland u andere Delegaten aus Sydney bereits angekommen sind. So muss ich mich diesmal in meiner europ. Correspondenz kurz fassen, bitte Sie aber aufs Innigste mich lieb zu behalten, u. sich auch am Lebensabend zu schonen, damit Sie der Wissenschaft u den Ihrigen in Ihrer grossartigen Anstalt recht recht lange erhalten bleiben. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ganz der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14 December 1884.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My best thanks for your kind letter, noble friend, and for all the good wishes you harbour for me. Your retirement from your leading position in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora </seg>is a great loss for horticulture, even though you are replaced by the excellent Professor Engler, who is displaying such extraordinary drive in his work, much like you. May he retain the same sound good health you enjoy, for only the most robust constitution can cope with only an hour's sleep. I myself suffer more and more from insomnia, which really became chronic already during the travels of my younger years, when I usually could lie down only to rest, not to sleep, partly because of the hostilities of the natives, partly because of the behaviour of the horses, not to mention the total discomfort, when the bed consists of a woollen blanket with the saddle as pillow, usually without the shelter of a tent. Since my removal from the Gardens through envy and nepotism I no longer get <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">any</hi>
               </seg> regular exercise, and sleeplessness has become so unbearable that it is almost wearing me out.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am really touched by your news of the intention of a great gift.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Tsar presented M with a diamond ring; see M to E. von Regel, 19 September 1885 (in this edition as 85-09-19a) and M to E. von Regel, 21 September 1885. See also M to J. Traill, 15 September 1885.</p>
               </note> I did not expect it in any way, because I have already received gifts from there from the highest places and feel I have no claims on such overwhelming benevolence! But it would be improper not to oblige the highest favour. I must ask you, however, as my dear friend, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> to have it sent immediately, and not through official channels, but to arrange the consignment through Watson &amp; Scull, Lower Thames Street, at a later date. I have reported already in my last letter, that the flower paintings of the Captain's wife, Mrs Rowan,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ellis Rowan.</p>
               </note> have arrived back safely, and also that through your kindness we duly received the medals here.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M and Ellis Rowan were both awarded gold medals at St Petersburg's International Exhibition of Horticulture, earlier in 1884, M for the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea barbara</seg> that he exhibited, Rowan for her flower paintings. <seg style="">For details of the exhibits, see </seg>St Petersburg Exposition Internationale d'Horticulture (1884); Rowan's twelve 'Portraits de plantes de l'Australie' are listed (p. 1) under 'M-me Rowers, à Melbourne', giving the names of the species included in each; M's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea </seg>is catalogued (p. 7), as 'Une fougère en arbre, Todea barbara' [A tree fern], with the comment '<seg style="">Cet exemplaire est reçu au printemps 1883 et se trouve dans les serres du Jardin Imp. de botanique, étant trop lourd pour être transporté à l'exposition' </seg>[This specimen was received in the spring of 1883 and is in the greenhouses of the Imperial botanic garden, being too heavy to be transported to the exhibition].</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the week just started I have to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">preside over the Geographical Society</hi>
               </seg> here<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Geographical Society of Australasia (Victorian Branch).</p>
               </note> and, following the meeting, a Geographic Congress is to take place over several days. Sir Edward Strickland and other delegates from Sydney have already arrived for it. As a result I have to keep my European correspondence short this time. But I ask you sincerely to keep me in affectionate remembrance, and to take care of yourself in the evening of your life, so that you will remain preserved for a long time yet in your grand institute, for science and for your family.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Devotedly Yours </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
