<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ At pp. 238 and 239 (February 20) the question is raised — What is Eucalyptus colossea? and gratuitously it is added, "It is a peculiarity of Baron von Mueller that he rarely sends out specimens or ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1875/75-05-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>75.05.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ At pp. 238 and 239 (February 20) the question is raised — What is Eucalyptus colossea? and gratuitously it is added, "It is a peculiarity of Baron von Mueller that he rarely sends out specimens or ...</title>
               <date when="1875-05">1875-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1875/75-05-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eucalyptus diversicolor</term>
               <term>Cupressus Lambertiana</term>
               <term>Cupressus macrocarpa</term>
               <term>Calythrix tetragona</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus colossea</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus fissilis</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus obliqua</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Gardeners' Chronicle</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ At pp. 238 and 239 (February 20) the question is raised — What is Eucalyptus colossea? and gratuitously it is added, "It is a peculiarity of Baron von Mueller that he rarely sends out specimens or ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">75.05.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">To the Gardeners' Chronicle</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'Home correspondence’, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gardeners' chronicle</seg>, 26 June 1875, p. 823 (B75.06.01), and headed '<name key="Eucalyptus%20colossea">Eucalyptus colossea</name>'. It is dated to May as the last likely date it would have been written to have been received in time to be included in the issue of 26 June.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At pp. 238 and 239 (February 20) the question is raised — What is <name key="Eucalyptus%20colossea">Eucalyptus colossea</name>? and gratuitously it is added, "It is a peculiarity of Baron von Mueller that he rarely sends out specimens or seeds of plants without provisional names," &amp;c. I had to read over this sentence several times before I could make myself believe that " without" had been substituted in error for "with." Will your correspondent cite the numerous "provisional names?"<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The item was anonymous.</p>
               </note> No phytographic worker has ever been more careful in adopting correct names than myself. I can fairly state that I have reduced thousands of useless synonyms of other writers on Australian plants first, to their real names; instance <name key="Calythrix%20tetragona">Calythrix tetragona</name>, to which I reduced correctly seventeen species of acknowledged high authorities; and if on rare occasions I, like my compeers, have adopted provisional names, there was full reason for it, which must be apparent to the meanest understanding. Even in so difficult a genus as Eucalyptus—in which first of all by myself sound principles for specific demarcation were established—nearly all the species (about half a hundred) established by me have stood the test of comparison with original specimens of species previously known and mostly ill-described before my time. That in such a genus an occasional duplicity<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>duplication?</p>
               </note> may occur (as in similar instances with <name key="Cupressus%20macrocarpa">Cupressus macrocarpa</name> and Lambertiana) can readily be comprehended; so it is yet an unsettled point whether the E. fissilis should be separated as a species or as a variety from E. obliqua; the wood and bark of both are very distinct to the woodsplitters, builders, and commercial dealers. Thus it was for a very long time uncertain when this, my E. diversicolor—one of the fifty called Blue Gum tree of West Australia—was identical with the famous Karri tree;<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M had requested Bentham to adopt the name <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. colossea</seg>, instead of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. diversicolor</seg>, a change he had made informally in B65.04.01, p. 14, but the proposal was not accepted: see M to G. Bentham, 25 December 1865 (in this edition as 65-12-25d) and G. Bentham to M, 19 March 1863. M, however, later used it formally in B69.10.01, p. 42. </p>
               </note> and this identity I was only able to establish when I visited West Australia personally in 1857,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1867?</p>
               </note> after the name E. colossea was adopted for the Karri-wood in our locality, and also in several foreign industrial exhibitions. When this identity was made out, I informed M. Ramel and many other correspondents of the fact.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. However, the comment to which M was objecting says: 'Mr. Ramel, writing in the Illustration Horticole, says that the E. diversicolor of the Flora Australiensis was sent to him by Mueller as E. colossea, and that he intends retaining the latter name for it, as more appropriate'. Ramel made his comment in a letter headed 'Les Eucalyptus en Australie' in the February 1875 issue of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">L'illustration horticole</seg>, vol. 22, p. 32, a letter that was translated into Portuguese in the November issue of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Jornal de horticultura practica</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 6, p. 218</seg>.</p>
               </note> It seems almost beneath one's dignity to spend time in refuting attacks, such as the one in your number of Feb. 20; but the baseless attacks of traducers have brought an honourable departmental position to the dust (while under the Civil Service regulations of this colony I could not defend myself), and no one in Europe seems to care to aid in rebuilding it, so far as I can perceive. Whenever in my writings E. colossea was mentioned it was coupled with the vernacular name "Karri," hence there could be no great difficulty in finding out what it was, and even that difficulty could have been easily removed by a letter to myself. There are still several Eucalypti about whose exact specific position I am uncertain, and to avoid confusion temporary names have to be adopted for them. Even after many centuries of the study of plants in your own country the controversy about the British Oaks in not yet brought to a close—i.e., whether you have one species with two varieties, or two species. Cannot then some allowance be made for 150 Eucalypti? Surely, therefore, a little more charity might have been shown in this instance to a distant foreign worker, who would fain have hoped that he had struggled here against illiberality and envy for a quarter of a century not altogether in vain.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gardeners' chronicle,</seg>
                     <seg style=""> 3 July 1875, p. 16 responded to the letter:</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Baron Mueller has construed our note at p. 238-9, vol, i., on the inconvenience of applying the same specific names to different species without publishing the reasons for the change, into a personal attack on himself. </seg>Nothing was further from our thoughts, for we are well aware of, and have gladly drawn attention to, his labours in the cause of science, and fully appreciate the results. <seg style="">… We regret, therefore, that he should have regarded our remarks in a light different from their intended bearings, and hasten to disclaim any wish or intention to depreciate his invaluable contributions to the botany of Australia. Indeed, so long as systematic botany is studied, so long will the name of </seg>
                     <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Ferdinand Mueller</seg>
                     <seg style=""> maintain a prominent and honourable position as the most copious contributor to, and earnest promoter of, the study of the vegetable productions of his adopted country; and we do not doubt that future generations of Australians will more fully appreciate the value of his services than the present. We simply pointed out a case in which we think that a certain name ought to have been quoted in the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora Australiensis</seg>
                     <seg style="">. Perhaps the way in which we expressed the fact that Baron </seg>
                     <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Mueller</seg>
                     <seg style=""> rarely sends out specimens or seeds of plants without provisional names is liable to the construction he has put upon it. Our meaning was that he has been in the habit of giving names to new species, or what he believed to be such, and in cases where these names have for some reason been discarded, they are not quoted. This is done, doubtless, with the laudable intention of reducing the synonymy. Baron </seg>
                     <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Mueller's</seg>
                     <seg style=""> views, like those of most naturalists, regarding the limits of species, have undergone a great change since he first began publishing, and the desire to suppress all names that have not actually been published does not deserve severe censure, even if the practice cause some inconvenience. The sentence, "Of this we might adduce numerous instances," refers to the preceding clause — "a plant once thoroughly known under a certain name by gardeners, retains it to the end." We believe, however, that we are right in stating that Baron </seg>
                     <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Mueller</seg>
                     <seg style=""> rarely sends out specimens without names, and those given to imperfectly known or new species must of necessity be provisional pending their publication. As might be expected, some of them are afterwards rejected, but which it is not so easy to ascertain, if they are not quoted. And when the same name is subsequently taken up for a really new species, it is confusing to those unacquainted with the nature of the change. Nevertheless, we regret that Baron </seg>
                     <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Mueller</seg>
                     <seg style=""> has regarded our strictures in the light of a personal attack, though we feel sure that no one else would take that view of the matter. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ferd. von Mueller,</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Melbourne</seg>
               <seg style="">.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <ab rend="plant%20names"
                style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; font-style: italic; "
                type="heading">
               <name key="Calythrix%20tetragona">Calythrix tetragona</name>
            </ab>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cupressus%20Lambertiana">Cupressus Lambertiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cupressus%20macrocarpa">Cupressus macrocarpa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus%20colossea">Eucalyptus colossea</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20diversicolor">Eucalyptus diversicolor</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20fissilis">Eucalyptus fissilis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20obliqua">Eucalyptus obliqua</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
