<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Botanic Museum ¶ Melbourne, ¶ 28/6/75 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In response to a question of the Honorable H. J. Wrixon in the Legislative Assembly on the 24th inst., concerning the "best means of arresting by plant...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1875/75-06-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>G75/7793, unit 880, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>75.06.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Botanic Museum ¶ Melbourne, ¶ 28/6/75 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In response to a question of the Honorable H. J. Wrixon in the Legislative Assembly on the 24th inst., concerning the "best means of arresting by plant...</title>
               <date when="1875-06-28">1875-06-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1875/75-06-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Leptospermum laevigatum</term>
               <term>Stenotaphrum Americanum</term>
               <term>Casuarina quadrivalvis</term>
               <term>Lepidosperma gladiatum</term>
               <term>Agrostis stolonifera</term>
               <term>Melaleuca parviflora</term>
               <term>Lupinus albiflorus</term>
               <term>Festuca litoralis</term>
               <term>Acacia pycnantha</term>
               <term>Cynodon Dactylon</term>
               <term>Elymus arenarius</term>
               <term>Lupinus arboreus</term>
               <term>Mesembryanthemum</term>
               <term>Psamma arenaria</term>
               <term>Ulex Europaeus</term>
               <term>Acacia armata</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Robert Ramsay</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Botanic Museum ¶ Melbourne, ¶ 28/6/75 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In response to a question of the Honorable H. J. Wrixon in the Legislative Assembly on the 24th inst., concerning the "best means of arresting by plant...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">75.06.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Robert Ramsay</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">G75/7793, unit 880, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS written by a clerk and edited and signed by M. The file cover has an annotation by W. H. Odgers: 'Mr Lascelles | Please have two copies made | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">WH.O</hi>
                     </seg> | One to be sent to Mr. Wrixon | One to be sent to Boro Council Warrnambool'. A further annotation confirms that the copies were sent on 8 July 1875.</p>
               </note>Botanic Museum</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">28/6/75</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In response to a question of the Honorable H. J. Wrixon in the Legislative Assembly on the 24th inst., concerning the "best means of arresting by planting or otherwise the encroachment of sand along the western coast",<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to W. Odgers, 24 June 1875, written when M saw that a question from Henry Wrixon, MLA, has been put down for Parliament. M offered to prepare a special report, and Odgers minuted a request that he do so. M no doubt addressed his report to Ramsay because he was Acting Chief Secretary at the time.</p>
               </note> I have the honor to inform you that, when from the 3rd till the 6th of April last I travelled for the first time through a part of the Warrnambool and Port Fairy district (with a primary object of becoming acquainted with the vegetation of this part of our colony for a special school-book on native Victorian plants), I observed that along the whole coast line between the above mentioned towns the sandridges had become utterly denuded of their native vegetation, that consequently the sand, thus set free, rolled unchecked onward inland by the force of prevailing antarctic winds, and that already the southern outskirts of the fine pastoral and agricultural country of those districts and even some of the town-lands had severely suffered by the unhindered and steady progress of these sand waves. Enquiring into the causes of the total destruction of the original sand-vegetation, I was informed by the settlers, that actually a public road had been sanctioned many years ago over these sand-rises and that, moreover, the very sandhills, which should have been scrupulously guarded against traffic of any kind, formed part of a pastoral commonage. The inevitable consequence has been a total annihilation of all the trees, bushes, sedges, creeping herbs and grasses which once bound the sand together, the original trees in all likelihood being recklessly removed for fuel.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As really these extraordinary arrangements for the use and occupation of the coastridges threatens to lead to an extensive and permanent devastation of the rich lands situated nearest inland, and as moreover the original road is now not even visible along the shifting sand, and as the supposed common affords no longer the slightest vestige of forage, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">I would respectfully recommend</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1, that a new pastoral common should be proclaimed, if land is still available near inland for this purpose, should such common really be requisite, and that at all events the right of commonage on the present area should be permanently withdrawn, in order that the whole sandtract, now already widely dilated, may be restored to its natural purpose of protection and shelter, and once more be brought within due bounds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2, With a view of raising a new vegetation for binding these sand-downs I beg to suggest, that any encroachment and traffic whatever on these sands should be strictly interdicted; otherwise any remedial measures will be hopeless.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3, In order to give vigorous and lasting effects to this recommendation it would be requisite that an experienced cultivator, fairly provided with the necessary means, should be chosen to exercise surveillance against any further inroads or traversings on the sand, that it should be his duty to prevent cattle, horses sheep, goats and fowl from roaming over the sands, while simultaneously he could carry out the simple instructions, under which those of the native and foreign sand-plants, which are best adapted for consolidating sandy ridges, and to which I shall briefly refer hereafter, can be raised. In all European countries the sand-shores are under the supervision of special officers, to prevent by apt and well understood cultural processes and by exclusion of traffic, the otherwise certain ingress of sand from the coast formations.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4, It is recommended to effect extensive sowings of seeds of plants thriving in drift sand all over the denuded area, and this should be effected during the cool season; besides creeping plants of such kinds as do not readily yield seeds or are not easily raised from seeds should be set out bodily on the sand.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5, The officer thus in charge should have his abode permanently near to the sand ground, which measure would enable him to raise the coast pines of South Europe, North Africa, California and many other countries, as also numerous other sand plants, within a nursery area, for final transplanting on the sand.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6, It may be requisite that some fencing be erected, if the pounding act cannot be rigorously or advantageously enforced; though the impassability of the now obliterated old road and the existence of a good and straight main road between Warrnambool and Belfast does not seem to call for the expensive fencing process, especially as this would in no direct way aid in staying the sand.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>7, I would next proceed to offer some guidance in the choice of the various plants, available for the indicated purpose, and I shall refer also briefly to some of the methods, adopted in other parts of the globe, to bring or to maintain drifting coast sand under control.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As regards our own native plants we are very favorably placed to choose from them for subduing any rolling sand; indeed some have attained celebrity in these respects abroad.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The tall "Sandstay" bush (<name key="Leptospermum%20laevigatum">Leptospermum laevigatum</name>) yields seeds copiously, which under some slight cover of brush germinate readily on the sand itself. It was found advantageous, to use over this plant for brushfences along sand when in fruit, the seeds gradually dropping soon germinating under the shelter thus afforded.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">It was found ... thus afforded. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is an insertion by M.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The dense growth of this shrub or small tree, its handsome appearance, together with its comparative rapidity of growth render it one of the most important plants of our choice. Among the grasses here obtainable the Doorba or native<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">native <seg style="font-style: italic; ">inserted by M</seg>.</p>
               </note> Couch-grass (<name key="Cynodon%20Dactylon">Cynodon Dactylon</name>) is one of the best among dwarf widely rooting kinds; the dispersion is best effected from the rooting parts cut into pieces, each of which will take root. A tall Fescue (<name key="Festuca%20litoralis">Festuca litoralis</name>) can easily be transferred in a rooted state from others of our shores, it having seemingly become extinct on the tract in question. Sods of our two kinds of <name key="Mesembryanthemum">Mesembryanthemum</name> should be scattered over the ridges, and the Sword-rush (<name key="Lepidosperma%20gladiatum">Lepidosperma gladiatum</name>) be planted out copiously. There are many other plants in our territory, which admirably help to solidify the sands; whatever sandplant has deeply penetrating perennial and particularly creeping roots may by transplantation or dissemination be called into aid. The drooping Sheoak (<name key="Casuarina%20quadrivalvis">Casuarina quadrivalvis</name>) is the best among indigenous trees to be raised on the edge of the drift-sands, and as a shelter-tree against sea storms it is in latitudes like ours unsurpassed. At the Cape of Good Hope our Golden Tanners<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Tanners <seg style="font-style: italic; ">inserted by M</seg>.</p>
               </note> Wattle (<name key="Acacia%20pycnantha">Acacia pycnantha</name>) and some allied Australian species have set an effectual barrier to the moving sands; copious dissemination of these also here would be extremely desirable, especially as seeds can cheaply be gathered. <name key="Melaleuca%20parviflora">Melaleuca parviflora</name> (one of the bushes or trees improperly called Teatrees) is capable of forming, as may be noticed beyond Queenscliff, dense tall thickets, to the exclusion of any other shrubby plant on pure coast-sands. In Scandinavia, as I observed for years myself,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">During his youth in Schleswig-Holstein, then a part of Denmark.</p>
               </note> and elsewhere in West Europe, preference is given to two tall reedy grasses for fixing the sanddrifts, namely the Lyme grass (<name key="Elymus%20arenarius">Elymus arenarius</name>) and the Marram or tall Bentgrass (<name key="Psamma%20arenaria">Psamma arenaria</name>) The seeds of these form an article of trade in Europe, and can thus be cheaply imported. The strong roots of both creep widely along the sand and the extensive propagation of these important plants is easily effected, when once they are established, from divisions of the root. In places subject to the ingress of stock it is advantageous, as I explained already to settlers in the Western coast-districts, to sow the Furze or Whin or Gorze (<name key="Ulex%20Europaeus">Ulex Europaeus</name>) and our own Kangaroo Thorn (<name key="Acacia%20armata">Acacia armata</name>), as their prickly foliage protects them against the browsing animals; they moreover run up with great ease from soaked seeds, scattered at the commencement of the cool season over the sands. After my return I forwarded some of these latter kinds of seeds to the localities named. Broom plants, Clovers of several kinds, Luzerne, various grasses, among the latter the flat Buffalo grass (<name key="Stenotaphrum%20Americanum">Stenotaphrum Americanum</name>), the creeping Fiorin grass (<name key="Agrostis%20stolonifera">Agrostis stolonifera</name>) are very eligible, provided that stock can be kept from the enticing pasture thus provided. If this can be effectually carried out, then the Californian method of subduing loose sand is one of the very best: Two somewhat shrubby species of Lupins (<name key="Lupinus%20arboreus">Lupinus arboreus</name> and L. albiflorus<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">IPNI</seg>; error for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">L. albifrons</seg>? See n. 1 to M to J. Hooker, 18 January 1877 (in this edition as 77-01-18a).</p>
               </note>) are selected there for the reclamation of the sands, their taproots penetrating to an extraordinary depth, whereas their stems do not gain a height above 3 feet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In order that the young Lupins may get hold of the sands and establish themselves, they are sown along with Barley, because the quickly sprouting cereal will hold the sand in two or three weeks and will prevent thus the more delicate young seedlings of the Lupin plants from being suffocated. The latter in about a year or less will cover the sands. Seeds of both kinds mentioned could be ordered from San Francisco.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As the full utilisation of our extensive sandy coasts for cultural purposes involves also questions of some industrial importance, I would finally allude at least to the desirability of converting the barren coasts, now unsheltered and bare over wide tracts, into Pine plantations, as since the commencement of this century has been done on many of the coastlines of France. The Haleppo Fir, whose real home is the loose coast sand, grows on such even more rapidly than on firm land. The Mediterranean Cluster-Pine, the Scotch Fir, the Californian Pinus insignis, the Virginian Frankincense Pine and many other Pines, yielding deal-wood, turpentine and pitch, as well as a host of other utilitarian trees such as our own Sandarac Cypress, not to speak of New Zealand Flax and a large array of other kinds of plants, will fully succeed on coast sands, hitherto with us so little utilized. For fuller data bearing on this subject I may refer to the prints of my lectures, delivered at the technologic museum,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B71.04.03, B71.13.03.</p>
               </note> also to my explanatory lists of industrial plants contained in four of the volumes of the Acclimatisation Society,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B72.13.02, B74.13.06. </p>
               </note> the reissue of which publication in a connected volume I have recommended on former occasions.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Published as B76.12.04.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Sir</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Honorable Rob. Ramsay, M.L.A.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Warrnambool standard</seg> published M’s report on 13 July 1875, p. 4 (B75.07.02), together with a critical discussion of it (see below). The Warrnambool Borough Council met on the same day, at which time the Town Clerk, H. T. Read, read M's report to the meeting. 'The Mayor said than an objection might be raised to the proposal to remove the custody of the Common from the Council, as suggested by Baron von Mueller. On the suggestion of the Mayor it was resolved that a letter be sent to the Chief Secretary intimating that action had been taken by the Council on the subject, and soliciting any further information. Cr. Hider moved and Cr. Cramer seconded, that the document be referred to the Public Works Committee, with a recommendation that the views propounded be carried out, as far as practicable.' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Warrnambool standard</seg>, 16 July 1873, p. 4) (see also <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Warrnambool examiner</seg>, 14 July 1873, p. 2; and Minute book 8, p. 52, 13 July 1875, Borough Council records, City of Warrnambool archives, Warrnambool).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>H. T. Read acknowledged receipt of M's report to the Chief Secretary's Department, 22 July 1875: 'I may mention that for years past this Council have devoted a great amount of thought and expended considerable sums of money, in endeavours to stay sand encroachment' (G75/8550, unit 880, VPRS 3991 inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria). H. J. Wrixon acknowledged his copy of M's report on 19 July 1875 (G75/8319, unit 880, VPRS 3991 inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">The Warrnambool standard </seg>published an editorial on the subject of M's report on 13 July 1873 (p. 2): 'From Baron Von Mueller's report which we publish in full in another column, it will be seen that the remedy which he proposes for the encroachment of sand on this coast is rather of the heroic order. He would not only have the hummocks and sand-drift planted and sown and kept free from traffic and cattle, but he also suggests that the whole of the commonage adjacent to the coast should be revoked as a further protection against sand. Residents in this locality must know that so extreme a measure is quite unnecessary; but since the Baron's report has been laid before Parliament, and may be dealt with by Government officers who are not personally acquainted with the western district, it is right that the circumstances should be accurately stated. Baron Von Mueller, it will be noticed, paid a very hurried visit to the district for the first time, and probably was not aware that he would be asked to furnish any report on this subject; at all events, he seems to have the ides that the commonage could be taken away without involving any interest save that of the townsfolk who depasture their cattle there, and possibly imagines that the common does not extend far from the hummocks. The fact is, however, that part of the Warrnambool common lies at a much greater distance from the encroaching sand than the centre of the town does; and if the whole of the common is to be closed from fear of sand-drift we might with equal reason ask that the sites of all the public offices should be changed, and proceed to shift the whole town a mile or so inland! The Merri river, partly in its natural and partly in its diverted bed, constitutes a barrier against the encroachment of sand; and we should be sorry to suppose that even the further side of the river would not be available in future for industrial purposes. The common on this side of it may not only be used at present for depasturing cattle without doing the slightest harm, but is regarded as the area on which factories will be built, through which a railway will be constructed, and which will be intersected before very long with roads and homes. Already, the land bordering the Merri has been taken up under industrial licenses, and the greater part of it is being turned to good account. It is thus evident that Baron Von Mueller's proposed cure is much stronger than the malady requires. We should even owe an apology to our readers for pointing out facts so obvious, were it not, as we have already said, that silence might leave an erroneous impression on the minds of those at a distance from Warrnambool who may take a general interest in the subject. Our remarks do not in any degree detract from the great value of the Baron's report in other respects. he gives abundant information as to the ways in which the sand may be effectually combated and even converted from an enemy into a friend; and he speaks with the authority of one who knows his subject thoroughly. His idea is that a curator should be appointed by Government to prevent encroachment within a defined area, with sufficient means at his disposal to form a nursery for suitable trees and shrubs, and to plant these out and sow seeds in profusion; and there can be no doubt that if his plan were followed the greater part of what is now a desert and dangerous waste might be converted into a scene of verdure, and that useful industrial results might be derived from the culture of pines and other trees even under such apparently adverse conditions. This is a subject to which Baron Von Mueller has given a great deal of his time, and, though his services have been hardly compensated, the information which he has published will yet bear fruit in valuable forest culture. To the recently published proceedings of the Zoological and Acclimatisation Society of Victoria, we observe that he has added a supplement containing a further list of select plants eligible for Victorian industrial culture, with descriptions, and also a geographical index showing the countries in which plants which he has enumerated flourish. The special attention which he has given to the subject, combined with his well-known acquirements, renders his report deserving of the best attention.’</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The<seg style="font-style: italic; "> Age</seg> also published an article on the 'Sand-Drifts in the Western District', 6 July 1875, p. 3, with extensive extracts from M’s report, that was reprinted in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Warrnambool examiner</seg>, 10 July 1875, p. 4.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wrixon subsequently gave notice of a further question that he intended to put in the Legislative Assembly on 29 July 1875; he now proposed asking the Chief Secretary 'if the Government intend to take steps to give effect to the recommendations of [M's] report' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 29 July 1875, p. 7). No report of a response has been found, and the Government fell a few days later.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also Heathcote &amp; Maroske (1996).</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20armata">Acacia armata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20pycnantha">Acacia pycnantha</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Agrostis%20stolonifera">Agrostis stolonifera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarina%20quadrivalvis">Casuarina quadrivalvis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cynodon%20Dactylon">Cynodon Dactylon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Elymus%20arenarius">Elymus arenarius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Festuca%20litoralis">Festuca litoralis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lepidosperma%20gladiatum">Lepidosperma gladiatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leptospermum%20laevigatum">Leptospermum laevigatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lupinus%20albiflorus">Lupinus albiflorus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lupinus%20arboreus">Lupinus arboreus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Melaleuca%20parviflora">Melaleuca parviflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mesembryanthemum">Mesembryanthemum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Psamma%20arenaria">Psamma arenaria</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stenotaphrum%20Americanum">Stenotaphrum Americanum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ulex%20Europaeus">Ulex Europaeus</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
