<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 1 February 1856. ¶ Dear friend, ¶  ¶ Dr Steetz brought me the other day the two pamphlets as well as your greetings, for which I am very grateful to you. I was very pleased to hear from you a...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/possibly-delete/M56-02-01-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Andersson Saml., Centre for History of Science, Royal Academy of Science, Stockholm.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M56.02.01</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 1 February 1856. ¶ Dear friend, ¶  ¶ Dr Steetz brought me the other day the two pamphlets as well as your greetings, for which I am very grateful to you. I was very pleased to hear from you a...</title>
               <date when="1856-02-01">1856-02-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/possibly-delete/M56-02-01-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Nils Andersson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 1 February 1856. ¶ Dear friend, ¶  ¶ Dr Steetz brought me the other day the two pamphlets as well as your greetings, for which I am very grateful to you. I was very pleased to hear from you a...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M56.02.01</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Nils Andersson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Andersson Saml., Centre for History of Science, Royal Academy of Science, Stockholm.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope: 'Sr Wohlgeboren | Herrn Adjunct N. J. Andersson | Mitgl. der Academie der Wissen- | schaften | in | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Stockholm</hi>
                     </seg> | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">frei</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <hi rend="underline">'.</hi>
                     </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 1 Febr 1856</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Geehrtester Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Dr Steetz überbrachte mir in diesen Tagen die beiden Broschüren nebst Ihren Grüssen, wofür ich Ihnen recht sehr dankbar bin. Ich habe mich gefreut, endlich einmal etwas von Ihnen zu hören; ich würde Ihnen schon lange geschrieben haben, aber niemand wusste wo Sie sich aufhielten, der eine sagte in Upsala, der andere in Lund u.s.w. Weshalb Sie nicht in Lund sind, erfahre ich jetzt erst, man darf Ihnen aber wohl Glück wünschen, dass Sie in Stockholm bleiben können, dort ist es doch besser und angenehmer für Sie als in Lund. Im vorigen Jahre sind Sie uns wieder entwischt, ich hatte mir fest eingebildet, Sie würden nach Hamburg kommen. Als mir die Zeit zu lang wurde, schrieb ich an Sie durch einen nach Berlin reisenden Freund, aber der Brief kam uneröffnet zurück, Sie waren fort. Unser Hamburg muss schlecht bei Ihnen angeschrieben sein, sonst hätten Sie es nicht ganz vergessen. Wie hatte ich mich darauf gefreut, Sie eine Zeitlang bei mir im Hause zu haben, um zwischen meinen Gräsern zu wählen und in der mussigen Stunde meiner kleinen Familie von Ihrer herrlichen Reise zu erzählen. Diesen Genuss haben Sie böser Mann (um mit meiner Frau zu reden) uns geraubt, hoffentlich aber nicht für immer, denn ich denke, Sie kommen nächstens einmal wieder. Reisen Sie dann aber nicht über Hamburg, so hole ich Sie persönlich von Berlin, dessen Sand Sie ganz verblendet zu haben scheint.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie werden sich gewundert haben, dass ich Ihnen noch immer keine Nachricht über Ihre Lebermoose gebracht habe; der [einfache] Grund ist der, dass Gottsche sie noch immer nicht fertig gemacht hat. Jetzt endlich ist er dabei, da ich ihm nur unter der Bedingung die Neuholländischen Hepaticae überlassen habe, dass er erst die Ihrigen absolvirt, und ich hoffe Ihnen bald die Bestimmung übersenden zu können. Der Gottsche arbeitet sehr langsam, aber dafür auch sehr gut. Ob Sie mir zur Bedingung gemacht, dass Ihnen Gottsche die Exemplare zurück geben soll, das habe ich vergessen, Dr Gottsche wird es aber wohl noch wissen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben mir mit Ihrer Arbeit über die Galapagos Inseln im vergangenen Jahre eine grosse Freude gemacht! Und nun wollen Sie diese Freude noch vergrössern, indem Sie mir von Ihren Doubletten der Pflanzen anbieten. Das ist sehr edelmüthig von Ihnen gedacht; ich nehme Ihr Anerbieten aber auch mit Vergnügen an. Das Gebiet der Galapagos ist für mein Herbarium eine terra incognita, ich habe nichts von daher, deshalb ist alles erwünscht, je mehr desto lieber, die interessanten <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Compositae</hi>
               </seg> nicht zu vergessen. Ich nehme Ihr Anerbieten aber nur unter der Bedingung an, dass ich Ihnen etwas dagegen schicken darf. Hierzu liegen hinreichende Vorräthe von Pflanzen aus Südaustralien, Port Natal, Cap, Nordamerika u.s.w. zu Ihrer Auswahl da. Ich habe auch immer noch Gräser aus Südafrika für Sie liegen, aber immer nicht senden mögen, so lange Sie nicht irgendwo Anker geworfen. — Welche herrlichen Gräser hätten Sie sich erwerben können, wenn Sie nicht so unerbittlich gewesen wären und die Bearbeitung der Müller'schen Gramineen aus Südaustralien verweigert hätten. Müller hat in den letzten Jahren die Alpen von Südaustralien bereist und dort verschiedene interessante Agrostis Arten etc gesammelt. Einige derselben hat Müller kürzlich selbst beschrieben. — Sind Sie auf den Cap Verden gewesen? Wo nicht, so habe ich noch verschiedene schöne Gräser von dort in mehrfachen Exemplaren, die Dr Schmidt daselbst sammelte. Wünschen Sie nur, was ich habe gebe ich gern. — Ich hätte gerne auch von Ihnen ein Exemplar der neuen Algengattung [Virginias]. Sie kennen meine Liebhaberei für Algen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin in der letzten Zeit ganz aus der Correspondenz mit Ihrem Vaterlande herausgekommen, ich weiss nicht ob <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ich</hi>
               </seg> Schuld daran [...]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">There is a line above this one at the top of the page, cut off in photocopying and illegible</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> gewesen bin, scheint mir böse zu sein; wenn ich nur wüsste warum. Dass ich in meiner Flora Hamburg mich über einige seiner Carices nicht gleicher Meinung mit ihm äusserte, kann er mir doch unmöglich übel genommen haben! Ich denke man soll seine Meinung immer offen aussprechen, die Wahrheit behält doch immer den Sieg. — Fries hat mir früher das Herbarium normale mitgetheilt, den letzten Fascikel habe ich aber nicht erhalten. Da mir natürlich viel daran liegt, das Werk complet zu besitzen, so möchte ich Sie ersuchen, ob Sie Fries nicht bitten könnten, es Ihnen für mich zu senden; ich will gerne Swan-River Pflanzen oder von Müller gesammelte dafür wieder geben. Geht das nicht, so bin ich auch bereit, diesen letzten Fascikel zu kaufen. Fries [sandte] mir die vor Jahren an Sie gesandten Salices vom Cap vor ungefähr einem oder andertahalb Jahren zurück; ich schrieb ihm damals sogleich und beantwortete seinen Brief in Bezug auf den Tausch, habe aber bis diesen Augenblick nichts darauf gehört. — Von Areschoug erhielt ich vor einiger Zeit durch Buchhändlergelegenheit einige Broschüren aber keinen Brief. Ich werde ihm nächsten schreiben. An Theden sandte ich im vorigen Winter ein kleines Packet mit Hamburgischen Pflanzen, das er hoffentlich erhalten hat.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie [...]<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">2 or 3 words illegible, thick black line runs through the centre fold of the paper.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> [eine] Verbindung mit Ihrem klassischen Lande ist, ersehen Sie aus Vorstehendem und aus folgender Bitte. Es ist kürzlich von Zetterstedt eine kleine Abhandlung über [<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Andraea]</hi>
               </seg> publicirt, worin eine neue Art beschrieben ist. Dürfte ich Sie wohl bitten, mir diese kleine Schrift zu kaufen, den Betrag werde ich Ihnen mit Dank zurückerstatten. Die hiesigen Buchhändler können mir die hier nicht verschaffen. Sollte es möglich sein, zugleich ein Exemplar der darin beschriebenen Art zu erhalten, so wäre mir das doppelt lieb. Ich habe nämlich einige Andraeen aus Neuholland erhalten, die auch nicht beschrieben sind, wenn nicht die eine mir der neuen schwedischen übereinstimmt, welches nicht unwahrscheinlich ist. Gern will ich dem Geber eine neuholländische dagegen schicken. — Nehmen Sie nicht übel, lieber Freund, dass mein erster Brief seit langer Zeit Sie so in Thätigkeit setzt, ich bin aber gerne erbietig, ein ähnliches für Sie zu thun, wenn Sie mir eine Gelegenheit dazu geben wollen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin gespannt, von Ihnen zu hören, wie es Ihnen im Allgemeinen und im Speciellen geht; ob Sie verheiratet sind, darnach hat meine Frau zuerst gefragt; Sie wissen, das interessirt Frauen ganz gewaltig. Neulich hatten wir den ersten Band der Reise Ihrer Fregatte und da [haben] Frau und Kinder sich über die Japanischen u Chinesischen, besonders die [Tahit[enischen] Gesichter amüsirt, meine Frau hatte kürzlich [Gerstackers] Tahiti gelesen, und meinte, Sie könnten vielleicht [<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sadie</hi>
               </seg>]<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Top cut off in photocopy.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> kennen gelernt haben <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>— Seien Sie für heute von uns allen herzlich gegrüsst und erfreuen Sie bald mit einigen Zeilen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihren</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie schätzenden</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 1 February 1856.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Steetz brought me the other day the two pamphlets as well as your greetings, for which I am very grateful to you. I was very pleased to hear from you at long last; I should have written to you long ago, but nobody knew where you were, one said in Uppsala, the other in Lund, etc. I am only just finding out why you are not in Lund, and it is, I expect, a cause for congratulations that you were able to remain in Stockholm, where it is better and more convenient for you than in Lund. You escaped us again last year, I had been firmly convinced that you would come to Hamburg. When it took too long for my liking I wrote to you via a friend who was travelling to Berlin, but the letter was returned unopened. You were gone. Our Hamburg must be in your bad books or you would not have forgotten us so completely. I had so looked forward to having you in my home for a while, to choose from my grasses and during leisure hours to tell my little family about your wonderful voyage. You naughty man (to quote my wife) have robbed us of this delight but we hope not for ever, because I think you will come here again some time. But if you don't travel via Hamburg then, I shall personally come and get you from Berlin, where the sand seems to have blinded you completely.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will have wondered why I have not yet brought you any news about your Hepaticae; the simple reason is that Gottsche<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">biogr. details.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> still has not finished them. He is finally working on them, as I only let him have the New Holland Hepaticae<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Gottsche did the Hepaticae as part of the 'Plantae Muellerianae' series in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg>; see Gottsche (1856).</p>
               </note> under the condition that he completes yours first, and I hope to be able to send you the determinations soon. That Gottsche is very slow, but on the other hand his work is very good. I have forgotten whether you made it a condition for me that Gottsche has to return the material to you, but Dr Gottsche will probably still remember.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have given me great pleasure with your work about the Galapagos Islands last year! And now you make that joy even greater by offering me duplicates of your plants. That is a very generous thought and I accept your offer with pleasure. The Galapagos Islands are unknown territory for my herbarium, I have nothing from there, therefore everything is wanted, the more the better, the interesting <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Compositae</hi>
               </seg> not to be forgotten. But I accept your offer only under the condition that I may send you something else in reciprocation. There are adequate stocks here of plants from South Australia, Port Natal, the Cape Province, North America, etc. for you to choose from. I have grasses from South Africa still lying here for you but had not wanted to send them until you had put down your anchor somewhere. — <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>What wonderful grasses you could have acquired if you had not been so unrelenting in refusing the work on Mueller's Gramineae from South Australia. Mueller has travelled in recent years in the alps of southern Australia, and collected there various interesting <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Agrostis</seg> species etc. Mueller has recently described some of them himself.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B53.04.01, B55.13.05.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>— Did you visit the Cap Verde Islands? If not, I have several beautiful grasses from there in several duplicates, collected there by Dr Schmidt.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Schmidt visited the Cap Verde Islands in 1851; see J. A. Schmidt (1852). Sonder worked up and listed the algae included in this work, including description of some new species, pp.125-7.</p>
               </note> Just wish: what I have, I am happy to give. — I also should like from you a specimen of the new algal genus from Virginia. You know my predilection for algae.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In recent times I have been completely out of correspondence with your fatherland, I do not know if it is <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
               </seg> fault, [...]<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Line at top of page cut off in photocopying, I need the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">
                        <hi rend="underline">good</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; "> photocopy from Johannes. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> seems to be annoyed with me, if only I knew why. He could hardly have taken offence that I expressed an opinion different from his about some of his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Carices</seg> in my <seg style="">Flora of Hamburg!</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Check correct title and citation.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I believe one should always express one's opinion openly, in the end truth will always win through. — Fries sent me the herbarium normale earlier on, but I have not received the last fascicle. As it is of course important to me to own the complete work, I should like to ask you if you could not ask Fries to send it to you for me; I am happy to give plants from the Swan River<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Collections by Ludwig Preiss?</p>
               </note> or plants collected by Mueller in return for it. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>If that does not suit, I am also happy to purchase this last fascicle. Fries returned to me the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Salices</seg> from the Cape, sent to you years ago, about one or one-and-a-half years ago; I wrote to him immediately at the time and replied to his letter concerning the exchange, but so far have heard nothing back. — A while back I received some pamphlets through a book-dealer opportunity from Areschoug, but no letter. I sent a small parcel of Hamburg plants to Theden<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Who is he? Biogr. info wanted.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> last winter, I hope he has received them.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How [...]<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">2 or 3 words illegible, thick black line runs through centre fold of paper (heavily foxed?) on photocopy. Does Johannes have a better copy?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> a communication with your noble country is, you can gather from the above and from the following request. A small paper on [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <hi rend="underline">Andraea</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">]</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; font-weight: bold; ">Andrea</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">? Hardly, Bromeliaceae, a genus confined to South America. </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; font-weight: bold; ">Andraea</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; "> not in J.C.Willis. Check Zetterstedt publ. in Cat. Roy. Soc.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> was recently published by Zetterstedt, in which a new species was described. May I ask you to buy this little publication for me, I shall refund you the amount with thanks. The book dealers here can't get it for me. Should it be possible to obtain at the same time a specimen of the species described in it, I should be doubly pleased. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have received several <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Andraeae</seg> from New Holland that are not yet described either unless one of them agrees with the new Swedish species, which is not unlikely. I would be happy to send the donor one from New Holland in return. — Please do not be offended, dear friend, that my first letter in a long time immediately puts you into action like this, but I will gladly do something similar for you, if you will give me the opportunity.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am looking forward to hearing from you, how you are in general and, in particular, whether you are married, that was the first thing my wife asked about; you know that is something that interests women mightily. Recently we got the first volume of the voyage of your frigate<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Check: what was the voyage Andersson accompanied, and what the publication of the results arising from it? Citation.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and my wife and children were amused by the pictures of the Japanese and Chinese and especially the Tahitians. My wife recently has read Gerstäcker's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Tahiti</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Friedrich Gerstäcker (1816-1872), German (Hamburg) novelist and traveller, worked his way through the United State, South America, Polynesia, and Australia, and wrote colourful adventure stories. (ref. J. O. Thorne (ed.), Chambers's Briographical Dictionary, revised ed., Edinburgh, 1968.) — 'Sadie' is probably a fictional character in the book. <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Check citation.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and wondered if perhaps you might have met [<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sadie].</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">Top of Photocopy cut off. Good p/c needed from Johannes.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> — For today sincere regards from us all, and please us soon with a few lines.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With my esteem</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
