<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mt Gambier, 2nd August 1852. ¶  ¶ Probably you will have counted me amongst the lost by now, dear Müller, but for this time I have returned to life and Mt. Gambier. As I already remarked in my letter ...</title>
            <author>Eduard Wehl</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1852/52-08-02-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M106.12, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>52.08.02</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Eduard Wehl</author>
               <title>Mt Gambier, 2nd August 1852. ¶  ¶ Probably you will have counted me amongst the lost by now, dear Müller, but for this time I have returned to life and Mt. Gambier. As I already remarked in my letter ...</title>
               <date when="1852-08-02">1852-08-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1852/52-08-02-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Mt Gambier, 2nd August 1852. ¶  ¶ Probably you will have counted me amongst the lost by now, dear Müller, but for this time I have returned to life and Mt. Gambier. As I already remarked in my letter ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">52.08.02</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Eduard Wehl</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M106.12, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope front addressed by Wehl: 'Paid | F. Müller Esq. Ph. D. | Care of Mr Heuzenröder | Chemist | Rundelstreet | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Adelaide</hi>
                     </seg>'. Front post-marked GPO, South Australia, 12 August 1852. The letter would have just reached M before he departed for Melbourne on 14 August (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Adelaide morning chronicle</seg>, 16 August 1852).</p>
               </note>Mt. Gambier,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>SA.</p>
               </note> 2te August 1852.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie werden mich, lieber Müller, um diese Zeit wohl bereits unter die Verschollenen gesetzt haben, aber dieses Mal bin ich noch einmal wieder zum Leben und nach Mt. Gamb. gekommen. Wie ich schon in meinem Brief an Cl. bemerkt habe, war es mir in der letzten Zeit an den Diggins fast unmöglich zu schreiben, dazu verzögerte sich meine Abreise länger, als ich wünschte, wozu noch die Zeit der Herreise kömmt, was zusammen mein langes Schweigen verursacht hat. Von meinem Ergebnisse als Goldgräber kann ich wenig rühmen. Mit Blandowsky war es nicht möglich etwas zu machen und was ich erzielt habe, 3 1/2 lbs Gewicht, habe ich grösstentheils in den letzten sechs Wochen gemacht, seit ich mich von ihm getrennt hatte. Es würde mich ja hier zu weit führen die Gründe und Umstände zu beschreiben, warum mit Bl. nichts anzufangen war, Sie kennen ja sein Wesen. Er gab sich immer das Ansehen, als ob er es besser verstände, das Gold zu finden, als Andere, und beurtheilen könne, wo es läge, damit ist er aber gänzlich durchgefallen. Er verband sich mit 3 Engländern von hier und mehrere Gruben, die nach seiner Angabe gesunken waren, ergaben nichts, so dass zwei von den Leuten ohne sich weiter um ihn zu kümmern, einen Platz ausmarkten, sanken und Gold fanden, und zwar meinten sie, dass die Grube 60 bis 80 lbs Gewicht ausgeben würde. Die Parthie arbeitete noch daran, als ich abreiste, und natürlich mit Blandowsky als headminer. Es war dies in derselben Gulley wo wir schon immer gearbeitet hatten, die Gruben sind von 35 bis 40 Fuss tief. Mein Ertrag ist noch dadurch bedeutend geschmälert, dass ich dort ein Pferd und Karre kaufen musste, was £75 kostete. Mein eigenes Pferd war acht Tage vor meiner Abreise dicht beim Zelte weg gestohlen. Ihre Fragen betreffend, thut es mir leid, dass ich keine davon zur Genüge beantworten kann. Aus den Zeitungen weiss ich nur, dass Wohnungslokale in Melbourne gegenwärtig schwerer zu bekommen sind, denn jemals vorher. Ich sollte denken, dass, wenn Sie einmal ernstlich der Meinung sind, nach Melbourne überzusieldeln, Sie wenigstens bei einer Bude durchaus nichts verlieren könnten. Sollten Sie dieselbe nicht gebrauchen, so würde sie ihren Preis immer wieder bringen. Wenn Sie's irgen möglich machen könnten, so sollten Sie Ihre Schwester ja mitnehmen, es würde für Sie mit grossen Annehmlichkeiten verbunden sein und ich sollte denken, Clara würde auch lieber bei Ihnen bleiben. Nun zuletzt, ob ich Sie dann und wann ablösen will, um zu botanisieren. So weit ich's gegenwärtig versprechen kann, will ich's gerne thun; da aber Niemand weiss, was kommen wird bei diesem Chaos, worin sich gegenwärtig Alles bewegt, so lässt sich in dieser Hinsicht wenig sagen. Nach Adelaide werde ich, trotz meines sehnlichen Wunsches diesen Winter doch wohl nicht kommen können; wenn die Wege trocken werden, geht's wieder fort nach den Diggins und werde ich Sie dann sobald ich nur abkommen kann mal in Melbourne besuchen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun hätte ich noch einige Bitten an Sie. Erstens mir eine neue Brille zu besorgen. Ich habe die alte nur deshalb mitgeschickt, damit Sie die Stärke des Glases beurtheilen können, es ist Nr.8. Nehmen Sie womöglich eine mit silbernen oder wenigstens neusilbernen Gestell. Ferner wollte ich Sie bitten, mir etwas gute Kuhpockenlymphe zu besorgen, es sind hier eine Menge Kinder in der Umgegend zu impfen und ich habe den Leuten versprochen, die Lymphe, wenn irgend möglich anzuschaffen. Sollte es Ihnen möglich sein, so würden Sie mir einen grossen Gefallen thun, wenn Sie beides mit nächster Post schickten. Und mich zugleich wissen liessen, ob Sie mir von Ihren eignen Droguen ablassen können oder ob ich an Heuzenröder schreiben muss. Bei Heuzenröder habe ich noch £3.15.2. zu Gute, welche Sie vorläufig für die Brille etc. in Beschlag nehmen können. Also mit nächster Post einigen Zeilen von Ihnen entgegen sehend grüsst Sie</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">der Ihrige</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>E. Wehl M.D. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Die Brille habe ich besonders abgesandt. Sie finden einige "Specimens" dabei, welche Sie vielleicht interessieren. Wenn Sie wollen, so können Sie auch die Münzen, die Heuzenröder noch von mir hat, in Beschlag nehmen. Ich schickte ihm dieselben um sich einige davon auszusuchen, und er hat sich nie wieder etwas davon merken lassen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Mt Gambier, 2nd August 1852.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Probably you will have counted me amongst the lost by now, dear Müller, but for this time I have returned to life and Mt. Gambier. As I already remarked in my letter to Clara, I found it almost impossible to write during my last period in the diggings. In addition my departure was delayed longer than I would have wished. Add to that my journey here, and you have the reason for my long silence. I cannot boast much about my achievements as a gold digger. It was impossible to do anything with Blandowski, and what I have attained, about 3 1/2 lbs in weight, was mainly found during the last six weeks, after I had separated from him. It would lead too far to go into all the reasons and circumstances here of why nothing could be done with Blandowski, but you know yourself what kind of person he is. He always gave himself airs, as if he knew better than others where to find the gold, and as if he could judge where the layers would be, but he failed miserably in that. He joined up with 3 Englishmen from here, and several shafts, which were sunk according to his instructions, yielded nothing. As a result two of the people pegged out a claim for themselves without paying any further attention to him and found gold. They even estimated that the shaft would yield 60 to 80 lbs in weight. The party was still working there, when I left and, of course, with Blandowski as head miner. This was in the same gully where we had always worked; the shafts are 35 to 40 feet deep. In addition my profit was considerably reduced, because I had to buy a horse and cart there which cost me £75. My own horse was stolen from near the tent only a week before my departure.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Concerning your questions: I am sorry that I cannot answer any of them adequately. I only know from the newspapers that accommodation is at present harder to get than ever before. I would think that, when eventually you really have made up your mind to move to Melbourne, you would lose nothing with a shack. If you no longer need it, it would always return its price. If it is at all possible, you should certainly take your sister with you. It would prove to be of great convenience to you, and I should think that Clara, too, would much rather stay with you. Now finally: whether I will stand in for you now and then so you can botanise. As far as I can promise at the moment I will be happy to oblige. But as nobody knows what the future will hold with the current chaos that exists everywhere, I cannot say much in that respect.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In spite of my ardent wish I am not likely to be able to come to Adelaide this winter. When the roads dry out it's off again to the diggings. I will then visit you in Melbourne as soon as I can get away.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now I still want to ask you some favours. Firstly to get me new glasses. I am sending the old ones along only so you can judge the thickness of the lenses, they are No. 8. If possible take one with a silver or at least an argentan frame. Further I would like to ask you to get me some good cowpox vaccine. There are a lot of children in the vicinity here who need to be vaccinated, and I have promised the people to obtain the vaccine if at all possible. If you are able to attend to that you would do me a great favour by sending both by the next mail. And let me know at the same time, if you can let me have some of your own drugs, or whether I will have to write to Heuzenröder. I still have £3.15.2 credit with Heuzenröder, which you can sequestrate for the time being for the glasses etc.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>While looking forward to a few lines from you with the next mail I send my regards,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Yours E. Wehl M.D.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I have sent the glasses separately. You will find a few specimens with them, which may perhaps be of interest to you. If you like you can also confiscate the coins, which Heuzenröder still has from me. I sent them to him to pick out a few for himself, and he has never let on a thing about them since.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
