<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Millicent, ¶  March 12th, 1901. ¶ My dearest Clara, ¶  ¶ You will have expected a reply to your letter before this, but I waited to see Willie &amp; then I wanted to think it over. The boys &amp; I think it b...</title>
            <author>Clara Wehl</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M1901-03-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M100B, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M1901.03.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Clara Wehl</author>
               <title>Millicent, ¶  March 12th, 1901. ¶ My dearest Clara, ¶  ¶ You will have expected a reply to your letter before this, but I waited to see Willie &amp; then I wanted to think it over. The boys &amp; I think it b...</title>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M1901-03-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Clara Doughty</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Millicent, ¶  March 12th, 1901. ¶ My dearest Clara, ¶  ¶ You will have expected a reply to your letter before this, but I waited to see Willie &amp; then I wanted to think it over. The boys &amp; I think it b...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">M1901.03.12</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Clara Wehl to Clara Doughty</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RB MSS M100B, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Millicent,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">SA.</p>
               </note> March 12th, 1901.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dearest Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will have expected a reply to your letter before this, but I waited to see Willie &amp; then I wanted to think it over. The boys &amp; I think it best to let Mr. Potter alone now,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clara Wehl died 31 July 1901. In 1908 Clara Wehl's daughter Mrs Henrietta Sinclair initiated an action through Sydney solicitors seeking a writ of administration which was about to be served just before William Potter died. After consultation between the representatives of Henrietta Sinclair and Clara Doughty and of the Büttner brothers an Originating Summons to seek the Supreme Court's ruling on matters to do with the administration of the estate was issued by the Büttners with Clara Doughty as defendant. The case was heard in Chambers in August 1909 (see notes to C. Topp to H, and A. Büttner, 29 January 1909, in this edition as M1909-01-29). </p>
               </note> for there cannot be much left to make it worth while to go into expense for; even the house must have lost in value being so long neglected &amp; Dr. Büttner holding mortgage over it, the balance would not be much.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The statement of liabilities included in M's probate documents includes an overdraft to the Royal Bank of Australia Ltd secured by the deposit of title deeds of the land (VPRS 28/P0002, 62/802 Ferdinand J H Von Mueller: Grant of probate, 27 November 1896). Clara Wehl was evidently mistaken in believing that Alexander Büttner held the mortgage at the time of M's death. Earlier, the family had understood that the proceeds from the sale of M's possessions, including his house, would be used 'to pay expenses for the finishing &amp; publishing of the last parts of his works'; see C. Wehl to H. Sinclair, 20 October 1896 (in this edition as M96-10-20).</p>
               </note> Then you see the Will debars us from interfering.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M's last will and testament (in this edition as 84-06-17).</p>
               </note> Uncle has put it so entirely in the Trustees hands; in fact as Ted says,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ferdinand Edward Wehl.</p>
               </note> he might as well have left it all to them; they have been his bosom friends so let them keep it!, as they are not ashamed to do so. Dr. Büttner advised me not to interfere with Mr. Potter as he was trying to get a fund for the family from the federal parliament, if the said parliament think it a just claim, it will be very acceptable; but I am certainly not going to beg it.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No such fund was awarded by the Australian Parliament.</p>
               </note> I know you will think as I do. You can of course act independently of me, if you wish to do so but I would not be drawn into a lawsuit for anything. I will write though to Mr. Potter to send that box of things he spoke of if it does not come soon, cant think what he is waiting for; nor why the monument is not placed yet, he had nearly funds enough long ago.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">The monument on M's grave was unveiled on 26 November 1901 by </seg>the Governor-General of Australia, the Earl of Hopetoun (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 27 November 1901, p. 9, col. a).</p>
               </note> I have not heard if the herbarium is sold yet.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had presented his herbarium to the Victorian Government many years earlier; see M to W. Hooker, 20 August 1865. In his will, however, he had held out the hope that the Government would acknowledge 'the justness of making some monetary allowance to my heirs for the botanic collections, which I accumulated by private means from 1840 til to the present time, and which became united with those portions of the Museum-plants, which were acquired at Governments expense'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thank you very much for the sweet little flower; I am glad my brothers resting place is kept neat. I return Miss Kings letter,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Georgina King?</p>
               </note> they are very kind in taking so much interest in Uncles estate. Uncle has had so many true friends.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A pencilled note in an unknown hand has been added at this point, in space at the bottom of the page: '? (Who are they Clara? I mean the true friends: are they Potter &amp; Co?). If I get my holiday next month I may do some good by going there &amp; looking things up, but I must be authorised by you &amp; Mother.' The reference to a holiday 'next month' suggests that the writer may have been Clara Wehl's son Ted who, Clara indicates, was expecting to be granted a holiday then.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am glad you &amp; Mrs. Chapman<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">'Mrs Chapman' and other persons in the remainder of the letter have not been identified, unless indicated in a note.</p>
               </note> had such nice holidays, Ted is looking forward to his, next month I think, the first he is getting in the 5 years he has been at this Office. Meta<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Clara Wehl's yougest child, Meta Agnes Wehl, was to marry Andrew Stenhouse in September 1901.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> will soon be home now, yes she seems very happy, dear little girl, I wish it was not Broken Hill she is going too, but as you say she has the advantage of being near Lu.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clara Wehl's daughter, Louise Matthiessen.</p>
               </note> If Mrs. Mann is in Town yet give her my love, has she good news of her son Fred? do you know Berthas son Jack (the third) has gone to Africa?<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In an Australian contingent to fight in the Boer War? If 'Jack' is the son of Bertha Harris, née Wehl, there is no record of him or a person with a similar name in the Boer War service records in the National Archives of Australia, series B4418 (accessed 8 May 2022).</p>
               </note> such nonsense, I am very cross about it. - Glen's had the news that Alic is seriously ill at Port Elizabeth,<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Cape Province, South Africa.</p>
               </note> they did not know whether ill or wounded. Lena &amp; Hilda came in to day, they tell me Jack Clark has applied to go, Will will miss him he had him so many years. Last week Bill Plate was killed - the horse fell with him. - Geo is still with Overheus, they were all well.<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clara Wehl's daughter Mattilde had married Henry Overheu in 1879; 'Geo' is presumably her younger brother George Albert Wehl.</p>
               </note> Am anxious to hear from Ferd,<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Clara Wehl's son James Henry Ferdinand Wehl.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> there has been very heavy rain in N.W., rivers overflowing, he has to cross some when travelling with his teams. Marie<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clara Wehl's unmarried daughter Maria Magdalene Wehl.</p>
               </note> &amp; I are going to call on Fanny to morrow; Bessie will have a nice long holiday. We were surprised to see Mrs. Burton's house advertised for sale; did you know? Good night dear, give my love to Mrs. Chapman,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Your loving Aunt</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Clara Wehl</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Marie sends love. Also Ted.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
