<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Professor J. Agardh, ¶ Lund. ¶ Hamburg, 10 January 1854. ¶ Esteemed Sir, ¶  ¶ An acquaintance of mine is travelling to Sweden tomorrow and offers to take the enclosed publication with him, which I ...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M54-01-10-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Agardh papers, Lunds Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M54.01.10</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>To Professor J. Agardh, ¶ Lund. ¶ Hamburg, 10 January 1854. ¶ Esteemed Sir, ¶  ¶ An acquaintance of mine is travelling to Sweden tomorrow and offers to take the enclosed publication with him, which I ...</title>
               <date when="1854-01-10">1854-01-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M54-01-10-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Cutleria multifida</term>
               <term>Taonia solieri</term>
               <term>Polysiphonia</term>
               <term>Conferva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jacob Agardh</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">To Professor J. Agardh, ¶ Lund. ¶ Hamburg, 10 January 1854. ¶ Esteemed Sir, ¶  ¶ An acquaintance of mine is travelling to Sweden tomorrow and offers to take the enclosed publication with him, which I ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M54.01.10</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Jacob Agardh</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Agardh papers, Lunds Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Herrn Prof. J. Agardh</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lund</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg d. 10 Janr 54.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Werthester Herr,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein Bekannter von mir reist morgen nach Schweden und erbietet sich, beifolgendes Heft mitzunehmen, das ich ohne einige Zeilen beizufügen, nicht abgehen lassen kann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eigentlich hätte ich Ihnen schon vor langer Zeit schreiben sollen, denn ich habe Ihnen für Ihre freundliche Mittheilung Ihres Algenwerkes recht vielen Dank zu sagen. Unzählige Male habe ich es mir vorgenommen, und ganz ernsthaft damals, als ich das Vergnügen hatte, Ihren Vater bei mir zu sehen, aber die vielen amtlichen Geschäfte liessen es nicht zu. Dann wollte ich auch gerne erst die Müller'schen Algen absolviren und dazu gehörte mehr Zeit als ich erwartete. Sie müssen nämlich wissen, dass ich unserm Freunde, Senator Binder hauptsächlich zu verdanken habe, dass man mich vor zwei Jahren in das Sanitätscollegium wählte und damit mir ein recht schwieriges und zeitraubendes Amt aufbürdete, das ich aber nicht ablehnen konnte. Uebrigens bin ich jetzt so eingearbeitet, dass ich öfter wieder von Binder's unbestimmten Algen vornehme, auch meine eigne Sammlung in Ordnung bringen kann. Nachdem ich längere Zeit keine Algologie mehr getrieben hatte, musste ich mich erst wieder einarbeiten. Dass ich manches noch nicht ganz in Ihrem Sinne aufgefasst ist mir mehr als wahrscheinlich, und ich bitte Sie deshalb freundlich, mit den beifolgenden Algis Müllerianis &amp; Zollingerianis etwas Nachsicht zu haben. Da Freund Müller jezt festen Fuss in Südaustralien gefasst und von der Regierung angestellt ist, so werde ich noch recht viele Gelegenheit haben, über die Algen Australiens etwas zu veröffentlichen, ich erwarte noch gegenwärtig eine Sendung von Port Philipp, die nach dem Briefe viel Interessantes enthalten soll. Was ich bis jetzt erhalten habe, ist meistens nur in wenigen Exemplaren vorhanden, dennoch werde ich Ihnen von manchen neuen Arten ein Exemplar mittheilen können, das geschehen soll, so wie ich die Zeit gehabt haben werde für Müllers und meine Sammlung abzunehmen. Im ersten Frühlinge erhalten sie bestimmt ein Packet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Interessant ist doch die immer mehr hervortretende Uebereinstimmung vieler das Adriatische Meer bewohnenden Algen mit denen der Küste vom südlichen Australien. Ich bin nicht im Stande gewesen, die <name key="Cutleria%20multifida">Cutleria multifida</name> sowie Taonia Solierii zu unterscheiden. Harvey wird wahrscheinlich die Beispiele noch bedeutend vermehren.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Algen aus Java von Zollinger habe ich schon vor drei Jahren bestimmt; erst jetzt hat mir Zollinger einige Abdrücke zu geschickt. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich will nicht hoffen, dass die Herausgabe Ihrer Species Algarum ins Stocken gerathen ist; es würde allgemeines Bedauern erregen. Wer sich jemals mit Algologie beschäftigte, weiss Ihre Arbeit und Ihren Fleiss zu würdigen, und wird Ihnen grossen Dank wissen, wenn Sie es bis zu Ende führen. Welche Schwierigkeiten haben Sie aber noch bei den grossen Gattungen <name key="Polysiphonia">Polysiphonia</name>, <name key="Conferva">Conferva</name> etc. zu überwinden! Kützing hat es Ihnen mit letzterer Gattung nun freilich leichter gemacht, dass er die Arten abbildete, aber selbst mit den alten Arten ist wenig zu machen. Möge Ihnen der Himmel Gesundheit und Ausdauer schenken! Mit wahrer Freude habe ich Harvey's Nereis boreali-americana begrüsst; ein solches Werk söhnt uns oft völlig wieder aus, wenn einmal die Lust vergangen ist. Was wird Harvey noch leisten, wenn er gesund bleibt. Er ist am 10 October glücklich auf Ceylon angekommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Indem ich Ihnen zum Schlusse nun meinen Glückwunsch zum soeben angetretenen neuen Jahr abstatte, wünsche ich, dass im Lauf desselben unsere Beziehungen wieder vermehrt werden und wir das Vergnügen haben mögen, Sie im Sommer wieder einmal hier zu sehen. Binder, der sich Ihnen bestens empfehlen lässt, ist augenblicklich an rheumatischen Beschwerden leidend, hat überhaupt in der letzten Zeit sehr gealtert, welches seinen angestrengten Arbeiten zuzuschreiben ist. Er wollte eigentlich seine Algensammlung verkaufen, ich sträube mich aber so viel als möglich dagegen, und suche es ihm auszureden. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit der Bitte um Ihr ferneres Wohlwollen und dem verbündlichsten Dank für die gütigst geschenkten Hefte Ihrer Species Algarum, verbleibe ich</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>ergebenster</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To Professor J. Agardh,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Lund.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 10 January 1854.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An acquaintance of mine is travelling to Sweden tomorrow and offers to take the enclosed publication with him, which I cannot dispatch without first adding a few lines.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I really should have written to you long ago, because I have to offer you many thanks for kindly sending me your work on algae. I made the good intention innumerable times, and quite seriously at the time, when I had the pleasure of having your father<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">C. A. Agardh.</p>
               </note> with me, but the many official duties prevented it. Then I also wanted to finish Mueller's algae first, and that took more time than I had expected. You have to understand that, thanks mainly to our friend Senator Binder,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Nicolaus Binder, Mayor of Hamburg.</p>
               </note> they elected me to the Public Health Council two years ago, and with that burdened me with a rather difficult and time-consuming office which, however, I could not very well refuse. However, I am now so well settled into it, that I am again able to take up Binder's unidentified algae more frequently,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder curated Binder's large private algal herbarium, and had permission to take duplicates of interest to him for his own collections (pers. comm. W. Prud'homme van Reine, Leiden University).</p>
               </note> and also to put my own collections in order. After not having been engaged in algology for a long period I had to get back into it again at first. It is more than likely that I have not yet understood many species quite in your sense, and for that reason I beg you to show a little indulgence towards the enclosed 'Algae Muellerianae' and 'Zollingerianae'.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sonder (1852) and Sonder (1853a), which was not actually published until 1855 (TL2), contain Sonder's discussions of M's algae. Zollinger's collection is probably that listed in Sonder (1854), where Sonder described some new species.</p>
               </note> As friend Mueller has now firmly established himself in southern Australia and is employed by the Government, I shall no doubt have many opportunities to publish something on the algae of Australia. I am at present expecting a consignment from Port Phillip which, according to his letter,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> should contain much of interest. What I have obtained so far has usually been represented by only a few specimens, yet I should be able to send you a specimen of many of the new species. This is to be done as soon as I have found the time to take out the material for Mueller<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">M expected that correspondents to whom he sent collections for working up would return a set of named specimens for the Melbourne collection</seg>.</p>
               </note> and for my own collection. You can be sure of receiving a parcel by the beginning of Spring.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is interesting to see the more and more pronounced agreement of so many algae inhabiting the Adriatic Sea with those found on the coast of southern Australia. I have been unable to differentiate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cutleria%20multifida">Cutleria multifida</name>
               </seg> or <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Taonia%20solieri">Taonia solieri</name>
               </seg>. Harvey will probably be able to multiply these examples considerably. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I had already determined Zollinger's algae from Java three years ago, but it is only now that Zollinger sent me a few reprints.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do hope that the publication of your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Species algarum</seg> has not come to a halt,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Agardh (1848-1901).</p>
               </note> that would cause general regrets. Anyone who ever engaged in algology is able to appreciate your work and your dilligence and will be very grateful to you if you complete the work. But what difficulties you will have to overcome with the large genera <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Polysiphonia">Polysiphonia</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Conferva">Conferva</name>
               </seg> etc.! With the latter genus Kützing has made your task easier, it is true, by having illustrated the species,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kützing (1846-69).</p>
               </note> but even with the old species little can be done. May Heaven grant you health and perseverance! I have greeted Harvey's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Nereis boreali-americana</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Harvey (1851-8).</p>
               </note> with great joy; such a work often reconciles one, when one has temporarily lost interest. What may Harvey yet produce, if only he remains healthy! He arrived safely in Ceylon on 10 October.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">From Ceylon, Harvey travelled on to Australia; see Ducker (1988).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finally I send you my best wishes for the just commenced New Year, and I wish that in its course our communications may become once again more frequent, and that we may have the pleasure of seeing you here once more in summer. Binder, who sends you his regards, suffers from rheumatic problems just now. He has generally aged a lot lately, which is attributed to his strenuous work. He really had intended to sell his algal collection, but I oppose him as much as I am able to and try to talk him out of it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Please maintain your good will towards me and accept my sincere thanks for the issues of your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Species algarum</seg>. I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>most devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Conferva">Conferva</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cutleria%20multifida">Cutleria multifida</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polysiphonia">Polysiphonia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Taonia%20solieri">Taonia solieri</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
