<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Ferdinand Mueller, Doctor of Philosophy, of Melbourne, Australia, applies to our Faculty for the conferring of a doctoral degree in absentia. A Rostocker by birth, he learned the apothecary trade a...</title>
            <author>the Medical Faculty, Universität Rostock,</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M57-10-28-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Medizinische Fakultät, Promotionsakte Ferdinand Müller, Universitätsarchiv, Rostock.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M57.10.28</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>the Medical Faculty, Universität Rostock,</author>
               <title> ¶ Ferdinand Mueller, Doctor of Philosophy, of Melbourne, Australia, applies to our Faculty for the conferring of a doctoral degree in absentia. A Rostocker by birth, he learned the apothecary trade a...</title>
               <date when="1857-10-28">1857-10-28</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M57-10-28-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>the Department for Educational Affairs, Schwerin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Ferdinand Mueller, Doctor of Philosophy, of Melbourne, Australia, applies to our Faculty for the conferring of a doctoral degree in absentia. A Rostocker by birth, he learned the apothecary trade a...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M57.10.28</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From the Medical Faculty, Universität Rostock, to the Department for Educational Affairs, Schwerin</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Medizinische Fakultät, Promotionsakte Ferdinand Müller, Universitätsarchiv, Rostock.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Annotated: 'Gesuch der med. Facultät zu Rostock um die Uebertragung des Allerhöchsten Kanzlerrechtes zur Promotia in absentia des Doctors der Philosophie Ferdinand Müller in Melbourne.' — [Application of the medical Faculty in Rostock for the transfer of the Highest Chancellor's authority for the promotion in absentia of the Doctor of Philosophy Ferdinand Müller of Melbourne.]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'An das h. Grossh. Minst., Abth. f. U. A. zu Schwerin.' — [To the Highest Grand-Ducal Ministry, Department for Educational Affairs in Schwerin.]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'Exped. d. 30. Octbr 1857.' — [Dispatched 30 October 1857.]</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Doctor der Philosophie Ferdinand Müller zu Melbourne in Australien bewirbt sich bei unserer Facultät um die Ertheilung des Doctorgrades in absentia. Derselbe, ein geborener Rostocker, lernte die Apothekerkunst zu Tönningen im Herzogthum Schleswig, conditionirte daselbst einige Jahre als Gehülfe, absolvirte sein Examen als Apotheker und bezog dann die Universität Kiel. Hier dem Studium der Naturwissenschaften und insbesondere dem der Botanik sich widmend, erwarb er sich unter Veröffentlichung einer lateinisch geschriebenen Inaugural- Dissertation die philosophische Doctorwürde und verliess weiterhin Europa, um sich nach Australien zu übersiedeln. Seine äussere Lebenssubsistenz durch Ausübung der Medizin, zu welcher er sich hauptsächlich durch Selbststudium befähigt hatte, sichernd, gab er sich restlos seiner Neigung zur Erforschung der dortigen Pflanzenwelt hin und veröffentlichte wiederholt in Englisch-Australischen Zeitschriften die werthvollen Erkenntnisse seines Fleisses, die wegen der besonderen Berücksichtigung der Heilkräfte der neu beschriebenen Pflanzen auch für die Medizin ein unmittelbares Interesse haben. Er ist zur Zeit Director des botanischen Gartens zu Melbourne, in Anerkennung seiner Verdienste schon im Jahre 1852 zum Governments Botanist ernannt, in welcher Eigenschaft die gedruckt uns vorliegenden amtlichen Berichte über die Vegetation der Colonie Victoria von ihm verfasst wurden, und hat die Zusicherung eines Professors der Botanik an der in erst genannter Stadt zu begründenden Universität. Seit Anfang dieses Jahres ist er nach einer anderthalbjährigen Abwesenheit von seiner Reise mit Mr Gregory zur Erforschung des nördlichen Australiens und der Quellen des Victoriaflusses nach Melbourne zurückgekehrt und hat eine Beschreibung und Karte dieser Reise seinem ehemaligen Landesherren, unserm Allerdurchlauchtigsten Grossherzogs unterthänigst überreichen lassen. Wir halten dafür, dass in dem Vorstehenden sich genügende Motive vorfinden, um dem Gesuche des Bittstellers zu entsprechen und beantragen daher bei einem hohen Grossherzoglichen Ministerium Abth. für U.-A.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Unerrichts-Angelegenheiten.</p>
               </note> Zwecks Promotion des Doctors der Philosophie Ferdinand Müller zu Melbourne zum Doctor der Medicin in absentia die Transferirung des Allerhöchsten Kanzlerrechtes auf den Professor Spitta als den derzeitigen Dekan unserer Facultät.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Rostock, den 28, October 1857.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand Mueller, Doctor of Philosophy, of Melbourne, Australia, applies to our Faculty for the conferring of a doctoral degree in absentia. A Rostocker by birth, he learned the apothecary trade at Tönningen<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. Tönning. While the Müller family lived in Tönning, M did his pharmacy training in Husum.</p>
               </note> in the Duchy of Schleswig, was employed there for some years as an assistant, passed his examination as pharmacist, and then entered the University at Kiel. Here he devoted himself to the study of the natural sciences and in particular to botany, and obtained a Doctorate of Philosophy with the publication of an inaugural dissertation in Latin, and subsequently left Europe to emigrate to Australia. His livelihood secured through the practice of medicine, for which he had qualified largely through self-education, he devoted himself entirely to his inclination to explore the vegetation there, and repeatedly published in English-Australian journals the valuable results of his work, which are of direct interest also for medicine because of the particular consideration given to the medicinal properties of the newly described plants. He is currently Director of the botanic garden in Melbourne. Already in 1852 he was appointed Government Botanist in recognition of his merits,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M's appointment dated from 26 January 1853.</p>
               </note> and in this capacity wrote the reports on the vegetation of the Colony of Victoria, which we see before us in print. He has been assured of a professorship in botany in the above city at the university about to be founded there.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The University of Melbourne was founded in 1855; there was never any suggestion that a chair in botany would be created there for M.</p>
               </note> At the beginning of this year he returned to Melbourne after an absence of one-and-a-half years from his expedition with Mr Gregory for the exploration of northern Australia and the sources of the Victoria River, and has most humbly presented a description and map of this journey to his former Sovereign, our Most Serene Highness, the Grand Duke. We consider that the above provides sufficient motives to accede to the application of the supplicant and consequently, for the purpose of conferring a Doctor of Medicine in absentia on Ferdinand Mueller, Doctor of Philosophy, of Melbourne, apply to the august Grand-Ducal Ministry, Department for Educational Affairs, for the transfer of the Most High Chancellor's authority to Professor Spitta as the current Dean of our Faculty.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Rostock, 28 October 1857.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
