<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Hamburg, 21 October 1857] ¶  ¶ The father of Dr Ferdinand Mueller, a native of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, took part in the war of liberation under Prince Gustav and was one of the few, who returned from t...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M57-10-21-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Universitätsarchivs Rostock; Prom. med. 7, 1857/58; Müller, Ferdinand.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M57.10.21</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>[Hamburg, 21 October 1857] ¶  ¶ The father of Dr Ferdinand Mueller, a native of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, took part in the war of liberation under Prince Gustav and was one of the few, who returned from t...</title>
               <date when="1857-10-21">1857-10-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M57-10-21-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Johannes Roeper</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[Hamburg, 21 October 1857] ¶  ¶ The father of Dr Ferdinand Mueller, a native of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, took part in the war of liberation under Prince Gustav and was one of the few, who returned from t...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M57.10.21</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Johannes Roeper</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Universitätsarchivs Rostock; Prom. med. 7, 1857/58; Müller, Ferdinand.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Biographical notes on M by Wilhelm Sonder that accompanied a letter from Sonder to Roeper dated 21 October 1857 that has not been found. The file includes a list of documents submitted to the medical faculty of Rostock University in support of M's application for the granting of a medical degree; for details, see M to J. Roeper, 21 July 1857 (in this edition as 57-07-21a). Both Sonder's letter and these biographical notes are listed.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Vater von Dr Ferdinand Müller, ein geborener Mecklenburg-Schweriner machte den Freiheitskrieg mit unter Prinz Gustav, und war einer der wenigen, die aus der Schlacht bei Sehestedt zurückkehrten. Er wurde nach seiner Rückkehr an einem Thore in Rostock als Zollbeamter angestellt. Nach seinem Tode verliess die Frau mit ihrem Sohn und zwei Töchtern Rostock und siedelte nach Tönning über zu ihrem dort wohnenden und noch lebenden Bruder, Namens Martens. Nachdem Ferdinand Müller hier die Schule verlassen, trat er in das Apothekergeschäft des Herrn Becker daselbst. Nach beendeter vierjähriger Lehrzeit conditionirte er einige Jahre und studierte darauf in Kiel. Nach abgelegtem Apothekerexamen erwarb er sich nach Einreichung einer kleinen bot Arbeit über die Vegetation des südwestlichen Seestrandes von Schleswig das Diplom als Doctor Philosophiae. Vor zehn Jahren entschloss er sich aus Liebe zu seinen Schwestern, deren Gesundheitszustand ein südliches Klima erfordete, seinen Plan, Medizin und Naturwissenschaften zu studieren, aufzugeben, und nach Südaustralien auszuwandern. In Adelaide wollte es ihm nicht glücken, er war genöthigt einige Jahre in eine Apotheke als Leiter derselben einzutreten. Unterstützung von Verwandten und Bekannten in Europa setzten ihn in den Stand in Melbourne eine Apotheke anzulegen. Hier wusste er durch seinen Eifer für Botanik und Naturwissenschaften überhaupt, die Aufmerksamkeit des Gouverneurs Latrobe auf sich zu lenken, welches zur Folge hatte, dass er im Jahre 1852 als Government Botanist angestellt wurde. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ueber seine Thätigkeit als solcher geben die beiliegenden drei Berichte Zeugnis. Im Anfang dieses Jahres kehrte er mit der Gregory'schen Expedition zur Erforschung des nördlichen Australiens nach anderthalbjähriger Abwesenheit nach Melbourne zurück, wo er unter Beibehaltung seiner früheren Stellung zugleich Director des kürzlich begründeten botanischen Gartens geworden ist. Als Beweis von Dr Müller's Tüchtigkeit möchte wohl gelten, dass der gegenwärtige Gouverneur der Provinz Victoria Müller's jährliches Einkommen auf 600 Pfund Sterling erhöht und ihm ein eigenes neues Haus im botanischen Garten erbauen lassen hat.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">W. Sonder Dr</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">[Hamburg, 21 October 1857]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>The father of Dr Ferdinand Mueller, a native of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, took part in the war of liberation under Prince Gustav and was one of the few, who returned from the battle near Sehestedt. After his return he was employed as customs officer at one of the city gates in Rostock. After his death his wife with her son and two<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Louise Müller had three surviving daughters who moved with her to Tönning, Iwanne, Bertha and Clara.</p>
               </note> daughters left Rostock and moved to Tönning to her brother residing and still living there by name of Martens.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Johann Ferdinand Mertens.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> After Ferdinand Mueller had left school here, he entered the pharmacy of Dr Becker there.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Albert Becker, In Husum, Schleswig.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Having completed his four years apprenticeship, he worked there for a further few years and then studied in Kiel. After he had passed his pharmaceutical examinations, he obtained the diploma of a Doctor of Philosophy with the submission of a small botanical work on the vegetation of the south-western sea shore of Schleswig. Out of love for his sisters, whose health required a southern climate, he decided 10 years ago to give up his plan to study medicine and the natural sciences and to emigrate to South Australia. He did not have much luck in Adelaide, and found himself obliged to work for several years as manager of a pharmacy. Support of family and friends enabled him to establish a pharmacy in Melbourne. By his enthusiasm for botany and natural sciences in general he was able to attract the attention of Governor Latrobe. As a result he was appointed Government Botanist in 1852.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was appointed Victoria's Government Botanist on 26 January 1853.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The three enclosed reports<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Reports not found; they are identified as parts of B53.10.01, B54.10.01 and B55.11.01, among the evidence submitted in support of M's being awarded the MD degree; see M to J. Roeper, 21 July 1857 (in this edition as 57-07-21a), n. 8.</p>
               </note> bear witness to his activities in this capacity. At the beginning of this year he returned to Melbourne after an absence of one and a half years with the Gregory expedition for the exploration of northern Australia.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> Here, while retaining his former position, he became Director of the recently founded Botanic Gardens. As proof of Dr Mueller's ability should be added that the current Governor of the province of Victoria has raised Mueller's annual salary to £600 Sterling, and has had a new house built for him in the Botanic Gardens. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dr W. Sonder.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
