<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 10 August 1863. ¶ Esteemed friend, ¶  ¶ I am writing today with the news that the case with Mueller's plants from New Holland ¶  has been dispatched today to Ch. Petit &amp; Co in Lübeck, to be f...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M63-08-10-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M63.08.10</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 10 August 1863. ¶ Esteemed friend, ¶  ¶ I am writing today with the news that the case with Mueller's plants from New Holland ¶  has been dispatched today to Ch. Petit &amp; Co in Lübeck, to be f...</title>
               <date when="1863-08-10">1863-08-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M63-08-10-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Spongotrichum dichotomum</term>
               <term>Dictyurus australasicus</term>
               <term>Thuretia teres</term>
               <term>Callithamnion</term>
               <term>Halodictyon</term>
               <term>Hanowia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jacob Agardh</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 10 August 1863. ¶ Esteemed friend, ¶  ¶ I am writing today with the news that the case with Mueller's plants from New Holland ¶  has been dispatched today to Ch. Petit &amp; Co in Lübeck, to be f...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M63.08.10</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Jacob Agardh</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Hamburg 10 Aug 63</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrtester Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bring Ihnen heute die Nachricht, dass die Kiste mit den neuholländischen Müller'schen Pflanzen an Ch. Petit &amp; Co in Lübeck abgegangen ist, um pr. Dampfschiff an Herrn Cronholm, Buchhändler in Malmö mit Ihrer Addresse weiter befördert zu werden. Sie werden Herrn Cronholm hiervon gefälligst benachrichtigen. Die Sammlung ist grösser geworden als ich geglaubt habe, ich habe sie lange nicht angesehen. Es wird aber </seg>wohl ¾ der<seg style=""> Arten neu für Sie sein, und ich denke, Sie werden damit zufrieden sein, wenn auch mehrere Arten, von Müller's ersten Reisen in kleinen Exemplaren vorhanden sind. Es sind 1300 Species, wofür ich mir 130 Thal. preuss. Crt erbitte. Jetzt sind alle Pflanzen verkauft, worüber ich mich freue, denn das Zusammenlegen und Zettelschreiben ist keine angenehme Arbeit. Wenn ich Ihnen späterhin Nachträge zu diesen Pflanzen liefern dürfte, so kann das nur privatim, als Tausch oder Geschenk von meiner Seite geschehen, da Dr Müller jetzt keine Zeit mehr zum Sammeln hat und wie ich fürchte, nach seiner bevorstehenden Verheiratung mit einer Engländerin aus vornehmer Familie, die Botanik vernachlässigen wird. Indess hat die jetzt erscheinende Flora australiensis von Bentham den Nebentitel "assisted by Dr Müller", so dass dieses wichtige Werk wohl noch unter seiner Beihülfe vollendet werden dürfte. Von Algen war aus den ersten Sendungen nur wenig mehr vorhanden, es waren auch nur wenige Exemplare da, die grösstentheils in mein Herbarium eingereiht worden sind, und wovon ich Ihnen später, wenn Sie mir Ihre Wünsche aufgeben wollen, etwas mittheilen werde. Ich bedaure, dass Sie meine letzten Nachträge zu den Algis Müllerianis in der Linnaea nicht gesehen haben, Sie würden sonst gewusst haben, dass mein </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Dictyurus%20australasicus">Dictyurus australasicus</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> ein älterer Name ist als </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Thuretia%20teres">Thuretia teres</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Harv. Leider schickt mir Schlechtendal keine Abdrücke meiner Arbeiten, sonst hätte ich Ihnen davon abgegeben. Ich kann mich immer noch nicht dabei beruhigen, dass </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Halodictyon">Halodictyon</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Zan einerlei sein soll mit </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Hanowia">Hanowia</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">. Ich habe <name key="Halodictyon">Halodictyon</name> in Herbaria und halte sie für verschieden. Noch anders scheint mir die Pflanze zu sein, und ganz wie ein </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Callithamnion">Callithamnion</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, welche Kützing von Meneghini erhielt und im 12t. Bde der Tabulae phycolog. sehr gut abbildete. Ich lasse mir in diesen Tagen von Lenormand dessen Originalexemplar kommen, um endlich ins Reine zu gelangen. — Was Areschoug als </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Holonema</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> beschrieben hat, ist sicher nichts als </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <name key="Spongotrichum%20dichotomum">Spongotrichum dichotomum</name>
                  </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Kütz. Bei letzterem ist der Standort falsch, es soll anstatt St Croix heissen Vera Cruz. Kützing hat die Pflanze in meinem Zimmer beschrieben, ich habe sie noch, und auch dieselbe Pflanze von Liebmann bei Vera Cruz gesammelt. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Da unser guter Binder noch im Ostseebade ist, kann ich ihm Ihren Wunsch wegen seiner Photographie noch nicht mittheilen, werde es aber bei der Rückkehr thun, da auch Lenormand dasselbe wünscht. Mein Bild erhalten Sie hierbei; ich darf Sie nun auch wohl um das Ihrige dagegen bitten für mein Album botanischer Freunde, wo ich Ihnen den Platz zwischen Binder &amp; Lenormand zugedacht habe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn ich weiss, dass Sie exotische Pflanzen kaufen, kann ich Ihnen mitunter etwas davon anbieten, da mir häufig Sammlungen zum Verkaufen angestellt werden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Da ich nicht weiss, ob Sie noch in Stockholm sind, addressire ich den Brief noch an Prof. Andersson.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich verbleibe</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>hochachtungsvoll ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 10 August 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am writing today with the news that the case with Mueller's plants from New Holland<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sonder had offered to sell Agardh a collection of M's plants, 'completely different from those from Western Australia, which you own from Preiss. … The collection contains a lot of the plants newly discovered by Dr Mueller, especially from the Australian alps, of which only odd specimens have reached Europe' (W. Sonder to J. Agardh, 8 July 1863 (Handskr. Avdl., Universitetsbibliotek, Lund, Sweden).</p>
               </note> has been dispatched today to Ch. Petit &amp; Co in Lübeck, to be forwarded per steamer with your address to Mr Cronholm, bookdealer in Malmö. You will be so good as to notify Mr Cronholm of this. The collection has turned out to be larger than I had thought, but I had not looked at it for a long time. Three-quarters of the species will probably be new to you; I think you will be satisfied with them, even though several species from Mueller's earliest journeys are represented only by small specimens. There are 1300 species, for which I ask you for 130 Prussian Thaler Courant. All the plants are now sold, I am happy about that for the sorting and writing of labels is not a pleasant job. If I may later on send you further supplements to these plants, I can do so only privately, as exchange, or as a gift from me, as Dr Mueller no longer has time to collect now, and I fear that after his imminent marriage to an English lady from a noble family he is going to neglect botany.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Euphemia Henderson, to whom M was engaged, is not known to have had any connection to the nobility. See also M to E. Henderson, 10 April 1863, where he forecasts 'the end of my botanical writings probably for a long while, God knows how long'. Perhaps he had made a similar comment to Sonder?</p>
               </note> At the same time the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg> by Bentham now being published<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bentham (1863-78).</p>
               </note> carries the subtitle 'assisted by Dr Mueller', so that this important work will probably still be completed with his assistance. There was not much left by way of algae from his first consignments, there had only been a few specimens which were mostly incorporated into my herbarium. But later on, if you will communicate your wishes, I shall send you bits of them. I regret that you did not see the last additions to my 'Algis Muellerianis' in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Linnaea</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sonder (1853a).</p>
               </note> Otherwise you would have known that my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Dictyurus%20australasicus">Dictyurus australasicus</name>
               </seg> is an older name than <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Thuretia%20teres">Thuretia teres</name>
               </seg> Harvey. Unfortunately Schlechtendal does not send me reprints of my papers, otherwise I should have sent you one. I still cannot accept that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Halodictyon">Halodictyon</name>
               </seg> Zanardini should be identical with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hanowia">Hanowia</name>
               </seg>. I have <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Halodictyon">Halodictyon</name>
               </seg> in my herbarium and consider it to be different. And different again, and quite like <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Callithamnion">Callithamnion</name>
               </seg>, seem to me to be the plants that Kützing obtained from Meneghini and illustrated very well in the 12th volume of his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Tabulae phycologicae.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Kützing (1846-69).</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I am just getting Lenormand to send me his authentic specimen, so that I can finally settle this. — What Areschoug has described as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Holonema</seg> is surely nothing other than <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Spongotrichum%20dichotomum">Spongotrichum dichotomum</name>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>Kützing. The locality for the latter is wrong, instead of St Croix it should read Vera Cruz. Kützing has described the plant in my room, I still have it, and also the same plant collected by Liebmann near Vera Cruz.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As our good Binder is still at the Baltic Sea resort, I cannot yet pass on to him your desire for his photograph, but shall do so on his return, as Lenormand, too, has the same wish. You receive my photo herewith, so I can now ask you to reciprocate by sending me yours for my album of botanical friends, where I have reserved you a place between Binder and Lenormand.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Once I know whether you buy exotic plants, I shall occasionally be able to offer you some, as I am often offered collections for sale.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As I do not know whether you are still in Stockholm, I still address the letter to Professor Andersson. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>respectfully devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Callithamnion">Callithamnion</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dictyurus%20australasicus">Dictyurus australasicus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Halodictyon">Halodictyon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hanowia">Hanowia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Spongotrichum%20dichotomum">Spongotrichum dichotomum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Thuretia%20teres">Thuretia teres</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
