<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royal Administration, ¶  ¶ I have the honour to submit a report on the consignments transmitted to the Royal Natural History Museum by Dr Ferd. Mueller, Director of the zoological and botanic Gardens ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand Krauss</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M67-12-07-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M67.12.07</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand Krauss</author>
               <title>Royal Administration, ¶  ¶ I have the honour to submit a report on the consignments transmitted to the Royal Natural History Museum by Dr Ferd. Mueller, Director of the zoological and botanic Gardens ...</title>
               <date when="1867-12-07">1867-12-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M67-12-07-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Internet link</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="56">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="44">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard von Schmidlin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Royal Administration, ¶  ¶ I have the honour to submit a report on the consignments transmitted to the Royal Natural History Museum by Dr Ferd. Mueller, Director of the zoological and botanic Gardens ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">M67.12.07</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">From Ferdinand Krauss to Eduard von Schmidlin</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A draft copy of this letter with many deletions and marginal and interlined text insertions is also on file. The clean copy used here is filed under a cover letter from Golther, Minister for Church and Educational Affairs, to the Office of the Director of the Royal Scientific Collections, dated 5 January 1878.</p>
               </note>Königliche Direction</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>habe ich die Ehre über die an das K.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Königliche.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> Naturalien Kabinet überschickten Sendungen des Dr. Ferd. Müller, Director des zoologischen u. botanischen Gartens in Melbourne in Australien Bericht zu erstatten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Schon im Jahr 1860 hat Dr. F. Müller dem Novara-Reisenden Dr. v. Hochstetter eine Sammlung von 11 Säugethieren, 38 Vögeln und 1 Säugethier Skelet zusammen im Werth von ca. 200 fl zur Übergabe an das K. Nat. </seg>Kabinet mitgegeben. <seg style="">Mit der Übersendung des Danksagungsschreibens für dieses Geschenk habe ich Dr. Müller damals unsere Sammlung aufs Wärmste empfohlen u. auch einen Tausch mit württemb.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">württembergischen.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> </seg>Naturalien angeboten. <seg style="">Er liess sich aber darauf nicht ein u. gab auch keine weitere Nachricht.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Erst zu Anfang dieses Jahres hatte ich Gelegenheit mit dem mir persönlich bekannten Botaniker Dr. W. Sonder in Hamburg in Verbindung zu treten u. erfuhr durch denselben, dass Dr. Müller beabsichtige, künftig alle seine Sendungen von Naturalien als Schenkung in einem deutschen Museum zu concentriren. Dr. Sonder, durch Herausgabe einer Flora capensis unter seinen Fachgenossen rühmlichst bekannt, ist nemlich</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">nämlich.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> nicht nur ein sehr intimer Jugendfreund von Dr. Müller, sondern besorgt ihm auch schon lange alle seine Angelegenheiten in Europa. Ins besondere hat er auch alle Sendungen von Naturalien, welche Dr. Müller in den letzten Jahren an die Museen verschiedener Staaten geschickt hat, befördert u. ebenso die Auszeichnungen, die ihm von mehrer Seiten durch Verleihen von Orden &amp;c zu Theil geworden sind, vermittelt.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine solche durch Dr. Müller in Aussicht gestellte, sehr viel versprechende Quelle zur Vermehrung unserer Sammlungen ergriff ich sofort mit aller Energy u. veranlasste Dr. Sonder es bei Dr. Müller zu vermitteln, dass er diese Schenkungen im hiesigen K. Naturalien Kabinet niederlegen möchte, indem ich die Versicherung damit verband, dass dieselben neben der nutzbringendsten Verwendung gewiss überall eine dankbare Anerkennung finden werden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zu gleicher Zeit habe ich ihm eine ausführliche Liste aller der australischen Wirbel- und wirbellosen Thiere, welche für unsere Zwecke wünschenswerth sind, für Dr. Müller übergeben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die 4 beiliegenden von Dr. Sonder an mich gerichteten Briefe, welche ich Königler Direction schon früher behufs einer Anfrage wegen Erfüllung der darin angedeuteten Wünsche mitgetheilt habe, geben über Sonders Correspondenz mit Müller näheren Aufschlusss und in No 4 derselben meldet Sonder die Zustimmung von Dr. Müller zu allen sein Anträgen zu Gunsten unserer Anstalt. Wir dürfen uns also der Hoffnung hingeben, dass das K. Naturalien Kabinet wie vor 30 Jahren durch die Freigebigkeit des Freiherrn von Ludwig die südafrikanische, bald auch durch Dr. Ferd. Müller die höchst eigenthümliche Fauna u. Flora Neuhollands in hervorragender Reichhaltigkeit vertreten haben wird.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Noch ehe diese zustimmende Antwort von Dr. Müler eingetroffen, schickte Dr. Sonder im Juni alle bei ihm vorräthig liegenden Müller'schen Naturalien hierher u. im August diejenigen, welche in der Zwischenzeit aus Neuholland angekommen sind, wofür ich vorläufig im Namen der Anstalt gedankt habe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die erste dieser Schenkungen bestand</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">a) aus einigen von Dr. Müller selbst verfassten naturwissenschaftlichen Schriften, sowie aus Waffen u. Geräthschaften der Neuholländer, welche ich sogleich an Ob. </seg>Stud. <seg style="">Rath</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Oberstudienrath.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> v. Stälin übergeben hatte u. von ihm zu etwa 80 fl. taxirt wurden, und</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">b) aus 8 Säugethieren u. 130 Vögeln zusammen im Werth von 380 fl.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zu gleicher Zeit sind an Seine Majestät den König für die königlichen Gärten zwei prachtvolle baumartige Farne (Dicksonia antarctica) angekommen, die vielleicht 150 Jahre alt seyn mögen u. wohl zu 200 fl. angeschlagen werden dürfen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die zweite Schenkung enthielt 6 Säugethiere, 88 Vögel, 250 Insekten u. 16 osteologische u. botanische Gegenstände im Werth von 400 fl.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bei diesen beiden Sendungen waren, da sie nicht mit Rücksicht auf unsere Wünsche gesammelt waren, viele Doubletten, die theils zur Ergänzung u. Verbesserung der vorhandenen Vögel, theils zum Tausch verwendet werden, aber es waren auch 5 werthvolle grosse Känguruhs, das seltene Stachelschnabelthier (Tachyglossus), einige andere Beutelthiere, ferner die grosse australische Trappe, 2 Kraniche, einige seltene Raubvögel, mehrere interessante Papageien, schöne Ibis u. andere Arten, die sehr willkommen u. auch auf unserer Desideraten-Liste vorgemerkt waren.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gestern kam eine dritte Schenkung hier an, die mir schon vor einigen Wochen angezeigt war u. die ich vor Absendung dieses Berichtes abwarten wollte.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie enthält neben einigen Schriften, die ich an die K. Bibliothek abgegeben habe, 2 Säugethiere, 79 Vögel, einige Conchylien, botanische u. mineralogische Gegenstände im Werth von ca 190 fl. In dieser Sendung sind hervorzuheben ein seltener Seeadler, ein sehr grosser Pelikan u. eine prachtvolle u. kostbare Argonauta, wahrscheinlich eine neue Art.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Gesammtwerth aller von Dr. Ferd. Müller erhaltenen Schenkungen darf wohl auf c. 1200 fl. angeschlagen werden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Über den Lebenslauf des Dr. Ferd. Müller hat Dr. Sonder in No 2 seiner Briefe ausführlich geschrieben.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. Müller ist in Rostock geboren, erlernte in Husum die Pharmacie, studirte in Kiel Medicin u. Naturwissenschaften u. reiste vor 20 Jahren nach Australien, wo er zuerst bald als Arzt bald als Apotheker sein Glück versuchte, später in Anerkennung seiner naturwissenschaftlichen Kenntnisse als Governments Botanist angestellt wurde, als solcher viele Reisen machte u. auch an der grossen Expedition Gregory's von der Ost- nach der Westküste Neuhollands Theil nahm. In Melbourne wurde er von der Regierung mit der Anlage des botanischen u.. zoologischen Gartens betraut u. ihm daselbst nach Gründung der Universität eine Lehrstelle übertragen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Als Director dieses sehr ausgedehnten Gartens ist Müller ausserordentlich thätig, betheilgt sich ausserdem an allen gemeinnützlichen Unternehmungen u. hat sich in der literarischen Welt durch Herausgabe vieler trefflicher Abhandlungen u. Werke, welche er zum Theil schon der K. Bibliothek zum Geschenk gemacht hat, einen so hoch geschätzten Namen erworben, dass ihn die meisten wissenschaftlichen Institute durch Aufnahme als Mitglied ehrten, wie aus dem beigehefteten Titel des 4. Bandes seiner Fragmenta Phytographiae austr. zu entnehmen ist.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie ihn die Wissenschaft hoch achtet, so danken ihm die naturhistorischen Museen in Copenhagen, Paris, Turin, Wien, Hannover, u. Gotha für seine freigebigen Schenkungen von Naturalien. Dafür sind ihm von ihren Regierungen Auszeichnungen zu Theil geworden, und es ist ihm sogar von einer auswärtigen Regierung der Barontitel zugesichert worden, wenn ihr das beabsichtigte Stipendium u. künftig alle Naturalien zugewendet werden. Der Müller hat aber als Deutscher Mann das Anerbieten abgelehnt.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn nun neben diesen vielen Auszeichnungen u. neben den oben verzeichneten Schenkungen im Werth von 1200 fl. in Berücksichtigung zu nehmen ist, dass Dr. Ferd. Müller, kaum 40 Jahre alt, unseren Instituten noch manchen Schatz von Sammlungsstücken zum Geschenk machen wird u. dass sein Anerbieten ein glänzendes genannt werden kann, so möchte ich Königliche Direction um Vermittlung bitten, dass Dr. Ferd. Müller durch Verleihen des Ritterkreuzes der Württembergischen Krone ausgezeichnet werde.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die 4 beiliegenden Briefe von Dr. Sonder, die jedoch nicht zur Mittheilung geschrieben, sondern vertraulich an mich gerichtet sind, bitte ich mir wieder zurück geben zu wollen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Stuttgart den 7. Dezember 1867.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. F. Krauss.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">Royal Administration,</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>I have the honour to submit a report on the consignments transmitted to the Royal Natural History Museum by Dr Ferd. Mueller, Director of the zoological and botanic Gardens in Melbourne in Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Already in the year 1860 Dr F. Mueller gave a collection of 11 mammals, 38 birds, and the skeleton of 1 mammal, to a total value of about 200 florins, to Dr von Hochstetter, who travelled with the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Novara </seg>expedition,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ferdinand Hochstetter was a member of the Austrian <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Novara</seg> expedition, 1857-9, that visited Melbourne in 1859, and he stayed with M while in Melbourne.</p>
               </note> for presentation to the Royal Natural History Museum. In my letter of thanks for this donation I commended our collections most warmly to Dr Mueller at that time and also offered to enter into exchange with Württemberg natural history objects. But he did not respond to this, nor did he give any further news. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Not until the beginning of this year, when I had occasion to communicate with Dr W. Sonder of Hamburg, a botanist with whom I am personally acquainted, did I hear from him that Dr Mueller intended to concentrate in future all his natural history consignments as a donation in one German museum. Dr Sonder, well known and respected among his colleagues in his field for the publication of a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora capensis</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Harvey &amp; Sonder (1859-65).</p>
               </note> is not only a very intimate friend of Dr Mueller from youth, but for a long time has acted as agent for him in all European matters. He has also forwarded in particular all the transmissions of natural history objects that Dr Mueller has sent to the museums of various countries in recent years, and also acted as intermediary in the matter of the decorations that came Dr Mueller's way in the form of Orders &amp;c bestowed on him from several sides.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I immediately grasped with great vigour such a very promising source for the increase of our collections as that held out by Dr Mueller, and I had Dr Sonder intercede with Dr Mueller so that he would deposit these donations in our Royal Natural History Museum here by giving him the assurance that, apart from their great beneficial use, they would always and everywhere elicit grateful appreciation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the same time I passed on to him a detailed list for Dr Mueller of all those Australian vertebrates and invertebrates that would be desirable for our purposes. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The 4 enclosed letters from Dr Sonder to me, which I already communicated to the Royal Administration earlier concerning a request for the fulfilment of the wishes indicated therein, give more detailed information on Sonder's correspondence with Mueller, and in the fourth of them Sonder reports Dr Mueller's agreement to all his proposals in favour of our institute. We may therefore nurture the fond hope that, as by the liberality of Baron von Ludwig 30 years ago with South African, so the Royal Natural History Museum will soon, through Dr Mueller, also have the most singular fauna and flora of New Holland represented in outstanding abundance.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Sonder last June sent here all of Mueller's natural history objects he was holding at the time, even before the affirmative answer from Dr Mueller had arrived, and then in August those that had arrived in the interim from New Holland. I have meanwhile thanked him for them in the name of the institute.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first of these donations consisted of</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">a) some of the natural history publications written by Dr Mueller himself, as well as weapons and artefacts of the Australian aborigines, which I immediately passed on to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Oberstudienrath</seg> von Stälin, and their value was estimated by him at 80 florins; and</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">b) 8 mammals and 130 birds at a total value of 380 florins.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the same time two splendid tree-like ferns (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia antarctica</seg>) that may be 150 years old and could probably be valued at 200 florins have arrived for His Majesty the King for the Royal Gardens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The second donation contained 6 mammals, 88 birds, 250 insects, and 16 osteological and botanical objects to the value of 400 florins.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Because they had not been sent in <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>consideration of our wishes, these two consignments contained many duplicates, and served partly to augment and improve the existing bird collections and are partly being used for exchange, but there were also 5 valuable large kangaroos, the rare Australian Spiny Ant-Eater (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Tachyglossus</seg>), a few other marsupials, the great Australian Bustard, 2 cranes, a few rare birds of prey, several interesting parrots, beautiful ibis and other species, which are very welcome and also had been on our list of desideratae.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A third donation arrived yesterday that had already been made known to me several weeks ago, and for which I had been waiting before submitting this report.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It contains, apart from a few publications that I passed on to the Royal Library, 2 mammals, 79 birds, some shells, botanical and mineralogical objects to a value of about 190 florins. Deserving special mention in this consignment are a rare sea eagle, a very large pelican, and a wonderful and precious <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argonauta,</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to W. Sonder, 13 May 1867.</p>
               </note> probably a new species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The total value of all the donations received from Dr Mueller could probably be estimated at about 1,200 florins.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">The files at the Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde include two undated and unsigned memos assessing the value of M’s donations through 1867.  It is not certain that either note was used in the preparation of the present letter, but they are included here for convenience.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>One is limited to the value of the ferns, and must be dated to after 20 December 1867, when M received his 'von':</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach genauer Rücksprache mit Dr. v. [...] dürften die 7 Riesenstämme der baumarigen Farne von Dicksonia antarctica u. Todea rivularis, welche Hr Dr. Ferd. v. M. in Melbourne Sr Maj d. K. für die Gewächshäuser der Wilhelma zum Geschenk gemacht hat, auf 1200 </seg>
                     <seg>៛ </seg>
                     <seg style="">anzuschlagen seyn. [The Kymer Riel symbol is used here and below to represent the currency symbol for Reichstaler]</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">[After a detailed discussion with Dr von [...] the 7 giant trunks of the tree-like ferns of </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Dicksonia antarctica</seg>
                     <seg style=""> and </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Todea rivularis</seg>
                     <seg style=""> that Dr Ferdinand von Mueller in Melbourne sent His Majesty the King as a gift for the glasshouses of the Wilhelma, should be estimated at 1200 </seg>
                     <seg>៛.]</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The other, headed 'Berechnung der Naturalien von F. v. Müller in Melbourne’ [Estimates of natural history objects from F. von Mueller in Melbourne], includes the value of a cash donation to estabish a travel grant for young naturalists that had not been received in Stuttgart by the date of this letter (see W. Sonder to F, Krauss, 28 July 1868 (in this edition as M68-07-28)) but that was anticipated (see above and annotation by Krauss on W. Sonder to F. Krauss, 12 November 1867 (in this edition as M67-11-12)). The heading and the second 1867 entry are in Krauss’s hand, the other entries are in a different, unidentified hand. The heading, at least, must have been written after 20 December 1867, when M received his ‘von’. Values are given as:</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1867. Schriften u. ethnolog. Gegenst. [Publications and ethnological articles] 80 </seg>
                     <seg>៛</seg>
                     <seg style=""> </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1867. Riesen Farn Stämme an die Wilhelma [Giant tree ferns for the Wilhelma]</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>6 Dicksonia antarctica à 200 </seg>
                     <seg>៛</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1 Todea rivularis à 300 </seg>
                     <seg>៛</seg>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1500 </seg>
                     <seg>៛</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Stipendium [Grant]<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3516 </seg>
                     <seg>៛</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An initial entry, in the same unidentified hand but without a valuation, has been deleted: </seg>'1860. Febr. [ZW...] 1590. Säugethiere' [1860. February [ZW...] 1590 mammals].</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Sonder has written at large on Dr F. Mueller's curriculum vitae in the second of his letters.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See W. Sonder to F. Krauss, 9 May 1867.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. Mueller was born in Rostock, learned pharmacy in Husum, studied medicine and natural sciences in Kiel, and emigrated to Australia 20 years ago, where in the beginning he tried his luck sometimes as a doctor, sometimes as a pharmacist, later was employed as Government Botanist in recognition of his scientific knowledge, as such travelled much and also took part in Gregory's expedition<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> from the east to the west coast of Australia, in Melbourne the creation of the botanic and zoological Gardens was entrusted to him, and after the foundation there of the University was appointed lecturer.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mueller is extremely active as Director of these very extensive Gardens, in addition is involved in all philanthropic enterprises, and in the literary world has gained such high esteem by the publication of many excellent papers and works, some of which he has already donated to the Royal library, that most scientific institutes have honoured him by electing him one of their members, as can be seen from the enclosed title page of the 4th volume of his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This title page, listing, in Latin, M's honours and memberships to that point, is attached to the letter: see <ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uiug.30112009958460;view=1up;seq=5"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">
                        <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0563c1; ">https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uiug.30112009958460;view=1up;seq=5</seg>
                     </ref>. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>While science holds him in high regard, the natural history museums in Copenhagen, Paris, Turin, Vienna, Hannover and Gotha thank him for his generous donations of natural history objects. In return, decorations have been bestowed on him by many governments, and one foreign Government has even assured him of the title of Baron if his endowment of a foundation and all his future natural history objects were given to them. But, as a German, Dr Mueller has rejected this offer.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now considering all these many distinctions, and all the above-mentioned donations to the value of 1,200 florins, and considering further that Dr Ferd. Mueller, barely 40 years old, will make a gift of many treasures in collection items to our institutes, and that his offer is a splendid one, I should like to ask the Royal Administration to arrange that Dr Ferd. Mueller be honoured by having the Knight's Cross of the Crown of Württemberg conferred on him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I ask that the 4 enclosed letters from Dr Sonder, which were not written to be communicated but to me personally in confidence, will please be returned to me.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr F. Krauss.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgart, 7 December 1867.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
