<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royal Administration! ¶  ¶ In a letter of 3 March that I received on 12 April, ¶  Dr Ferd. von Mueller in Melbourne has written to me aside from the warmest expressions of pleasure and gratitude for t...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand Krauss</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M68-06-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M68.06.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand Krauss</author>
               <title>Royal Administration! ¶  ¶ In a letter of 3 March that I received on 12 April, ¶  Dr Ferd. von Mueller in Melbourne has written to me aside from the warmest expressions of pleasure and gratitude for t...</title>
               <date when="1868-06-25">1868-06-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M68-06-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard von Schmidlin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Royal Administration! ¶  ¶ In a letter of 3 March that I received on 12 April, ¶  Dr Ferd. von Mueller in Melbourne has written to me aside from the warmest expressions of pleasure and gratitude for t...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M68.06.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Ferdinand Krauss to Eduard von Schmidlin</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An incomplete (last page missing) draft copy with much crossing out, insertions and corrections is also in the file.</p>
               </note>Königliche Direction!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. Ferd. v. Müller in Melbourne hat mir in einem Schreiben vom 3. März, das ich den 21. April erhielt, neben den wärmsten Ausdrücken der Freude u. Dankbarkeit für den ihm von Seiner Majestät gnädigst verliehenen Orden der Württemb. Krone Folgendes in Betreff des Reise Stipendiums geschrieben:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"Als <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Beginn</hi>
               </seg> meiner <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">thatsächlichen</hi>
               </seg> Dankbarkeit hoffe ich wird Ihre Regierung es nicht verschmähen, wenn ich nun gleich etwa £300 als ein zwar kleines Stipendium Kapital durch meinen theuren Freund Dr. Sonder übersende, bittend dass es der Regierung gefallen möge, die kleine Summe in Staatseigenthum anzulegen, damit aus den jährlich erwachsenden Zinsen ein in Tübingen studirender Mediciner, der sich für naturwissenschaftliche Reisen ausserhalb Europa gleichzeitig vorbereitete, mit unterstützt würde. Die Ausübung der Medicin macht es dem Reisenden möglich, als Schiffsarzt u. als Hospitirender mit viel geringeren Mitteln fremde Länder zu erreichen u. zu durchforschen, als es unter andern Verhältnissen möglich ist, u. dies veranlasst mich die Studien der Medicin für die Verwerthung des Stipendiums bindend zu machen. Sollte kein Bewerber zu irgend einer Zeit auftreten, so könnte der so erhöhte Ertrag des Stipendiums späteren Aspiranten zu Nutze kommen. Ich wünschte, dass Sie, verehrter Herr Professor, den Stipendium Zins demjenigen geben, den Sie am würdigsten halten, u. denke mir, dass Pietät u. Dankbarkeit demjenigen, der diesen kleinen Vortheil geniessen mag, veranlassen werden, einen Theil seines Sammelertrags aus fernen Landen dem Stuttgarter Museum zuzuwenden, was aber kaum gesetzliche Bedingung werden könnte. Ich habe mit dieser Post einen Wechsel von 360 Pf. St.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Pfund Sterling.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>auf 1 Monat Sicht an Herrn Dr. Sonder gesandt u. bitte Sie mit diesem vortrefflichen Manne zusammen diese kleine Angelegenheit so zu regeln, als Sie es beide für gut finden mögen. Dann gehe ich noch mit dem Gedanken um, etwas später ein anderes Stipendium ebenfalls bei Ihnen zu errichten, das dem zur Reise ausgebildten Arzte, der das erste Stipendium genoss, einige Hülfsgelder aus den erwachsenden Zinsen liefern sollte, um seine Forschungen zu erleichtern. Darüber mehr in späteren Briefen."</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Aus Gründen der Bescheidenheit habe ich geglaubt es abwarten zu sollen, bis von Seiten Dr. W. Sonder's in Hamburg mir die Anzeige gemacht werde, dass die von Dr. v. Müller bestimmte Summe angekommen sei u. in welcher Weise er diese Stipendien-Angelegenheit behandelt zu haben wünsche.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In dieser Erwartung kam inzwischen von Dr. F. v. Müller den 14. Juni ein zweiter Brief vom 24. April direct an mich an, in welchem er für das von den Beamten des K. Nat. Kabinets an ihn gerichtete Schreiben dankt u. dann folgendermassen fortfährt:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"Mein Dank sollte aber ein thatsächlicher seyn.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Antiquated spelling of 'sein'.</p>
               </note> So freut es mich denn, dass bereits vor zwei Monaten ein Stipendium Kapital von £300. — Herrn Dr. Sonder brieflich eingehändigt ist, das Ihnen übersandt werden wird u. hoffentlich wenn auch keine üppige doch bleibende Früchte Ihrer Anstalt tragen wird. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Recht bald</hi>
               </seg> nun will ich ein 2tes Stipendium gründen, das dem durch Studien vorbereiteten Arzte einige wenn auch geringe Hülfsmittel für aussereuropäische Reisen schaffen sollte. Ueber die Einzelheiten der Anordnungen bitte ich Sie mit dem vortefflichen Dr. Sonder zu berathen."</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Folge dieses zweiten Briefs habe ich am 23. Juni Dr. Sonder den das Stipendium betreffenden Inhalt der beiden Briefe mitgetheilt u. sehe nun einer baldigen Nachricht von ihm entgegen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. v. Müller hat aufs Neue Sendungen von Vögeln, Fischen in Weingeist u. von Schriften angekündigt.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrungsvoll,</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Stuttgart den 25. Juni 1868</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr. F. Krauss.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Royal Administration!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In a letter of 3 March that I received on 12 April,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to F. Krauss, 3 March 1868 (in this edition as 68-03-03a).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Dr Ferd. von Mueller in Melbourne has written to me aside from the warmest expressions of pleasure and gratitude for the Order of the Württemburg Crown graciously bestowed on him by His Majesty,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See A. von Egloffstein to M, 20 December 1867.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> the following in respect to the travel grant:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>“As a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">start</hi>
               </seg> of my gratitude <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">in actual fact</hi>
               </seg> I hope your Government will not disdain it, if I send immediately about £300 as a, though small, capital grant through my dear friend Dr Sonder with the request that it may please the Government to invest the small sum in Government bonds, so that from the annually accruing interest a medical student in Tübingen, who at the same time is preparing himself for scientific travels outside Europe, can receive some financial support. The practice of medicine makes it possible for the traveller to reach and explore foreign countries with far fewer means as a ship's doctor or a trainee than would be possible under ordinary conditions, and this is why I feel bound to make the study of medicine binding for the use of the foundation. Should no applicant come forward at a given time, the thus increased amount could benefit later candidates. I wish that you, esteemed Professor, will give the interest from the foundation to the person you consider most worthy, and I imagine that piety and gratitude will cause the person who enjoys this small advantage to turn over part of his collections from distant countries to the Stuttgart Museum, but this can hardly be made a contractual condition. I have sent with this mail a bill of exchange for £300 Sterling for 1 month at sight to Dr Sonder, and ask that you together with this excellent man will arrange this little matter n a way that both of you find fit and proper. I am further considering to establish, also with you, another foundation a little later on, that, from its accrued interest, will provide the doctor prepared for travelling who enjoyed the first grant with some financial support to assist in his researches. But more about this in later letters.”</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For reasons of discretion I have thought to wait until notification was given to me on the part of Dr Sonder in Hamburg that the sum determined by Dr von Mueller had arrived and in what manner he wished to have this grant matter handled.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meanwhile in this expectation a second letter of 24 April<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to F. Krauss, 24 April 1868 (in this edition as 68-04-24c).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> from Dr von Mueller directly to me arrived on 14 June, in which he thanked the officers of the Natural History Cabinet for the letter directed to him and then continued as follows:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>“But my gratitude is to be shown in deeds. I am therefore pleased that already 2 months ago, capital was handed over to Dr Sonder by letter for a foundation to the amount of £300 (approximately 2000 Reichsthaler), which will be transmitted to you and will, I hope, bear if not abundant then at least lasting fruit for your institute. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Quite soon</hi>
               </seg> now I shall institute a second foundation that should provide a few, even though sparse, resources for extra-European travel for the young doctor who has prepared himself by studies. I ask you to consult with the excellent Dr Sonder about the details of the rules.”</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In consequence of this second letter, on 23 June I have communicated the contents of both letters concerning the grant to Dr Sonder<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and now expect an early answer from him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr von Mueller has anounced a new consignments of birds, fishes in alcohol and publications. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgart 25 June 1868</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr F. Krauss.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
