<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ [...] I have now taken steps concerning the matter of our friend von Mueller, and largely on this account my reply to your letter was delayed. You are aware that Mr von Golther is no longer the Min...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Krauss</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M71-04-10-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M71.04.10</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Krauss</author>
               <title> ¶ [...] I have now taken steps concerning the matter of our friend von Mueller, and largely on this account my reply to your letter was delayed. You are aware that Mr von Golther is no longer the Min...</title>
               <date when="1871-04-10">1871-04-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M71-04-10-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Wilhelm Sonder</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ [...] I have now taken steps concerning the matter of our friend von Mueller, and largely on this account my reply to your letter was delayed. You are aware that Mr von Golther is no longer the Min...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M71.04.10</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Ferdinand von Krauss to Wilhelm Sonder</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. MS is a handwritten and apparently only partial copy in an unknown hand, annotated at the top by Krauss '<seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Abschrift</hi>
                     </seg> | Brief an Sonder v. 10. April 71' [<seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>
                     </seg> | Letter to Sonder of 10 April 1871].</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...] Was nun die Angelegenheit mit unserem Freund von Müller anbelangt, so habe ich nun noch weitere Schritte gethan, wodurch hauptsächlich die Beantwortung Ihres Briefes verzögert wurde. Sie wissen, dass H. v. Golther nicht mehr Cultusminister ist, sondern H. v. Gessler der wohl mit den Schenkungen Müllers vertraut gemacht worden ist, aber sie nicht miterlebt hat wie v. Golther. Der Referentist aber noch derselbe und interessirt sich immer noch gleich warm für M. wie früher. Durch ihn wurde nach vorhergegangener Berathung mit mir der Müller'sche Wunsch dem Minister vorgetragen unter Mittheilung Ihres Briefes. Obgleich die Erhebung in den Freiherrnstand bei uns zu den grossen Seltenheiten gehört und viele Schwierigkeiten darbietet, so ist der Minister geneigt von seiner Seite zu thun, was er kann. Doch hängt es von dem Beschluss des ganzen Ministerraths und vor Allem von dem Willen des Königs ab. — Unter den Schwierigkeiten will ich beiläufig nur die anführen, dass für das Erheben in Freiherrnstand nach einen alten Gesetz die Entrichtung von 1200 fl. Sporteln von Seiten des Geadelten verbunden ist, die man in diesem Falle doch erlassen sollte, worüber aber keine Garantie gegeben werden konnte. Wie ich Ihnen schon früher andeutete, würde es die Sache erleichtern, wenn unser Freund durch eine weitere bedeutende Stiftung und namentlich durch eine Schenkung einer grossen Sammlung von Naturalien oder grossen und seltenen Thieren &amp;c &amp;c. auf Einmal einen Eclat machen würde, worüber man öffentlich einigen Lärm machen könnte. Dies ist auch Ansicht des Referenten. — Hiezu kämen dann die bisherigen Schenkungen und insbesondere die erste Stiftung, die schwer ins Gewicht fiele. — Ich würde gewiss nicht verfehlen, den Werth der bisher geschenkten Naturalien hervorzuheben, wobei ich freilich Ihnen (unter uns) nicht verschweigen darf, jedoch ohne undankbar zu sein zu wollen, dass wir von unseren Desideraten gerade die wichtigeren und werthvolleren Gegenstände noch nicht erhalten haben. Ich darf Sie deshalb nur daran erinnern, was ich über die verschiedenen Sendungen an Sie berichtete. Von der Bereitwilligkeit zum Gelingen dürfen Sie von meiner Seite überzeugt sein, aber Sie dürfen ja nicht glauben, wie Sie schreiben, dass es von mir abhänge. — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich werde auch als Vorbild den Baron von Ludwig anführen, der allerdings eine immense Schenkung (ca 30,000 fl. gemacht hat.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bei Allem ist es mir aber unbegreiflich, warum dadurch die wankende Stellung unseres Freundes in einer engl. Colonie wieder befestigt werden kann, da doch dieses Krämervolk auf Adel und Orden keinen Werth legt und dazu solche Leute, wie ich an Ludwig oft erlebte, verhöhnt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">[...]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[...] I have now taken steps concerning the matter of our friend von Mueller, and largely on this account my reply to your letter was delayed. You are aware that Mr von Golther is no longer the Minister for Culture, it is now Mr von Gessler<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Theodor von Gessler succeeded Ludwig von Golther as Württemberg's Minister for Church and School Affairs on 3 May 1870.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> who, though he has been acquainted with Mueller's donations, has not personally experienced them like von Golther. But the Secretary<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Gustav von Silcher.</p>
               </note> is still the same, and is still as warmly interested in M as before. He was the one who, after first consulting me, presented Mueller's wish to the Minister, together with your letter. Although an elevation to the rank of Baron<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">'Freiherr', a rank carrying hereditary nobility, whereas the 1867 Knight's Cross of the Order of the Crown bestowed on M by the King of Württemberg gave personal nobility.</p>
               </note> is a great rarity here and is connected with many difficulties, the Minister is inclined to do everything he can on his part. But it depends on a resolution by the whole Ministerial Council and especially on the good will of the King. Among the difficulties I just want to mention is that to be elevated to the rank of Baron requires the payment by the person so raised of a fee of 1,200 fl.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Gulden.</p>
               </note> according to an old law. While in this case it ought to be dispensed with, no guarantee could be given in this regard. As I have previously indicated to you already, the matter would be made easier if our friend could make a big impression by a further significant endowment<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">To the Mueller Foundation.</p>
               </note> and particularly by the donation of a large collection of natural history objects or of large and rare animals &amp;c. &amp;c. about which one could make a lot of noise in public. That is also the opinion of the Secretary. To this would then be added the previous donations and in particular the endowment of the first foundation, which would weigh heavily in the balance. I would certainly not fail to emphasise the value of the natural history objects donated so far, although I cannot hide from you (in confidence between us) that, without meaning to be ungrateful, we have not yet received from our list of desiderata the most important and more valuable objects. In this respect I also may remind you of what I reported to you regarding the various consignments.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Krauss regularly complained about poor packaging resulting in damaged specimens, poor or inadequate collections, too many duplicates of objects sent previously, inadequate labelling of specimens, and so on.</p>
               </note> You can be assured of my willingness to have the matter succeed, but you must not think, as you write, that it depends on me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall also cite Baron von Ludwig as a precedent,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Baron Karl von Ludwig, a dealer in natural history objects in Capetown, South Africa, who was raised to the nobility for supplying the Natural History Museum in Stuttgart with large numbers of specimens, especially of the large African animals.</p>
               </note> although he made an immense donation (about 30,000 fl.).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But when all is said and done, I cannot comprehend how the shaky situation of our friend could be consolidated by this in an English colony, as these small-minded, mercenary people attach no value to nobility or Orders, but rather make fun of such people, as I saw happen frequently to Ludwig.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[...]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
