<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Stuttgart 4 January 1872 ¶ To the Royal Ministry for Foreign Affairs. ¶ Report of Herald of Arms Stälin ¶ Reference: Baron von Mueller’s arms. ¶ Royal Ministry...</title>
            <author>Christoph Friedrich von Stälin</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M72-01-04-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>E 56 Bü. 28, Hauptstaatsarchiv, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M72.01.04</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Christoph Friedrich von Stälin</author>
               <title>Stuttgart 4 January 1872 ¶ To the Royal Ministry for Foreign Affairs. ¶ Report of Herald of Arms Stälin ¶ Reference: Baron von Mueller’s arms. ¶ Royal Ministry...</title>
               <date when="1872-01-04">1872-01-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M72-01-04-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Johann von Wächter</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Stuttgart 4 January 1872 ¶ To the Royal Ministry for Foreign Affairs. ¶ Report of Herald of Arms Stälin ¶ Reference: Baron von Mueller’s arms. ¶ Royal Ministry...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">M72.01.04</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">From Christoph Friedrich von Stälin to Johann von Wächter</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">E 56 Bü. 28, Hauptstaatsarchiv, Stuttgart.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Christoph Friedrich von Stälin was Württemberg’s Royal Herald of Arms, Johann von Wächter the Minister for Foreign Affairs. MS annotation: 'pr. 5. Janr: 1872' [presented 5 January 1872].</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Attached documents: </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>a) M's sketch for his choice of his coat of arms, annotated by him on the reverse 'Vielleicht ist eine einfach ovale Schildform vorzuziehen. <seg style="">Das Coronet môchte vielleicht von den Blättern nicht berührt werden. Die Zeige in der Mitte stellen den Eucalyptus Globulus dar, eine Baumart, welche durch mich so segensreich für die Beholzung vieler Wüstenländer nicht nur Australiens sondern auch anderer Theile der Erde geworden ist.' </seg>[Perhaps a simple oval shape would be preferrable for the shield. The coronet should perhaps not be touched by the leaves. The branches in the centre depict <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus globulus</seg>, a species of tree which through me became so beneficial for the afforestation of many desert areas not only in Australia, but in many parts of the earth.] </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>b) The coat of arms proposed by Stälin and subsequently accepted by M. It is annotated 'Der Tournierhelm soll nach Äusserung des Herrn Wappencensors <seg style="font-style: italic; ">en face</seg> ausgeführt werden. <seg style="">Im Diplom wurde die Krone auf dem Skizzenbild mit 7 Perlen angebracht.' </seg>[The tournament helmet, according to remarks by the Herald of Arms, is to be executed facing forwards. In the certificate the crown on the sketch has 7 pearls attached to it.]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Regarding the designs for the coat of arms, see M to J. von Wächter, 8 October 1871 (in this edition and 71-10-08a), <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and Wächter to M, 8 January 1872.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">Stuttgart den 4. </seg>Jan. 1872.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">An das K. Ministerium der auswärtigen Angelegenheiten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Bericht des Wappencensors Stälin</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">betr: Das Freiherrlich von Müller'sche Wappen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Königlichem Ministerium</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>beehre ich mich auf den Hohen Erlass vom 18. Dec. 1871 zu berichten, dass die im Rückanschluss folgende Zeichnung des Freiherrn von Müller in Melbourne kein Wappen ist. Da eine weitere Vernehmung des Freiherrn unthunlich zu sein schein, so dürfte nichts übrig bleiben, als in ein, ihm neu zu verleihendes Wappen von seinem Entwurfe thunlichst viel aufzunehmen. Das Wappen wird dadurch freilich sehr einfach, was, da die einfachen Wappen die ältesten sind, bei Neuadelichen allerdings selten vorkommt; allein es ist von der andern Seite doch bedenklich, ohne Vorwissen des Betheiligten einen ganz neuen Wappenschild zu schaffen. Was die Form des Schildes betrifft, so könnte der gewöhnliche französische in den Freiherrnbrief gemalt werden. Da diese Form in der Blasonirung nicht angegeben wird, so steht es dem Empfänger frei, ob er für sich eine ovale (italienische) oder sonstige Form wählen will.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unmassgeblich erlaube ich mir nun die Aufreissung eines Wappens, wie in der Anlage beifolgt, vorzuschlagen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dem Wappenmaler dürfte zu bemerken sein, dass die Eucalyptus Globulus gräulich grüne Blätter habe und gelblich weiss blühe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine gut colorirte Abbildung bedaure ich nicht aufweisen zu können und kann nicht bestimmt versichern, ob das Exemplar, welches in der K. Wilhelma sein soll, jetzt in Blüthe steht, wiewohl die Blüthezeit des Baumes in den Jahresanfang fällt. In Ermanglung einer sichern Vorlage könnten die Farben schwach angedeutet und der Freiherr darauf aufmerksam gemacht werden, dass er solche im Wappenbrief naturgetreu ausmalen lassen möchte. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Erhaltene Decorationen seinem Wappen anzuhängen oder solches mit denselben zu umgeben, steht natürlich in jedermanns Willkür. Da solche jedoch rein persönlicher Natur sind, so gehören sie nicht in einen vererblichen Wappenbrief.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ehrerbietig</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Stälin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">In goldenem Felde zwei aufrechte unten verschlungene Zweige der Eucalyptus Globulus. Auf dem, mit der Freiherrnkrone gezierten Schilde hängt ein offener gegitterter goldgekrönter Turnierhelm, darauf drei Straussfedern, die mittlere golden, die äussere schwarz. Helmdecken aussen schwarz, innen golden. Unter dem Schilde steht auf einem fliegenden rothen Bande mit goldenen Buchstaben der Wahlspruch:</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">VIRTUTE INGENIOQUE VALEMUS.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgart 4 January 1872</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To the Royal Ministry for Foreign Affairs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Report of Herald of Arms Stälin</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Reference: Baron von Mueller’s arms.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Royal Ministry</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honour to report on the high decree of 18 December 1871 that the sketch by Baron von Mueller in the enclosure is not a coat of arms. As a further questioning of the Baron seems to be impractible, nothing remains but to undertake from his design a new coat of arms to be bestowed on him as quickly as possible. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Because of this the coat of arms will of course be very simple, which, as the simple arms are the oldest, certainly seldom occurs among the newly enobled. But it is from the other side questionable to create a quite new coat of arms without previous knowledge of the <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>person involved. Concerning the shape of the shield, the usual French one can be painted in the baronial charter. As this shape is not cited in the emblazonry, the recipient is free to choose an oval (Italian) or other shape for himself.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unauthoritively I permit myself to suggest now the drawing of a coat of arms as in the sketch enclosed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It may be remarked to the heraldic painter that the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus globulus</seg> has greyish-green leaves and yellowish-white flowers.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I regret not being able to show a well coloured illustration and cannot definitely afirm whether the specimen that is said to be in the Royal Wilhelma<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Botanical garden in Stuttgart.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is now in flower, although the blossom time of the tree falls at the beginning of the year. For want of a reliable model the colours could be indicated faintly and the Baron could be made aware that he might have them painted true to nature in the charter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Attaching decorations received to his coat of arms or surrounding it with them is of course at everyone’s discretion. However, as such are purely of a personal nature, they do not belong in a hereditary charter of arms.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Stälin</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In a golden field two upright twigs of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus globulus </seg>interlaced below. On the shield decorated with the baronial crown hangs an open barred gold-crowned jousting <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>helmet, on it three ostrich feathers, the middle one gold, the outer black. Helmet cover black exterior, gold interior. Under the shield is the motto on a flowing red band with gold letters:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Virtute ingenioque valemus.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
