<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg 8 March [18]75 ¶ Dear Friend! ¶  ¶ I still owe you an answer to your letter of 15 January. I have endeavored in vain to ascertain who sent the trunk to you from here. I know nothing of it! As ...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M75-03-08-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M75.03.08</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg 8 March [18]75 ¶ Dear Friend! ¶  ¶ I still owe you an answer to your letter of 15 January. I have endeavored in vain to ascertain who sent the trunk to you from here. I know nothing of it! As ...</title>
               <date when="1875-03-08">1875-03-08</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M75-03-08-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg 8 March [18]75 ¶ Dear Friend! ¶  ¶ I still owe you an answer to your letter of 15 January. I have endeavored in vain to ascertain who sent the trunk to you from here. I know nothing of it! As ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M75.03.08</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand von Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotated by Krauss 'R. 25. März' [Replied 25 March].</p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 8 März 75</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin Ihnen noch immer eine Antwort auf Ihren Brief vom 15t Januar schuldig. Ich habe mich vergebens bemüht zu erfahren, wer Ihnen von hier den Stamm geschickt hat, ich weiss von nichts! Da auch in unsres Barons Briefen keine Silbe davon vorkam, so habe ich bei ihm angefragt, worauf natürlich noch keine Antwort hier sein kann.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von dem sauberen Herrn Baumann und seiner Kiste fehlt ebenfalls jede Nachricht. Ob Baumann wieder zurückgereist ist oder aber noch in Süddeutschland oder der Schweiz sich aufhält, darüber kann ich keine Auskunft erlangen, da selbst seine hiesigen Verwandten nichts darüber zu wissen scheinen. Ich habe unserm Dr Müller über die Angelegenheit ausführlich berichtet, er möge das Nöthige beordern um wenigstens die Kiste wieder zu erlangen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">letzte</hi>
               </seg> Kiste glücklich angelangt ist, wissen Sie aus meinen beiden Zusendungen. Ihre grössere Kiste ist durch Nachlässigkeit, sowohl meines Hausknechtes als auch des Spediteurs um 8 oder 14 Tage später befördert als ich beordert hatte, ich denke sie wird bei Ankunft dieses Briefes bereits in Ihren Händen sein. Es wäre möglich, dass in Ihrer Kiste, die nicht geöffnet ist, ein Paket mit Algen für mich sich befinde. In der Aufzählung des Inhalts der grossen Kiste, welche ausser Ihren Gegenständen noch zehn andere Pakete umfasst, war mein Paket mitaufgeführt, ich habe es aber nicht vorgefunden. Sollte es Ihrer Sendung beigeschlossen sein, so bitte ich es mir pr Post zuzusenden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben wohl gehört, dass hier von einem Reisenden Godefroys eine kleine Anzahl des neuen Fisches Ceratodus Forsteri angekommen ist, als ich davon erfuhr, waren sie bereits vergriffen. Unser Museum hat das grösste u schönste Exemplar erhalten, wir haben aber runde 200 Thaler dafür zahlen müssen. Allerdings hat Herr G. unsern Schmerz darin etwas gemildert, dass er uns einen schönen neuen Vogel dazu geschenkt hat, der auch seine 100 Thal. werth sein soll. Die frühere Reisende Frau Dietrich sagt mir gestern, dass sie ohne Zweifel im Mai wieder nach Australien reisen werde, namentlich um Ceratodus zu sammeln. Da sie jetzt die Lokalität genau kennt, wird sie schon eine gute Erndte halten. Ausserdem schickt G. im ersten Frühjahr auch einen Reisenden nach Neuguinea.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unser Baron Müller ist wahrscheinlich in diesem Augenblick auf der Reise, die er angetreten hat, um der grossen Hitze auszuweichen. Im Allgemeinen ist sein Befinden jetzt besser, er scheint die grosse Aufregung glücklich überwunden zu haben.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit bestem Grusse</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg 8 March [18]75</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Friend!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I still owe you an answer to your letter of 15 January. I have endeavored in vain to ascertain who sent the trunk to you from here. I know nothing of it! As not a syllable about it was to be found in our Baron's letter, either, I have asked him, to which of course no answer can be here yet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Any news of the smart Mr Baumann and his crate is likewise lacking.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See W. Sonder to F. von Krauss, 20 November 1874 (Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart).</p>
               </note> I can obtain no information about whether Baumann has come back again or is still staying in South Germany or Switzerland, because even his relatives here seem to know nothing about it. I have reported in full to our Dr Mueller about it, so that he could order what needs to be done at least to get the crate back again.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You know from both of my consignments that the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">last</hi>
               </seg> crate arrived safely. Through the negligence of my servant as well as the forwarding agent, your larger crate was dispatched 8 or 14 days later than I had ordered. I think it will be already in your hands by the time this letter arrives. It's possible that in your crate that was not opened, there is a packet of algae for me. In the account of the contents of the large crate which, besides your objects, includes ten other parcels, my parcel was specified, but I have not found it. Should it be enclosed in your consignment, I ask you to send it to me by post.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have probably heard that a small number of the new fish, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ceratodus forsteri</seg>, arrived here from a traveller of Godefroy's. When I learned of it, they were already sold. Our museum has received the largest and finest specimen, but we had to pay a good 200 Thalers for it. Admittedly Mr G. soothed the pain somewhat by presenting a beautiful new bird to us that is said to be worth his 100 Thalers. The previous traveller Frau Dietrich said to me yesterday that she would no doubt travel to Australia again in May, especially to collect <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ceratodus</seg>. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Because she now knows the locality exactly, she will get a good harvest. In addition G. is also sending a traveller to New Guinea next spring.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Our Baron Mueller is probably on a journey at this moment that he set out on to avoid the great heat.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M went to Tasmania for about 2 weeks from 27 January to 14 February 1875.</p>
               </note> In general his state of health is better now. He seems to have overcome the great commotion safely.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With best greetings</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
