<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dear Friend, ¶ As you will ascertain from the enclosure, some crates from Melbourne for you are presently under way again. According to my inquiry at our present forwarding agent in London, Watson &amp; S...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M80-05-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M80.05.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Dear Friend, ¶ As you will ascertain from the enclosure, some crates from Melbourne for you are presently under way again. According to my inquiry at our present forwarding agent in London, Watson &amp; S...</title>
               <date when="1880-05">1880-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/Selected Mentions letters/M80-05-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>table</term>
               <term>note</term>
               <term>multi-row cell</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Dear Friend, ¶ As you will ascertain from the enclosure, some crates from Melbourne for you are presently under way again. According to my inquiry at our present forwarding agent in London, Watson &amp; S...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">M80.05.00</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">From Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand von Krauss</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation: 'Rep. d. 29. <seg style="">Mai gedankt, u Empfang der 3 Kisten v. 2. </seg>Juli oder 6. Juli angezeigt'. [Replied 29 May, thanked, and receipt of 3 crates acknowledged from 2 July or 6 July]. The letter is dated to May 1880 on the basis of this annotation and a letter to Krauss from the agents Watson &amp; Scull dated 15 Jun 1880 saying that they had forwarded to Sonder, for forwarding on to him, the material described in the enclosure that accompanied the present letter.</p>
               </note>Lieber Freund,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie Sie aus der Beilage ersehen, sind gegenwärtig wieder einige Kisten aus Melbourne für Sie unterwegs. Nach meiner Anfrage bei unseren jetzigen Spediteuren in London, Watson &amp; Scull sollte das Schiff Shannon im Anfange dieses Monats in London eintreffen, bis zu diesem Augenblick ist aber noch keine Anzeige darüber hier eingetroffen. Mit Segelschiffbeförderung ist auf einige Wochen niemals eine Vorbestimmung zu treffen. Ich würde mit dieser Anzeige auch wohl noch etwas gewartet haben, wenn ich nicht neulich von unserm Baron den Auftrag erhalten hätte, Ihnen die 30 Mk, welche Sie für die unglücklichen letzten Kisten haben bezahlen müssen, zurückzusenden. Er ist selbst unglücklich über die Beschädigung der werthvollen Gegenstände und will nicht, dass Sie nun noch Unkosten daran haben sollen. Sonderbar ist es mir immer, dass an der grossen Kiste, die ich in dem trocknen Zimmer des Spediteurs von allen Seiten besichtigt habe, keine Spur von Nässe oder sonstiger Beschädigung zu bemerken war. Da ich die eine der Kisten öffnen musste, um das für mich bestimmte herauszunehmen u. in dieser Kiste, die allerdings in London geöffnet war, was nicht geschehen soll, keine Beschädigung durch Wasser bemerkte, so konnte ich nicht vermuthen, dass die Ihrige gelitten haben dürfte, sonst hätte ich sie in meiner Gegenwart umpacken lassen. Ihre Kisten gehen sonst immer direct weiter, sie bleiben höchstens 1 oder 2 Tage beim Spediteur stehen, da ich zu weit von der Stadt entfernt wohne, um sie ins Haus nehmen zu können. Wir wollen wünschen, dass so etwas nicht wieder passirt; der neue Spediteur hat versprochen, auch dafür sorgen zu wollen, dass keine Kiste wieder geöffnet werde. Auf dem Transport von London bis Hamburg kann in den grossen Dampfschiffen keine Beschädigung durch Wasser stattfinden, ohne dass man sofort hier solches bemerken könnte. So wie die Kisten hier ankommen, sollen sie ohne Aufenthalt weitergehen und zwar frachtfrei bis zu Ihnen. Es scheint Ihnen unbekannt zu sein, wie ich aus Ihrer Aeusserung bemerke, dass die Eisenbahnen für naturhistorische Gegenstände einen nicht unbedeutenden Aufschlag entnehmen. Mit des Barons Absicht, Europa einen Besuch zu machen, scheint es diesmal wieder nichts zu werden, wenigstens erwähnt er in seinem neulichen Briefe nichts mehr davon. Ich hatte mich wirklich schon darauf gefreut, ihn in diesem Sommer hier zu sehen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was die Sache mit dem Schenken an das hiesige Museum anbetrifft, so bin ich ganz unschuldig daran. Im vorigen Jahre äusserte der Baron in einem Briefe, es könnten von den zahlreichen Doubletten </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">vielleicht</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> einige an das Hamburg. Museum gelangen. In einem der vorhergehenden Briefe sprach er von dem Rostocker Museum. Ich gebe auf solche Aeusserungen, die unserm Freunde in seiner Gutmüthigkeit oft entfallen, nichts. Da ich ihn </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">niemals</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> aufgefordert habe, dem hiesigen Museum etwas zu schenken, so kann ich mir seine Aeusserung nur damit erklären, dass M. vielleicht geglaubt hat, etwas hierher schenken zu müssen, weil er Mitglied des Hamburg. naturwiss. Vereins ist, und als solcher immer regelmässig die Schriften dieses Vereins erhält. Obgleich ich Mitglied der Museums-Commission bin, und oft den Wunsch gehört habe, es möchten unseren Sammlungen doch auch einmal austral. Sendungen zukommen, so gehen solche Aeusserungen bei mir doch stets in das eine Ohr hinein und aus dem anderen wieder heraus. Ich habe vor ungefähr 10 bis 12 Jahren einmal von Herrn Groener ein dutzend bunter Papageien u. von Dr. Müller einige andere kleine Bälge aus Australien erhalten, die ich zu einer Vogelglocke ausstopfen lassen wollte. Letzteres ist unterblieben, die Vögel waren beim öfteren Wechsel der Wohnungen verpackt u. in Vergessenheit gerathen. Als sie im vorigen Jahr wieder zum Vorschein kamen, habe ich einen Theil derselben an unser Museum geschenkt, die übrigen liegen noch bei mir. Sie können sich darauf verlassen, dass ich niemals unsern Baron überreden werde, zoolog. Gegenstände an ein anderes Museum als das Stuttgarter zu senden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was das Malheur mit den Algen anbetrifft, so werden Sie bereits von Herrn Dr. von Zeller gehört haben, dass ich gar keinen Werth darauf lege. Ich habe schon oft neuseeländische Algen erhalten und interessire mich weniger für diese als für neuholländische. Ich habe ja auch eine hinreichende Quantität davon erhalten und nichts darunter gefunden, das ich nicht schon erhielt. Einen diese Algen betreffenden Brief schreibe ich heute noch an Herrn v. Zeller.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin recht gespannt auf die neueren Nachrichten aus Australien, es ist ein neues Ministerium gewählt, das vielleicht günstigere Blicke auf unseren Baron richtet.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bei diesem schönen Frühlingswetter befindet sich Alles wohl, wenigstens hier im Norden. Möge dasselbe bei Ihnen und den Ihrigen in vollem Maasse der Fall sein.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit bestem Grusse</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Die Geldkarte geht mit diesem Briefe ab</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As you will ascertain from the enclosure, some crates from Melbourne for you are presently under way again. According to my inquiry at our present forwarding agent in London, Watson &amp; Scull, the ship </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Shannon</seg>
               <seg style=""> should arrive in London at the beginning of this month, but up to this moment no information about it has arrived here as yet.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">Krauss had been told of the shipment in M to F. von Krauss, 16 February 1880, and that Sonder would arrange the shipment from London. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Shannon</seg> cleared out of Melbourne on 11 February and arrived in London on 2 June (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 12 February 1880, p. 2 and 4 June 1880, p. 5).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Making an arrangement beforehand with dispatch by sailing ship is never of a few weeks. I would probably have waited somewhat with this information, if I had not recently received the instruction from our Baron to return to you the 30 Marks that you had to pay for the unfortunate last crate. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>He is unhappy himself about the damage to the valuable items and does not intend that you now should still have expenses about it. It is always strange to me that no trace of damp or other damage was to be seen on the large crate, which I had examined on all sides in the dry room of the forwarding agent.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">Water damage was reported In F. von Krauss to M, 13 December 1879.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Because I had to open one of the crates to take out what was destined for me, and in this crate, which by the way was opened in London, which should not happen, no damage by water was noticed, I could not suspect that yours might have suffered. Otherwise I would have had it unpacked in my presence. Your crates otherwise always go on directly, they remain at most 1 or 2 days at the forwarding agent's, because I live too far from the city to be able to take them into the house. We shall wish that such a thing doesn't occur again. The new forwarding agent has promised to see that no crate is opened again. No damage by water can take place in the large steam ships on the transport from London to Hamburg without someone here noticing it immediately. As soon as the crates arrive here, they will be forwarded without delay and indeed freight-free to you. It seems to be unknown to you as I see from your remark that the railways take off a not insignificant impost for natural history specimens. The Baron's intention to make a visit to Europe seems to have come to nothing again this time, at least he does not mention anything more about it in his recent letter. I really had looked forward to seeing him here this summer.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Concerning the matter of the gifts to the local museum, I am completely innocent. Last year, the Baron remarked in a letter that </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> some of the numerous duplicates could come to the Hamburg Museum. In one of the previous letters he spoke of the Rostock Museum. I pay no heed to such remarks, which often slip out from our friend in his kindliness. As I have </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">never</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> asked him to present anything to the museum here, I can only explain his remark by M's perhaps believing he had to present something here, because he is a member of the Hamburg natural history society and as such always receives the publications of this society regularly. Although I am a member of the Museum Commission, and often have heard the wish that Australian consignments might reach our collections too, such remarks always go in one ear and out the other with me. About 10 to 12 years ago I once received a dozen bright parrots from Mr Groener and some other small skins from Australia from Dr Mueller, which I wanted to have stuffed at a bird[…]. The latter was left undone, the birds were packed up in the frequent changes of houses and sank into oblivion. When they came to light again last year, I gave a part of them to our museum, the remainder are still with me. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>You may rest assured that I shall never urge our Baron to send zoological items to a museum other than the Stuttgart one.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will have already heard from Dr von Zeller concerning the misfortune with the algae that I place no value at all on it. I have often received New Zealand algae and I am less interested in these than in New Holland algae. You know I have received a sufficient quantity of them and found nothing among them that I have not received already. I shall write a letter to Mr von Zeller today concerning these algae.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am most anxious about the new information from Australia. A new Ministry has been elected that perhaps will fix a more favourable glance on our Baron.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Everyone is well at least here in the North with this beautiful spring weather. May the same be the case in full measure with you and yours.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With best greetings</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The money card goes off with this letter.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Enclosure with letter<seg style="font-weight: bold; ">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Melbourne 12 February 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Pr "<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Shannon</hi>
               </seg>"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">3 cases 1/3</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">for <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Stuttgard</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">D. K. 1 <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one case containing</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Stuttgard</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <table n="Table1">
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">One large pair of grey Kangooroh</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; "
                        rows="3">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 36pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">}</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; "
                        rows="3">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">from Victoria</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">One blue Wallaby </p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">One large black Eagle</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">One pair of Nestors. New Zealand</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">One parcel of […]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">No 2 <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one case containing</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Collection of Native Weapons from Albany West Australia list attached</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Birds nests from Victoria Could not get the names yet.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">No 3<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one box containing</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">About 60 reptiles etc. from Nicoll Bay West Australia</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
