<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Museum ¶ 1/8/73. ¶ To the honorable the Chief Secretary ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department ¶ i.e. the Chief Secretary's Department, ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-08-01a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>D73/9915, unit 669, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.08.01a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Museum ¶ 1/8/73. ¶ To the honorable the Chief Secretary ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department ¶ i.e. the Chief Secretary's Department, ...</title>
               <date when="1873-08-01">1873-08-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-08-01a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Francis</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Museum ¶ 1/8/73. ¶ To the honorable the Chief Secretary ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department ¶ i.e. the Chief Secretary's Department, ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">73.08.01a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Francis</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">D73/9915, unit 669, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot. Museum</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">1/8/73.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">To the honorable the Chief Secretary</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. the Chief Secretary's Department, of which the Government Botanist's Department was a constituent part.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the byefollowing memorandum from the Lands-Office and the replies thereto.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. A. Wallis to M, 31 July 1873. M evidently also sought details and included G. Luehmann to M,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1 August 1873 (in this edition as 73-08-01c), an account of Bacchus's visits.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The bot. Museum, ever since it has been founded by me in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1858<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The estimates of 1859 expenditure presented to Parliament in October 1858 for the Government Botanist included £1,000 for the erection of a museum and lecture room (see Victoria, Legislative Assembly (1858)<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Estimates of the revenue and expenditure of the Government of Victoria for the year 1859</seg>, Melbourne, pp. 32, 60). In M to J. O'Shanassy, 24 October 1858, M wrote that 'The intended erection of a larger building in the reserve… [would] give the fullest access to his extensive and carefully examined botanical collections, which he desires… to transfer permanently to this department as a nucleus of a State collection.' The tender for the erection was placed in November 1859, (T. Balmain to M, 22 November 1859). It was furnished and occupied by the end of the year, and the collection of Victorian plants M had placed at the public library were added in April (M to A Tulk, 6 April 1861).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>has been open from 8 a.m. til 5 p.m. to the public, and on no occasion has been access thereto denied.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>on no … denied is underlined in pencil.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>If the complaint refers to the want of access at this moment to the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Australian Grasses</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and allied plants, then I must point out, that they are and will be for some months under<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">final arrangement, analysis and description</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for the seventh volume of the Australian Flora, (all the collections formed by me since 1840 being included) and that until this is completed any disturbance among this part of the collection would be mischievous or retard the research. So it would have been with the Orchideae a few month<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>ago. In fairness I should add, that I have named for Mr Bacchus, who always showed himself most gentlemanly to me,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        </seg>For an example of public acknowledgement, see text of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>an<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>address by William Bacchus to the Ballarat Farmers'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Club,10 February 1872, where he wrote 'I have given the names by which I have been in the habit of distinguishing them before I obtained the botanical names from Baron yon Muller, to whom I take this opportunity of. expressing my thanks for the valuable information he has given me' (Bacchus (1872)).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on repeated<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>occasions numerous specimens of native grasses and other plants, which he forwarded to me from Ballarat.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 8 August 1873 A. Wallis, Secretary of Agriculture, minuted: 'From the Govt Botanist's letter it would appear that at such times as any section of the museum plants is under examination by him, no other person can gain access thereto, whether for the purpose of study or otherwise. This, in my humble opinion, is a most unsatisfactory state of things, and if enforced on the present occasion will be attended by serious loss to a large section of the public. Mr Bacchus, who for upwards of 30 years has studied our native grasses both by practical observation in the field and scientifically, has kindly consented to contribute to the next volume of the transactions of the Dept of Agriculture a comprehensive paper on our native pastures, giving the scientific and common names of each grass and the results of his observation and experience as to their relative feeding capabilities, their relative powers of resisting drought, the season of the year at which they produce the most food, and other information of a practical and highly useful nature. Mr Bacchus however, with a view to make his paper more complete, is anxious to compare some of his specimens with those contained in the national Herbarium, to make sure that he has them correctly named. Considering then that no account of our native grasses has yet been published, and that a paper containing practical information such as Mr Bacchus alone in this colony can furnish would be of inestimable service to persons engaged in Agricl. pursuits throughout the colony, I am of opinion that the Govt Botanist, since he cannot possibly require all the Grasses for study at one and the same time, should be requested to render Mr Bacchus every assistance in the accomplishment of his useful work.' Wallis forwarded this minute to the Chief Secretary 'by direction of The Honble the Minister of Lands and Agriculture'. The Minister, J. Casey, added a comment of his own: 'In allowing the Govt Botanist the use of the Herbarium it was<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>not<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>intended nor is it reasonable that he should prevent its being inspected when necessary. It is admitted Mr Bacchus was denied access to the plants.' On 12 August 1873 the Chief Secretary, James Francis, instructed: 'The Government Botanist will give Mr Bacchus access to these Grasses or plants &amp; arrange generally for the courteous interchange of information'.</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 16 August 1873,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>M replied by<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>a further<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>minute<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on the file: 'I<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>have anticipated the wish, expressed by the hon. the Chief Secretary, in affording on all occasions the fullest possible information in all branches of my Department, and shall not fail to do so also in future. To render this information in the Museum still more extensive, I placed even my own voluminous collections there, formed since the last 34 years. Mr Bacchus, as stated already by me,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">got</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">all his grasses</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">and other pasture plants</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">named by me already</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">long</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">ago</hi>
                        </seg>, like I have named such for other similarly observant colonists, since many years; moreover he was even promised an early supply of dried specimens, and got besides on many occasions previously living grasses and other industrial plants for testculture at his place. This and other official attention, experienced from me, he has acknowledged with gratitude on various public occasions.'</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the Victorian Legislative Assembly on 23 October,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>J. J. Casey, then Minister of Agriculture, said that the 'refusal to comply with the application of Mr Bacchus, president of the Ballarat Farmers' Club, for certain plants, made to the curator of the Botanical Gardens, had been contrary to his instructions and much to his regret' (<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(Melbourne), 24 October 1873, p. 3). Since M was no longer associated with the Gardens, this comment implies that Bacchus had (also?) applied to William Guilfoyle. However, Luehmann's letter reports that Bacchus had visited the herbarium twice, once at the end of June, and then at the end of July. M lost responsibility for the Gardens on 1 July.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to be, Sir, your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
