<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Millswyn Street, South Yarra, ¶ 26 August 1873. ¶  ¶ Once I became aware, noble friend, that your important essay on a form of root rot in cereal crops gave rise to expressions of various differences ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-08-26-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.08.26</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Millswyn Street, South Yarra, ¶ 26 August 1873. ¶  ¶ Once I became aware, noble friend, that your important essay on a form of root rot in cereal crops gave rise to expressions of various differences ...</title>
               <date when="1873-08-26">1873-08-26</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-08-26-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Xenodochus carbonarius</term>
               <term>Xenodochus ligniperda</term>
               <term>Puccinia graminis</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/1b060daa-acf7-4f10-8ec9-4b86e45baef7">Sanguisorba</term>
               <term>Restiaceae</term>
               <term>Desmidium</term>
               <term>Erysiphe</term>
               <term>Oidium</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="56">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="44">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl Mücke</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Millswyn Street, South Yarra, ¶ 26 August 1873. ¶  ¶ Once I became aware, noble friend, that your important essay on a form of root rot in cereal crops gave rise to expressions of various differences ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">73.08.26</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl Mücke</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Deutsche Zeitung </seg>(Tanunda), 18 September 1873, p. 5 (B73.09.07). Mücke had sent the letter to the editor of the newspaper with a cover note:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ich halte mich, der wichtigen Sagen wegen, verpflichtet, folgenden Brief des Hrn. Baron v. Müller, den dieser, von den höchsten Gelehrten, allen Universitäten und Gelehrten-Gesellschaften der Erde als Autorität anerkannte grosse Botaniker, so eben an mich zu richten die Güte hatte, mit der freundlichen Erlaubniss desselben, bekannt zu machen, dessen Urtheil über meine anspruchlosen Untersuchungen des Take all wohl von höherer Bedeutung sein möchte, als des eines namenlosen Privat-Gelehrten, Namens A. Müller, der durch sein veröffentlichtes Urtheil und durch die Art und Weise desselben sofort zeigt, wess Geistes Kind er ist. C. Mücke.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">[Because of the importance of the matter, I consider it my duty to publish, with his permission, the following letter from Baron von Mueller, which he, the great botanist, acknowledged as authority by the most eminent scientists and all the universities and learned societies of the earth, had the kindness to address to me. His opinion on my modest researches on the Take-all should be of greater significance than those of a unknown independent scholar named A. Müller, who by his published opinion and the manner in which it was worded immediately shows what sort of person he is. C. Mücke.]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There is an English translation of the article in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">South Australian chronicle and weekly mail</seg>, 27 September 1873, p. 5 (B73.09.08).</p>
               </note>Millswyn-Street, South Yarra, 26. Aug. 1873.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nachdem ich wahrgenommen, edler Freund, dass Ihre wichtige Abhandlung über eine Form der Wurzelfäule des Getreides von der L.S. zu dem Ausdruck von mancherlei Meinungs-Verschiedenheit Anlass gab, so halte ich es für meine Pflicht, Ihnen alsbald einige Auseinandersetzungen über den Pilz, um den es sich handelt, vorzulegen. Von meinem Krankenzimmer aus kann ich es hier nur kurz thun, selbst wenn nach meinem Auszuge aus meiner vormaligen Amtswohnung, meine Privat-Bibliothek aufgepackt<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">ausgepackt?</p>
               </note> wäre, die einstweilen unzugänglich ist. Ich habe nicht einmal die längeren Mittheilungen über die Discussion in unserer deutschen Zeitung lesen können, und aus der L.S. ist mir bisher Nichts über die Verhandlungen zugegangen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zunächst drücke ich mein Mitleid aus darüber, dass ein anspruchsloser Privatforscher, isolirt dastehend im fernen Ausland, nicht mehr gütige Rücksicht von der L.S. oder vielmehr einigen ihrer Mitglieder genoss, selbst wenn Ihre Untersuchungen nicht von der hohen Wichtigkeit wären, welche jeder Gerechte denselben zuschreiben wird. Ich kann es so recht empfinden, wie Sie ohne Rath oder Mithilfe sich haben abquälen müssen, und Sie, Bester, werden auch recht klar bei einer solchen Gelegenheit eingesehen haben, mit welchen Schwierigkeiten ich allein stehend zu kämpfen hatte, ohne Museum oder zulängliche Bibliotheken. Hätte ich nicht meine ganzen Privatmittel dem Herbeischaffen der Hilfsmittel für meine Studien geopfert, meine Untersuchungen hätten hier auch keine Selbstständigkeit annehmen können. Übrigens handelt es sich ja in Ihrer Schrift nicht um naturgeschichtliche Einzelheiten eines thierischen oder pflanzlichen Parasiten, sondern einfach um die Frage nach der Ursache und Bekämpfung dieser Getreide-Fäule, und diese Frage haben Sie genügend, ja glänzend gelöst.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dann schuldige ich es Ihnen nun, auseinanderzusetzen, warum ich den Pilz, über den Sie vor einigen Jahren Auskunft wünschten, die Bezeichnung gab, welche Sie für Ihr Werk annahmen. Der Pilz selbst ist mir nur aus Ihrer Zeichnung bekannt, die aber für die annähernde Kunde vollständig genügt. Man schickte mir hier zu verschiedenen Zeiten Getreideproben, an denen sich der Pilz finden sollte, indessen er war aus solchen nicht heraus zu präpariren, und von Ihnen selbst habe ich keine Präparate gehabt. Um Ihnen einigermassen einstweilen auf Ihre Anfrage gerecht zu werden, verglich ich Ihre Zeichnung mit den Diagnosen oder Illustrationen solcher Pilze, welche mir hier zur Hand waren und glaubte, dass selbiger in das Genus Xenodochus gestellt werden müsse, wie solches jetzt im weiteren Sinne von Dr. Rabenhorst aufgefasst wird. Es war mir freilich wohl bekannt, dass die von Ihnen gezeichnete Pflanze merklich von dem ursprünglichen <name key="Xenodochus%20carbonarius">Xenodochus carbonarius</name>, des Dr. von Schlechtendal abweiche, nicht nur in der Art des Vorkommens, (die bei X. carbonarius auf den Blättern von Sanguisorbeen-Arten ist,) sondern auch in einigen Structur-Verhältnissen. Dann müssen wir aber bedenken, dass wir die Metamorphose sehr vieler Faden- und Staubpilze noch gar nicht kennen. Hat doch der geniale und beharrliche Dr. de Bary erst vor wenigen Jahren nachgewiesen, dass die seit 3000 Jahren als Getreide-Rost bekannte <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name> in Aecidium Stadien, die sich auf Laubsträuchern entwickeln, übergehe. So ist ja auch manches Oïdium nur ein Stadium von <name key="Erysiphe">Erysiphe</name>-Arten. Um Ihnen aber darzuthun, dass der Pilz der Wurzelfäule sich gar sehr mit dem der Holzfäule mancher Coniferen vergleichen und, wie ich es gethan, generisch zusammenfassen lasse, lege ich Ihnen eine Abzeichnung des <name key="Xenodochus%20ligniperda">Xenodochus ligniperda</name> aus einem von Professor Willkomm's Werken vor, so dass Sie unabhängig selbst urtheilen können. Es war fern von mir, über diesen Pilz anders als vorläufig und andeutend zu sprechen, denn ich habe ja keine Original-Exemplare selbst untersuchen können. Dann müsste ich auch mehrere hundert £ aus meinem Gehalte speciell für mycologische Werke aufopfern, um eine Untersuchung dieser Art durchgreifend durchzuführen. Ich habe nahe an tausend £ aus meinen Privatmitteln für wissenschaftliche Werke geopfert, konnte solche Mittel aber nicht auf eine blosse Abtheilung der wissenschaftlichen Literatur verwenden, als die der Mycologie. Ich füge dies nur an, damit Sie, Bester, sehen mögen, dass ich trotz meiner enormen und ruinirenden Privat-Aufopferungen in manchen Fällen etwa so hilflos dastehe, wie Sie selbst. Nun kommt noch dazu, dass die Pilze erst in dem letzten Band, also dem 9. der Flora Australiens, behandelt werden sollen. Daher habe ich das eingehende Studium derselben und den Kauf der nöthigen Werke bis zu der Zeit des neunten Bandes verschoben. Uebrigens sind die grössten Kenner nicht immer einmal mit jedem Theil der Literatur versehen. Sogar mein ehrwürdiger greiser Freund, der Prof. M. I. Buckeley, musste<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">wusste?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> von der Willkomm's Abhandlung, von welcher ich Ihnen der bezügliche Auszug und die dahin gehörende Abzeichnung mache, über Xenodus ligniperda nichts, und fragte deshalb bei mir vor. Der edle Mann, trotz seines grossartigen meisterhaften Wirkens seit vierzig Jahren, fast ausschliesslich zwischen den Pilzen, kann auch nicht gerade jeder Abhandlung Herr werden. Was eine etwaige Unvollständigkeit oder theilweise Ungenauigkeit Ihrer Zeichnungen anlangt, so können Sie sich trösten, wenn Sie bedenken, dass selbst unser grosser Freund Prof. Ehrenberg in mehreren Desmidiaceen Organe beschrieb, die aus Täuschung entsprangen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mein Unwohlsein erlaubt es nicht, weiter in die Sache gerade jetzt einzugehen. Wenn Sie aber den Gegenstand irgendwie weiter mit mir besprechen wollen, so will ich gern irgend eine Frage von Ihnen, soweit ich's vermag, beantworten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass fast endlose Irrthümer aufzuklären sind, selbst grosser Meister, ist mir in der letzten Woche erst recht klar geworden, wie ich die Familie der Restiaceen für den 7. Band der Flora bearbeitete. Ich werde Ihnen den Druck meiner Abhandlung alsbald vorlegen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit ehrender Ergebenheit und dankbarer Erinnerung</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Müller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Millswyn Street, South Yarra,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">26 August 1873.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Once I became aware, noble friend, that your important essay on a form of root rot in cereal crops gave rise to expressions of various differences of opinion in the L. S.,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Linnean Society [of London]. The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London</seg>, 1873, p. iv, contain the following details from the meeting of 20 March 1873:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">Read: extracts from a pamphlet (communicated by F. S. Dutton, Esq., Agent-General S.A.) "On the 'Take-all' Corn-disease of South Australia," by Dr. Carl Mücke; also from a letter "On the 'Take-all' and 'Red Rust,'" addressed by the Rev. M. J. Berkeley, in December 1868, to Dr. J. H. Gilbert, and from a Report on the same subject to the Directors of the South Australian Company, by Messrs. Lawes and Gilbert (both printed in the Journal of the Royal Horticultural Society, vol. ii. pt. 6).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Secretary then read a letter, dated the 10th instant, from the Rev. Mr. Berkeley, to whom Dr. Mücke's pamphlet had been forwarded by the President; and a discussion afterwards followed, in which Mr. Bentham, Mr. Currey, Mr. M'Lachlan, Mr. A. Müller, and Mr. Dutton took part.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3543in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">A letter from one of the discussants, Albert Müller, to South Australia's Agent General in London, dated 24 March 1873, was published in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">South Australian register</seg>, 9 September 1873, p. 4. In this, Müller reports that Mücke <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>had sent a copy of his prize essay, Mücke (1870), to the President of the Linnean Society of London, George Bentham, who sent it to 'several Fellows [including himself] with the request that we would read it and then give our opinions'. All 'agreed in this point, that the facts advanced by Dr Muecke are utterly untrustworthy, both in an entomological and mycological point of view, and that therefore his conclusions and practical advice could not be fully relied upon'.</p>
               </note> I considered it my duty to place before you forthwith a few explanations about the fungus concerned. I can only do so very briefly from my sickbed here, even if my private library, which is currently inaccessible, were unpacked since my move from my former official residence.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's move from the Director's residence following his dismissal, effective from 30 June 1873.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have not even been able to look at the lengthy communications about the discussion in our German newspaper, and I have not yet received any of the Proceedings from the Linnean Society.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To start with I want to express my sympathy that a modest private researcher, standing in isolation in a far-away foreign country, did not receive kinder consideration from the L. S., or rather from some of its members, even were your researches not of such great importance, something every just person must grant them. I can really feel with you, how you had to exert yourself without advice or assistance. And in such a situation, dear Sir, you will have been able to realise very clearly against what difficulties I had to fight, standing alone, without museum or adequate libraries. Had I not sacrificed all my whole private means for the acquisition of the resource materials necessary to my studies, my researches could not have gained any independent standing. By the way, in your essay you do not deal with the scientific details of an animal or plant parasite, but simply with an inquiry into the cause and control of this grain rot, and you have addressed this question adequately, even brilliantly.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Therefore I now owe it to you to explain why I gave to the fungus on which you requested information some years ago the name that you used in your work. The fungus is known to me only from your drawing which, however, is completely adequate for comparative purposes. I was sent cereal samples at various times that were supposed to have been infested with the fungus, but I was unable to obtain preparations of it from them and I did not have any preparations from you personally. To do at least some justice to your request in the interim, I compared your drawing with diagnoses or illustrations of such fungi as I had available to me here and believed that it should be placed in the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Xenodochus</seg> as it is understood in a wider sense by Dr Rabenhorst. I was of course well aware, that the plant drawn by you differed markedly from the original <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Xenodochus%20carbonarius">Xenodochus carbonarius</name>
               </seg> of Dr von Schlechtendal, not only in the manner of its occurrence (which in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">X. carbonarius</seg> is on the leaves of <name key="Sanguisorba">Sanguisorba</name> species), but also in some of its structural arrangements. At the same time we must also consider that we do not yet know the metamorphosis of many <seg style="color: #000000; ">thread and dust fungi.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">For M’s understanding of fungal life cycles, see M to J. Barrow, 15 February 1868.</p>
               </note> The brilliant and persistent de Bary was able to prove only a few years ago that <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name>
               </seg>, known for 3000 years as cereal rust, transfers to deciduous shrubs in its <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Aecidium</seg> stage. Thus many an <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Oidium">Oidium</name>
               </seg> is only a stage of an <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Erysiphe">Erysiphe</name>
               </seg> species. But to demonstrate to you, that the fungus causing root rot compares very well with that of the wood rot of many conifer species and can be combined with it on a generic level as I have done, I enclose a copied drawing of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Xenodochus%20ligniperda">Xenodochus ligniperda</name>
               </seg> from Professor Willkomm's publications,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The drawing was not published with M’s letter. See Willkomm (1866-7), vol. 1, p. 82 and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">passim</seg>; tab. 1, fig. 4.</p>
               </note> so that you may be able to judge independently for yourself. I had no intention to comment on this fungus other than to give some indication in the interim, as I was unable to examine authentic samples myself. Then I would have to sacrifice several hundred £ from my salary specifically for mycological publications, to undertake research of this kind effectively. I have sacrificed close to a thousand £ out of my private means for scientific publications, but was unable to spend such sums on just one field of scientific literature such as mycology. I add this only so that you may see, dear Sir, that in spite of my enormous and ruinous private sacrifices I am often left just as helpless as you yourself are. Added to this is the circumstance that the fungi will be dealt with only in the last, that is the 9th volume, of the Flora of Australia. For that reason I have delayed their intensive study and the purchase of the necessary literature until the 9th volume.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78) concluded with vol. 7, and did not cover the fungi. </p>
               </note> By the way, even the greatest experts do not always possess all the literature in all fields. Even my venerable old friend Professor M. I. Buckeley<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Typesetter’s' error for M. J. Berkeley?</p>
               </note> did not know of Willkomm's publication on <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Xenodochus%20ligniperda">Xenodochus ligniperda</name>
               </seg> from which I copied the relevant extract and drawing for you, and enquired about it from me.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See notes to M to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gardeners' chronicle</seg>, December 1869 (in this edition as 69-12-00e).</p>
               </note> The noble man, in spite of his superb and masterful work almost exclusively on fungi for forty years, is not able to have every publication at his command. As far as any possible deficiency or partial inaccuracy in your drawing is concerned, you may console yourself by remembering that even our great friend Professor Ehrenberg described organs in several <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Desmidium">Desmidium</name>
               </seg> species that were based on error.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My illness does not permit me to pursue the matter further just now, but if you wish to discuss the subject further with me, I shall gladly answer any questions you may have to the best of my ability.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I became very much aware, just in the last week, that almost endless errors, even from great masters, need to be cleared up, when I worked on the family <name key="Restiaceae">Restiaceae</name> for the 7th volume of the Flora.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78), vol. 7, pp. 208-46. M's main working-up of the <name key="Restiaceae">Restiaceae</name> is in B73.08.01, pp 64-101, with some additions in B74.09.02, pp. 236-8. See Lucas (2003) for a discussion of M's working methods in preparing material to be sent to Bentham at Kew.</p>
               </note> I shall present a copy of my publication to you soon.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With respectful devotion and grateful remembrance</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Desmidium">Desmidium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Erysiphe">Erysiphe</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Oidium">Oidium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Restiaceae">Restiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sanguisorba">Sanguisorba</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xenodochus%20carbonarius">Xenodochus carbonarius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xenodochus%20ligniperda">Xenodochus ligniperda</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
