<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot Garden, ¶ 11/4/73. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 7th instance, ¶ Letter not found, but see n. 2 to M to J. Casey. 31 March 1873 (in ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-04-11-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>J73/7110, unit 750, VPRS 44/P inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.04.11</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot Garden, ¶ 11/4/73. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 7th instance, ¶ Letter not found, but see n. 2 to M to J. Casey. 31 March 1873 (in ...</title>
               <date when="1873-04-11">1873-04-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-04-11-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Casey</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot Garden, ¶ 11/4/73. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 7th instance, ¶ Letter not found, but see n. 2 to M to J. Casey. 31 March 1873 (in ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">73.04.11</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Casey</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">J73/7110, unit 750, VPRS 44/P inward registered and unregistered correspondence, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">11/4/73.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 7th instance,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found, but see n. 2 to M to J. Casey. 31 March 1873 (in this edition as 73-03-31a), for a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>recommendation<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>by the Secretary for Agriculture, A. Wallis, that M's museum should be demolished and a new one built within the Botanic Garden.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and beg in reply, that you will allow me to explain the real requirements for the extension of my Museum, as you, Sir, are probably not fully aware of what I deem needful.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1, The Museum building was placed fourteen years ago with the sanction of the hon. Capt. (now Colonel) Pasley, R.E., then Minister of public works, in its present position, that site being the only one well adapted within the area under my control as Director of the botanic Garden for such a structure, it being of the utmost importance that collections of dried plants, readily perishable through moisture, should be located on the highest rise free of all adflux of humidity. This principle is always designedly adhered to, and is as important as other considerations are for the choice of a site of an observatory.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS marginal annotation by A. Wallis: 'The Govt Botanist has lost sight of the fact that the ground near to his own residence is also situated on the brow of a hill, and that it is consequently free from dampness. Besides, modern improvements in the art of ventilation leave no excuse for houses erected in these days being damp.'</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2. I would therefore respectfully advise, that the site of my Museum not be changed, as the existing building, so far as completed, in every respect is adapted for its purpose.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3. As however during the last 14 years my collections have vastly increased, I would repeat for your friendly consideration my application for the extension of the building in accordance with the originally approved design. Thus the middle portion would next have to be constructed at an expenditure of about £800 in basalt, unless a temporary annex of iron was only provided, with a view of utilizing the material of the same subsequently for other purposes, as pointed out in my previous letter.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M to J. Casey, 31 March 1873 (in this edition as 73-03-31a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4. The existing portion of the building cost without the very extensive repositories<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>over one thousand pound Sterling; the repositories &amp;c have cost several hundred pounds Sterling. The latter could only be shifted at very great expense, while the building itself<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>cannot be moved with any view, even after great expenditure, to re-utilize the material to advantage.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS marginal annotation by A. Wallis: 'If the middle portion will cost £800 in basalt, I presume the southern wing will cost not less than did the northern one, viz now £1000. It would perhaps be advisable to obtain from the Public Works Dept an estimate of the cost of erecting an ornamental brick structure, similar to the museum at the university.'</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>5. While therefore the sum of £800.- .-<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>would provide the desired continuation of the building, a sum of nearly £3000.- .-<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>would be required, if a building entirely new was to be erected with no more space and accommodation as the £800 would provide, and with the prospect of injury and even ruin to the collections, which have rendered so far as plants are concerned this colony illustrious and on the formation of which the toils of my life have been largely spent for the last thirty four years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have ventured to place these facts of a special professional bearing with frankness before you, being convinced that you wish to promote in every respect the welfare of my institution for the benefit of this country. I am also certain, that on a personal visit to the spot you would perceive, that no necessity at all exists for the sacrifice of the present Museum-Building, and that any new walks might well be formed without encroachment on the Museum site. It is however right to avail myself of this opportunity respectfully to state, that I have not been consulted on any new work regarding paths &amp;c<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>even in that portion of the bot. reserve, which according to the plan, submitted lately to Parliament, was left me, though even there the treelines are broken, the ground ploughed &amp;c without the least reference to myself.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS marginal annotation by A. Wallis: 'The drive has been taken in this position as it is that which was approved of by the Board of Examiners from whose decision Mr Sayce did not consider himself entitled to depart'.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>For Joseph Sayce's role see notes to M to J. Casey, 31 March 1873 (in this edition as 73-03-31a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be, Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Direct. botan. Garden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">The honorable the Minister of Lands.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 27 April 1873, Casey commented: 'As there is a difference of opinion as to the site for a Museum the matter must stand over for the present &amp; if possible I will visit the two sites myself before the estimates are finally prepared'. M responded on 3 May: 'As we are now already in the eleventh month of the financial year, and as this requisition could first be presented only on the 11. Nov. 1872 in consequence of the deferred votes, I fear that the sum intended for the extension of my Museum may lapse unless it can early be brought under contract. Should the recommended extension not yet be decided on, then I would respectfully request to be allowed to substitute an other requisition for other likewise urgent building-work, for which out of the vastly decreased vote at my present disposal I could not provide. Otherwise the sum, set under requisition apart for the Museum purposes may be entirely lost to my Department.' Wallis added on 9 May: 'The Honble The Minister of Lands &amp; Agriculture desires me to request the Govt Botanist to furnish particulars of the buildings he wishes to be erected', to which M responded by recommending that the building housing the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Victoria regia</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>water-lily<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>be extended;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>see M to J. Casey, 12 May 1873<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 73-05-12a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
