<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 18/6/73. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In reply to your communication of this day, ¶  I have the honor to inform you, that only two letters of those received by me from the Lands Department, rema...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-06-18-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>C73/7740, unit 1022, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.06.18</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 18/6/73. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In reply to your communication of this day, ¶  I have the honor to inform you, that only two letters of those received by me from the Lands Department, rema...</title>
               <date when="1873-06-18">1873-06-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-06-18-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Francis</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Garden ¶ 18/6/73. ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ In reply to your communication of this day, ¶  I have the honor to inform you, that only two letters of those received by me from the Lands Department, rema...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">73.06.18</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Francis</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">C73/7740, unit 1022, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot. Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">18/6/73.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reply to your communication of this day,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See W. Odgers to M, 18 June 1873 (in this edition as 73-06-18a).</p>
               </note> I have the honor to inform you, that only two letters of those received by me from the Lands Department, remain hitherto unanswered. 1, one from the Assistant Commissioner, dated 31 May, informing me on behalf of the Ministry as a whole, that my position as Director of the bot. Garden is to be abolished, and asking at what date before the beginning of next month, I would be able to vacate my office-dwelling. To this letter I could as yet not give a positive answer, because I have hitherto in vain endeavoured to arrange for an abode elsewhere, never foreseeing that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">within a single months</hi>
               </seg> notice I should have suddenly to leave a home of very many years, such as any one in my position would have fairly expected to be intended for life. As soon as my arrangements are completed, I shall not fail to give the information through the same channel, by which it was asked by Government, even should I finally be compelled to seek shelter for my private effect by mere storage somewhere. I was not aware of the necessity of replying to the Assistant Commissioners letter, until I knew myself the day, when I could move into a new abode, for which I have sought ever since; but regarded it self understood, that I must give up my quarters at the end of this month. I have now however sent a formal answer to that effect to the Lands Office.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The finall two sentences are a marginal addition by M.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The second letter, as yet left unanswered, concerns a return of contributions, received in my Department during 1870. The request for such a document was made by the hon. the Minister of the Lands Department on the 21 of last month, and the return is now nearly completed, notwithstanding the anxieties, disturbances and additional toil, arising unexpectedly out of the necessity of preparing for my removal from the bot. Garden. I should be glad, if <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">two disinterested officers could be appointed by Government, to take formal delivery</hi>
               </seg> of all property of the bot. Garden in the beginning of next month.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reference to the willingness of the Government to grant me kindly (apparently ordinary) leave of absense, I beg respectfully to point out, that I sought by my letter of the 15th of this month only "<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">permission to travel in Australia or the adjacent islands for researches in connection with my works</hi>
               </seg>". I have however since the last few days discussed with medical friends more fully the advisability of such travels, (meaning in reality <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">explorations beyond the settlements</hi>
               </seg>), and feel, that I ought to act on their advice, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not to take the field again at my age</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>and with my much reduced strength. Under these circumstances, while thanking you and your honorable colleagues for your <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">kind intentions I shall be unable to avail myself of them</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If however, as I anticipate, it is the desire of the Ministry, to render the last few years of my life not altogether cheerless, nor my existence one of continuous humiliations, nor my further literary services altogether lost, I would solicit, that some <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">modest, dignified and permanent provision</hi>
               </seg> may be made for my future, after the 21 years of incessant and toilsome service incurred by me for the creation and maintenance of my Department, that the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">position of Gov. Botanist may be restricted solely to Museum services</hi>
               </seg>,<seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>that I may be allowed (while also yet advising on scientific subjects in future as far as I can without the mechanism of a Department) to hold the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Directorship over my Museum and Library as an honorary one</hi>
               </seg>, and that in accordance with the letter of the Government under date 31 May 1873, I may "be allowed the exclusive use of the Museum", which contains also all <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my private collections commenced 34 years ago</hi>
               </seg>; and further that "the provisions accordingly made on the estimates of the ensuing year" may be left under my professional and administrative control. I have already stated, that all my private means have been sunk in my department and my researches, and that the mere difference between the salaries of each of my professional compeers and my own in the course of a series of years amounted to many thousands of £ in their favor, altho' their position was neither socially nor scientifically heavily taxed like my own.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The final sentence is a marginal addition by M.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I can then hope in comparative tranquillity to furnish early my portion of the 7th and 8th volumes of the great work, published by the President of the Linnean Society and myself, and while thus not detaining that venerable man, I shall likely regain strength and new courage for such future work amidst my fellow colonists as providence may still destine for me. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be, Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 23 June 1873 the Chief Secretary, J. Francis, minuted that M be asked 'whether he withdraws his request for 12 months leave of absence'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
