<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanical Garden ¶ 18 March 1873 ¶ Very dear Sir ¶ I have the honour to reply to your last week’s letter. ¶ Letter not found. ¶  The acclimatization of the Eucalyptus in the more temperate p...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-03-18-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Archivio Centrale dello Stato, Rome, Ministero d'Agricoltura, Industria e Commercio, Direzione Generale dell’Agricoltura. Versamento I, Busta 121.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.03.18</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanical Garden ¶ 18 March 1873 ¶ Very dear Sir ¶ I have the honour to reply to your last week’s letter. ¶ Letter not found. ¶  The acclimatization of the Eucalyptus in the more temperate p...</title>
               <date when="1873-03-18">1873-03-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-03-18-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eucalyptus Amygdalina</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Coccifera</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Marginata</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Vernicosa</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Colossea</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Coriacea</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Globulus</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Rostrata</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Urnigera</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Obliqua</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Stricta</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Alpina</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Gunnii</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Giuseppe Lovera di Maria</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanical Garden ¶ 18 March 1873 ¶ Very dear Sir ¶ I have the honour to reply to your last week’s letter. ¶ Letter not found. ¶  The acclimatization of the Eucalyptus in the more temperate p...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">73.03.18</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Giuseppe Lovera di Maria</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Archivio Centrale dello Stato, Rome, Ministero d'Agricoltura, Industria e Commercio, Direzione Generale dell’Agricoltura. Versamento I, Busta 121.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS is not in M's hand.; it is probably an Italian translation prepared from a letter written originally by M in English. MS was forwarded </seg>with a covering letter dated 9 January 1874 from the Ministero della Marina, Direzione Generale del Personale, to the Ministero d'Agricoltura, Industria e<seg style=""> Commercio, in which it was noted that Lovera was the person 'to whom the contents of the Dispatch were sent'. The dispatch also included a packet of seeds of </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptus globulus</seg>
                     <seg style=""> from Lovera. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>See also G. Verdon to M, 4 March 1873 (in this edition as 73-03-04a), and M to J. Casey, 10 March 1873</seg>.</p>
               </note>Giardino botanico di Melbourne</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">18 Marzo 1873</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Pregiatissimo Signore</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mi pregio rispondere alla di Lei lettera della settimana decorsa. L'acclimatazione dell'Eucalipto nelle parti più temperate dell'Italia, potrebbe senza dubbio tornare di grandissima utilità. Tali alberi infatti oltre ad appartenere alle specie sempre verdi crescono con una celerità straordinaria, producono combustibile di buona qualità e legname da costruzione solido e duraturo, più presto ed in quantità maggiore di ogni altro albero, e possiedono finalmente speciali proprietà medicinali e industriali come olii volatili, resine principi tannini etc. Ciò non di meno l'Eucalipto non potrebbe rimpiazzare il pino e molti altri alberi adatti ad usi speciali e che soli possono servire per pavimenti, tavoli, alberi di bastimento, mobilia e arnesi di certi generi determinati, anche se vogliamo lasciare da parte alcune specie di resine e di trebentina<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>terebentina?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> che solo possono ottenersi dalle Conifere. L'Eucalipto però non può acclimatarsi che nei paesi che sieno esenti da forti ghiacci. Ma qualore le circonstanze atmosferiche sieno favorevoli la parte che esso potrebbe prendere nella formazione di nuove foreste può essere di grande importanza e potrebbe anche diventare preponderante sopra ogni altra specie di albero. Naturalmente i terreni agricoli di buona qualità hanno troppo valore in paesi sufficientemente popolati perchè si possa usarli per l'Eucalipto. Siccome però questa specie di alberi non ha bisogno di irrigazione e prospera anche nel suolo il più sterile così tutti quei luoghi che non sono adatti all'agricoltura potrebbero benissimo essere utilizzati con piantagioni dei medesimi. In un opuscolo pubblicato nel 1871 negli Atti della Società di Acclimatazione di Victoria io detti già i nomi e le qualità speciali di circa 300 specie di alberi che potrebbero esser cresciuti utilmente in questa Colonia. Quella nota comprendeva tutti gli alberi più importanti che si conoscono in tutte le parti del Globo ad eccezione delle tropicali. Essa potrebbe benissimo applicarsi all'Italia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Per ciò che riguarda le provincie settentrionali e conseguentemente più fredde dell'Italia l'Eucalipto non potrebbe crescere che sui pendii più bassi delle Alpi giacché tali montagne ad una certa elevazione diventano troppo fredde per quest'albero. Le qualità che si incontrano a più grande altezza sui monti del Sud Est dell'Australia (dai 4000 a 5000 piedi sul livello del mare — 1216 a 1320 metri) sono l'<name key="Eucalyptus%20Coriacea">Eucalyptus Coriacea</name>, E. Gunnii, E. Alpina, E. Coccifera, E. Vernicosa, E. Urnigera, E. Stricta: nessuna però di queste specie produce alberi di alto fusto nei luoghi più freddi nei quali pure continuano a crescere. L'<name key="Eucalyptus%20Obliqua">Eucalyptus Obliqua</name>, E. Globulus, E. Amygdalina, E. Coriacea crescono sulle nostre montagne fino ad un livello di 3000 ad anche 4000 piedi (da 912 a 1216 metri) ad altezza gigantesche, specialmente nelle vallate riparate dove raggiungono dimensioni assolutamente colossali. L'E. Amygdalina è quello che nelle valli più fresche (non però più fredde) supera tutti le altre specie in dimensione. L'E. Rostrata, tanto preziosa pel suo legname da costruzione di una straordinaria durata, L'E. Colossea e l'E. Marginata non crescono generalmente in luoghi molto elevati. Che anzi la prima specie rammentata trovasi solamente sulle rive dei fiumi. Tutte però possono sopportare qualche poco di gelo.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Tutto compreso a me sembra che le specie più importanti di Eucalipto potrebbero benissimo crescere in Italia se si usa la precauzione di allevarli in vivai ben riparati e piantarli all'aperto quando le piante abbiano circa un'anno. Tali piantagioni dovrebbero farsi dopo che i geli invernali sono finiti e prima che incomincino grandi calori estivi. Moltissime località tanto in piano che in monte tanto nell'Italia settentrionale che nella meridionale vi sarebbero adattate. Nel primo inverno si verificherebbe poi fino a qual latitudine e livello tali pianti potrebbero crescere in Italia. E così l’esperienza di un solo anno potrebbe fornire prova sufficiente per l’avvenire.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>E’ impossibile precisare gli estremi di freddo e di livello a cui gli Eucalipti possono non solo crescere ma essere commercialmente utili. Potrei solo dire che in quei luoghi ove l'E. Obliqua, l'E. Globulus e l'E. Amygdalina raggiungono nelle nostre montagne grandi proporzioni la neve si ferma in inverno spesso per molti giorni ma non mai per mesi intieri. Là dove la neve si ferma a lungo gli Eucalipti sono ridotti solo allo stato di arboscelli e non danno per ciò legname quantunque però possano sempre essere di grandissima utilità per fermare il suolo, per le loro essenze, principj tannini e medicinali.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Il prezzo medio all ingrosso dei semi dell'E. Globulus, E. Amygdalina e E. Obliqua è ora ridotto a circa 15 scellini la libbra* (circa ₤40 per chilo<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Symbol obscured, probably ₤ (lira); the price conversion was almost certainly added by the translator.</p>
               </note>). Negli anni passati era molto più caro, ma essendo ora stabilita, grazie specialmente alle mie raccomandazioni, una regolare esportazione, si può oggigiorno risparmiare la spesa di impiegare un collettore speciale. La semente di E. Rostrata, E. Marginata, E. Colossea e diverse altre sono molto più care. Alcune anzi sono costosissime giacché non possono raccogliersi che con molta difficoltà. Come ho già detto questi semi dovrebbero essere seminati in vivai, trapiantati quindi a tempo umido e fresco quando le pianticelle sieno alte cinqu[e] o sei pollici (il che può farsi facilmente con la vanghetta di Keyer e trapiantati ancora una volta quando sieno alte un piede (30 cm). Questo secondo trapianto potrebbe farsi ai luoghi ove esse debbono poi restar fisse. Tanto le vallate che i luoghi esposti sulle montagne sarebbero egualmente adattati.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nel Bullettino della Società di Agricoltura di Algeri del 1869 io trattai più a lungo e più dettagliatamente dell'acclimatazione dell'Eucalipto nell'Affrica Settentrionale. Sarà molto facile in Italia a chi si interessi in questa materia il procacciarsi tale opuscolo.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Qualora Ella desiderasse maggiori schiarimenti si rivolga pure liberamente al</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Suo devotmo<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>devotissimo?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>(Firmato) Barone F. Von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">*Con una libbra di semente si possono ottenere molte migliaja di piante.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanical Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">18 March 1873</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Very dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honour to reply to your last week’s letter.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> The acclimatization of the Eucalyptus in the more temperate parts of Italy could no doubt be of the greatest utility. In fact, these trees, besides belonging to the evergreen species grow with extraordinary rapidity, produce good quality fuel and solid and durable construction timber, sooner and in greater quantity than any other tree, and they also possess special medicinal and industrial properties such as vegetable oils, resins, tannin principles, etc. Nevertheless, the Eucalyptus could not replace the pine or several other trees suitable for special uses and which alone can serve for floors, tables, masts, furniture and tools of certain kinds, even if we want to leave aside some species of resins and terebenthine that can only be obtained from Conifers. Yet the Eucalyptus can only acclimatize in those countries that are free from strong ice. If weather conditions are favourable, however, the role it could take in the formation of new forests could be of great importance and could even exceed that of any other species of tree. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Obviously, good quality agricultural land is too valuable in sufficiently populated countries to be used for the Eucalyptus. But since this species of tree does not need irrigation and thrives even in the most barren soil, all those areas that are not suitable for agriculture could be used perfectly well with plantations of the same. In a pamphlet published in 1871 in the Proceedings of the Acclimatisation Society of Victoria,</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B71.13.01.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> I gave the names and the special qualities of about 300 species of trees that could be usefully grown in this colony. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>That note included all the most important trees known in all parts of the globe except the tropics. It could perfectly apply to Italy.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Regarding the northern and consequently colder provinces of Italy, the Eucalyptus could only grow on the lower slopes of the Alps, since these mountains become too cold for this tree at a certain height. The kinds that can be found at a greater altitude in the mountains of south-eastern Australia (from 4000 to 5000 feet above sea level - 1216 to 1320 metres) are the <name key="Eucalyptus%20Coriacea">Eucalyptus Coriacea</name>, E. Gunnii, E. Alpina. E. Coccifera, E. Vernicosa, E. Urnigera, E. Stricta: but none of these species produces tall trees in the coldest places in which they yet continue to grow. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The <name key="Eucalyptus%20Obliqua">Eucalyptus Obliqua</name>, E. Globulus, E. Amygdalina, E. Coriacea grow to gigantic heights in our mountains up to a level of 3000 and even 4000 feet (from 912 to 1216 metres), especially in sheltered valleys where they reach absolutely colossal dimensions. The E. Amygdalina is the one that in the cooler (but not colder) valleys surpasses all the other species in size. The E. Rostrata, so precious for its building timber of extraordinary duration, the E. Colossea and the E. Marginata generally do not grow in very high places. On the contrary, the first species mentioned is only found on the banks of rivers. All of them, however, can withstand a bit of frost.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All this considered, I believe that the most important species of Eucalyptus could grow extremely well in Italy if you take the precaution of raising them in well-protected nurseries and planting them outdoors when the plants are about a year old. These plantings should be done once the winter frosts are over and before the great summer heat begins. Many localities, both on the plain and up in the mountains and whether in northern or southern Italy would be adapted. In the first winter the latitude and altitude at which these plants could grow in Italy would be considered. Thus a one-year experience could provide sufficient evidence for the future.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is impossible to specify the extremes of cold and altitude at which the Eucalyptus can not just grow but be commercially useful. I can only say that in those places in our mountains where the E. Obliqua, the E. Globulus and the E. Amygdalina reach large proportions, snow often stays in winter for many days but never for entire months. Wherever the snow stays for a long time the Eucalypts are reduced to the form of shrubs and do not therefore provide timber, though they can always be very useful to secure the soil, for their essences, tannins and medicinal principles.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The average wholesale price of seeds of E. Globulus, E. Amygdalina and E. Obliqua is now reduced to about 15 shillings a pound* (</seg>about ₤40<seg style=""> per kilo</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See n. 3.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">). Over the past few years, it was much more expensive, but now, thanks to my recommendations, a regular export trade has been established, today we can save the expense of employing a special collector. The seeds of E. Rostrata, E. Marginata, E. Colossea and several other types are much more expensive. Some are indeed very expensive, since they can only be collected with great difficulty. As I said, those seeds should be sown in nurseries, then transplanted during wet and cool weather when the seedlings are five or six inches high (which can easily be done with a Keyer's spade</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Not identified.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> and transplanted once again when they are one foot tall (30 cm). This second transplanting should be to the places where they must then remain. Both valleys and exposed locations in the mountains would be equally suitable.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the Bulletin of the Algiers Society of Agriculture of 1869, I dealt more extensively and in greater detail with the acclimatization of the Eucalyptus in North Africa.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B69.06.02.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> In Italy it will be very easy, for those who are interested in the matter, to find this pamphlet.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Should you wish further clarification, feel free to contact me.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Yours very truly</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">(Signed) Baron F. Von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">* With a pound of seed several thousand plants can be obtained.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Alpina">Eucalyptus Alpina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Amygdalina">Eucalyptus Amygdalina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Coccifera">Eucalyptus Coccifera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Colossea">Eucalyptus Colossea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Coriacea">Eucalyptus Coriacea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Globulus">Eucalyptus Globulus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Gunnii">Eucalyptus Gunnii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Marginata">Eucalyptus Marginata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Obliqua">Eucalyptus Obliqua</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Rostrata">Eucalyptus Rostrata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Stricta">Eucalyptus Stricta</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Urnigera">Eucalyptus Urnigera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Vernicosa">Eucalyptus Vernicosa</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
