<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot. Museum ¶ 1/8/73. ¶ To the honorable the Chief Secretary ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department the byefollowing memorandum ¶  from the L...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-08-01a.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>D73/9915, unit 669, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.08.01a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot. Museum ¶ 1/8/73. ¶ To the honorable the Chief Secretary ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department the byefollowing memorandum ¶  from the L...</title>
               <date when="1873-08-01">1873-08-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-08-01a.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>James Francis</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot. Museum ¶ 1/8/73. ¶ To the honorable the Chief Secretary ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department the byefollowing memorandum ¶  from the L...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">73.08.01a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To James Francis</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">D73/9915, unit 669, VPRS 3991/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Melbourne bot. Museum</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">1/8/73.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To the honorable the Chief Secretary</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to submit to you, as the ministerial Head of the Department the byefollowing memorandum<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See A. Wallis to M, 31 July 1873.</p>
               </note> from the Lands-Office and the replies thereto. The bot. Museum, ever since it has been founded by me in 1858 has been open from 8 a.m. til 5 p.m. to the public, and on no occasion has been access thereto denied<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">on no … denied <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is underlined in pencil.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> If the complaint refers to the want of access at this moment to the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Australian Grasses</hi>
               </seg> and allied plants, then I must point out, that they are and will be for some months under <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">final arrangement, analysis and description</hi>
               </seg> for the seventh volume of the Australian Flora, (all the collections formed by me since 1840 being included) and that until this is completed any disturbance among this part of the collection would be mischievous or retard the research. So it would have been with the Orchideae a few month<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">sic.</p>
               </note> ago. In fairness I should add, that I have named for Mr Bacchus, who always showed himself most gentlemanly to me, on repeated occasions numerous specimens of native grasses and other plants, which he forwarded to me from Ballarat.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to be, Sir, your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to J. Lichmann, 1 August 1873. On 8 August 1873 A. Wallis, Secretary of Agriculture, minuted: 'From the Govt Botanist's letter it would appear that at such times as any section of the museum plants is under examination by him, no other person can gain access thereto, whether for the purpose of study or otherwise. This, in my humble opinion, is a most unsatisfactory state of things, and if enforced on the present occasion will be attended by serious loss to a large section of the public. Mr Bacchus, who for upwards of 30 years has studied our native grasses both by practical observation in the field and scientifically, has kindly consented to contribute to the next volume of the transaction of the Dept of Agriculture a comprehensive paper on our native pastures, giving the scientific and common names of each grass and the results of his observation and experience as to their relative feeding capabilities, their relative powers of resisting drought, the season of the year at which they produce the most food, and other information of a practical and highly useful natire. Mr Bacchus however, with a view to make his paper more complete, is anxious to compare some of his specimens with those contained in the national Herbarium, to make sure that he has them correctly named. Considering then that no account of our native grasses has yet been published and that a paper containing practical information such as Mr Bacchus alone in this colony can furnish would be of inestimable service to persons engaged in Agric pursuits throughout the colony, I am of opinion that the Govt Botanist, since he cannot possibly require all the Grasses for study at one and the same time, should be required to render Mr Bacchus every assistance in the accomplishment of his useful work.' Wallis forwarded this minute to the Chief Secretary 'by direction of The Honble the Minister of Lands and Agriculture'. The Under Secretary, John Moore, forwarded it the same day with the minute: 'In allowing the Govt Botanist the use of the Herbarium it was <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">not?</seg> intended nor is it reasonable that he should prevent its being inspected when necessary. It is admitted [sic] Mr Bacchus was denied access to the plants.' On 12 August 1873 the Chief Secretary, James Francis, instructed: 'The Government Botanist will give Mr Bacchus access to these Grasses or plants &amp; arrange generally for the courteous interchange of information.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 16 August 1873 M replied: 'I have anticipated the wish, expressed by the hon. the Chief Secretary, in affording on all occasions the fullest possible information in all branches of my Department, and shall not fail to do so also in future. To render this information in the Museum still more extensive, I placed even my own voluminous collections there, formed since the last 34 years. Mr Bacchus, as stated already by me, <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">got</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">all his grasses</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">and other pasture plants</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">named by me already</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">long</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">ago</hi>
                     </seg>, like I have named such for other similarly observant colonists, since many years; moreover he was even promised an early supply of dried specimens, plants for testculture at his place. This and other official attention, experienced from me, he has acknowledged with gratitude on various public occasions.'</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
