<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private ¶ Melbourne ¶ 6/11/73. ¶  ¶ I felt sure, dear Dr Hooker, that you would support my view of declining on principle a transfer of my services to the University, even if a vacancy had occurred, w...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-11-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Kew correspondence, Australia, Mueller, 1871-81, ff. 125-8.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>73.11.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Private ¶ Melbourne ¶ 6/11/73. ¶  ¶ I felt sure, dear Dr Hooker, that you would support my view of declining on principle a transfer of my services to the University, even if a vacancy had occurred, w...</title>
               <date when="1873-11-06">1873-11-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1873/73-11-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Private ¶ Melbourne ¶ 6/11/73. ¶  ¶ I felt sure, dear Dr Hooker, that you would support my view of declining on principle a transfer of my services to the University, even if a vacancy had occurred, w...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">73.11.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Joseph Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Kew correspondence, Australia, Mueller, 1871-81, ff. 125-8.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Each sheet is so headed, but later headings are not transcribed.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">6/11/73.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I felt sure, dear Dr Hooker, that you would support my view of declining on principle a transfer of my services to the University, even if a vacancy had occurred, which was not the case, and even if my pulmonary suffering did not prevent me from entering on any regular course of lectures.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Hooker, 16 June 1873.</p>
               </note> I thought it also my duty to the Directors, whose colleague I have been so long, not to set a dangerous precedent. Your emphatic approval of my refusing to be tossed about from place to place, gives me a great moral support, as I can mention to influential friends here your views with every propriety.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hooker's letter, to which M is apparently referring, has not been found.</p>
               </note> That you with your great friends will come to the rescue, inspires me with new hope for the future! Indeed I stand in need of that rescue in my undeserved persecution, which indeed is utterly without example. Of course my feelings, which are naturally those of generosity and kindness, have become at last so embittered that I am hardly able to control my expressions and actions [now].</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Under the late Mr Haines, the late Mr Nicholson, Mr OShanassy and the late Mr Heales I was treated for more than a dozen of years as Director with every consideration and was fairly though never lavishly supported. My intercourse with all these ministers was of the most pleasing &amp; friendly kind! So it is not <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
               </seg> fault if I cannnot get on now.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">My intercourse ... get on now, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is a marginal note with its intended position indicated by an asterisk</seg>.</p>
               </note> But after that my carreer has been marred here more or less by every one of my ministerial Chiefs through withholding the most modest but necessary means by their listening to ignorant and low men on the Argus and one or 2 other papers, by their taking not the slightest pain to acquaint themselves with my work and my requirements. Finally I was starved out at the Garden, and as I held still on, hoping for better time, I was ejected at a months notice, to make place for the utter unscientific cousin<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">William Guilfoyle.</p>
               </note> of the wife of the Minister of the Department. Then even no means were left me to carry on the branch of Gov Botanist, even if it was not highly derogatory to hold such an office without being held worthy to administrate the bot Garden, which in reality is the place and the organisation, in which my researches in any Direction are to obtain vitality.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since I last wrote the usual "additional estimates" came before the Parliament <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I applied for what was needed, without the slightest allusion to anything partaining of the bot Garden. You are aware, that I had only £300 granted working expenses for my whole responsible and multifarious Departmental services, beyond my modest salary. Bear kindly in mind, that this is a very expensive country (not in all, but in most things). — So I applied for a collector £150, a laboratory operator £150, for Benthams subsidy £100; for a messenger and outdoor agent (consignments, freights &amp;c) £120, for books and instruments, something, orphan-labor, an office room, a place for the physical necessities of life, (not even such is left me and my clerk), also for the purchase of additional Museum collections, for extension of the Museum Building (it being only one overcrowded room, to which nothing is added since 14 years! Of all these reasonable requests only the one concerning the item of £100 for Mr Bentham was granted by the Ministry, or rather Mr Francis, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">our</hi>
               </seg> present Prime Minister, while the other 78 members of the Lower House with 1 or 2 excepted would all as cheerfully have voted thousands of £ for me, as the[y] <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">did</hi>
               </seg> vote £1300 last week on the additional estimates for the working of the Observatory, that institution having had granted already £2400 working expenses for this financial year, irrespective of the Directors Salary and irrespective of his and his many Assistants free quarters. You will see, therefore, my dear Dr Hooker, that it is intended willingly and studiously to starve me out of the remaining part of my official position, to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">put me down,</hi>
               </seg> and to render any real progress of my work and any extensive utility of my labors an utter impossibility. This is my impression, and there is not a single fact, which leads redeemingly to other conclusions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If I had ever been a political agitator or had committed a single bad act, I could understand this; but as it is — I can’t, unless because I am of teutonic extraction, though I lived several years longer in Australia than all my life in Europe. The revenue is overflowing. This week many thousands £ defraudations and embezzlements in the Lands Department, extending over a long time, came to light; but the principle permanent officer<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Clement Hodgkinson.</p>
               </note> spends largely his time, instead of looking after his proper duties, to lay out Gardens &amp; Parks of the City and has swallowed up as a Chief over the new Curator also the bot Garden, its conservatories &amp;c. altho his knowledge of plants consists in having mastered a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">few</hi>
               </seg> names of trees, which he first saw at the bot Garden or got from the Nurserymen</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is my duty towards myself to explain all this, otherwise you would form but a poor judgement of your former colleague. You must also remember, that we have universal suffrage, that everybody votes at 21 and upwards, that a few <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hundred</hi>
               </seg> voters form a constituency, that we have <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">payment </hi>
               </seg>of members &amp;c. Many of the members are not in affluent circumstances, and what operated much against me <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">this</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; "> </seg>year was the fact, that any rupture in Parliament would have caused a dissolution of the House, whose triennium expires next year, and thus the Members would sit only 2½ instead of 3 years. It is needless to assure you, that I gladly would turn my back upon the colony, but I cannot leave my 34 years collections of plants behind in the very midst of my work. I must yet try to shed additional light on the plants of Central and tropical Australia and must see the Monocotyledoneae through with Mr Benthams aid.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I could of course never think of taking office elsewhere at my age, and with the prospect of being treated just in the same manner after a few years at an other place. For any other position elsewhere of course a younger man or a local man is working up. I would become an interloper on him. I asked for a modest pension after 22 years service but it was refused.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Francis, 18 June 1873.</p>
               </note> It would have been only the interest of a private fortune sunk by me into the Department. I could of course only accept a pension by being allowed the Honorary Direction of the Museum &amp; Library and by being the Administrator of such fund as for the Museum &amp; Publications may still be voted.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On one point, emanating from your very generous and noble letter,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> dear Dr Hooker, I must be allowed to differ with you. It is your idea, that you would <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi>
               </seg> be glad to have nothing to do with Kew Garden, if you could securely continue your literary work. I am not altogether surprised at this view of yours, preceiving that it was the view on the spur of a moment. But having long and carefully meditated on <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">this </hi>
               </seg>subject, I cannot but warn you of the great danger of enunciating this idea. You would find yourself hampered at all sides. You could no longer order a single thing about the most valuable &amp; rare culture plants. You might be hindered proper access for study. You would be sure to be foiled on any attempt to order upon any thing. You would <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not save time</hi>
               </seg>, but would waste it in circumlocution and jealous hinderances and in want of means. Your votes would be seized on; indeed you could no longer go to the Garden without pain. No! my dear Dr Hooker, remain generalissimus, but keep <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">good</hi>
               </seg> &amp; <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">faithful</hi>
               </seg> officers under you; then your administration will be easy &amp; fruitful; not otherwise. You want an hours daily exercise and that hour is quite sufficient for your giving your orders as a Horticultural Director. What interest could it be to you to bring through correspondents new plants, new seeds &amp;c into England, unless you could keep them under your own control.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 14 August 1873 Hooker wrote to H. Barkly: 'Last night I heard from Mueller, that they had taken the Garden from him — I am deeply sorry for him, though I am sure it is for the best; he loaded himself with duties scarcely germane to his post, and which no human head could effectively administer on the scale he attempted. He is after all uncommonly well off, with his full salary, and collections and Library, a Museum Keeper, Clerk, and house rent, and all day long for Science! I am sure I would jump at such a post here, for the Garden is a very onerous duty, in its Public aspect most especially. Lord Canterbury spent the other evening here, and told me of the moral certainty of Mueller losing the Garden. I only hope that they will appoint a Gardener with some love of plants for their own sakes to it.' (RBG Kew, Letters from Joseph Hooker vol. 1, Ada-Bar, ff. 207-9.[typescript carbon copy of unknown provenance]): Barkly replied, 30 November 1873, agreeing that 'the best thing for [M] is to have nothing to do with the gardening department' (RBG Kew, Director's letters, South African letters, A-G 1865—1900. ff. 188-9).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You might see Mr Michie about me, the present Victorian Agent General. He did for years show himself kindly to me, but as he was Attorney General to the last M'Culloch Ministry, his good feelings were for a time (he being misled) alienated from me. The step however you propose is kind &amp; <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">good</hi>
               </seg>! It was not instigated by me. It will bring men in power here to shame.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As yet I have no assurance, that the Library will be left me, though the correspondence on the subject<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to J. Francis, 7 September 1873.</p>
               </note> came to a stand still, but it may be brought to a climax after a few weeks, when Parliament is to be dissolved or rather expires. Whether I am to be provided for again on the estimates I do not know. Perhaps not! I have sold everything off, to keep on with my service. I keep two people on my <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">private</hi>
               </seg> expense for Departmental duties, pay for Office rent, House rent &amp;c. But what can I do in this expensive country with £300! as the whole working expense of a Department! You might kindly see not only the hon Mr Michie, but also Lord Canterbury, and some means might be devised then to bring <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">European</hi>
               </seg> Influence to bear not merely on the paltry financial question, but on that of professional honor &amp; position particularly.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Always Your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir Hercules Robinson is here on a visit; though 17 years in correspondence with him I am ashamed to show myself before him, after I am driven out of the Directorship.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Could you kindly give me an estimate of your annual <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Museum</hi>
               </seg> expense altogether, including building, prints, light[,] paper, [tons] fuel, books, journals, clerks, Assistants &amp;c, freights, travelling expenses, postage, stationary</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With £300 Salary at the bot Garden I could do more than with £800 out of it. My impression is, that the increase was [merely] given, in order to be able to have some excuse to fall back on though my ruin was inflicted<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A newspaper cutting is pasted onto Folio 129, but no source is indicated. The item reads: 'Baron von Mueller has hardly left the Botanic Garden when he is missed. At the meeting of the Ballarat Farmers' Club on Saturday last, one of its leading members, Mr. Bacchus, complained that he was now refused the assistance in test culture, which used to be so willingly given. Baron von Mueller introduced a large number of plants for scientific and commercial purposes, fodder plants, medicinal plants etc., and when he had a sufficient number on hand he was accustomed to distribute specimens to persons whom he could rely upon taking an interest in their development. In his day a portion of the ground was set apart for the growth of new hedge shrubs, oil and textile plants, specimens of grasses and fodder herbs, plants for dyeing, etc. Some of the specimens Mr. Bacchus received from the Baron last year died off, and on applying for others he was politely informed, it seems, that that sort of thing was to be discontinued. The gentleman himself is disgusted, and his Farmers' Club is indignant, and now that the mischief has been done, we are likely to have a protest against the present idea of spending many thousands per annum at our central botanic garden upon geraniums, pansies, and sweet williams, in order that nursemaids may exclaim "How pretty!" Very likely it would have been well to allow Baron von Mueller anoher [printer's error] £1,000 per annum in order to beautify the grounds, but the course taken has been to sacrifice the useful purpose of the institution, and to convert a botanic garden into mere pleasuregrounds. Instead of an institution which should instruct as well as delight, we are to have a cockney tea garden without the tea. When they have rooted up the imported plants, the new managers will doubtless put cockle-shells round the beds. Instead of the shrubs of commerce which would enrich the land as well as adorn it, they will let us have a monkey and a fountain. Then the transformation will be complete.'</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
