<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Gardens, ¶ February 21,1870. ¶  ¶ I am under great obligations to you, dear Mr Baird, for the interest evinced by you in Mr. Powell's communication relative to supposed new trace of ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1870/70-02-21-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>70.02.21</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Gardens, ¶ February 21,1870. ¶  ¶ I am under great obligations to you, dear Mr Baird, for the interest evinced by you in Mr. Powell's communication relative to supposed new trace of ...</title>
               <date when="1870-02-21">1870-02-21</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1870/70-02-21-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Robert Baird</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Gardens, ¶ February 21,1870. ¶  ¶ I am under great obligations to you, dear Mr Baird, for the interest evinced by you in Mr. Powell's communication relative to supposed new trace of ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">70.02.21</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Robert Baird</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from 'The fate of Leichhardt', <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg>, 14 March 1870, p. 2 (B70.03.01) (reprinted in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Queenslander</seg>, B70.03.02). The text is introduced in each case by a letter to the Editor from Robert Baird dated 12 March, as follows:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </seg>On the 8th of February last, you were kind enough to publish a letter addressed to me by Mr. Powell, in which he imparted intelligence received from the aborigines as to the existence of a white man amongst them. Since then I have communicated with Dr. Mueller, of Victoria, and beg to hand you a copy of his letter to me, in the hope that you will find room for it in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Courier</seg>. The question of Australian exploration, apart from all considerations of the great pioneer Leichhardt, is one of great interest, and I do hope and expect that the people of Queensland will “do something” to forward it.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter to which Baird refers was published in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg>, 9 February 1870, p. 3, being introduced by a letter from Baird dated 8 February. Powell reported that while living in the vicinity of Cooper’s Creek, </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">About the end of last October I took a few days’ journey to the west, accompanied by a black boy, who has been with me for several years. On Cooper’s Creek I encountered a tribe of natives who informed me that at a certain distance to the west, a white man crippled with disease was living with and supported by a tribe of natives. They state that a great many summers since a party of white men, with a number of horses, plenty of flour and firearms, crossed Cooper’s Creek about seventy or eighty miles below the junction of the Barcoo and Thomson Rivers, travelling in a westerly direction. That the whole of the party were taken ill with what I suppose to have been a malignant fever, or fever or ague; that all died with the exception of one man, and he was completely crippled; that since his own supplies became exhausted, he has been supported by the natives, but that he is in such a state that he is perfectly incapable of travelling. I cannot form any idea of the distance; the blacks only tell that it is a great man[y] “sleeps” to the westward.’ Having been unable, he said, to follow this up himself at the time, Powell suggested that a small search party be sent out ‘to extricate this unhappy man (if he be still alive), from his hopeless captivity.</p>
               </note>Melbourne Botanic Gardens,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">February 21,1870.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am under great obligations to you, dear Mr Baird, for the interest evinced by you in Mr. Powell's communication relative to supposed new trace of Dr. Leichhardt’s party, and for the attentive kindness which prompted you to bring this gentleman's letter to you under my special notice. Undoubtedly some measure should early be adopted for ascertaining the correctness of these new tidings in reference to the missing explorers, especially as the locality assigned to the stay of the survivor is not altogether out of the direction which Dr. Leichhardt might have been compelled to adopt under adversities, more particularly in a retrogressive movement. The remotest verified traces of Dr Leichhardt exist on the Barcoo, somewhat below its junction with the Thomson River; and others again a considerable distance down on the Flinders River; and as the intervening country has been traversed by several explorers and squatters without further positions of Leichhardt being found, it is but reasonable to assume that the last party penetrated further westward. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This more western country towards Mr. Stuart's track carries with it also the interest of novelty, and therefore geographical exploration would give to searches for Leichhardt's party in that direction an additional impetus, especially as this part of the country seems promising for pastoral pursuits, for which again the increased means of transit offer more and more facilities. In our leaving the dromedaries in Queensland, we have entertained a hope that these useful creatures would, by squatters or small survey parties, be utilized to reconnoitre in manifold directions the vast prairies of Queensland, with a view to pastoral settlements; and in this work South Australia, with a territory actually stretching across the continent, would likewise have a deep interest. To give, however, at once the whole subject before us a practical and independent bearing, in order that the coming cool season may not be lost for the search, I suggest, in the cause of humanity and scientific progress, that a few of Leichhardt’s friends in these Australian colonies should unite in raising a handsome reward for any such tidings of the fate of this great explorer and his companions, as will set for ever the surmises about their fate at rest. To this reward fund I will very gladly contribute myself, and invoke the aid of the generous ladies of the Leichhardt Search Committee for rendering it an adequate inducement to an enterprising bushman to go out on this new errand of Leichhardt's supporters and friends. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Friends in other colonies should act in the same spirit; and above all the Barcoo settlers and others on the outskirts of the S.W. interior of Queensland, and the N.E. inland territory of South Australia, might so easily unite in equipping, almost without any cost under local facilities, a light party for an at least preliminary search after the supposed survivor. Of this such a party may rest assured, that their high-minded engagement would carry not only the sympathy of all Australia with it, but that also enough of generous people exist among us who would not allow any noble and successful exertions for so philanthropic an object to pass without a mark of substantial gratitude.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is a very remarkable fact that the long occupation of a post for exploration at Cooper's Creek, and its subsequent settlement, together with all the other explorations of both geographers and squatters, have not given further clues to Leichhardt's fate.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Still it must be remembered that parties travelling rapidly over a new country may pass traces of a lost party within a few yards with- out being aware of it, unless, as it would be in this instance, the natives were under special guidance interrogated. The exaggerated or contradictory, and often unfounded stories of the aborigines, have also greatly shaken our faith in their statements; yet, in a case like this, when actually a survivor of Leichhardt is said to be, after twenty-two years of suffering, in existence yet, and when he could give us at least full and reliable information on the fate of his companions, and on their discoveries and achievements, it devolves on us to adopt prompt measures for a rescue, perhaps not yet altogether too late; and it becomes our duty to take such action as will reflect honor on our patriotism, and be worthy <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of civilised states.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Trusting to hear of you again, I remain, honored Sir, your very regardful,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>FERD. VON MUELLER.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">P.S. — You are quite at liberty, dear Mr. Baird, to make public use of this letter if you deem it advisable. — F. v. M.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
