<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 6 November 1870. ¶  ¶ The troubles of the war, ¶  esteemed Professor, will have distracted your attention so much from less important events, even in geography, that for t...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1870/70-11-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>70.11.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 6 November 1870. ¶  ¶ The troubles of the war, ¶  esteemed Professor, will have distracted your attention so much from less important events, even in geography, that for t...</title>
               <date when="1870-11-06">1870-11-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1870/70-11-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Zygophyllum billardierei</term>
               <term>Pomaderris myrtilloides</term>
               <term>Pimelea microcephala</term>
               <term>Adenanthos dobsonii</term>
               <term>Eremophila scoparia</term>
               <term>Minuria leptophylla</term>
               <term>Scaevola spinescens</term>
               <term>Aster exiguifolius</term>
               <term>Disoon platycarpus</term>
               <term>Dodonaea stenozyga</term>
               <term>Geijera parviflora</term>
               <term>Styphelia hainesii</term>
               <term>Westringia rigida</term>
               <term>Myoporum deserti</term>
               <term>Aster calcareus</term>
               <term>Solanum simile</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic Garden, ¶ 6 November 1870. ¶  ¶ The troubles of the war, ¶  esteemed Professor, will have distracted your attention so much from less important events, even in geography, that for t...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">70.11.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Petermann: 'Erh. 4. Jan. 1871' [Received 4 January 1871]. For a published version of this letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 97-9.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im botan Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 6. Nov. 1870.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Kriegsunruhen, verehrter Herr Professor, werden Ihre Aufmerksamkeit so sehr von minder wichtigen Ereignissen selbst in der Geographie abgelenkt haben, dass ich seit zwei Monaten Ihnen keine weitern Mittheilungen zukommen liess. Doch da vermuthlich der Segen eines dauernden sicher begründeten Friedens seinen Einfluss von neuem wird geltend machen für die Hebung der Kenntnisse, so will ich nun meine Sendungen auch nicht länger unterbrechen u schicke ich Ihnen diesmal eine Zeichnung des Zuges von Mr Forrest längs der Bights. Es ist recht schade, dass in einem so regenvollen Jahre wie dies (das am meisten regnigte<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">verregnete?</p>
               </note> von 23 Jahren die ich hier verlebte) dieser junge Geograph nicht seinen Weg über Lake Barlee nach Eucla nahm, oder dass er nicht das Schiff einige Wochen am letztgenannten Hafen zurückhielt um einige Breitengrade nordwärts von dort ins Innere einzuschneiden. Die Vegetation von der Bight ist nach den kürzlichen Sammlungen von Forrest derjenigen vom Spencer Gulf ähnlich, nicht aber der von Südwestaustralien. So finden sich am Port Eucla: <name key="Scaevola%20spinescens">Scaevola spinescens</name>, <name key="Geijera%20parviflora">Geijera parviflora</name>, <name key="Aster%20calcareus">Aster calcareus</name>, <name key="Westringia%20rigida">Westringia rigida</name>, <name key="Solanum%20simile">Solanum simile</name>, <name key="Minuria%20leptophylla">Minuria leptophylla</name>, <name key="Disoon%20platycarpus">Disoon platycarpus</name>, <name key="Pimelea%20microcephala">Pimelea microcephala</name>, <name key="Dodonaea%20stenozyga">Dodonaea stenozyga</name>, Zygophyllum Billardierei. Am Point Dover kommen vor <name key="Pomaderris%20myrtilloides">Pomaderris myrtilloides</name>, <name key="Aster%20exiguifolius">Aster exiguifolius</name>, <name key="Eremophila%20scoparia">Eremophila scoparia</name>, Styphelia Hainesii, Adenanthos Dobsonii, <name key="Myoporum%20deserti">Myoporum deserti</name>. Einige dieser Pflanzen sind dem Kalkland der Bight eigenthümlich. Mr. Forrest hofft die Mittel für eine neue Reise diesmal von Lake Barlee nach Lake Termination zu erlangen. Ich habe ihm gerathen, meinen ersten Vorschlag anzunehmen, nämlich von dem Ursprung des Murchison Flusses nach Nordost zu Carpentaria zu steuern, denn es möchte sich leicht ereignen, dass er sich am Lake Barlee eingeengt findet in wasserlosem Lande, das ohne Kameele nicht ganz leicht zu durchschreiten wäre, während doch die lange Murchison Linie entfernte sichere Anhaltspunkte liefert.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Könnte der Glanz der deutschen Waffen nicht Preussen Colonien in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Nordafrika</hi>
               </seg> liefern?! Der ungeheure Erdtheil Afrika ist ja vom Norden her sehr unvollständig occupirt, u. der Tod Vogel's u. Beurmann´s sollte gerächt werden! Welche herrliche Colonien könnten nicht dort begründet werden für Gewürzcultur, Cacao, Kaffee u. derlei Producten, die wir jetzt aus Indien oder dem tropischen Amerika erlangen. Früher oder später wird ja doch eine Eisenbahnlinie die Wüste durchschneiden. Warum sollen die Länder nahe dem Ursitze der geistigen Cultur u. so viel näher wie Indien u. andere Tropenländer, warum sollen die nach 2000 Jahren noch länger verschlossen bleiben? u. solche Tyrannen, wie die von Wadai u. Dahomei noch immer fort die grässlichsten Menschenopfer herbeiführen?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dann hat ja <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Mittel Afrika</hi>
               </seg> seine Gebirgsländer mit kühlem Klima, zugänglich vom Nil. Kann Preussen nicht dort Ordnung, Cultur u neue Sitze für Civilisation schaffen! Ohne Colonien wird sich Deutschland nie als eine Grossmacht mit andern Staaten messen können.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets Ihr Sie Ehrender</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Würden Sie nicht diese Ideen in den Mittheilungen besprechen?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Selbstverständlich möchte ich meinen Namen nicht erwähnt haben in eine Besprechung über die Begründung deutscher Colonien jenseits des<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">der?</p>
               </note> Französischen Besitzungen in Nord Afrika. Jedenfalls sollte Territorium für mehr als eine Nation dort sein, u das kann ja nur zur höchsten Cultur führen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">6 November 1870.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The troubles of the war,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Franco-German war, 1870-1.</p>
               </note> esteemed Professor, will have distracted your attention so much from less important events, even in geography, that for the past two months I have not sent you any further communications. However, since the blessing of an enduring, securely based peace will probably advance once more its influence for the promotion of knowledge, I shall interrupt my transmissions no longer, and this time I am sending you a drawing of Mr Forrest's route along the Bight.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">John Forrest's exploring expedition along the Great Australian Bight, 1870.</p>
               </note> It is a great pity, that in such a rainy year as this (with the highest rainfall in the 23 years that I have spent here), this young geographer did not make his way to Eucla via Lake Barlee,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to A. Petermann, 6 September 1869 (in this edition as <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>69-08-06b).</p>
               </note> or that he did not delay the ship in this latter harbour for a few weeks, in order to travel inland from there for a few degrees of latitude northwards. The vegetation at the Bight, according to Forrest's recent collections, resembles that of Spencer's Gulf but not that of south-west Australia. Thus we find at Port Eucla: <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Scaevola%20spinescens">Scaevola spinescens</name>, <name key="Geijera%20parviflora">Geijera parviflora</name>, <name key="Aster%20calcareus">Aster calcareus</name>, <name key="Westringia%20rigida">Westringia rigida</name>, <name key="Solanum%20simile">Solanum simile</name>, <name key="Minuria%20leptophylla">Minuria leptophylla</name>, <name key="Disoon%20platycarpus">Disoon platycarpus</name>, <name key="Pimelea%20microcephala">Pimelea microcephala</name>, <name key="Dodonaea%20stenozyga">Dodonaea stenozyga</name>, <name key="Zygophyllum%20billardierei">Zygophyllum billardierei</name>
               </seg>. At Point Dover are found <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Pomaderris%20myrtilloides">Pomaderris myrtilloides</name>, <name key="Aster%20exiguifolius">Aster exiguifolius</name>, <name key="Eremophila%20scoparia">Eremophila scoparia</name>, <name key="Styphelia%20hainesii">Styphelia hainesii</name>, <name key="Adenanthos%20dobsonii">Adenanthos dobsonii</name>, <name key="Myoporum%20deserti">Myoporum deserti</name>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Myoporum%20deserti">Myoporum deserti</name>i</seg>?</p>
               </note> A few of these plants are peculiar to the calcareous country at the Bight. Mr Forrest hopes to obtain the means for a new expedition, this time from Lake Barlee to reach to Lake Termination. I have advised him to accept my first proposition, which was to travel from the source of the Murchison River in a north-easterly direction to the Gulf of Carpentaria, for it might easily happen, that he finds himself stranded at Lake Barlee in waterless country, which is not very easily traversed without camels, while the long Murchison line provides distant secure points of reference.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lake Termination does not appear on modern maps but was the name given to the system of salt lakes, now known as Lake Gregory, at the furthest inland point reached by Gregory and M in 1856.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Could not the splendour of German arms obtain colonies for Prussia in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">North Africa</hi>
               </seg>?! The vast continent of Africa has been only very incompletely occupied from the North, and the deaths of Vogel and Beurmann<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Eduard Vogel and Moritz Beurmann were both killed by local tribesmen while exploring the Sahara.</p>
               </note> should be avenged! What glorious colonies could be founded there for the cultivation of spices, cacao, coffee, and similar products, which we now acquire from India or tropical America. Sooner or later a railway line will cross the desert. Why should the countries so near the source of intellectual culture, and so much closer than India or other tropical lands, why should they continue to remain closed after 2,000 years? — and why should <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>such tyrants as those in Wadai and Dahomey still continue to bring about the most dreadful sacrifice of <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>human lives?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Central Africa</hi>
               </seg>, of course, has its mountainous areas with a cool climate, accessible from the Nile. Could not Prussia create order there, and culture, and new centres of civilization?! Without colonies Germany will never be able to stand comparison as a great power with other nations.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Could you not discuss these notes in your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen</seg>?<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No discussion on this subject has been found in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen aus Justus Perthes' geographischer Anstalt</seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It goes without saying, that I do not wish to have my name mentioned in any discussion about the founding of German colonies beyond the French territories in North Africa. In any case, there should be enough territory for more than one nation, and that can indeed only lead to the highest culture.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Adenanthos%20dobsonii">Adenanthos dobsonii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Aster%20calcareus">Aster calcareus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Aster%20exiguifolius">Aster exiguifolius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Disoon%20platycarpus">Disoon platycarpus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dodonaea%20stenozyga">Dodonaea stenozyga</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eremophila%20scoparia">Eremophila scoparia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Geijera%20parviflora">Geijera parviflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Minuria%20leptophylla">Minuria leptophylla</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myoporum%20deserti">Myoporum deserti</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20microcephala">Pimelea microcephala</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pomaderris%20myrtilloides">Pomaderris myrtilloides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Scaevola%20spinescens">Scaevola spinescens</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Solanum%20simile">Solanum simile</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Styphelia%20hainesii">Styphelia hainesii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Westringia%20rigida">Westringia rigida</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Zygophyllum%20billardierei">Zygophyllum billardierei</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
