<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ I have recommended for the Search Expedition only such measures as, away from any party interests and any individual wishes, would accomplish the great object of gaining tidings of Leichhardt, and ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-02-00b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.02.00b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ I have recommended for the Search Expedition only such measures as, away from any party interests and any individual wishes, would accomplish the great object of gaining tidings of Leichhardt, and ...</title>
               <date when="1867-02">1867-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-02-00b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Samuel Mee</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ I have recommended for the Search Expedition only such measures as, away from any party interests and any individual wishes, would accomplish the great object of gaining tidings of Leichhardt, and ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">67.02.00b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Samuel Mee</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg>, 12 March 1867, p. 3, an article headed Leichhardt Search Expedition (B67.03.01). The article begins with a letter to the editor signed L., that commences: Sir,— Observing, in your issue of Saturday last, a leading article on the above subject, I am prompted to send you, for publication, the following extracts from a letter just received from Dr. Mueller, of Melbourne. … The allusion to Mr. Davies refers to a suggestion conveyed to Dr. Mueller that the employment, as interrogator and interpreter, of one so skilled in the aboriginal dialects as "the Duramboy" is known to be, would be likely to prove of great service to the Expedition.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter was also published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Empire</seg> (Sydney), 19 March 1867, p. 3 (B67.03.02).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An extract from Ms letter was published many years later in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg> in an article by Mee, Recollections of "Durramboi" (see B89.06.03). From this, we learn the addressee and approximate date of Ms letter. In his article, Mee is remembering the search for Ludwig Leichhardt by the Ladies Leichhardt Search Expedition in 1865-6. Mee reports receiving a letter from M before the expedition (see M to S. Mee, 1865 (in this edition as 65-00-00b)) and in February 1867 receiving another letter: This was after the death of the first leader of the expedition (Mr MIntyre).</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have recommended for the Search Expedition only such measures as, away from any party interests and any individual wishes, would accomplish the great object of gaining tidings of Leichhardt, and of fulfilling what he intended. This I am bound to do by Christianity, by obligation to science, and by my special oath as a physician. I am still most eager to render the search as effectual as possible; and had the party been formed in Brisbane, great facilities would have existed for attaching Mr. Davies<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>James Davis (Durramboi).</p>
               </note> to the expedition. His services as interpreter among some of the tribes would be likely to prove of the greatest possible importance. …<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ellipsis in source text.</p>
               </note> The hand of death having removed from us the gallant man to whom the enterprise was entrusted in the first instance,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. Duncan McIntyre.</p>
               </note> it has left us only shattered means to redeem our promise to the supporters of the enterprise, for a two years search; and any extra expenditure to be incurred by sending special members from distant localities to the field of action were altogether beyond our reach.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I expressed, however, publicly, a hope that, at the termination of the present enterprise, its continuance would become an object of active and united measures of Queensland, New South Wales, Victoria, South Australia, and West Australia;—for all these colonies are industrially and commercially interested in the occupation of the interior, to which further geographical researches will so much tend. It is unnecessary that such expenditure should be a heavy one; from £200 to £300 annually from each colony would maintain a party, already organized, trained, and moreover still provided with camels, in the field; but we should guard against the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">disbanding</seg> of the expedition, because a renewal from absolutely new elements would be very costly. This new support will be needed in the latter part of the year; and nothing would give me greater gratification, should new measures be carried out, than to see secured Mr. Davies aid and actual services; and I am quite persuaded that the ladies who have so thoughtfully directed the enterprise, will be most willing to cause to be carried into effect any wishes for the furtherance of the enterprise expressed in a colony which so generously and gracefully has come to the succour of the present expedition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a sum between £900 and £1100 a small yet efficient party, once formed, may be maintained. Such outlay will entirely be spent in Australia. It will, if continued but for a few years, cause the whole of the western half of the continent to be mapped, and disclose its leading features for settlement. West Australia is likely to bear its share, by strengthening its future pastoral explorers by the introduction of dromedaries from Aden; and thus the support of movements from the north or east would devolve on the four eastern colonies.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meanwhile the ladies have directed their party to the south-west from Carpentaria; and I should not at all be surprised if we hear of their arrival in the settlement of Nichol Bay,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>WA.</p>
               </note> or even further south, before the next hot season sets in.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In his article, Mee adds: On receipt of the letter … I again called upon Mr. Davis, and read it to him. He seemed highly delighted with the Barons kind allusions to and appreciation of, his proffered services. Davis did not, however, join the expedition, for the reason given in Ms letter.</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
