<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 29 January 1867. ¶ Excellency, ¶  ¶ A few days ago I was most pleasantly surprised to see Mrs Smillie back once more in this country, a surprise that was all the greater, a...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-01-29-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Bundesarchiv, Koblenz.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.01.29</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 29 January 1867. ¶ Excellency, ¶  ¶ A few days ago I was most pleasantly surprised to see Mrs Smillie back once more in this country, a surprise that was all the greater, a...</title>
               <date when="1867-01-29">1867-01-29</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-01-29-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Macarthuria neocambrica</term>
               <term>Molluginaceae</term>
               <term>Macarthuria</term>
               <term>Marianthus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Hügel</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 29 January 1867. ¶ Excellency, ¶  ¶ A few days ago I was most pleasantly surprised to see Mrs Smillie back once more in this country, a surprise that was all the greater, a...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">67.01.29</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Hügel</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Bundesarchiv, Koblenz.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope front: 'Seiner Excellenz dem Baron | Carl von Huegel, Grosskreuz | u Commandeur hoher Orden, | kaiserl. österreich. Gesandter am | Hofe | zu | Brüssel. | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Ferd. Mueller, M.D., FRS</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">.</seg>' [To His Excellency Baron Carl von Huegel, Grand Cross and Commander of high Orders, Imperial Austrian Ambassador at the Court of Brussels].</p>
               </note>Melbourne im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 29. Januar 1867.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Excellenz!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vor wenigen Tagen wurde ich aufs Angenehmste dadurch überrascht, dass ich Mrs Smillie wieder in diesem Lande sah, eine Überraschung die um so grösser war, als ich nicht einmal von der Absicht dieser Dame wusste, zu uns in den Süden zurückzukehren. Meine leidende Schwester, seitdem dahin geschieden, hatte eine höchst-gütige Aufnahme im Smillie'schen Hause in Süd-Australien, u das hat in mir eine dankbare Erinnerung an die Familie wach gehalten. Bei meinem Besuch zu der Mad. Smillie, welche gerade jetzt ihren Aufenthalt bei einer Schwester hat, wurde Ihrer, Herr Baron, sogleich gedacht, u. es war für mich ein glücklicher Augenblick in deutscher Sprache von den Töchtern der Dame meine Aufmerksamkeit auf ein Bild Ihrer Exzellenz hingelenkt zu sehen, ein Bild das ich mit Verehrung betrachtete u auf das Ihre Verwandten wahrhaft stolz sind. Ich erbat mir die Erlaubniss einem Briefe an Sie einige Worte beifügen zu dürfen. Ich fühlte den Drang, Herr Baron, Ihnen zu sagen, dass während der Jahre 1840-46 mich die Schilderungen der Vegetations Australiens von Ihnen so erregten zu einer Zeit, wie ich die phytologische Untersuchung des südwestlichen Schleswig kaum den Knabenjahren entwachsen vornahm, dass ich mich im Jahr 1847 diesem südlichen Continente zuwandte, wie ich ein wärmeres Klima für die Schwester zu suchen hatte. Sie, Exzellenz, haben mich daher hier in meine Bahn gezogen, nachdem die geistreichen u anmuthigen Ergüsse von dem grossen Humboldt, von meinem edlen Freunde v. Martius u von Darwin, dem ich mit Schmerz in seiner Transmutations Theorie entgegengetreten, mich zum Forschen in entlegnen Weltgegenden begeistert hatten. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihre</hi>
               </seg> Schriften, Exzellenz, gaben die Entscheidung! Es wurde nun mein Lebensplan ein Universalwerk über die Pflanzen Australiens (das freilich nicht einmal Europa besitzt) zu entwerfen u nachdem ich 25000 Meilen für diesen Zweck hier reiste u die grösste Pflanzensammlung der Erde in Bezug auf Australien zusammen brachte (etwa 160,000 Pflanzen), ist es möglich geworden eine Reihe unabhängiger Bände hier zu veröffentlichen u mit unserem gemeinsamen Freunde Bentham verbunden die "Flora Australiens" zu liefern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich glaubte, edler Mann, diese Mittheilung möge Ihnen eine Stunde grosser Genugthuung bereiten, wenn <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> auf jene Zeit der Mühen zurückblicken, wie Sie in aufopferndem geistigen Schwunge den Gefahren u Beschwerden in diesem Erdtheil entgegen gingen, zu einer Zeit wie ich ein ganz kleiner Knabe war, bald nachher ein armes Waisenkind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit 1847 habe ich Ihre enumeratio in fast täglichen Gelegenheiten berathen und wie hat sich seit jener Zeit unsere Kenntniss des Australlandes erweitert! Selbst helfend stets seit jener Zeit wie hat sich die Landkarte Australiens ausgefüllt! Ihr liebliches Genus <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name> umfasst jetzt 17 Arten u. Ihre <name key="Macarthuria">Macarthuria</name>, der ich zuerst die Stellung unter den Molugineen zuwiess, hat jetzt auch ihre Vertreterin in einer östlichen Art, meiner <name key="Macarthuria">Macarthuria</name> Neo-Cambrica, die ich im 5. Bande meiner Fragmenta phytographiae <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Australiae beschrieben habe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist indessen nicht meine Absicht, verehrter Herr Baron, als Eindringling zu erscheinen u so in Einzelnes einzugehen. Es war nur mein Wunsch, Ihnen den Gruss tiefster Demuth-vollster Ergebenheit darzubringen u daran den Wunsch zu knüpfen, dass es mir gestattet sei, die Tage, die schönen Herbsttage eines thatenvollen u. ehrenreichen Lebens durch das gelegentliche Einstreuen von ein paar Blumen verschönen zu dürfen. Kann ich dies, o! so gebieten Sie, edler Herr, unzögernd über meine Dienste.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">In tiefster Ehrerbietung</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">29 January 1867.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Excellency,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A few days ago I was most pleasantly surprised to see Mrs Smillie back once more in this country, a surprise that was all the greater, as I had not known even of the intention of this lady to return to us here in the South. My suffering sister, since departed,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha Doughty, née Müller, died on 7 September 1861.</p>
               </note> found a most kind reception in the Smillie household in South Australia, and because of this I remember the family with gratitude. During my visit with Mad. Smillie, who is at the moment staying with a sister, we immediately thought of you, Baron, and it was a happy moment for me, to have my attention drawn in the German language by the lady's daughters to a picture of Your Excellency, a picture, on which I gazed with veneration and of which your relatives are truly proud. I asked for permission, that I might add a few words to a letter to you. I feel compelled, dear Baron, to tell you that during the years 1840-46 the descriptions of the Australian vegetation by you<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hügel's plants were described in Endlicher <seg style="font-style: italic; ">et al.</seg>(1837).</p>
               </note> excited me so much at a time when, barely past boyhood, I undertook the phytological exploration of south-western Schleswig, that in 1847 I turned towards this southern continent, when I had to find a warmer climate for my sister.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bertha Müller, who already then was showing signs of the tuberculosis that eventually killed her.</p>
               </note> You, Excellency, have therefore drawn me here into my path, after the ingenious and charming outpourings of the great Humboldt, of my noble friend von Martius, and of Darwin,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">There were various multi-volume editions of Humboldt's travels, for example Humboldt (1805-34), as well as numerous abbreviated editions, including some in German; <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>C. Martius (1821-31); Darwin (1839), a German edition of which was published in Braunschweig in 1844. See Freeman (1977).</p>
               </note> whom I opposed with sadness in his transmutation theory, had enthused me to explore distant parts of the world. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Your</hi>
               </seg> writings, Excellency, were the deciding factor! It now became my life's plan, to draw up a universal work on the plants of Australia, and after having travelled over 25,000 miles here for this purpose and brought together the largest collection of plants in the world as regards Australia (approximately 160,000 plants), it has become possible to publish a number of independent volumes here and, combined with our mutual friend Bentham, to deliver the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora of Australia.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I thought, noble Sir, these communications might give <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> an hour's gratification, when you look back on that time of toil, when <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> went out to meet the dangers and difficulties in this continent<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Hügel visited Australia in 1833-4. See Huegel (1994).</p>
               </note> with dedicated mental ardour at a time, when I still was a very small boy, and soon afterwards a poor orphan.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since 1847 I consulted your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Enumeratio</seg> on an almost daily basis,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. Endlicher <seg style="font-style: italic; ">et al. </seg>(1837).</p>
               </note> and how has our knowledge of Australia expanded since that time! — and how the map of Australia has been filled in since that time, always without assistance! Your lovely genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name>
               </seg> now comprises 17 species, and I was the first to place your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Macarthuria">Macarthuria</name>
               </seg> among the <name key="Molluginaceae">Molluginaceae</name>, where it now has a representative in an eastern species, my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Macarthuria">Macarthuria</name> neo-cambrica</seg>, which I described in the fifth volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B65.06.02, p. 28.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is, however, not my intention, esteemed Baron, to appear as an intruder and go into detail. It was only my desire, to offer you a greeting with my most humble devotion, and to attach to it the wish, that I may be permitted to embellish the days, the beautiful autumn days of an active and honourable life by the occasional scattering of a few flowers. May I do so, O noble Sir, command my services without hesitation.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With deepest respect</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Macarthuria">Macarthuria</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Macarthuria">Macarthuria</name> neo-cambrica</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Molluginaceae">Molluginaceae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
