<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne bot Garden, ¶ 23/2/67 ¶  ¶ Allow me, honored and dear Sir, to send you some seeds of a very superior forage lentil of China, which will prove a valuable acquisition wherever it goes. Is the ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-02-23a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Colonial Secretary's Office - letters received, acc. 36, vol. 589, ff. 67-8, State Records Office of Western Australia, Perth.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.02.23a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne bot Garden, ¶ 23/2/67 ¶  ¶ Allow me, honored and dear Sir, to send you some seeds of a very superior forage lentil of China, which will prove a valuable acquisition wherever it goes. Is the ...</title>
               <date when="1867-02-23">1867-02-23</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-02-23a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/a1562570-aa17-4483-a8cb-47e71fe8e2f1">Bromus unioloides</term>
               <term>Bromus Schraderi</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d9d593f3-cf3a-4cd0-8346-da90200383ad">Xanthorrhoea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Frederick Barlee</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne bot Garden, ¶ 23/2/67 ¶  ¶ Allow me, honored and dear Sir, to send you some seeds of a very superior forage lentil of China, which will prove a valuable acquisition wherever it goes. Is the ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">67.02.23a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Frederick Barlee</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">Colonial Secretary's Office - letters received, acc. 36, vol. 589, ff. 67-8, State Records Office of Western Australia, Perth.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne bot Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">23/2/67</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Allow me, honored and dear Sir, to send you some seeds of a very superior forage lentil of China, which will prove a valuable acquisition wherever it goes. Is the <name key="Bromus%20unioloides">Bromus unioloides</name> (or <name key="Bromus%20Schraderi">Bromus Schraderi</name> or Californian Prairie Grass) in your colony. If not I can well send it. The xanthorrhoea resins &amp;c received from Consul Were shall be carefully examined in my laboratory. It is a somewhat tedious operation, which the other duties connected with the Exhibition<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Intercolonial Exhibition, Melbourne, 1866-7.</p>
               </note> have prevented me from entering on as yet The Ladies Leichhardt Search Expedition is now advancing towards your territory &amp; I boast it will not only attain its great object, but also serve your interest in opening communications with the northern settlements &amp; mapping part of your country.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Enclosed with MS is a clipping from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg> (Melbourne), 22 February 1867, p. 5, headed ‘The Search for Leichardt’. The first part of this article is a report of actions taken during the Ladies' Leichhardt Search Expedition following the death of the leader of the expedition, Duncan McIntyre, and his deputy William Sloman who was appointed to succeed him. It begins with a quotation from a letter of William Landsborough (addressee not stated, but likely to be M), from the Burke settlement, Gulf of Carpentaria (Qld), and adds details of the health and plans of the party that may be drawn from Landsborough's letter. This is followed by text that may be summarizing information given in letters written by Duncan McIntyre's brother Donald to Donald Campbell and M (see Donald McIntyre to M, December 1866 (in this edition as 66-12-00d), and then a summary of a letter written by Donald McIntyre from Dalgannally station (Qld) on 22 December 1866, the addressee of which is not given, In which McIntyre expresses sorrow at the death of William Sloman, and is quoted as saying that 'Mr Barnett will start from his camp in a few days, fully equipped for the contract time', and that 'a female camel died a few days ago from the effects of a snake bite'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The remainder of the article, which is clearly separated from the earlier part and its addressee identified in an otherwise equivalent report in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Herald</seg> (Melbourne), 22 February 1867, p. 3, is a letter from W. F. Barnett to the Ladies’ Leichhardt Search Committee, as follows:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Camp, Ladies' Leichhardt Search Party, Julia Creek, Carpentaria, 21st December, 1866. — To the Committee, Ladies' Leichhardt Search Expedition. — Ladies, — I have the honor to inform you that in consequence of the death of Mr W. T. Sloman, the late leader of the expedition, Mr Donald M'Intyre has appointed me for that position, which appointment, I trust, will meet your gracious approval. Mr Sloman followed several of the Gulf waters, but did not succeed in discovering any further traces of Leichhardt. It was on his return near the junction of the Alexander and Leitchhardt [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">sic</seg>] rivers, that, according to Dr. White's report, a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">coup de soleil</seg>, acting upon an organic disease of the heart, caused his death in a few hours. Mr Donald M'Intyre has already communicated to his family this sad loss. I intend to follow out, so far as I know and am able, the intentions of our late gallant and much to be lamented leader Duncan M'Intyre, deeming those to be the best to find traces of Leichhardt. But to complete the search I shall not have time, unless some unforeseen and happy discovery should take place <seg style="font-style: italic; ">en route</seg>. I beg to report the death of a female camel, caused by the bite of a snake. This is unfortunate; but for accidents of this kind there is no help. Also I may inform you of the birth of four young ones, who are doing well. This country is admirable for these valuable animals, there being an abundance of the food they are most fond of. It is with pleasure that I beg to inform you that the camels and horses are in splendid condition, which reflects much credit upon those who have had the charge of them; in fact all the properties of the expedition are very complete ad in good order. The services of Dr. White will be a great boon to the party, especially as by his kind and unassuming manners he has gained the confidence of us all. Mr M'Calman will also accompany us, whose services will be of much advantage, as knowing him of old, I can entirely depend anything that is given him to do will be done well. There has been plenty of rain and the country is in splendid condition, I do not fear for the want of water during my intended journey. Indeed, I may be troubled with too much of it, as it is impossible to travel this country for several days after storms, and these we may expect at this season of the year. I hope to be starting very shortly, and be assured, ladies, I shall use my utmost endeavors to gain your favor by fulfilling the trust reposed in me. Sincerely wishing to be able ere long to send you the news of some pleasing discovery. Your obedient servant,</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5909in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>(Signed) W. FRED. BARNETT.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Let me remain,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>dear Mr Barlee,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your regardful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Pray recommend me to the friendly remembrance of Governor Hampden<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Governor of WA at the time was J. S. Hampton. MS annotation by Barlee: 'Answd private note | F.P.B. | 15:3:67.' Letter not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>has Mr Hunt brought no botanical specimens from his Expedition?<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Note by M on a separate sheet.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Bromus%20Schraderi">Bromus Schraderi</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Bromus%20unioloides">Bromus unioloides</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
