<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queenscliff, 27 August 1867. ¶  ¶ Today, noble patron and friend, my letter brings you among other news also some harsh and sad tidings. Your famous, kind nephew Dr F. Bayer, recently still full of vi...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-08-27-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.08.27</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Queenscliff, 27 August 1867. ¶  ¶ Today, noble patron and friend, my letter brings you among other news also some harsh and sad tidings. Your famous, kind nephew Dr F. Bayer, recently still full of vi...</title>
               <date when="1867-08-27">1867-08-27</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-08-27-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Casuarina quadrivalvis</term>
               <term>Cinchona condaminea</term>
               <term>Acacia mollissima </term>
               <term>Casuarina suberosa</term>
               <term>Casuarina glauca</term>
               <term>Cakile maritime</term>
               <term>Anguillaria </term>
               <term>Oligarrhena </term>
               <term>Pentachondra</term>
               <term>Andersonia </term>
               <term>Sprengelia</term>
               <term>Styphelia </term>
               <term>Cystanthe</term>
               <term>Decaspora</term>
               <term>Needhamea</term>
               <term>Richea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Queenscliff, 27 August 1867. ¶  ¶ Today, noble patron and friend, my letter brings you among other news also some harsh and sad tidings. Your famous, kind nephew Dr F. Bayer, recently still full of vi...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">67.08.27</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Martius: 'praes. 22. Oct. 1867' [received 22 October 1867].</p>
               </note>Queenscliff, 27/8/67.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Heute, edler Gönner und Freund, bringt Ihnen mein Brief gleichzeitig mit anderen eine herbe Trauerbotschaft. Ihr berühmter, jüngst noch lebenskräftiger, gütiger Neffe, Dr. F. Bayer lebt nicht mehr! Sein Hinscheiden ist ein Verlust gleich unersetzlich einem weiten Kreise von Freunden, unberechnungsbar für die aufblühende Colonie, in der dieser grosse Arzt fast zwanzig Jahr lang wirkte. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Mir</hi>
               </seg> kam die plötzliche Todesnachricht nicht ganz unerwartet. Dr Bayer besuchte vor wenigen Monaten Melbourne, und ein Blick auf das leidende Äussere genügte mir zur Überzeugung, dass seine Lebensfrist, bliebe er im Zwang der ärztlichen Praxis, eine ganz kurze sein müsse. Ich verhehlte ihm meine Ansicht nicht, und wurde in derselben nur bestärkt, wie mir der Arme eine Reihe Symptome angab, die auf fast gänzlich erschöpfte Nervenkraft hindeuteten. Ich beschwor ihn, seinem edlen Beruf nicht sein Leben zu opfern, und bat scheidend seine Gemahlin, ihn wenigstens jedes Jahr für einen Monat Wald- oder Bergreisen unternehmen zu lassen. Meine Furcht war aber nicht, dass er in den kühlen erfrischenden Lüften unserer herrlichen Wintermonate hinsinken würde, aber mir bangte, er würde den nächsten Sommer nicht durchleben in einer enormen rastlosen ärztlichen Thätigkeit; und da der gute Mann mich wenige Wochen vor seinem Tode noch einlud in seinem letzten Brief, seine Gastfreundlichkeit in Adelaide zu geniessen, so dachte ich zeitig im Sommer hinüber zu gehen, und ihn in die Bergwälder und in die mit Farnbäumen beschatteten Thäler Tasmaniens sich erholen zu lassen, wo ich ihm die Erholung durch physikalische Demonstrationen noch vielleicht anziehender gemacht haben würde. Der Mensch denkt, Gott lenkt! — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unbezweifelbar war es Dr Bayer's Absicht so lange in der Praxis zu verharren, bis sein jetzt studierender Sohn die grossen Arbeiten des Vaters jugendfrisch und unter dessen Lenkung fortführen könne. Ich führte Dr Bayer bei seinem Hiersein im März bei dem Gouverneur u dessen Gemahlin ein, aber war betrübt, dass er nicht die ländliche Stille für Erholung gewählt. Wir können den Mann, den Freund, den Arzt nicht ersetzen. Wie schade, dass er, der mit Glücksgütern reich gesegnet, der eine blühende Familie heranwachsen sah, u der sich der Achtung u Liebe aller Colonisten bewusst war, nicht in Ruhe einen langen Lebensabend durchleben konnte! </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich selbst bin hierher geflüchtet, um aus den Wirren u. Gelärm des grossen Departements, das ich schuf, herauszukommen für eine Weile, nachdem ich seit 1862 nicht einen Tag fort gewesen. Mein Schlaf war dahin, so mein Begehr für Nahrung. Hier im Anblick des majestätischen Oceans legt sich der Sturm des Gemüths, ich sammle mich für ruhigeres Denken u sehe wieder mit neuen Hoffnungen, die schon erloschen, in die Zukunft.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Anguillarien, die durch die grünen Matten der Frühlingsfrische brechen, erinnern mich an meine Kindheit, an die Schneeglöckchen unserer Wiesen. Die Boten der wiederkehrenden Vegetation brechen hervor in grossblumigem Sonnenthau; und Cakile maritima hier im Küstensande lässt mich glauben, ich wanderte wiederum an den sturmumtobten Küsten Scandinaviens. Ich werde aber auch mit der Wiederkehr der Frühlingsblumen, die Schiller so herrlich in seiner poetischen Allegorie besang, an dies gemahnt, dass ich ein Jahr näher dem Ende meiner Lebensbahn gerückt, u für das Wirken dieses Jahres dem Lenker der Welten Rechenschaft zu geben. Wie eitel ist uns mehr u mehr mit hineilenden Jahren der Tand werthloser Vergnügungen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Wahrheit von des befreundeten Owen's Worten wird auch hierüber mir mehr u mehr klar. Der Rausch der Vergnügungen, die nicht wirkliche Erholungen sind weder für Geist noch Körper, hat manchen schon frühzeitig hinsinken lassen. Wir müssen versuchen, die Gedanken der grossen Menge mehr u mehr auf die Wunder der Natur zu lenken, ihr grosses Gotteswalten im freien Anblick empfinden lassen. Innerhalb 16 deutscher Meilen erhebt sich hier ein Alpenhang (Baw-Baw), den ich zuerst erstieg, untersuchte u triangulirte. Ich will für Maulthiere einen Weg dahin durch die Bergwälder brechen lassen u ein Brackenhaus dort zu bauen anrathen, wohin für <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wahre</hi>
               </seg> Erfrischung unsere Stadtbewohner eilen können, um dem Basaltstaube, der Hitze u den Miasmen, ja und dann auch den Wirren der Stadt zu entgehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>"Kennst du den Berg mit seinem Wolkensteg?, das Maulthier sucht im Nebel seinen Weg. Dahin! Dahin! möcht ich mit dir, o mein Geliebter, ziehn!"</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Jetzt, wo ich diesen Brief schliesse, wandle ich wieder eine Stunde an den Klippen entlang. Ich nehme Samen der <name key="Casuarina%20suberosa">Casuarina suberosa</name>, der schönsten von Allen, von <name key="Casuarina%20quadrivalvis">Casuarina quadrivalvis</name> u. <name key="Acacia%20mollissima%20">Acacia mollissima </name>zum Ausstreuen mit, um waldiges Grün an den schroffen Felsabhängen und den Sandwellen mit Geschwindigkeit entstehen zu lassen! Der Kaiser Napoleon hat mir in einem eigenhändigen Schreiben seinen Beifall ausgesprochen, auch in der Sahara diese dem Sirocco widerstehenden Bäume, hervorzurufen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe die so wunderbaren Casuarinen alle jüngst auf ihre wahren Grenzen zurückgeführt. Es giebt davon in Australien 14; einige wie C. glauca wandern von der Ost zu Westküste. <seg style="">Eine Zwergart von Westaustralien blüht massenhaft, wenn bloss 1½ Zoll hoch im ersten Jahre schon! </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>Wenn ich nicht im Freien bin, arbeite ich hier für unsern genialen u unermüdlichen Freund Bentham an Epacrideen. Seit R Br's Zeit sind die Arten an Zahl verdreifacht u so die einstmaligen Gattungsmerkmale nicht mehr haltbar. Ich stelle das Genus <name key="Styphelia%20">Styphelia </name>im weitern Sinne her, <name key="Decaspora">Decaspora</name> bleibt mit <name key="Pentachondra">Pentachondra</name> vereint, <name key="Needhamea">Needhamea</name> u. <name key="Oligarrhena%20">Oligarrhena </name>bleiben. <name key="Andersonia%20">Andersonia </name>kommt zu <name key="Sprengelia">Sprengelia</name>, <name key="Cystanthe">Cystanthe</name> zu <name key="Richea">Richea</name> &amp;c. Sie werden bald meine Ansicht veröffentlicht finden. Den 5ten Band der Fragmenta, der diesen Weg anbahnte, ist unlängst an Ihre ehrwürdige Akademie gesandt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meine Krankheit hat es verhindert eine Sendung an Sie zu vollenden. Es soll eine meiner ersten Handlungen sein, nach der Rückkehr mein Versprechen zu lösen. Möge die Vorsehung Sie in gnädigen Schutz nehmen u Sie noch lange zum Segen des Wissens erhalten.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich sammele für Agassiz die Frischwasserfische u habe ihm das Versprechen abgelockt, eine Ichtologie Australiens zu liefern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe Cinchona Condominea hier im Freien überwintert und nun gegen 10,000 Pflanzen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Queenscliff, 27 August 1867.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Today, noble patron and friend, my letter brings you among other news also some harsh and sad tidings. Your famous, kind nephew Dr F. Bayer, recently still full of vitality, is no longer alive! His passing is a loss equally irreplaceable for a large circle of friends, as it is incalculable for the flourishing Colony, where this great doctor has been labouring for almost 20 years. To <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">me</hi>
               </seg> the sudden news of his death did not come quite unexpected. Dr Bayer visited Melbourne a few months ago, and one glance at his suffering appearance sufficed to convince me that, were he to remain under the burden of his medical practice, the span of life remaining to him would be but a very short one. I did not keep my views from him, and was only confirmed in them, when the poor man described to me a number of his symptoms, that indicated a totally exhausted nervous system. I implored him, not to sacrifice his life to his noble profession and, when saying farewell, asked his wife to at least make him undertake each year a month's journey into forests or mountains. But my fear was not that he might die in the cool refreshing air of our glorious winter months, but I feared he might not survive the next summer in his enormous restless medical activity. As the good man invited me in his last letter<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> only a few weeks before his death to accept his hospitality in Adelaide, I intended to go over there early in summer, and to get him into the mountain forests and the shaded fern gullies of Tasmania to recover, where I might perhaps have made the recovery more attractive by physical demonstrations. Man proposes, God disposes!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It was undoubtedly Dr Bayer's intention, to remain in his practice, until his son, still studying, could have carried on his father's great work with youthful vigour and under his guidance. During his visit here I introduced Dr Bayer to the Governor and his wife, but was distressed, that he had not chosen rural tranquillity to recover. We can not replace the man, the friend, or the doctor. What a shame that he, who was so richly blessed with all the good things in life, who saw a radiant family grow up, who enjoyed the respect and affection of all the colonists, could not live on in peace through a long old age!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I myself have fled here, to get out for a while of the pressures and clamour of the large Department that I created, after not having had a day's break since 1862. My sleep was gone, as was my desire for food. Here, facing the majestic ocean, the storm of the emotions quietens down, I can collect myself for calmer thoughts and once more look to the future with hopes, that had already been extinguished, now once more renewed.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Anguillaria</seg> breaking through the spring-fresh green meadows remind me of my childhood and the snowdrops in our pastures. The heralds of the new vegetation break forth in large flowered sundews, and the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cakile maritima</seg> in the coastal sands here make me think, that I am wandering once more on the storm-swept coasts of Scandinavia. However, the return of the spring flowers, so wonderfully extolled by Schiller in his poetic allegory,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not identified.</p>
               </note> also warns me, that I have come another year closer to the end of my life, and that I shall have to give an account of this year to the Ruler of the universe. How vain the tinsel of useless pleasures becomes for us increasingly with the fleeting years!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Here, too, I come to see more and more clearly the truth of my friend Owen's words. The euphoria of pleasures, that are no real relaxation for either mind or body, has sent many a man to an early grave. We must try to direct the minds of the masses more and more to the wonders of nature, to experience the mighty works of God in her contemplation. Sixteen German miles<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">One German mile = 4.6 English miles or 7.35 km approximately.</p>
               </note> from here rises an alpine elevation (the Baw-Baws); I was the first to climb it, explore and triangulate it. I want to get a path for mules cleared to there through the mountain forests, and to suggest a lodge be built there, where our city dweller can hasten for <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">true</hi>
               </seg> refreshment, to escape from the basalt dust, the heat, the miasma, and yes, also the pressures of the city.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'Do you know the mountain with its cloudy pass?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The mule seeks its path through the fog.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>There! There I want to go with you,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>O my beloved!'<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An adaptation from Goethe's poem 'Mignon' (the first two lines of the third verse and the refrain of the first verse).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now, when I close this letter, I am going to walk again for an hour along the cliffs. I take seed of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Casuarina%20suberosa">Casuarina suberosa</name>
               </seg>, the most beautiful of them all, of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Casuarina%20quadrivalvis">Casuarina quadrivalvis</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Acacia mollissima</seg> along with me for sprinkling about, to create rapidly green forests along the steep cliff slopes and sand dunes. The emperor Napoleon, in a letter in his own hand,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. The letter and its context is mentioned in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin de la Société zoologique d'acclimatation</seg>, Series 2, vol. 4, 1867, pp. 163-6. Prospero Ramel and Edward Wilson are reported as receiving the same letter.</p>
               </note> has expressed his approval of raising these sirocco-tolerant trees also in the Sahara.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to J. Haast, 25 August 1864.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have recently reduced all these wonderful Casuarinas to their true limits. There are 14 species in Australia; some, like <seg style="font-style: italic; ">C. glauca</seg>, extend from the East to the West coast. A dwarf species from Western Australia flowers prolifically already in the first year, when only 1½ inches high!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When I am not outdoors, I work here on the Epacrids for our genial and tireless friend Bentham. Since Robert Brown's time the number of species has tripled and as a result the generic distinctions from then are no longer tenable.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">R. Brown (1810) has most of his epacrid descriptions.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I restore the genus <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Styphelia</seg> in its wider sense. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Decaspora">Decaspora</name>
               </seg> remains united with <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Pentachondra">Pentachondra</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Needhamea">Needhamea</name>
               </seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Oligarrhena</seg> remain. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Andersonia</seg> is placed in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Sprengelia">Sprengelia</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cystanthe">Cystanthe</name>
               </seg> in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Richea">Richea</name>
               </seg>, etc. You will soon see my views published.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See B67.09.01.</p>
               </note> The 5th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>, which laid the ground work for this course, was recently sent to your Academy.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Royal Bavarian Academy of Sciences (Königlich Baierische Akademie der Wissenschaften), Munich.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My illness has prevented me from completing a transmission to you. To make good this promise will be one of my first actions on my return. May Providence graciously protect you and keep you for a long time yet as a blessing to science.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I collected freshwater fish for Agassiz and have wrung from him the promise to produce an ichthyology for Australia.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have wintered <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cinchona%20condaminea">Cinchona condaminea</name>
               </seg> out in the open here and now have about 10,000 plants.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia%20mollissima%20">Acacia mollissima </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Andersonia%20">Andersonia </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anguillaria%20">Anguillaria </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cakile%20maritime">Cakile maritime</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarina%20glauca">Casuarina glauca</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarina%20quadrivalvis">Casuarina quadrivalvis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarina%20suberosa">Casuarina suberosa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cinchona%20condaminea">Cinchona condaminea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cystanthe">Cystanthe</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Decaspora">Decaspora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Needhamea">Needhamea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Oligarrhena%20">Oligarrhena </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pentachondra">Pentachondra</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Richea">Richea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sprengelia">Sprengelia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Styphelia%20">Styphelia </name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
