<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queenscliff, ¶  25/7/67 ¶  ¶ I have withdrawn here into rural tranquillity, noble Sir, to strengthen my precarious health under the influence of the sea air. For  ¶ six ¶  years I have not been out of...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-07-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.07.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Queenscliff, ¶  25/7/67 ¶  ¶ I have withdrawn here into rural tranquillity, noble Sir, to strengthen my precarious health under the influence of the sea air. For  ¶ six ¶  years I have not been out of...</title>
               <date when="1867-07-25">1867-07-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-07-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Marianthus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Queenscliff, ¶  25/7/67 ¶  ¶ I have withdrawn here into rural tranquillity, noble Sir, to strengthen my precarious health under the influence of the sea air. For  ¶ six ¶  years I have not been out of...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">67.07.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Martius: 'praes. 25. Sept.' [received 25 September].</p>
               </note>Queenscliff 25/7/67</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hierher habe ich mich in ländliche Stille zurückgezogen, edler Herr, um unter dem Einfluss oceanischer Lüfte meine schwankende Gesundheit zu kräftigen. Ich war seit <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sechs</hi>
               </seg> Jahren nicht aus der Anstalt. Gern würde ich weitere Mittheilungen, die zu Ansichten der Natur Australiens führen könnten, sammeln und zusammenstellen; aber in der grossen Anstalt u inmitten einer Jahrescorrespondenz von etwa 3000 Briefen ist es mir unmöglich gerade jetzt, wenn ich nicht das Hauptwerk meines Strebens, die Vegetation des Australcontinentes specifisch zu beschreiben, ausser Acht lassen will. Ich gehe aber mit dem Gedanken um, eine <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Statistik</hi>
               </seg> in tabularer Form über die 10,000 bekannten Pflanzen Australiens zu entwerfen, u diese Arbeit werde ich als Nebensache gleichzeitig mit den phytographischen durchführen. Den grössern Theil der Monopetalen habe ich für Benthams Werk vorbereitet u so wird die grosse Arbeit wohl in wenigen Jahren beendet u das für Australien gewonnen sein was wir im Zusammenhang nicht einmal für Europa besitzen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dem verehrten Baron v. Huegel hatte ich mit dieser Monatspost einige <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name> Arten zu senden u so schloss ich für Sie, edler Herr, den 5. Band meiner Fragmenta bei.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn nicht Vorbereitungen für den Empfang des Prinzen Alfred meine Musse zu sehr beschränkten, werde ich wohl endlich eine ordentliche Sendung für Sie herstellen können. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Entwurf eines Vegetationsgemäldes Australiens in dem Bande über unsere colonial Austellung sollte nur industriellen Zwecken dienen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die neuen lehrreichen Winke Ihres letzten Briefes lenken meine</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Anschauung in neue Spuren. Ich habe stets geglaubt, dass <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geologische</hi>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Verhältnisse manche als Arten hingestellte Varietäten bedingen u dies wurde mir unmerklich klar bei den Formen der Eucalypten. Gewisse Arten dieser Gattung werfen in bestimmten Bodenarten und damit verbundenen climatischen Verhältnissen die äussere Rinde ab, in andern Strecken u Lüften bleibt die Rinde stehen. Ebenso ist das Holz derselben Art unter andern geognostischen Verhältnissen sehr verschieden. Bis jetzt aber sind die geologischen Karten zu beschränkt um den Phytologen zu leiten u er selbst hat nicht ausgedehnte u specielle Gelegenheit die Felsarten u die daraus entstehenden Bodenarten zu untersuchen. In den Alpen hier u dort finden wir <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Varietäten</hi>
               </seg> klar verfolgbar abgegrenzt bei climatischen Regionen u. gesellen sich zu<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Continuation of letter filed in MSS collection as a separate undated manuscript.</p>
               </note> diesen Verhältnissen noch geologische Änderungen so entstehen Gebilde, die ohne dauerndes Studium der Bedingungen, welchen sie ihre Gestaltung verdanken, nach einigen äussern trügerischen wandelbaren Merkzeichen von den meisten Beobachtern als specifisch abgegrenzt hingestellt werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin ganz gerührt durch Ihre stete Güte u weiss nicht wie ich sie vergelten soll. Es ist aber immer ein Freudentag wenn ein Brief von Ihnen ankommt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Schliesslich entbiete ich nun nur noch meinen cordialen Gruss.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich habe selbst nicht viel nach Paris zur Ausstellung senden können, aber das wenige hat doch viel Arbeit erfordert u viel Zeit.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Queenscliff,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Vic.</p>
               </note> 25/7/67</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have withdrawn here into rural tranquillity, noble Sir, to strengthen my precarious health under the influence of the sea air. For <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">six</hi>
               </seg> years I have not been out of my institute. I would be happy to collect and collate further communications that could lead to views on the nature of Australia; but in the large institute and with an annual correspondence of about 3,000 letters it is at present impossible for me, unless I were to disregard the major thrust of my endeavour to describe specifically the vegetation of Australia. But I am thinking about preparing a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">statistic</hi>
               </seg> in tabular form on the 10,000 known Australian plants, and I intend to carry out this work on the side simultaneously with the phytographic labours. I have prepared the major part of the Monopetalae for Bentham's work, and thus the great task should be completed in a few years and achieve something for Australia that we do not even have for Europe as a cohesive work.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I had to send a few <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name>
               </seg> species to the venerated Baron von Huegel<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found; but see M to C. von Hügel, 29 January 1867.</p>
               </note> with this month's mail, so I took the opportunity to enclose the 5th volume of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg> for you, noble Sir. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If preparations for the reception of Prince Alfred<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Prince Alfred, Duke of Edinburgh, visited Melbourne in November 1867.</p>
               </note> did not restrict my leisure hours so much, I should at long last be able to put together a proper consignment for you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The sketch of the vegetation of Australia in the volume on our Colonial Exhibition<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B67.13.02.</p>
               </note> was only meant to serve industrial purposes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The new instructive suggestions in your last letter direct my views along new paths. I have always believed, that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geological</hi>
               </seg> conditions determine many variations looked on as species, and this became clear to me gradually with the forms among the eucalypts. Certain species of this genus shed their outer bark in particular soil types and connected climatic conditions, in other areas and climates the bark is retained. In the same way the timber of the same species can differ greatly under different geognostic conditions. But to date geological maps are too limited to guide the phytologist, while he himself does not have extended and specific opportunity to examine the rock types and the soil types arising from them. In the Alps we find <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">varieties</hi>
               </seg> here and there clearly and visibly defined by climatic regions and if geological changes are added to this, entities arise which, without constant study of the conditions to which they owe their formation, will from a few external, deceptive, changeable characteristics, be considered by most observers to be specifically distinct.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am very touched by your constant kindness and do not know how I shall repay you. But it is always a day of joy, when a letter from you arrives.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Finally I now still offer you my cordial regards.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I personally was not able to send much to Paris for the Exhibition,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Exposition Universelle, Paris, 1867.</p>
               </note> yet the little still cost much work and much time.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Marianthus">Marianthus</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
