<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ At first it gave us an infinity of trouble, for on this side the equator it seems to have departed from its normal habit, but the new moths are much less wild, and the larvae more ready to feed, th...</title>
            <author>Charles Brady</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-01-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.01.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles Brady</author>
               <title> ¶ At first it gave us an infinity of trouble, for on this side the equator it seems to have departed from its normal habit, but the new moths are much less wild, and the larvae more ready to feed, th...</title>
               <date when="1867-01">1867-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-01-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ At first it gave us an infinity of trouble, for on this side the equator it seems to have departed from its normal habit, but the new moths are much less wild, and the larvae more ready to feed, th...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">67.01.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Charles Brady</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 7 February 1867, p. 5, under the heading, 'The Acclimatisation Society'. The item is introduced with the following information: 'At the meeting of the Council on Tuesday ... a letter, addressed to Dr. Mueller, was also read from Mr Charles Brady, of Brisbane, stating that the Ailanthus silkworm had been successfully established in Queensland. Mr Brady says:–'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The item was subsequently reprinted in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane courier</seg>, 16 February 1867, p. 5, and elsewhere. It is dated to late January as the latest date on which it could have been sent from Brisbane to reach Melbourne in time to be read at the meeting on 5 February.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At first it gave us an infinity of trouble, for on this side the equator it seems to have departed from its normal habit, but the new moths are much less wild, and the larvae more ready to feed, than their predecessors; and we hope, with further experience, the next generation will prove as completely domesticated as it is in other countries. In the meanwhile they continue to thrive in all their stages.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The quotation is followed by: 'Mr. Brady kindly offers to send a supply of these worms to Melbourne, and concludes by stating that, thus far, the eggs have been found to hatch in the eighth, ninth, or tenth day from laying, and that it is perfectly practicable to maintain a perpetual succession of new brood from day to day throughout the year'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The published summary of the letter appears to confuse Brady's development of a system of rearing the Mulberry silk moth <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bombyx mori</seg> with that of his work with the Ailanthus species, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Samia cynthia</seg>. Kapus (1893) quotes George Bennett, 'writing in 1870': </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6736in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.0071in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Brady has, by special culture of varieties of mulberries during the springs, summers, autumns, and winters of more than three whole years, succeeded in raising successive small crops of silk from annual mulberry silkworms daily for a period of upwards of 1000 consecutive days.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Brady (1868), his pamphlet on the Ailanthus silkworm, makes no mention of this achievement. In 1872 he was granted land on the Tweed River to cultivate mulberry to establish a silk industry based on <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bombyx mori</seg>. He exhibited silk from that estate at the 1886 Colonial and Indian Exhibition in London, saying in an accompanying circular (Wood (1887), p. 337) that </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">the climate on the Tweed River furnishes the mulberry tree in great abundance, yielding daily supplies of the leaf from the </seg>end of July until April … The whole of the natural history of the mulberry silkworm, absolutely unchanged in its annual habit, is in view at one and the same moment, worms hatched on the day itself, and of every other day's, from one day old to full-grown ones, actually making their cocoons; the moths emerging, and new eggs being produced, which are a generation to proceed with in a subsequent season. Arranged beforehand, and in the hands of a skilled person, the process is as much under control as the machinery in a factory. It is animated, self-reproducing machinery, maintained by supplies of the silkworm's only natural food—the mulberry leaf.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
