<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Allow me to express to you the feelings of gratitude that I experienced in receiving anew, in your letter dated 29 July, ¶  manifest signs of your good will towards me, and be assured that I always...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-12-07-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>67.12.07</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ Allow me to express to you the feelings of gratitude that I experienced in receiving anew, in your letter dated 29 July, ¶  manifest signs of your good will towards me, and be assured that I always...</title>
               <date when="1867-12-07">1867-12-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1867/67-12-07-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Lepidospermum laevigatum</term>
               <term>Mesembryanthemum tegens</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/e91dc560-84d5-40c5-94bb-033f16503403">Melaleuca ericifolia</term>
               <term>Cinchona condaminea</term>
               <term>Fabricia laevigata </term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/b2325905-a7e5-4005-8bcb-9cbde29fd00c">Casuarina</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/dfe52d12-cc3f-4620-8a9b-ab8361322615">Acacia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="58">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="42">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Edouard Drouyn de Lhuys</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Allow me to express to you the feelings of gratitude that I experienced in receiving anew, in your letter dated 29 July, ¶  manifest signs of your good will towards me, and be assured that I always...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">67.12.07</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Edouard Drouyn de Lhuys</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is included in the report of the Society’s meeting on 6 March 1868, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin de la Société Impériale Zoologique d'Acclimatation</seg>, series 2, vol. 5, pp. 328-30 (B68.05.01), where the letter is introduced: 'M. Ferd. Mueller adresse la lettre suivante à M. le Président' [Mr Ferd. Mueller sends the following letter to the President]. The date of the letter is given in Raveret-Wattel (1873), p. 595 but with a year date of 1868 that is clearly wrong. At the meeting of the Society held on 5 July 1867, Cinchona culture was discussed (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin de la Société Impériale Zoologique d'Acclimatation</seg>, series 2, vol. 4 (1867), pp. 454-5, and the President announced that a committee was to study documents relating to its culture (p. 461).</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Permettez-moi de vous exprimer les sentiments de gratitude que j'éprouve en recevant de nouveau, dans votre lettre datée du 29 juillet, des signes manifestes de votre bienveillance pour moi, et recevez l'assurance que je regarde toujours comme un privilège de pouvoir venir en aide, si peu que ce soit, aux efforts si louables de la Société impériale d'acclimatation, qui s'honore du patronage de Sa Majesté l'Empereur et de la présidence de Votre Excellence. En réponse à vos questions sur la culture des Cinchonas en Australie, je dois vous dire que quelques plants de <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cinchona%20condaminea">Cinchona condaminea</name>
               </seg>, âgés de dix-huit mois, ont résisté dans des localités exposées à un froid de 2 degrés Farenh.; les parties tendres et les portions supérieures des tiges seulement étaient détruites sans qu'il en résultât aucun autre dommage pour la plante qui poussait de nouveau. Quelques autres pieds plantés dans une localité abritée n'avaient pas souffert du tout. Les graines lèvent avec facilité dans une serre; elles sont ensuite repiquées; les plants s'endurcissent graduellement et sont mis en plein air, abrités seulement par quelques branches, et y restent jusqu'au moment où ils sont transplantés dans les vallées ombragées et comparativement humides de nos montagnes. Je ne doute pas que les Cinchonas réussissent dans beaucoup de localités favorables, voisines de la Méditerranée. Si Votre Excellence le permet et si l'on pouvait s'entendre ou traiter avec les caravanes qui traversent le désert en Afrique, le terrible Sahara, pour qu'elles prennent avec elles des graines de nos arbres et de nos arbrisseaux, si bien aptes à résister à la sécheresse, pour les semer le long de leur chemin, j'espère bien que l'on pourrait faire encore sur le désert des conquêtes sérieuses, en y établissant graduellement une végétation. Je vous remettrais volontiers, dans ce but, des graines de nos <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
               </seg>, de nos <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>
               </seg>, de nos <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
               </seg>, etc., etc., en quantités suffisantes. Les graines des différentes espèces d'<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
               </seg> commencent à germer tout de suite si on les arrose avec de l'eau bouillante, et si, après avoir laissé l'eau refroidir, on les y laisse encore tremper quelques heures; cette opération pourrait être faite sans inconvénient dans le bivouac pendant la nuit. Notre petit <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Mesembryanthemum%20tegens">Mesembryanthemum tegens</name>
               </seg>, que nous trouvons même sur les rochers et dans les localités les plus arides, est également apte à former le commencement d'un gazon dans le désert. Les moindres branches de cette plante, mises en terre, prennent bientôt racine et commencent à pousser. J'en pourrais faire remettre en quantité à Londres, d'où, par l'intermédiaire peut-être de S. Exc. l'ambassadeur de France, on le remettrait en Afrique. Deux autres de nos arbres me paraissent devoir encore vous être recommandés. L'un, le <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Lepidospermum </seg>(<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fabricia</seg>) <seg style="font-style: italic; ">laevigatum</seg>, petit arbre d'ornamentation, très-utile pour retenir les sables mouvants sur le bord de la mer. Toutes nos côtes sont garnies ici de cet arbuste et je le crois convenable pour celles de la Méditerranée. L'autre, le <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>
               </seg>, arbuste très-joli, propre à l'ornamentation, est très-commun sur nos lagunes (alluvions?) d'eau douce ou salée. On le trouve ou dans l'eau ou dans des localités qui sont inondées pendant l'hiver, mais sèches en été. On peut en transplanter impunément des pieds même assez gros. Les feuilles de cette plante contiennent beaucoup <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>d'huile essentielle. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Allow me to express to you the feelings of gratitude that I experienced in receiving anew, in your letter dated 29 July,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> manifest signs of your good will towards me, and be assured that I always regard it as a privilege to be able to help, in however small a way, in the so laudable efforts of the Imperial Acclimatisation Society, which is honoured by the patronage of His Majesty the Emperor and Your Excellency's presidency. In response to your question about the cultivation of Cinchonas in Australia, I should tell you that some plants of <name key="Cinchona%20condaminea">Cinchona condaminea</name>, eighteen months old, have in exposed localities withstood a cold of 2 degrees Fahrenheit; only the soft parts and the upper portions of the stems were destroyed, without there resulting any other injury to the plant which shooted anew. Some other stalks planted in a sheltered locality have not suffered at all. Seeds come up easily in a greenhouse; they are then transplanted; the plants gradually toughen and are put in the open air, sheltered only by some branches, and stay there until the time when they are transplanted into the shaded and comparatively humid valleys of our mountains. I have no doubt that Cinchonas would succeed in many favourable localities beside the Mediterranean. If Your Excellency allows and if one could come to an arrangement or treat with the caravans that cross the African desert, the terrible Sahara, to take with them seeds of our trees and shrubs, so well suited <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to withstand drought, with them to sow them along the way, I believe one could even make serious inroads into the desert, by gradually establishing a vegetation there.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This sentence was followed in </seg>Raveret-Wattel (1873) by </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Toutefois, M. Mueller est d'avis que dans le but de donner aux semis toute chance de succès, il conviendrait de labourer une certaine étendue de terrain dans les endroits naturellement propices à la réception de la graine. “Si, par exemple, dans quelque vallée rocheuse et encaissée, on labourait quelques centaines d'hectares, ou, dans le cas où le terrain serait trop rocailleux, si l'on brisait la surface par quelque autre moyen, il est certain que les semences y germeraient sans courir les chances de perte qui auraient lieu dans des circonstances moins favorables. Cette vallée pourrait être aisément garantie contre l'incursion des chèvres, des chameaux ou d'autres animaux domestiques, surtout si un gardien était établi sur la plantation. On pourrait aussi recueillir l'eau des pluies pour des irrigations accidentelles.”</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[Mr <seg style="">Mueller, however, is of the opinion that, in order to give the seedlings every chance of success, a certain extent of land should be ploughed in places naturally favourable to the reception of the seed. "If, for example, in some rocky valley, some hundreds of hectares were ploughed, or if the ground was too rocky, if the surface were broken by some other means, seed would germinate there without running the risk of loss that there be under less favourable circumstances. This valley could easily be protected against the incursion of goats, camels or other domestic animals, especially if a custodian was established on the plantation. Rainwater could also be collected for incidental </seg>irrigation."]</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The passage quoted is from B69.06.02, p. 108.</p>
               </note> I would willingly send you, to this end, in sufficient quantities, seeds of our <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>, our <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>, our <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>, &amp;c., &amp;c. The seeds of the different species of <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name> begin to germinate immediately if one wets them with boiling water and, after leaving the water to cool, leaves them soaking for several hours; this could be done without inconvenience in camp overnight. Our little <name key="Mesembryanthemum%20tegens">Mesembryanthemum tegens</name>, which we find even on rocky crags and in the most arid localities, is equally suited to form the commencement of a lawn in the desert. The smallest branches of this plant, put in the ground, soon take root and begin to shoot. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I could have a quantity sent to London from whence, perhaps through His Exc. the French ambassador as intermediary, it might be sent to Africa. Two other trees of ours, it seems to me, ought to be recommended to you. One, Lepidospermum<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Leptospermum</seg>?</p>
                  </note>
               </seg> (Fabricia) laevigatum, a small ornamental tree, very useful to hold moving sands on the seashore. All our coasts here are adorned with this bush and I believe it well fitted for those of the Mediterranean. The other, the <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>, a very pretty bush, suitable as ornamentation, is very common on our sweet- and salt-water lagoons (alluvions?<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>The parenthetical query may be an editorial insertion.</p>
               </note>). It is found either in the water or in localities that are flooded in winter but dry in summer. They can be transplanted with impunity even as quite large stalks. The leaves of this plant contain much essential oil.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cinchona%20condaminea">Cinchona condaminea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Fabricia%20laevigata%20">Fabricia laevigata </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lepidospermum%20laevigatum">Lepidospermum laevigatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>.</p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mesembryanthemum%20tegens">Mesembryanthemum tegens</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
