<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>26 September 1862. ¶ Dear friend, ¶  ¶ Do not be angry with me because I have seemingly neglected you so much. I am in such a whirl of activities keeping me constantly on the move, that all too often ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-09-26a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, folder 204, no. 529, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>62.09.26a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>26 September 1862. ¶ Dear friend, ¶  ¶ Do not be angry with me because I have seemingly neglected you so much. I am in such a whirl of activities keeping me constantly on the move, that all too often ...</title>
               <date when="1862-09-26">1862-09-26</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-09-26a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Discoria</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">26 September 1862. ¶ Dear friend, ¶  ¶ Do not be angry with me because I have seemingly neglected you so much. I am in such a whirl of activities keeping me constantly on the move, that all too often ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">62.09.26a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, folder 204, no. 529, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">26/9/62</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Theuerer Freund.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zürnen Sie mir nicht, weil ich Sie scheinbar so vernachlässigte. Im bin in einem solchen Strudel von Geschäften stets in Bewegung gehalten, dass nur zu oft auch mit dem besten Willen das nicht rein Amtliche übersehen wird. Meine Mitarbeitung an dem grossen Werke über die Vegetation Australiens, an welchem der Präsident der Linneischen Gesellschaft von London beschäftigt ist, lässt mir auch wenig Mussestunden, wenn ich nicht stets bis tief in die Nacht arbeiten will, u wofür seit den wenigen letzten Jahren meine Gesundheit zu schwankend gewesen ist. Ich hoffte Ihnen mit diesem Briefe Ihre Wahl als Ehrenmitglied in unsere Gesellschaft anzeigen zu können, selbige ist aber leider noch nicht erfolgt, da zur Proposition nach den Rules die Genehmigung einer absoluten Majorität des Councils in sede gehört, und nun sind unsere Council meetings so schlecht besucht, dass wir dieser Vorschrift bisher nicht haben nachkommen können. Sie sehen hieraus, Theuerster, dass unsere Gesellschaft in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Verfall</hi>
               </seg> ist. Ihnen im Vertrauen kann ichs wohl sagen. Es ist keine Einmüthigkeit unter den Mitgliedern, im Gegentheil viel Feindseligkeit und wir haben wenig arbeitende Kräfte, da die wenigen wirklichen Gelehrten der Gesellschaft in Berufsarbeiten ihre Zeit fast gänzlich zu verwenden haben. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wann die transactions der beiden letzten Jahre erscheinen werden, weiss ich nicht. Viele Mitglieder sind aus Unzufriedenheit seit den letzten 2 Jahren zurückgetreten u so ist ein Theil der Fonds nicht länger verwendbar, den wir früher durch die Zahlungen der Mitglieder für Druck zusammenbrachten, u ich zweifle, ob das Parlament Subsidien liefern wird. Es ist ein Trost für mich, dass ich nicht mehr (seit langer Zeit) an der Spitze stehe u an dem Verfall der Gesellschaft keine Schuld trage. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Aber nun lassen Sie mich Sie aufs Innigste beglückwünschen zu der so wohl verdiente Ehre nicht nur Ihre philosophische Gesellschaft gegründet zu haben, sondern auch den Vorsitz in derselben einzunehmen, eine Ehre, auf welche Sie als Ausländer doppelt stolz sein können!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gleichzeitig mit diesem Briefe sende ich den jüngst erschienenen Band unserer Gesellschaft an Sie ab; derselbe hätte schon vor zwei Jahren erscheinen sollen. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn Ihre Gesellschaft vollständig ins Leben getreten ist, will ich mir die Ehre erweisen Ihnen die vollständige Series meiner bot Schriften, (soweit solche habhaft zu werden sind) zu überreichen. Und wenn ich Ihrer Gesellschaft anderweitig dienstbar sein kann, so gebieten Sie frei über mich.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die gütig mir gebotene Gelegenheit etwaige neue Beobachtungen über Neu Seeland's Pflanzen durch Ihr hoffnungsvoll […]blühendes Institut bekannt machen zu können, nehme ich mit dem grössten Danke an.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr Portrait ist mir eine herrliche Gabe, welche ich mit meinen besten Kleinodien theuer halten werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn Sie Ihre Statuten noch nicht bestimmt haben, so erlauben Sie mir Ihnen einen Rath zu geben. Lassen Sie alle Mitglieder eine [tüchtige] Summe als Lifemembers zahlen u deponieren Sie den Erlös in Staatseigenthum u verwenden Sie nur die Zinsen zum Druck. Diesen Plan habe ich von meinen scandinavischen Freunden entnommen, deren archeologische Gesellschaft so von Jahr zu Jahr reicher u literarisch productiver wird. Auch möchte ich Ihnen rathen Ihre Ehrensitze, wie es die Canadier gethan, auf eine bestimmte u unabänderliche Zahl festzustellen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sollte Ihnen oder Hr Travers (den ich freundlichst zu grüssen bitte) die beiliegende <name key="Discoria">Discoria</name> vorkommen so bitte ich recht sehr um einige vollständige blühende u Fruchttragen<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Frucht tragende.</p>
               </note> Exemplare zum Vergleich der gattunsverwandten<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">gattungsverwandten.</p>
               </note> australischen Arten.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit inniger Freundschaft </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">26 September 1862.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Do not be angry with me because I have seemingly neglected you so much. I am in such a whirl of activities keeping me constantly on the move, that all too often even with the best will what is not purely official duty is overlooked. My co-operation in the great work on the vegetation of Australia, in which the President of the Linnean Society of London<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">George Bentham.</p>
               </note> is engaged, leaves me little time for leisure, unless I want to work always deep into the night, and for that my health has been too precarious in the last few years. I had hoped to report to you with this letter your election as honorary member of our Society,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Royal Society of Victoria. Haast was elected an Honorary Member on 17 November 1862.</p>
               </note> but regrettably that has not yet taken place. According to the rules, permission by an absolute majority of Council members in session is required for the proposition. Our Council meetings have been so poorly attended, that so far we have not yet been able to comply with this rule. You can see from this, my dearest friend, that our Society is in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">decline</hi>
               </seg>. I can tell you this in confidence. There is no solidarity among the members, on the contrary much animosity and we have few working members as the few truly learned men in the Society have to spend nearly all their time on their professional duties.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not know, when the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions</seg> for the last two years will be issued.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions and proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria</seg>, vol. 6, which included the proceedings for 1861 and that should have included a paper by Haast, was not published until 1865.</p>
               </note> Many members have resigned during the past two years because of dissatisfaction, and thus a part of the funds are no longer available, that were formerly collected from members' contributions towards the printing. I doubt that the Parliament will provide subsidies. It is a consolation to me, that I am no longer (not since a long time) in charge,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was President in 1859. In 1862 he was a member of the Council.</p>
               </note> and do not bear any blame for the decline of the Society.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But now let me congratulate you most sincerely on the well-earned honour of having not only founded your Philosophical Society,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Philosophical Institute of Canterbury.</p>
               </note> but of occupying the Chair of the same, an honour of which you, as a foreigner, can be doubly proud!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the same time as this letter I am sending you the recently published volume of our Society; this should have been issued as long as two years ago.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transaction of the Royal Society of Victoria</seg>, vol. 5, for 1860.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When your Society has been fully inaugurated, I will do myself the honour of presenting you with a complete set of my botanical publications (in as far as such are still available). And if I can be of service to your Society in any other way, I am freely at your disposal. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The opportunity so kindly offered to me of publishing any likely future new observations on New Zealand's plants through your hopefully […]-flourishing Institute I accept with the greatest gratitude.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your photograph is a wonderful gift to me and I shall hold it precious with my best treasures.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Photograph not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If you have not yet set down your statutes, permit me to give you some advice. Have the members pay a goodly sum for life membership and deposit the amount in Government securities and use only the interest for printing. I have this plan from my Scandinavian friends, whose Archaeological Society<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M is no doubt referring to C. C. Rafn, secretary of the Royal Society of Nordic Antiquities, Copenhagen.</p>
               </note> is getting richer and more literary productive year by year. I would also advise you to restrict your honorary membership to a predetermined and unalterable number of seats, as the Canadians have done.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M may have been referring to Canada's constitutional arrangements whereby under the Union Act of 1841, the number of seats in the House of Assembly was fixed for each of the two constituent sections of the Union, Canada West (Ontario) and Canada East (Québec), no matter how their respective populations changed.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Should you or Mr Travers (to whom I ask you to give my sincerest regards) come across the enclosed <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Discoria">Discoria</name>
               </seg>,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="color: #000000; font-style: italic; ">Dioscorea</seg>
                     <seg style="color: #000000; ">?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I beg you to be so kind to send me a few complete flowering and fruiting specimens for comparison with generically related Australian species.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With sincerest friendship</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Discoria">Discoria</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
