<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>6 March 1862. ¶ Esteemed patron and friend, ¶  ¶ Since my letter to you of 12 September ¶  I have had the pleasure to safely receive all your kind letters, of 24 August, 25 September, 25 October, and ...</title>
            <author>August Petermann</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-03-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>62.03.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>August Petermann</author>
               <title>6 March 1862. ¶ Esteemed patron and friend, ¶  ¶ Since my letter to you of 12 September ¶  I have had the pleasure to safely receive all your kind letters, of 24 August, 25 September, 25 October, and ...</title>
               <date when="1862-03-06">1862-03-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-03-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Internet link</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="60">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="40">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">6 March 1862. ¶ Esteemed patron and friend, ¶  ¶ Since my letter to you of 12 September ¶  I have had the pleasure to safely receive all your kind letters, of 24 August, 25 September, 25 October, and ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">62.03.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS is a file copy. For a published version of this letter, see Voigt (1996), pp. 36-8.</p>
               </note>6. März 62.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrtester Gönner und Freund,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit meinem Schreiben an Sie vom 12. September habe ich das Vergnügen gehabt, alle Ihre lieben Zuschriften, vom 24. Aug., 25. Sept., 25. Okt. und 26. Nov., richtig zu erhalten, wie auch die beiden weiteren Wechsel für die deutschen Expeditionen in Afrika, im Betrage von resp. £7.17 und £11, wofür ich Ihnen und Ihren Freunden vom Comité und Seiner Hoheit dem Herzog beauftragt bin, ganz besondern Dank zu sagen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Unternehmen ist jetzt in 3 Abtheilungen getrennt, unter Heuglin, Munzinger und Beurmann, die auf drei verschiedenen Wegen in jeder Beziehung mehr leisten werden, als eine einzige Expedition, so dass desshalb auch die Freunde der Sache nicht den geringsten Grund zu der Befürchtung haben, dass das Unternehmen nicht zu einem ehrenvollen Resultate gelangen werde, wozu eine Zeitlang allerdings Veranlassung gegeben war durch die etwas einseitige u leichtsinnige Auffassung der Instruktion Seitens des frühern alleinigen Chefs, H. v. Heuglin, der sich hatte hinreissen lassen, zuerst nur der wissenschaftlichen Seite des Unternehmens Rechnung zu tragen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich liess Ihnen die Kölnische Zeitung vom 2. u 7. Februar bei Ihrem Erscheinen zuschicken, in welchen ein ausführlicher Vortrag von mir über die Expeditionen enthalten ist; hoffentlich werden Sie diese Zusendung lange vor Ankunft dieser Zeilen erhalten und so über den Stand der Sache Orientirung bekommen haben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin Ihnen äusserst dankbar für den gütigen Beischluss in Ihrem letzten geneigten Schreiben und der Kartenskizze von der Erkundung McKinlay's über die Burke'sche Expedition. In meinem letzten am 11.Febr. abgeschlossenen Hefte habe ich ausführlichen Bericht und die beiden inliegenden Karten gebracht über Stuart's zweite Reise und die grossartige Burke´sche Expedition, welche letztere freilich unter so schweren Opfern den Sieg sogar über Stuart erkämpft hat. Es gereicht dies der Kolonie Victoria wie besonders denjenigen, die an der Spitze der Sache standen, zum <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">höchsten</hi>
               </seg> Ruhme, denn dass unter allen Umständen bei der ersten Durchschneidung eines Kontinentes wie Australien Menschenleben verloren gehen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">könnten</hi>
               </seg>, war vorauszusehen, und wenn Stuart dasselbe grossartige Problem noch etwa ohne Verlust von Menschenleben lösen wird, so wird das eben erst bei einem <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dritten</hi>
               </seg> oder <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">vierten</hi>
               </seg> Anlauf geschehen, ein grosser Unterschied von einer ersten Durchbrechung. In meinem Bericht habe ich desshalb auch vor Allem auf die Lösung dieser grossartigen Aufgabe hingewiesen und von den kleinlichen Zwistigkeiten die seitdem ausgebrochen sind, keine Notiz genommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vor einigen Tagen sind auch die durch Ihre gütige Verwendung von Herrn Ligar geschickten Karten glücklich angekommen. Dieselben sind mir von grossem Interesse und Werth, wie alles ähnliche Quellen-Material. Ich bitte ihm die einliegenden Dankes-Zeilen gelegentlich zu übergeben. Stehen Sie vielleicht mit ähnlichen guten Leuten in: <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">South Australia,</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">New South Wales,</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Queensland,</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">West-Australia </hi>
               </seg>&amp; <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Tasmania</hi>
               </seg> in Verbindung? oder könnten mir die Namen &amp; Adressen geben?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ist das <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Tagebuch von Wills</hi>
               </seg> so lückenhaft, wie es in den Zeitungen publicirt wurde, oder werden vielleicht die fehlenden Stücke noch nachträglich veröffentlicht?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von den <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ersten</hi>
               </seg> Berichten <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Burke´s</hi>
               </seg> über die Expedition von Melbourne bis zum Cooper-Creek besitze ich gar nichts. Wird vielleicht über das ganze Unternehmen ein grösseres Werk vorbereitet?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ebenso habe ich oft schmerzlichst vermisst das Tagebuch oder einen vollständigen Bericht über die ältere Reise <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">A. Gregory's</hi>
               </seg> von Moreton B. längs des Barcoo nach Südaustralien von 1858.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Aber es ist gut, dass das Papier meinen vielen zudringlichen Fragen ein Ende setzt.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit innigster Verehrung und Dankbarkeit </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Petermann.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Können Sie mir nicht von unsern hiesigen Publikationen etwas bezeichnen, was ich Ihnen schicken darf? und auf welchem Wege? durch welche Adresse?</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">6 March 1862.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed patron and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Since my letter to you of 12 September<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A. Petermann to M, 12 September 1861.</p>
               </note> I have had the pleasure to safely receive all your kind letters, of 24 August, 25 September, 25 October, and 26 November,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M to A. Petermann, 24 August 1861 (in this edition as 61-08-24b); M to A. Petermann, 25 September 1861 (in this edition as 61-09-25b); M to A. Petermann, 25 October 1861; and M to A. Petermann, 26 November 1861.</p>
               </note> as also the two further bills of exchange for the German expeditions in Africa to the amounts of respectively £7/17/— and £11,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to A. Petermann, 25 September 1861.</p>
               </note> for which the Committee and His Highness the Duke<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Duke Ernst II of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, President of the committee that was organizing expeditions to search for the missing German explorer Eduard Vogel.</p>
               </note> asked me to give special thanks to you and your friends.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The enterprise has now been separated into 3 divisions, under Heuglin, Munzinger and Beurmann who, travelling along three different routes, will be able to achieve more in every respect than a single expedition, so that the friends of the venture need not have the slightest worry that the matter will not be brought to an honourable conclusion, for which, admittedly, there was cause to fear for a while through the somewhat one-sided and reckless interpretation of the instructions on the part of the former single leader, H. von Heuglin, who had been carried away to pay attention only to the scientific side of the enterprise.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I arranged for the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Kölnische Zeitung</seg> of 2 and 7 February, which contained a detailed lecture by me on the expeditions, to be sent to you on publication; I hope you will have received these transmissions long before the arrival of these lines and so will have obtained information on the state of the matter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am extremely grateful to you for the kind enclosure in your last gracious letter and for the sketch map of the search expedition by McKinlay for Burke's expedition. In my last edition, concluded on 11 February, I have published a detailed report and the two enclosed maps of Stuart's second journey, and on Burke's magnificent expedition,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Petermann (1862a); the maps accompanying the article have been digitized by the National Library of Australia, see <ref target="http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-232431385"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-232431385</ref> (Stuart) and <ref target="http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-232431008"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-232431008</ref> (Burke), accessed 18 August 2018. The part of the article concerning Burke includes German translations, taken from Melbourne's German-language newspaper <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Germania</seg>, of Wills's journal, Burke's notebook, and John King's report following his rescue. M was a member of the sub-committee of the Exploration Committee of the Royal Society of Victoria that was appointed at the Exploration Committee's meeting on 4 November 1861 to make transcripts of the documents, and he prepared the transcript of Wills's journal that he read at the next meeting of the Exploration Committee, on 6 November (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 5 November 1861, p. 5, and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 7 November 1861, pp. 5-6; the latter includes a copy of M's transcription). </p>
               </note> which even triumphed over Stuart, though with such heavy sacrifices. This redounds to the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">greatest</hi>
               </seg> honour for Victoria and especially for those who organized the enterprise, because it was to be expected that, no matter what the circumstances, lives <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">might</hi>
               </seg> be lost in the first traversing of a continent, and unless Stuart should per chance accomplish the same enormous task without the loss of human lives, it is sure to happen at a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">third</hi>
               </seg> or <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">fourth</hi>
               </seg> attempt, a great difference from a first crossing. I have therefore emphasised in my report predominantly the solution to this great task and have taken no notice of the small disputes that have arisen since then.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A few days ago the maps sent by Mr Ligar through your kind intercession arrived safely.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to A. Petermann, 26 November 1861, and C. Ligar to A. Petermann, 20 November 1861 (in this edition as M61-11-20).</p>
               </note> They are of great interest and value to me, as is all similar source material. I ask you to pass the enclosed thank-you note on to him, when the occasion offers. Are you perhaps in communication with similar good people in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">South Australia, New South Wales, Queensland, Western Australia</hi>
               </seg> and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Tasmania</hi>
               </seg>? Or could you give me their names and addresses?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Is the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">diary of Wills</hi>
               </seg> as fragmentary as was published in the newspapers,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus </seg>
                     <seg style="">(Melbourne)</seg>, 7 November 1861, pp. 5-6; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age </seg>
                     <seg style="">(Melbourne),</seg> 7 November 1861, p. 5; Herald (Melbourne) 7 November 1861, p. 5; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Germania</seg>, 15 November 1861, p. 191 and 22 November 1861, pp. 194-5, 196. Extracts or the full text were given in many other regional newspapers in Victoria, as well as in some of the other colonies and New Zealand. It was also published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of the Royal Geographical Society</seg>, vol. 32 (1862), pp. 459-76, plus a further transcription by James Smith, pp. 476-85, as part of 'Exploring expedition from Victoria to the Gulf of Carpentaria, under the command of Mr Robert O'Hara Burke', pp. 430-529. </p>
               </note> or will the missing parts perhaps be published later?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have nothing at all of the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">first</hi>
               </seg> reports from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Burke</hi>
               </seg> on the expedition from Melbourne to Cooper's Creek. Is perhaps a larger work in preparation on the whole enterprise?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the same way I have also often deeply regretted the lack of the diary or a complete report on the older journey by <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">A. Gregory</hi>
               </seg> from Moreton B.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Moreton Bay, Qld.</p>
               </note> along the Barcoo<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Barcoo River, Qld.</p>
               </note> to South Australia in 1858.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The diary of the expedition was published as a Parliamentary report, see A. Gregory (1858a), and also printed in newspapers, for example, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 8 November 1858, Supplement, p. 1. The map of the expedition route is available on line: <ref target="https://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-55177172/view?partId=nla.obj-55199713#page/n5"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">
                        <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0563c1; ">https://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-55177172/view?partId=nla.obj-55199713#page/n5</seg>
                     </ref>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is a good thing, that the end of the page puts a stop to my importunate questions!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With sincere respect and gratitude</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A. Petermann.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Could you not point out some publications here that I may send you? and by what route? per whose address?</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
