<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne botanic Garden, ¶ 18 June 62 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to inform you, that having in the afternoon of Saturday 14. instant received your letter, dated 13 June, ¶  desiring me to investigat...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-06-18-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>W62/3910, unit 749, VPRS 1189/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>62.06.18</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne botanic Garden, ¶ 18 June 62 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to inform you, that having in the afternoon of Saturday 14. instant received your letter, dated 13 June, ¶  desiring me to investigat...</title>
               <date when="1862-06-18">1862-06-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-06-18-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Cryptostemma calendulaceum</term>
               <term>Capsella bursa pastoris</term>
               <term>Cirsium lanceolatum</term>
               <term>Malva rotundifolia</term>
               <term>Erodium moschatum</term>
               <term>Marrubium vulgare</term>
               <term>Trifolium repens</term>
               <term>Stellaria media</term>
               <term>Lolium perenne</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>John O'Shanassy</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne botanic Garden, ¶ 18 June 62 ¶ Sir ¶  ¶ I have the honor to inform you, that having in the afternoon of Saturday 14. instant received your letter, dated 13 June, ¶  desiring me to investigat...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">62.06.18</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To John O'Shanassy</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">W62/3910, unit 749, VPRS 1189/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">18 June 62</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to inform you, that having in the afternoon of Saturday 14. instant received your letter, dated 13 June,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. On 25 May 1863 J. Wallace, of Ballark, wrote to the Chief Secretary reporting that his sheep had been poisoned and asking that someone be sent to investigate. O'Shanassy suggested that M or ‘Dr John McAdam’, or both, might 'go up and report on this very peculiar case.' The Undersecretary, John Moore, minuted on 10 June: 'Ask Dr Mueller' [V62/3466, unit 749, VPRS 1189, PROV].</p>
               </note> desiring me to investigate by personal inspection the cause of the recent death of a number of sheep at Mr Wallace's run at Ballark, I proceeded on Monday 16. instant by the noon train to Meredith and reached Mr Wallace's station early the following morning.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="color: #000000; ">See M to Royal Society of Victoria, 16 June 1862.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Ballark Station is situated at one of the upper branches of the Moorabul<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. Moorabool.</p>
               </note> River, the homestead occupying part of a beautiful basaltic valley.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Conducted by Mr Wallace to the paddock, in which the sheep had been pasturing immediately previous to their sickness, I found after a careful search of the whole ground no indication of the existence there of any herb known to me as deleterious or poisonous in the strict sense of the word. Like in all vallies rich of decomposed trap rock, the vegetation of grasses and herbs is also on this spot very luxuriant, especially at this season of the year, but is constituted only by ordinary native plants, whilst amongst the immigrated weeds I noticed only such as have become abundant in most districts of the colony, including <name key="Trifolium%20repens">Trifolium repens</name>, <name key="Lolium%20perenne">Lolium perenne</name>, <name key="Cirsium%20lanceolatum">Cirsium lanceolatum</name>, <name key="Stellaria%20media">Stellaria media</name>, <name key="Marrubium%20vulgare">Marrubium vulgare</name>, <name key="Erodium%20moschatum">Erodium moschatum</name>, <name key="Capsella%20bursa%20pastoris">Capsella bursa pastoris</name> and <name key="Malva%20rotundifolia">Malva rotundifolia</name>, all from Europe and the originally South African <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulaceum">Cryptostemma calendulaceum</name>, all widely spread over the colony.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Having learnt from Mr Wallace that the flock of sheep, of which the 87 died, had been brought from a drier upland part of his run to the deep humid valley in which the disaster occurred, and that the animals before they were brought to this paddock had been for about a day without food, my opinion became more confirmed, that the illness and death of these animals was not caused by their feeding on any particular poisonous herb growing at the spot, but most probably in consequence of the creatures after some abstinence gorging themselves with an exuberance of wet soft green food, which in its young state and taken in excess proves not unfrequently noxious to herds and flocks, especially when the latter are not accustomed to such localities, and it is not improbable that the large amount of soft and wet foliage of the <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulaceum">Cryptostemma calendulaceum</name> produced particularly the destructive effect on the animals, altho' at the time of my visit to Ballark a small flock of sheep, bred at the low valley of the homestead, was pasturing in the same paddock without any apparent injurious consequences.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No sheep or cattle had been kept in the paddock for months previous to the disaster; hence the growth of the weeds, augmented by the favorable season, was at the time, when the sheep were lost, most abundant. Mr Wallace informed me that under similar circumstances losses amongst his flocks had been sustained last season.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The loss of the sheep, which was the immediate cause of my visit, having taken place 2-3 weeks ago, it was beyond possibility to institute a very satisfactory examination of the stomachs of two of the perished animals, kept by Mr Wallace for the purpose. They did however not present any marks of internal abrasion, indicative of the action of metallic poison, nor did I discover on application of the ordinary chemical tests any traces of such poisons as usually are employed for dressing sheep, altho' many instances are on record of the incautious use of arsenic and mercury preparations for sheep-washing, which are often allowed to saturate the ground and may remain as anorganic poisons, an everlasting danger of destruction on such spots.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In examining the stomachs of the sheep I found the rumen and reticulum gorged with a semiliquid pulp of green food. The psalterium and abomasum were also more or less filled with triturated herbs, which on account of their softness would be rapidly regurgitated. But neither these stomachic cavities nor the oesophagus nor the pylorus showed traces of the action of metallic poison. The specific recognition of the herb in the stomachs of the animals would under any circumstances be equally out of the question as the recognition of any peculiar organic poison.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Wallace informed me, that the sheep were removed after a nights stay from the paddock and that a few days after their removal no further deaths occurred amongst the flock. The internal application of a spoonful of mustard and a spoonful of unmixed tar to most of the animals, which died, was evidently calculated to increase the inflammation, consequent on the overcramming of these sheep, as the above remedies would act as strong irritants, whilst under the circumstances emetic evacuants and demulcents would be indicated in order to remove the inciting cause of the disease and to involve the inflamed membranes and linings with an oleaginous and mucilaginous covering. Such remedies would be specially indicated by any of the Gentlemen of the veterinary profession, when consulted on the subject.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am gratified to be enabled to dispel the fears of the settlers in the locality, that a new noxious weed had sprung up on their runs, in as much as it is apparent that the danger of the reoccurrence of losses similar to those in Mr Wallace's flocks might readily be obviated by keeping the flocks at the early spring season in higher ground.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Should the cramming food, consisting of <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulaceum">Cryptostemma calendulaceum</name> have been, as I suppose, the primary cause of the disaster in this instance, then its effect must be ascribed to mechanical irritation, since this plant has under ordinary circumstances not proved deleterious to herds and flocks and would become only dangerous when it forms in moist weather the momentary prevailing and rapidly devoured food of stock unaccustomed to this plant, similar hurtful actions of green food, when consumed immoderately, and in wet weather being by no means of rare occurrence.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As the Cryptostemma has widely spread over the country, the ready opportunity is offered every where to investigate its varied effect on pastural animals.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I may add, that after explaining my views, Mr Wallace fully concurred in the lilekihood of their correctness.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your most obedient and humble servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller, M.D.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gov. Botanist</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The honorable the Chief Secretary</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;c<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>&amp;<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">On 22 August 1862 O'Shanassy minuted: 'Would it not be desirable for Dr Mueller to make known the results of his inquiry? Perhaps he would bring the subject forward in some way say the Royal Society or if he thinks any other place more suitable I shall be glad to know. "Prevention is better than cure". The knowledge of this case and the causes which may have led to so many deaths amongst a flock of sheep in a settled part of the country may prove eminently useful if promulgated.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M replied on 23 June: 'Acknowledging the force of the arguments of the honorable the Chief Secretary I would beg leave to suggest, that a copy of this report may be sent to Mr Wallace with a request, to place it after his perusal at the disposal of the editor of one of the local papers of the district, as there more particularly the information will be required.' O'Shanassy approved of M's suggestion on 27 June.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M’s report was published in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Melbourne economist</seg>, 18 July 1862 (B62.07.02) and reprinted in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">SMH</seg>, 30 July 1862 (B62.07.03). It was also widely summarized in, for example, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geelong advertiser</seg>, 26 July 1862, p. 2; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg> (Melbourne), 28 July 1862, p. 7; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 28 July 1862, p, 7; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Star</seg> (Ballarat), 1 August 1862, p. 3; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Farmers' journal and gardeners' chronicle, </seg>2 August 1862, p. 3; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Cornwall chronicle</seg> (Launceston, Tas.), 2 August 1862; <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mount Alexander mail</seg>, 11 August 1862, p. 3. </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Capsella%20bursa%20pastoris">Capsella bursa pastoris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cirsium%20lanceolatum">Cirsium lanceolatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cryptostemma%20calendulaceum">Cryptostemma calendulaceum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Erodium%20moschatum">Erodium moschatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lolium%20perenne">Lolium perenne</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Malva%20rotundifolia">Malva rotundifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Marrubium%20vulgare">Marrubium vulgare</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stellaria%20media">Stellaria media</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Trifolium%20repens">Trifolium repens</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
