<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 3 March 1862. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I am aware that I have acknowledged only recently the manifold demonstrations of your kindness; but to reward them is not...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-03-03-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>MS papers 37, no. 522, folder 204, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>62.03.03</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 3 March 1862. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I am aware that I have acknowledged only recently the manifold demonstrations of your kindness; but to reward them is not...</title>
               <date when="1862-03-03">1862-03-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1862/62-03-03-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Julius Haast</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 3 March 1862. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I am aware that I have acknowledged only recently the manifold demonstrations of your kindness; but to reward them is not...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">62.03.03</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Julius Haast</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">MS papers 37, no. 522, folder 204, Haast family papers, Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Melbourne im bot. u. zool. </seg>Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 3. März 1862.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Edler Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin es mir bewusst nur kürzlich die vielseitigen Beweise Ihrer Güte anerkannt zu haben; solche zu lohnen liegt es nicht in meiner Macht! Ihre stete Freundschaft, mit welcher Sie mich ehren, u die überschwengliche Güte, mit welcher Sie mein Wirken beurtheilen, erfüllt mich mit tiefem Dank. Gebe Ihnen die Vorsehung Kraft u Wohlsein, um in Ihrem herrlichen Wirkungskreise ungestört zu wirken <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>u der Forscher-Lorbeeren am Altar der Wissenschaft viele zu erringen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn es nicht unrecht wäre, möchte ich Sie beneiden um den Aufenthalt in der schönen Insel dort! Hier im langen dürren Sommer, unter den Miasmen einer Übervölkerung, im Staube eines grossen Verkehres, sehne ich mich oft hinaus in die freien leichten Lüfte der Alpen. Der Geist wird dort frisch belebt bei der Anschauung der grossartigen Natur, u der Körper erfrischt in den herrlichen Bergen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Jahre lange Überanstrengung in literarischen Arbeiten u drängenden Geschäftsleben, dazu die Strapazen, Entbehrungen der 1½ Jährigen Entdeckungsreise mit Gregory im tropischen Australien, haben meine Constitution etwas erschüttert, u leidend gelegentlich an Neuralgie, muss ich Sie, Theuerster, bitten nicht zu ungünstig es zu beurtheilen, wenn nicht Alles, was ich wünschte, für Sie thue. — Ihre Pflanzensammlungen sind noch immer nicht angelangt u tantalisirt anmerklich von Tage zu Tage sie zu durchblättern. Sind mir doch die Pflanzenformen Neuseelands so interessant wegen deren inniger Verknüpfung mit der Vegetation unserer Alpen. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wir haben es nicht fehlen lassen nach vielfacher Nachfrage u. man hat mich versichert, dass die sämtlichen längstlichen u jüngst von Ihnen u dem vortrefflichen Mr Travers zusammengebrachten u abgesandten Schätze nun bald anlangen würden. Es ist mir lieb, dass Sie diese Sammlungen unter Hooker u mir theilten; ihm dem Verfasser der Neuseeland Flora liegt es zunächst ob, zu seinem Werke Supplemente zu liefern, wofür ich ihm Notizen u meine Ansichten über Ihre u Herrn Travers Pflanzen mittheilen kann, ohne gerade als Rival aufzutreten. Es verlangt mich indessen sehr darnach früher oder später die Gelegenheit zu haben, eine Vegetations-Skizze der Chatham Inseln zu liefern, für welchen Zweck ich möglicher Weise einen Sammler dorthin senden werde. Ich habe mit Hr Katzenstein über die nothwendigen Anordnungen correspondirt. Für die Arbeit möchte ich gern die Materialien als Monopol besitzen, da Hooker nicht Gelegenheit hatte, die kleine Inselgruppe zu erforschen. Ich schuldige einer Akademie noch eine Abhandlung, für welche die Chatham Vegetation ein herrliches Thema liefern würde.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vor April wird die R. S. hier nicht wieder eine Sitzung halten u vor Mai oder Juni werden nicht die Formen durchgangen sein, um Sie als Ehrenmitglied zu creïren. Länger noch wird es währen, ehe Ihre Abhandlung durch die Presse gehen wird u daher werde ich um so bereitwilliger Anordnungen treffen, dass eine Kopie Ihrer Abhandlung in Manuscript an Hochstetter gelange. Eigentlich ist dies gegen unsere Statuten, da jedoch nur eine </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">deutsche Übertragung</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> verlangt wird, so kann ich wohl ohne directe Erlaubnis nachzusuchen, die Abhandlung Hochstetter zugänglich machen, u gedenke es bei der Märzpost zu thun.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der erste Band meiner Flora ist durch die Presse gebracht aber noch nicht gebunden, so dass ich selbigen erst später zu senden vermag. Inzwischen werden auch wohl Ihre Herbarien anlangen. Ihr letzter Brief kam über Sydney daher nicht gleichzeitig mit den Sammlungen. Wäre es nicht der Controlle wegen wünschenswerth, einen Frachtbrief von den Macklern zu erzwingen? Mir ist Angst, dass einmal eine Zusendung ganz verloren gehen möchte; so haben mich die vor vielen Monate von Hr Travers abgesandten Pflanzen noch immer nicht erreicht. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich denke, dass ich 2 Wochen lang meine Stadt Arbeiten abbrechen kann, um eine weitere Triangulation in den Alpen vorzunehmen. Dabei werde ich der Grossmuth gedenken, welche Sie in der Bezeichnung des Gletscherstromes mir erwiesen. Es wäre herrlich, wenn wir diese u Ihre Alpen einmal gemeinsam durchwandern können u vermögen Sie es, so besuchen Sie mich in der schönen Frühlingsjahreszeit u. nehmen Sie fürlieb mit der Gastfreundschaft, die mein Dach zu bieten vermag. Für Ihre eigene freundliche Einladung innigen Dank! Ich verspreche selbiger, wenn immer ich mich losmachen kann, zu entsprechen. In meinem Freunde Hr Katzenstein dort, werden Sie einen höchst schätzenswerthen Mann finden. Bei der Vertheilung unserer Pflanzendublette will ich freudig für Ihr Museum zurücklegen; Deponiren Sie nur dort auch numerirte Pflanzen Ihrer eignen Sammlung. Mir scheint unsere Briefe sind immer sehr lange unterwegs.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit inniger Freundschaft</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Bitte Hr Travers u Hr Katzenstein freundlichst grüssen zu wollen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich stimme mit Allem was Sie über Hr Droege sagen völlig überein.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, Botanic and Zoological Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">3 March 1862.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Noble friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am aware that I have acknowledged only recently the manifold demonstrations of your kindness; but to reward them is not in my power! Your steadfast friendship with which you honour me, the extravagant kindness with which you judge my labours, fill me with deep gratitude. May Providence grant you strength and good health to labour uninterrupted in your glorious field, and may you gain many laurels at the altar of science.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If it were not wrong, I could envy you your life in your beautiful island there! Here, during the long dry summer, with the pollution of over-population, in the dust of heavy traffic, I often long to get out into the fresh open air of the alps. There the spirit is revived in contemplation of wonderful nature, and the body is refreshed in the glorious mountains.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Long years of overwork in literary labours and pressing business affairs, in addition to the hardship and privations of the 1½ years on the exploring expedition with Gregory in tropical Australia,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> have depleted my constitution somewhat, and suffering periodically from neuralgia, I must ask you, dearest friend, not to judge too harshly when I cannot always do for you everything I would wish to do.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your plant collections still have not arrived, and I become daily more impatient to look through them. How interesting the New Zealand plant forms are to me on account of their close relationship with the vegetation of our alps.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We have not failed to make repeated enquiries, and I was assured that all of the long outstanding as well as the recent treasures brought together and dispatched by you and by the excellent Mr Travers would arrive soon. I am pleased that you divided the collections between Hooker and me. As the author of the Flora of New Zealand<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker (1853-5).</p>
               </note> it is in the first instance up to him to publish supplements to his work. Towards that I can send him notes for it and communicate to him my opinion on your and Mr Travers' plants, without being exactly regarded as a rival. However, I long very much to have the opportunity sooner or later to publish a vegetation sketch of the Chatham Islands, and towards this end I might possibly send a collector there. I have already corresponded about the necessary arrangements with Mr Katzenstein.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note> For this work I would like to have a monopoly on the materials, as Hooker had no opportunity to explore this small group of islands. I also owe a paper to an academy, and the Chatham vegetation would provide a marvellous theme for that.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's account of the vegetation of the Chatham Islands was eventually published as a separate work; see B64.10.02.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Royal Society of Victoria will not hold a session until April, and it will be May or June before the forms have been gone through to make you an honorary member.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Haast's nomination for honorary membership was not presented until the Society's meeting on 20 October 1862; he was duly elected at the following meeting, on 17 November.</p>
               </note> It will take even longer, before your paper will go through the press. I am therefore all the more willing to make arrangements to get a manuscript copy of your paper to Hochstetter. Strictly speaking that is in breach of our statutes; as, however, only a <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">German translation</hi>
               </seg> is required, I can probably make the paper available to Hochstetter without seeking direct permission, and intend to do so with the March mail.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Haast's paper, 'On the Physical Geography and Geology of New Zealand, principally in reference to the Southern Alps', was read at the Society's meeting on 26 May 1862. It was, however, lost during the four-year disruption in the publication of the Society's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions</seg>, 1861-5, and was never published in the journal. No German translation appears in the list of Haast's publications in H. von Haast (1948), pp. 1088 ff. However, Hochstetter (1863), p. 303, under 'Geologie' in the general bibliography, lists the English title as an 1861 publication in the 'Proceedings of the Melb. Royal Society'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first volume of my Flora<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B62.03.03.</p>
               </note> has gone through the press, but is not yet bound, so that I can't send it until later. In the meantime your collection should, I hope, have arrived. Your last letter came via Sydney and thus not together with the collections. Would it not be desirable for the purpose of keeping control to insist on a bill of lading from the brokers? I am afraid that one day a consignment might be lost altogether; for example, the plants sent to me by Mr Travers many months ago have still not reached me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I think I should be able to interrupt my work in the city for two weeks to undertake further triangulations in the Alps. While doing so I will remember your magnanimity, which you have extended to me in naming the glacier stream after me.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mueller Glacier, near Mt Cook, NZ.</p>
               </note> It would be wonderful, if we could wander together one day through these and through your Alps. If you are able, do visit me some time during the beautiful spring season and accept the hospitality my home can offer you. For your own kind invitation my sincere thanks! I promise to avail myself of it, if I can ever get away. You will find my friend Mr Katzenstein there to be an admirable man. While distributing our plant duplicates I am happy to put some aside for your Museum. Make sure you also deposit numbered plants of your own collections there. It seems to me our letters always take very long.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In sincere friendship</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Please be so kind and give my regards to Mr Travers and Mr Katzenstein.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Katzenstein Jr; see M to J. Haast, 24 December 1861 (in this edition as 61-12-24a).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I agree completely with all that you say about Mr Droege.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
