<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ The botanic Garden was set up by the former Governor La Trobe, ¶  a great admirer and promoter of the natural sciences, in one of the most beautiful parts of our neighbourhood. It is situated appro...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1858/58-01-00c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>58.01.00c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ The botanic Garden was set up by the former Governor La Trobe, ¶  a great admirer and promoter of the natural sciences, in one of the most beautiful parts of our neighbourhood. It is situated appro...</title>
               <date when="1858-01">1858-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1858/58-01-00c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Mesembryanthemum</term>
               <term>Nymphaea</term>
               <term>Stapelia</term>
               <term>Sedum</term>
               <term>Aloe</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Wilhelm Sonder</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ The botanic Garden was set up by the former Governor La Trobe, ¶  a great admirer and promoter of the natural sciences, in one of the most beautiful parts of our neighbourhood. It is situated appro...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">58.01.00c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Wilhelm Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found; for the extract given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hamburger Garten- und Blumen-Zeitung</seg>, vol. 14, pp. 168-70 (B58.04.02). The text is preceded by a cover note from Sonder to the editor of the journal dated 22 March 1858: Von meinem Freunde, dem Herrn Dr. Ferd. Müller, Director des botanischen Gartens zu Melbourne in Australien, erhielt ich dieser Tage einige Mittheilungen über den dortigen botanischen Garten, die vielleicht von vielen Lesern der Gartenzeitung nicht ohne Interesse gelesen werden dürften, weshalb ich Ihnen dieselben zur Benutzung übersende' [Today I received some communications from my friend, Dr Ferd. Müller, Director of the Botanic Garden in Melbourne, Australia, about the botanic Garden there, that might perhaps be of interest to many readers of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenzeitung</seg>, and which I therefore send to you for that purpose]. M's letter is dated to early January as the latest likely date that it could have been sent to have reached Sonder by mid-March.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der botanische Garten wurde vom früheren Gouverneur La Trobe, einem grossen Verehrer und Beförderer der Naturwissenschaften, in einem der schönsten Theile unserer Nachbarschaft angelegt. Er liegt etwa ½ englische Meile von dem Theile der Stadt Melbourne, welcher in Contact mit der grossen Steinbrücke über die Yarra Yarra steht. Der Garten ist an einer Seite vom Yarra=Fluss begrenzt und besteht aus 110 Ackern Landes, welches sich in sanften Undulationen nach der Yarra hinabsenkt, enthält einen kleinen Landsee, der in früherer Zeit durch den Austritt des Flusses während der Regenmonate gebildet wurde, jetzt aber durch einen trockenen Weg von den waldigen Ufern der Yarra getrennt ist. Im Schatten dieses anmuthigen Weges werden alle unsere deutschen Hain=Lieblinge wohl gedeihen, und ich beabsichtige längs des Wegs eine Allee immergrüner Bäume anzulegen, sobald ich dazu die nöthige Anzahl zusammenbringen kann. Einige der Abhänge sind felsig und sehr romantisch, ich hoffe diese schönen Parthien durch Einführung von Succulenten, namentlich des Caplandes als <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Mesembryanthemum">Mesembryanthemum</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Aloe">Aloe</name>, <name key="Stapelia">Stapelia</name>
               </seg>, u,s,w, zu verschönern. Deutschland wird mir dazu seine <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Sedum">Sedum</name>
               </seg>-Arten liefern, Amerika seine Cacteen, von denen manche hier ohne Schutz im Freien ganz gut fort kommen. Im Landsee des Gartens hoffe ich dereinst eine gute Sammlung der prächtigen Nymphäen zusammen zu haben, vielleicht auch die wundervolle Victoria Wasserlilie, obwohl für letztere vielleicht unser Winter doch zu kalt sein möchte. Bis jetzt sind die einheimischen Wasserpflanzen die einzigen Besitzer, welche Schaaren von wilden Enten mannigfaltiger Art, von Wasserhühnern, wilden Gänsen, Reihern etc. heranlocken, wo sie allein noch Schutz finden in dem weiten Umkreis der Hauptstadt. Dadurch, dass später ein paar Inselchen im See gehoben werden, wird sich derselbe noch mehr beleben, weil wenig von dem Federvolk in der Umgegend Ruhe genug findet, um seine Nester zu bauen. Ein grosses Drahtgebäude ist gerade fertig geworden in einer bepflanzten Schlucht für die Aufnahme europäischer Singvögel, namentlich Nachtigallen. Es ist so gross, dass es Bäume und Sträucher einschliesst, so dass die Thierchen ihre Gefangenschaft nur halb fühlen und uns durch Zuwachs erfreuen werden. Wir beabsichtigen auf diese Weise die Singvögel zu naturalisiren. Ein kleines Treibhaus ist </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">da; ein grösseres Kalthaus habe ich ziemlich diesen Winter mit Pflanzen gefüllt; ein noch grösseres Gewächshaus für tropische Pflanzen, welches mit Wasserdampf geheizt werden soll, ist im Entstehen. Die Militärmusik erfreut uns einmal in der Woche, ich baue jetzt einen hübschen Pavillon für den Zweck. Am See habe ich auch eine Drahteinhegung begonnen, welche Känguruhs, eine Gazelle, schwarze Schwäne, unsere Strausse, Dachse, Kaninchen seltener Art, Opossums und andere Thiere enthält und der Anfang eines zoologischen Gartens ist. Dass der Garten ein grossartiger wird, geht schon daraus hervor, dass ich zu Zeiten 50, beständig 20 Leute beschäftige. Der Gouverneur, der Rath und die Colonisten sind mir alle im grössten Wohlwollen zugeneigt; stolz bin ich als Deutscher auf diese Beweise von Güte und Vertrauen, es ist aber mein höchster Wunsch der Colonie Dienste zu leisten, welche das Vertrauen rechtfertigen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The botanic Garden was set up by the former Governor La Trobe,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Melbourne Botanic Garden was founded in 1846. See R. Pescott (1982) p. 16.</p>
               </note> a great admirer and promoter of the natural sciences, in one of the most beautiful parts of our neighbourhood. It is situated approximately half an English mile from that part of the city of Melbourne that is linked by the big stone bridge across the Yarra Yarra. The Garden is bordered on one side by the Yarra River and consists of 110 acres of land, which inclines towards the river in gentle undulations. It contains a small lake, formed some time in the past by the flooding of the river during the rainy months, but now separated from the wooded banks of the Yarra by a dry road. In the shade of this road all our favourite German plants of groves should thrive, and I intend to plant an avenue of evergreen trees along this road as soon as I am able to accumulate them in the necessary quantity. Some of the declivities are rocky and very romantic, I hope to beautify these lovely spots by the introduction of succulents, especially those of the Cape Colony, like <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Mesembryanthemum">Mesembryanthemum</name>
               </seg>,<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Aloe">Aloe</name>
               </seg>,<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Stapelia">Stapelia</name>
               </seg>, etc. Germany will provide me with its <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Sedum">Sedum</name>
               </seg> species for it, America with its cacti, some of these can grow here quite well without protection out in the open ground. In the lake of the Gardens I hope to bring together one day a good collection of the glorious <name key="Nymphaea">Nymphaea</name>e, perhaps even also the wonderful Victoria lily, although for the latter our winters might perhaps be too cold after all.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Victoria amazonica</seg> flowered for the first time, in a heated glass house, at the Melbourne Botanic Garden in 1867. See Maroske (1992).</p>
               </note> So far the the only occupants are the indigenous water plants, which attract flocks of wild ducks of many kinds, of water hens, wild geese, herons, etc., the only place where they still find a refuge in the wider surroundings of the capital city. By later raising up a few small islands in the lake it will become even more enlivened, because few of the feathered population find sufficient quiet in the surrounding areas to build nests. A large wire cage has just been completed in one of the planted gullies for the reception of European songbirds, in particular nightingales.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Maroske &amp; Gilfedder (1994).</p>
               </note> It is so large as to enclose trees and shrubs, so that the little animals are only half aware of their imprisonment and will delight us by increasing in numbers. We intend to naturalize the songbirds in this way. There is a small propagating house; I have just about filled up a larger cold house with plants this winter. A still larger glasshouse for tropical plants, to be heated with steam, is under construction.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M submitted plans for the heating of the palmhouse in March 1858. See M to J. O'Shanassy, 1 April 1858.</p>
               </note> We enjoy military band music once a week, I am now building a pretty pavilion for that purpose. At the lake I have also commenced putting up a wire fence enclosure that houses kangaroos, a gazelle, black swans, our emus, badgers, rare species of rabbits, possums and other animals, and is the beginning of a zoological garden. That the Garden is going to be grand is already indicated in that I currently employ 50, and permanently 20 persons. The Governor, the Council and the colonists are all very kindly inclined towards me. As a German I am proud of these demonstrations of kindness and trust, but it is my greatest wish to be of service to the Colony in such a way as to justify this trust.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Aloe">Aloe</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mesembryanthemum">Mesembryanthemum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Nymphaea">Nymphaea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sedum">Sedum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stapelia">Stapelia</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
