<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Let me congratulate you, dear Krichauff for the excellent manner in which you are conducting your Bureau. It has developed astonishingly quickly and proved very practical. I confine myself in rural...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-05-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.05.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ Let me congratulate you, dear Krichauff for the excellent manner in which you are conducting your Bureau. It has developed astonishingly quickly and proved very practical. I confine myself in rural...</title>
               <date when="1890-05">1890-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-05-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Accidium Babiridis</term>
               <term>Puccinia straminis</term>
               <term>Puccinia graminis</term>
               <term>Borragineae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/6cc2e9c9-7c72-4397-8fe8-d3399bcfb928">Berberis</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="69">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="31">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Friedrich Krichauff</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Let me congratulate you, dear Krichauff for the excellent manner in which you are conducting your Bureau. It has developed astonishingly quickly and proved very practical. I confine myself in rural...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">90.05.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Friedrich Krichauff</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Deutsche Zeitung</seg>, 21 May 1890, p. 1 (B90.05.03), where it was published under the heading 'Bemerkungen über Rotrost vom Baron Herrn von Müller' [Remarks on red rust by Baron von Müller] and introduced by 'Herr F. E. H. W. Krichauff hatte die Freundlichkeit, uns einen Teil eines Briefes des Barons Herrn von Müller an ihn zum Abdrucke in der "Austral. Ztg." zuzusenden. Wir kommen dem Wunsche gerne nach. Der Brief lautet:' [Mr F. E. H. W. Krichauff has been kind enough to send us part of a letter from Baron von Müller to him, for publication in the Austral. Ztg. We willingly comply with the request. The letter runs:]. An English translation was published in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bendigo advertiser</seg>, 31 May 1890, p. 3 (B90.05.02), and in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">South Australian register</seg>, 17 June 1890, p. 3 (B90.06.05).</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Lass meine Felicitation ausgesprochen sein, lieber Krichauff, für die vortreffliche Weise, in welcher Du Dein "Bureau" leitest! Es hat sich auffallend schnell entwickelt und sehr praktisch bewährt. Ich selbst beschränke mich im ruralen Wirken nur auf Korrespondenz und die Weiterführung der "Select plants", von welchem gewiss nützlichen aber auch in Südaustralien fast nie zitierten Werke eben eine Uebersetzung ins Portugiesische durch die Presse geht, nachdem eine deutsche und französische erschienen; eine spanische ist auch im Fortschritt. Bezüglich der Metamorphose des Rostpilzes möchte ich bemerken, dass die Arbeiten von Ploughwright nur diejenigen De Bary's etwas erweitern. Im großen Ganzen hatte der letztere den Cyklus der Entwicklungsstadien vor mehr denn 20 Jahren aufgeklärt, und er hatte die Aufmerksamkeit, mir die Resultate seiner Beobachtungen damals gleich direkt mitzuteilen, so dass ich den damals wöchentlich den Botanischen Garten besuchenden "Argus"-Rapporteur nicht nur den Vorgang an <name key="Berberis">Berberis</name> in Bezug auf <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name>, sondern auch an Borragineen</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">für die nahe verwandte <name key="Puccinia%20straminis">Puccinia straminis</name> demonstrieren konnte. Prof. Börnicke wies aber damals schon noch, dass das Fortbestehen der P. graminis nicht von <name key="Accidium%20Babiridis">Accidium Babiridis</name> abhängig sei. Im Jahr 1865 gab ich eine Vorlesung, die gedruckt und weit verbreitet wurde, vor der Agricult. Society of Sandhurst. Darin machte ich unter anderen darauf aufmerksam, dass der Rostpilz den Weizen auf etwas salinem Boden oder unter dem nahen Einfluss der Meeresküste nicht oder kaum angreift, so dass Experimente angestellt werden sollten für Zuthun von rohem Kochsalz bei Bestellung der Felder, was ja überhaupt Dungwert haben würde. Das Salz, welches an den salinen Seen inkrustiert in Südaustralien, wäre dafür sehr gut verwendbar.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Let me congratulate you, dear Krichauff for the excellent manner in which you are conducting your Bureau. It has developed astonishingly quickly and proved very practical. I confine myself in rural work just to correspondence and the continuation of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select plants</seg>, of which work, certainly useful but even in South Australia almost never cited, a translation into Portugese is currently going through the press<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to J. Henriques, 3 May 1889, in this edition as 89-05-03b. The Portuguese edition did not appear until 1905 (B05.13.01).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>after German and French ones were published.<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B83.13.06, B87.14.06.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg> A Spanish edition is also in progress.<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No Spanish edition was published and no information concerning a possible Spanish translation has been found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg> In reference to the metamorphosis of the rust fungus I may remark that the works of Ploughwright<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Plowright? See Plowright (1881).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg> only expand somewhat on that of De Bary.<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>De Bary (1866).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg> Upon the whole the latter explained the cycle of development stages more than 20 years ago and had the courtesy of informing me directly right at the time of the results of his observations,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> so that I could demonstrate to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> reporter, at that time visiting the Botanical Gardens weekly, not only the process in respect to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name>
               </seg> on <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Berberis">Berberis</name>
               </seg>, but also on <name key="Borragineae">Borragineae</name> for the closely related <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Puccinia%20straminis">Puccinia straminis</name>
               </seg>. Professor Börnicke,<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Typesetter's error for Körnicke? A report by Könicke that the berberry is not an essential part of the transmission, dating from the 1860s when the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> reporters were visiting the Gardens regularly, has not been seen; in M to J. Barrow, 15 February 1868 (B68.04.05) for the SA Royal Commission into diseases in cereals, M does not make this point, stating that in middle Europe de Bary had traced the development only on the leaves of the berberry bush, but that 'in Australia the mystery of their growth has not yet been penetrated'. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Körnicke (1877), p. 39 describes situations around Bonn and in East Prussia where the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                           <name key="Berberis">Berberis</name>
                        </seg> was absent from areas where <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                           <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name>
                        </seg>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>was common.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg> however, had already proved at that time that the continuance of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">P. graminis</seg> was not dependent on <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Accidium babiridis</seg>.<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Typesetters error for <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Aecidium berberidis</seg>? Translated as 'accidium of the barberry' in the version of this letter in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">South Australian register</seg>. </p>
                  </note>
               </seg> In 1865 I gave a lecture before the Agricultural Society of Sandhurst, which was printed and widely circulated.<seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now Bendigo, Vic. B65.04.05.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg> In it I pointed out amongst other things that the rust fungus does not or scarcely attacks wheat on somewhat saline soil, or under the near influence of the sea coast, so that experiments should be made for the addition of raw cooking salt in tilling the fields, which would afterall have value as manure. The salt, which is incrusted on all saline lakes in South Australia, would be very suitable for this.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter extract is followed by:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.472in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wir erlauben uns zu der Anführung des geehrten Herrn Briefstellers: "dass der Rostpilz den Weizen auf etwas salinem (salzhaltigem) Boden oder unter dem nahe Einfluss der Meeresluft nicht oder kaum angreift &amp;c" folgende Bermerkungen: Diese Ansicht ist als unrichtig längst aufgegeben. Der Rostpilz tritt auf salzhaltigem Boden, selbst auf Feldern, die unmittelbar an der Seeküste liegen, ebenso wohl und ebenso häufig auf als auf Binnenländereien. In Port Elliot, Encounter Bay, Victor Harbour, Port Gawler, Port Wakefield, Port Victoria in Südaustralien, wo die Weizenfelder in unmittelbarer Nähe des Meeres liegen, vergeht kein Jahr ohne Rosterscheinungen, die häufig so stark sind, dass der gesamte Weizenbestand zu Heu niedergemäht wird. Auf der langgedehnten und schmalen YorkesHalbinsel, über welche täglich die Seewinde mit ihrem Salzgehalte wehen, die selbst reich an Salzniedrungen ist, tritt der Rost so häufig und so vernichtend auf, als nur irgendwo auf einem Weizenfelde fern von der See. Mit diesen bekannten Thatsachen fällt denn auch die Annahme, dass Salz ein Mittel gegen den Rost sei. D. R.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.472in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">[We venture the following remarks to the quotation of the esteemed writer: "that the rust fungus does not or scarcely attacks wheat on somewhat saline soil, or under the near influence of the sea coast &amp;c." This opinion was dismissed long ago as incorrect. The rust fungus breaks out on saline soil, even on fields that lie directly on the sea coast, just as much and just as often as on inland country. In Port Elliot, Encounter Bay, Victor Harbour, Port Gawler Port Wakefield, Port Victoria in South Australia, where the wheat fields are close by the sea, no year goes by without appearances of rust, which are frequently so severe that the whole wheat crop is mown down to hay. On the elongated and narrow Yorke Peninsula, over which the sea wind blows daily with its salt content, and which is rich in salt depressions, the rust breaks out as frequently and as destructively as on any wheat field far from the sea. With these well known facts the assumption that salt is a remedy against the rust then also fails. The editor.]</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Accidium%20Babiridis">Accidium Babiridis</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Borragineae">Borragineae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Berberis">Berberis</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Puccinia%20graminis">Puccinia graminis</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Puccinia%20straminis">Puccinia straminis</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
