<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Monga ¶ 30/8/90. ¶ Most esteemed Baron, ¶  ¶ The day before yesterday I arrived back here and found your letter with the enclosed remittance, for which I thank you most sincerely. I herewith enclose t...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Bäuerlen</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-08-30-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M21, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.08.30</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Bäuerlen</author>
               <title>Monga ¶ 30/8/90. ¶ Most esteemed Baron, ¶  ¶ The day before yesterday I arrived back here and found your letter with the enclosed remittance, for which I thank you most sincerely. I herewith enclose t...</title>
               <date when="1890-08-30">1890-08-30</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-08-30-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eriostemon Coxii</term>
               <term>Hakea Macraeana</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Monga ¶ 30/8/90. ¶ Most esteemed Baron, ¶  ¶ The day before yesterday I arrived back here and found your letter with the enclosed remittance, for which I thank you most sincerely. I herewith enclose t...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">90.08.30</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Wilhelm Bäuerlen</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M21, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS found with specimen of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> baeuerlenii</seg> (MEL 733006), coll. W. Bäuerlen, Sugarloaf Mountain at the Clyde River, NSW, 1890. MS annotation by M: 'Beantw 7/9/90 F.v.M N. 321. (1884) vielleicht var von E. viminalis' [Answered 7/9/90 F.v.M. Nr 321, perhaps a variety of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. viminalis</seg>].</p>
               </note>Monga</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">30/8/90.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Geehrtester Herr Baron.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vorgestern langte ich wieder hier an u. fand Ihren Brief mit einliegender Remisse, für welche ich herzlichst danke, u. schliesse nun die Quittung ein, so dass dieselbe mit der ersten Post abgeht, denn wir haben hier die Post blos zweimal in der Woche.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Die Eucalypte, die Sie in mitgehendem Packet erhalten, scheint sich mit keiner deren in Ihrer "Eucalyptographia" illustrirten übereinstimmen zu lassen, wesshalb ich Ihnen sogleich einiges Material mit Notizen zusende, u. wenn erforderlich oder erwünscht kann ich Ihnen mehr u. grössere Ex. später senden. Diese Art fand ich vorgestern auf einer Höhe von etwa 4,000 f. als ein kleiner dünner Strauch von ungefähr 5'-10' f Höhe u. 2 Zoll im Durchmesser. Gestern nahm ich mir vor den Strauch abwärts zu verfolgen, u. so fand ich dass er weiter unten malleeartig wächst, d. h. mehrere Stämme kommen von einem Wurzelstollen, u. noch tiefer hinab wird er baumartig von ungefähr 40 f Höhe u. 6"-10" Zoll im Durchmesser, immer mit einem starken dicken Wurzelstollen, so dass die Art von 4,000 f bis ungefähr zu 2,500 f hinabsteigt. Blüthe, Frucht, Knospen u. Blätter bleiben sich auf den verschiedenen Elevationen immer gleich. Die Art wächst auf sehr steilem Boden, zwischen wilden Felsblöcken u. losem Steingeröll. Die sehr steile Bergseite auf welcher sie vorkommt schaut nördlich, u. auf dem südlichen Abhang des Berges konnte ich bis jetzt keine Spur derselben entdecken. — Zwar bin ich immer etwas schüchtern Ihnen Eucalypten Ex. zu senden, doch denke ich dass die mitgehende interressant ist, u. Ihnen nicht die Zeit unnöthigerweise raubt zumal da der Standort selbst schon merkwürdig ist, indem derselbe früher schon zwei neue Arten lieferte, namlich <name key="Eriostemon%20Coxii">Eriostemon Coxii</name> u. <name key="Hakea%20Macraeana">Hakea Macraeana</name>. Auf der obersten Elevation kommen die drei Arten miteinander vor. Eriost. hört aber schon nach ungefähr 200 f Niederung auf, während die Hakea die Eucalypte ganz hinunter begleitet. Auch ist diese Eucalypte die einzige die jetzt in dieser Region in Blüthe steht. Die Rinde ist glatt u. bräunlich von Farbe, sie streift sich in schmalen Bändern ab. Ich füge einige Notizen bei, welche an gepressten Ex. vielleicht nicht auffallend sind u. entgehen möchten. Der Kelch ist innen oft, jedoch nicht immer ganz blutroth oder rosenfarbig. Auch der Griffel ist oft ganz roth u. manchmal die eine Hälfte roth u. die andere grün, manchmal aber auch ganz grün. An der Aussenseite der Blüthe läuft oft, da wo die Stamen an dem Kelch sitzen ein schöner rother Ring herum, welcher dann den Blüthen ein liebliches Ansehen gibt. Es mag wohl blos Zuffall sein, aber an zwei Blumen bemerkte ich, dass sich der Griffel der Länge nach zu spalten anfing; die Theilung aber schien in der Mitte, d. h. der halben Länge des Griffels zu beginnen u. nicht ganz nach unten oder oben auszulaufen. Die Blätter sind ohne Glanz u. von gleicher Farbe an beiden Seiten. Die Blattkanten sind meistens roth, u. die äussere (convexe) Kante ist gewöhnlich röther, denn die innere (concave) Kante. Blätter des jungen Zustandes liegen bei. Die Krone des Baumes ist sehr licht, sogar unter den Eucalypten. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit besten Wünschen bleibe ich Ihnen stets ergeben</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Wilhelm Bäuerlen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C./o. Mr George MacRae</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Clyde Road</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Braidwood.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Monga<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">NSW.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">30/8/90.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Most esteemed Baron,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The day before yesterday I arrived back here and found your letter with the enclosed remittance, for which I thank you most sincerely. I herewith enclose the receipt, so that it leaves with the first mail, because we have the mail here only twice a week.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The eucalypt that you will receive in the accompanying parcel does not seem to agree with any of those illustrated in your <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptographia</seg>. For this reason I am sending you some material at once, together with notes. If required or desirable I can send you more and larger specimens later on. I found this species the day before yesterday at an altitude of approximately 4,000 feet as a small sparse shrub, about 5-10 feet tall and 2 inches in diameter. Yesterday I decided to follow the shrub downhill. I discovered that further down it grows mallee-like, that is, several trunks arise from the one rootstock, and still further down it becomes tree-like, to about 40 feet tall and 6-10 inches in diameter, always with a strong thick rootstock. Thus the species descends from 4,000 feet to about 2,500 feet. Flowers, fruit, buds and leaves remain the same at the different elevations. The species grows on very steep ground, between rough rock masses and loose boulders. The very steep side of the mountain on which it occurs faces north, and so far I have not been able to find any trace of it on the southern slope of the mountain.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am always a bit diffident about sending you <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> specimens, but I think that this present one will be of interest and will not waste your time unnecessarily, especially because the locality itself is remarkable in that it already yielded two new species in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eriostemon%20Coxii">Eriostemon Coxii</name>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">B84.12.02, p. 62.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Hakea%20Macraeana">Hakea Macraeana</name>.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">B86.11.02, p. 430.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The three species occur together at the highest elevation. But <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eriostemon</seg> disappears altogether about 200 feet further down, while the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hakea</seg> accompanies the eucalypt all the way down. This <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> is also the only one at present in flower in this region. The bark is smooth, brownish in colour, and is shed in narrow strips. I add a few notes of things that may not be very conspicuous in the pressed specimens and could be missed. The interior of the calyx is often but not always blood-red or rosy red. The style is also often completely red, sometimes half red and half green, but sometimes also completely green. At the level where the stamens are attached to the calyx, a lovely red ring often runs around the outside of the flower, which gives the flowers a very pretty appearance. It may be just coincidence but I noticed that on two flowers the style had begun to split lengthwise. The split seemed to start in the centre, i.e. halfway up the style, and did not continue all the way to the top or the bottom. The leaves are without gloss, with both sides the same colour. Leaf edges are usually red, and the outer (convex) edge is generally redder than the inner (concave) edge. Juvenile leaves are enclosed. The crown of the tree is very sparse, even among the eucalypts.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With best wishes I always remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wilhelm Bäuerlen</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>c/o Mr George MacRae</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Clyde Road</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Braidwood<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">NSW.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eriostemon%20Coxii">Eriostemon Coxii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Hakea%20Macraeana">Hakea Macraeana</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
