<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 3 Sept. 1890. ¶ The honorable Alfr. Deakin, M.L.A., ¶ Chief Secretary. ¶ Sir. ¶  ¶ In accordance with your request I have the honor, to report on the Lathyrus silvestris and other pasture-p...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-09-03-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>P90/3307, unit 240, VPRS 1163/P1 inward correspondence files, VA 672 Premier's Office, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.09.03</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 3 Sept. 1890. ¶ The honorable Alfr. Deakin, M.L.A., ¶ Chief Secretary. ¶ Sir. ¶  ¶ In accordance with your request I have the honor, to report on the Lathyrus silvestris and other pasture-p...</title>
               <date when="1890-09-03">1890-09-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-09-03-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/00f55ca2-3eac-40bb-b613-df907daed9b4">Medicago orbicularis</term>
               <term>Lathyrus silvestris</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/24bb1a3b-9acd-4f6b-b0f5-191f4dfb7f45">Medicago scutellata</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/a4946711-15f7-406b-ac7e-ac5f55dedc21">Lathyrus sativus</term>
               <term>Lathyrus Cicera</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/6d79a229-bb86-40a6-b453-d2fdcdfc7ba9">Oryzopsis</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Alfred Deakin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 3 Sept. 1890. ¶ The honorable Alfr. Deakin, M.L.A., ¶ Chief Secretary. ¶ Sir. ¶  ¶ In accordance with your request I have the honor, to report on the Lathyrus silvestris and other pasture-p...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">90.09.03</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Alfred Deakin</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">P90/3307, unit 240, VPRS 1163/P1 inward correspondence files, VA 672 Premier's Office, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 3 Sept. 1890.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The honorable Alfr. Deakin, M.L.A.,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Chief Secretary.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In accordance with your request I have the honor, to report on the <name key="Lathyrus%20silvestris">Lathyrus silvestris</name> and other pasture-plants, concerning which the West-Australian Government desires information. Through the Department of Agriculture here the above named Lathyrus has been brought under notice prominently in Victoria during the present year. The plant is long known in its European native countries as a perennial rambling herb of nutritive value, which — as its specific name implies, — likes wood-lands, and should in Australia prove particularly valuable in scrubby ranges. Already in the edition of 1888 I referred in the "select plants" specially to this <name key="Lathyrus%20silvestris">Lathyrus silvestris</name> as worthy of rural consideration,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B88.13.02, p. 279.</p>
               </note> but it should be borne in mind, that the "Jarosse", (<name key="Lathyrus%20sativus">Lathyrus sativus</name>) and an other of the "Flat Peas" (<name key="Lathyrus%20Cicera">Lathyrus Cicera</name>,) has caused, by frequent and copious use paralysis to pasture- or stable-animals, particularly through the pods of these plants, so that I have cautioned in the "Select plants" against the indiscriminate use of all the species of Lathyrus already by public means. As an ingredient of mixed pasturage the <name key="Lathyrus%20silvestris">Lathyrus silvestris</name> might become quite valuable, particularly when naturalized on stony or sandy declivities among other herbage; but we possess so many other equally nutritive plants, free of any danger, that the extensive utilisation of this Lathyrus seems hardly recommendable.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As regards the further information, desired by the W.A. Government about other plants, particularly suited for fodder and tried in Victoria, I would refer only to leading kinds, which, however, are likely to some extent already introduced as permanent possessions into the great western territory, especially as I have myself during the last thirty years forwarded rural seeds also to that part of the Australian continent in interchange for botanic specimens and seeds of W.A. native plants. Among English grasses, extensively grown in Victoria, should be mentioned as best, the Medow-Foxtailgrass, the Crested Dogtailgrass, the Cocksfoot-grass, the Meadow-Fescue, the perennial Rye-grass, the Timothy-grass, the Meadow Pea. (See index of vernaculars 504-517 in seventh edition of "Select plants"<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B88.13.02.</p>
               </note>) — concerning these and several other grasses and also herbs, recommendable for pastural purposes, special information being afforded in that work, of which many copies have successively found their way also to W.A. Among extra-english grasses should be mentioned as particularly noteworthy and as first introduced by me into Australia the Teosinte and the Coapim — besides these the Mitchell-grass, the Haleppo-Grass, the Southern Prairie-Grass, the <name key="Oryzopsis">Oryzopsis</name>, not to mention others freely noted in the work above quoted, and of which it would be well, that some hundreds of copies were distributed through West-Australia or there an <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">abridged edition</hi>
               </seg> for local use be brought out, containing all the plants, marked as prominently valuable with an <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">asterisk</hi>
               </seg>.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No such abridged edition was published.</p>
               </note> Regarding pasture- and stable-herbs doubtless the ordinary red and the common white clover are long since attended to in W.A. also, but perhaps not the Bersin-Clover, the Strawberry-Clover, the Alsike-Clover, the Carnation-Clover, the Japan-Clover. It is hardly necessary, to refer to the advantage of Luzerne-cultivation on a large scale and to that of the Vetch, Sainfoine and ordinary Grasses for which many regions of West Australia should be well adapted. But I would like, to draw particular attention to two species of Medicago, the M. orbicularis and M. scutellata, both introduced by me into Australia, as they are easily naturalized on pastures, are much liked by herds and flocks, and leave in the hot season the pods copiously on the ground for nutriment of pastoral stock without detriment to wool.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In new tracts of country, where as yet no detail experience in rural adaptation has been gained, it would be a good plan, to sow experimentally what Seed-Merchants call "Mixed pasture-grasses" and "Mixed pasture-herbs", in as much as after the end of the season in each locality it could be ascertained, which sorts had thriven best, so that then the specially eligible kinds could copiously be reared according to the then experience gained. All the plants, alluded to on this occasion, give a return in the first season; but the Carob-tree and some other highly important plants of woody growth should not be overlooked in general rural considerations within the great western colony, where the variety of clime in different regions through wide latitudes admits of very varied cultures and naturalizations. Indeed in an illustrated report on "the forest-resources of West-Australia", which on request I was happy to furnish honorarely to the authorities in Perth 1878, and which was published by the W.A. Government subsequently,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.13.10.</p>
               </note> I touched passingly also on the subject of the improvement of pastures there as desirable even in silvan districts.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I beg to accompany this document by a copy of the latest Edition of the "Select plants.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B88.13.02.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to be, Sir, your obedient and humble servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gov. Botanist.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">After it was typed up, M's letter was forwarded to the Premier's Office by T. Wilson, Undersecretary, on 16 September 1890, with 'a view to the Botanist's report being forwarded to the Chief Secretary of Western Australia'. An addendum by the Secretary for Agriculture, D. Martin, was sent to the Premier on 7 October, and both reports as well as a copy of M's book were forwarded to the Colonial Secretary, WA, on 13 October 1890.</p>
                  <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lathyrus%20Cicera">Lathyrus Cicera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lathyrus%20sativus">Lathyrus sativus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lathyrus%20silvestris">Lathyrus silvestris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Medicago%20orbicularis">Medicago orbicularis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Medicago%20scutellata">Medicago scutellata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Oryzopsis">Oryzopsis</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
