<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three years ago Messrs Crawford ¶ Alexander Crawford (1857-1935); Tiggott not positively identified; possible error for Piggott, several of this surname active in WA at this period? ¶  and Tiggot star...</title>
            <author>John Brooks</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-08-25b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.08.25b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>John Brooks</author>
               <title>Three years ago Messrs Crawford ¶ Alexander Crawford (1857-1935); Tiggott not positively identified; possible error for Piggott, several of this surname active in WA at this period? ¶  and Tiggot star...</title>
               <date when="1890-08-25">1890-08-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-08-25b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Triodia irritans</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/dfe52d12-cc3f-4620-8a9b-ab8361322615">Acacia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Three years ago Messrs Crawford ¶ Alexander Crawford (1857-1935); Tiggott not positively identified; possible error for Piggott, several of this surname active in WA at this period? ¶  and Tiggot star...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">90.08.25b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From John Brooks</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see 'Victoria-Spring wieder aufgefunden' [Victoria Spring found again], <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 19 November 1890, p. 6. <seg style="">The extract was footnoted: 'Mitteilung des Mr. S. P. Brooks </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">[sic] </seg>
                     <seg style="">zu Israelite Bay an Baron Ferd. von Müller, datiert 25. Aug. 1890, welche der Herr Baron die Güte hatte, uns zum Abdrucke zu übersenden' [Communication of Mr S. P. Brooks at Israelite Bay to Baron Ferd. von Mueller, dated 25 August 1890, which the Baron had the kindness to send us for printing].</seg>
                     <seg style=""> </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Vor 3 Jahren brachen die Herren Crawford und Tiggott von Mooldera im Eucla-Distrikte (mit Kameelen versehen) auf, um Victoria-Spring zu finden, welcher von dem Explorer Giles entdeckt und benannt worden war. Sie kehrten indess unverrichteter Sache zurück, und berichteten, dass sie weisse Sandhügel 1500 Fuss hoch gefunden hätten, aber alle Bemühungen die Quelle zu finden, wären vergeblich gewesen. Im vorigen Jahren zogen die Gebrüder Ponton auch dahin aus; 90 Meilen nördlich von ihrer Station trafen sie auf ein grosses Flussbett, mit einer Richtung nach Osten; sie folgten demselben; bis es sich in einer kleinen sandigen oder kiesigen Ebene verlief, umgeben von ziemlich hohen mit Sträuchern bestandenen Hügeln. Längs, des Flusslaufes waren in entfernten Zwischenräumen kleine Strecken reichen Graslandes, etwas grössere wurden in der Nähe der Hügel gefunden am östlichen Ende des Flusslaufes; im ganzen aber beschreiben diese Reisenden das Land als äusserst arm und steril. Sie fanden Wasser an vielen Stellen im Flussbette, genügend für ihren Gebrauch, aber nirgends von permanentem Charakter. In geringer Entfernung vom Flussbette, und stellenweise parallel damit, entdeckten sie Brown's Spuren, jene seiner Tour von Hampton-Plains nach Eyre's Patch, im Auftrage eines Eisenbahn-Syndikats. Auf einer seiner Lagerstätten fanden sie 6 Blechdosen mit präserviertem Fleisch, von denen 5 noch in ausgezeichnetem Zustande waren, obgleich sie in der Sonne gestanden hatten. Gewehre, Sättel und anderes Material, welches Brown hier hatte zurücklassen müssen, waren von den Eingeborenen fortgenommen worden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Fredric Neuman, ein intelligenter Schwede, welcher in dieser Gegend seit 5 oder 6 Jahren residiert, beschäftigte sich seit etwa einem halben Jahre mit der Erforschung des Landes, und teilte mir kürzlich die Ergebnisse seiner letzten Expedition mit, welche ich hier wieder gebe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nachdem er sich einen Eingeborenen als Führer verschafft hatte, der die Gegend bis 15 Meilen hinter Victoria-Springs kannte, reiste er 60 Meilen in nördlicher Direktion von Fraser's Range bis zu einem Felsen-Wasserloche ; weiter hinaus wurde das Land sehr arm, bestehend aus reinem, rötlichen, sandigen Boden, bedeckt mit dem stechenden Grase <name key="Triodia%20irritans">Triodia irritans</name>, und verkrüppeltem Euca!yptus-(Mallee) Gesträuch ; in einer Entfernung von 95 Meilen von Fraser's Range stiessen sie auf das oben von den Gebrüdern Ponton beschriebene Flussbett. Sie verfolgten dasselbe in einer meist nordwestlichen Richtung 90 Meilen weit über naturarmes Land ; kleine Stellen wurden hier und dort in diesem trockenen Flussbette gefunden, auf denen Mulga <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name> und krüppeliges Sandelholz wuchs, dazwischen spärliches, dürres Gras, welches die einzige Nahrung für ihre Pferde bildete. Obgleich viele Löcher im Flussbette gegraben wurden, fanden sie doch kein Wasser, ausser wo die Eingeborenen ihre Wasserlöcher hatten. Elnige derselben enthielten vollauf für Gebrauch, während an anderen die Hälfte der Pferde des Abends, die andere Hälfte des Morgens getränkt werden musste. Infolge der Dürre, welche in dieser Gegend geherrscht hat, benachrichtigten die Eingeborenen Neuman, dass er nicht weiter gehen könne, indem alles Wasser "Kakaboka" (tot) sei, aber dass an dem westlichen Ende des Flusslaufes ein grosser Salzsee sich befände, von welchem dieser Reisende glaubt — nach der Beschreibung der Eingeborenen — dass es derselbe sei, welcher von mir im Jahre 1875 entdeckt wurde, und bedauerte er sehr, dass es ihm nicht möglich war, dies nach eigener Anschauung zu bestätigen. In einer Entfernung von (nach Neuman's Berechnung) 135 Meilen von Fraser's Range, stiess die Partie auf Victoria-Spring. Neuman beschreibt das Wasser als aus der Umgebung zusammen leckend, nicht als eine richtige Quelle, etwa 12 Fuss im Quadrat. Seine durstigen Pferde tranken das Wasser etwa 6 Zoll herunter, aber in einer halben Stunde war es wieder gefüllt. Es ist umgeben von ungefähr 4000 Acker Grasland, dahinter Wüste mit Triodia-Gras und krüppeliger Mallee. Nahe dem Wasser waren viele Spuren von Giles' Expedition : Kameeldünger, Feuerplätze, Zeltstangen, mit Aexten gehauene Bäume, &amp;c. Palmen oder Grasbäume wurden nicht gesehen. Viele Emus kamen zu dem Wasser, und 15 Stück wurden geschossen; hätten die Reisenden mehr Ammunition übrig gehabt und grösseres Fleischbedürfnis, so hätten sie mehr als 100 schiessen, können. Neuman sah viele Eingegeborene</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eingeborene.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">; dieselben machten kein Geheimnis daraus, dass sie Kannibalen seien, sie klagten über die Zunahme der wilden Hunde, welche das Wild aufreiben, so dass es ihnen schwer fällt, das Leben zu fristen. Als er ihnen Stücke Emufleisch gab, verschlangen sie es, sobald es abgeschnitten war, ohne es nur mal zu wärmen. Er sah keine Kinder; sie benachrichtigten ihn, dass ein Knabe von 8—9 Jahren, den er aber nicht zu Gesicht bekam, der jüngste sei. Bei einer Gelegenheit, als er den Lauf des Flusses aufwärts verfolgte, traf er auf ein Lager von Eingeborenen. Nach der Anzahl von Speeren und Keulen zu urteilen, welche umher lagen, müssten nach Neuman's Urteil nahezu 600 Eingeborene hier kampiert haben ; er hatte kürz vorher einige Vögel geschossen, und der Knall hatte die Schwärzen verscheucht, nur 5 oder 6 hatten den Mut, zurück zu kehren.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">J. P. Brooks.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Israelite Bay, 25. </seg>
               <seg style="">August 1890.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter is followed by comments by M on Brooks's report; see M to the </seg>
                        <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>
                        <seg style="">, November 1890 (in this edition as 90-11-00) (B90.11.06). </seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Three years ago Messrs Crawford</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Alexander Crawford (1857-1935); Tiggott not positively identified; possible error for Piggott, several of this surname active in WA at this period?</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> and Tiggot started out from Mooldera in the Eucla district</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg style="">
                           <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>All places named are in WA.</seg>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> (provided with camels) to find Victoria Spring, which had been discovered and named by the explorer Giles. However, they returned without success and reported that they had found white sandhills 1500 feet high, but all efforts to find the spring had been in vain. In the previous year the Ponton brothers also set forth there; 90 miles north of their station they found a large river bed, with direction to the east; they followed it until it drained into a small sandy or gravelly plain surrounded by rather high hills covered with bushes. There were small stretches of rich grassland along the course of the river at distant intervals, somewhat larger ones were found close to the hills at the eastern end of the course of the river. However, these travellers described the land in general as extremely poor and sterile. They found water at many places in the bed of the river, enough for their use but nowhere of a permanent character. At a short distance from the river bed and here and there parallel with it they discovered Brown's tracks, those of his Hampton Plains trip to Eyre's Sand Patch under contract to a railway syndicate. At one of his camp sites they found six tins of preserved meat, of which five were still in excellent condition, although they had stood in the sun. Guns, saddles and other material that Brown had to leave behind here had been taken away by the Aborigines.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Frederic Neuman, an intelligent Swede who has resided in this region for five or six years, occupied himself for about half a year with exploration of <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the country and informed me recently of the results of his last expedition, which I repeat here.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After having obtained an Aborigine as a guide, who knew the region up to 15 miles behind Victoria Spring, he travelled 60 miles in a northerly direction from Fraser's Range up to a rocky water hole. Further on the country became very poor, consisting of pure reddish sandy soil, covered with the prickly grass </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Triodia%20irritans">Triodia irritans</name>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> and stunted </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> (mallee) bushes. At a distance of 95 miles from Fraser's Range they encountered the above river bed described by the Ponton brothers. They followed it in a mostly northwesterly direction 90 miles over naturally poor country. Small spots were found here and there in this dry river bed on which mulga </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> and stunted sandalwood grew, between which scanty dry grass that formed the only nourishment for their horses. Although many holes were dug in the river bed, they did not find water except where the Aborigines had their water holes. Some of them contained plenty for use, whereas at others half of the horses had to be watered in the evening, the other half in the morning. In consequence of the drought that prevailed in this region, the Aborigines informed Neuman that he could go no further, as all water was "Kakabola" (dead), but that at the western end of the water course there was a large salt lake, of which this traveller believed – according to the description of the Aborigines – that it was the same that was discovered by me in 1875 and he regretted very much that it was not possible for him to confirm this according to his own observation. At a distance of 135 miles from Fraser's Range (according to Neuman's reckoning) the party encountered Victoria Spring. Neuman described the water as trickling together from the surroundings, not as a proper spring, about 12 feet square. His thirsty horses drank the water down about six inches, but in half an hour it was filled again. It is surrounded by about 4000 acres of grassland, behind it desert with </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Triodia</seg>
               <seg style=""> grass and stunted mallee. Near the water were many traces of Giles's expedition: camel dung, fire-places, tent pegs, trees cut by axes &amp;c. Palms or grasstrees were not seen. Many emus came to the water and 15 of them were shot. Had the travellers more ammunition remaining and greater need for meat, they could have shot more than 100. Neuman saw many Aborigines, they made no secret that they were cannibals. They complained about the the increase of wild dogs that destroyed the game, so that it was difficult for them to live. When he gave them pieces of emu flesh, they gulped it down as soon as it was cut off, without even warming it. He saw no children. They informed him that a boy of 8-9 years, whom he however did not catch sight of, was the youngest. By chance as he followed the course of the river upstream, he came across a camp of the Aborigines. Judging by the number of spears and clubs that lay around, there must have been nearly 600 Aborignes camped here according to Neuman's opinion. Shortly before, he had shot some birds, and the report had frightened the Blacks away and only five or six had the courage to return.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. P. Brooks.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Israelite Bay, 25 August 1890.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acacia">Acacia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Triodia%20irritans">Triodia irritans</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
