<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ It may be of interest to you for your journal that at the large autumn exhibition of the local horticultural society I have brought mirrors into use for the first time. The effect is splendid. The ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-04-00a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.04.00a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ It may be of interest to you for your journal that at the large autumn exhibition of the local horticultural society I have brought mirrors into use for the first time. The effect is splendid. The ...</title>
               <date when="1890-04">1890-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-04-00a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Edmund Goeze</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ It may be of interest to you for your journal that at the large autumn exhibition of the local horticultural society I have brought mirrors into use for the first time. The effect is splendid. The ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">90.04.00a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Edmund Goeze</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see 'Einführung von grossen Spiegeln bei Blumen-Ausstellungen' [Introduction of large mirrors at flower shows], </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hamburger Garten- und Blumenzeitung</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 46, no. 6 (June 1890), pp. 269-70 (B90.06.05). The item is introduced: 'In einem vor Kurzem erhaltenen Briefe schreibt uns unser berühmter Freund, Baron Ferdinand von Mueller, Melbourne Folgendes' [In a recently received letter our famous friend Baron von Mueller of Melbourne writes as follows]. The article is signed 'G — e"; Edmund Goeze was the editor of the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hamburger Garten- und Blumenzeitung</seg>
                     <seg style="">. M's letter is dated to April 1890 as the latest likely date it could have been sent, to be quoted in the June issue of the journal.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">Es mag Ihnen für Ihre Zeitschrift von Interesse sein, dass ich bei der grossen Herbstausstellung der hiesigen Gartenbau-Gesellschaft zuerst Spiegel mit in Anwendung gebracht habe. Die Wirkung ist prachtvoll, durch die Reflexe wird das Sehfeld so verdoppelt, dass die Ausstellung sehr erweitert scheint. Spiegel sind zwar schon in europäischen (aber noch nicht in australischen) Gewächshäusern verwerthet worden, aber wohl nicht in ausgedehnterer Weise bei Blumen-, Gemüse- und Frucht-Ausstellungen und erscheint dies entschieden nachahmenswerth. Jeder Aussteller kann ja aus seiner Häuslichkeit einige Spiegel mitbringen, soweit sein Ausstellungs-Material und der Raum es erheischen.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The article concludes with an editorial comment: 'Auf den vielen Ausstellungen, welche wir im In- und Auslande zu besuchen Gelegenheit hatten, ist uns nie eine derartige Verwerthung von Spiegeln entgegengetreten, — mit einigem Kunstverständniss angebracht, dürften sie entschieden den Totaleindruck einer solchen Ausstellung wesentlich erhöhen und sind wir dem Herrn Baron sehr dankbar, dies freundlichst angeregt zu haben' [At the many exhibitions that we have had the opportunity to visit at home and abroad, we have never encountered such utilization of mirrors. </seg>
                     <seg style="">Employed with some feeling for art, they may decidedly enhance the total impression of such an exhibition substantialy and we are much obliged to the Baron for having most kindly suggested this]. See also M to Wittmack, 28 March 1890, for another report on this topic.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>It may be of interest to you for your journal that at the large autumn exhibition of the local horticultural society I have brought mirrors into use for the first time. The effect is splendid. The field of vision is so doubled by the reflection that the display seems enhanced very much. It is true mirrors have been utilized already in European glass houses (but not yet Australian), but probably not in a more extensive way in flower, vegetable and fruit exhibitions and this seems decidedly worthy of imitation. Each exhibitor can certainly bring some mirrors from his household as far as his exhibition material and the space warrents it.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
