<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ Finally after 42 years, the hope will probably be realised of clarifying the fate of Dr Leichhardt and his companions! Some months ago, a Mr Alexander M'Phee at Lagrange Bay ¶  heard through the Ab...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-02-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.02.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ Finally after 42 years, the hope will probably be realised of clarifying the fate of Dr Leichhardt and his companions! Some months ago, a Mr Alexander M'Phee at Lagrange Bay ¶  heard through the Ab...</title>
               <date when="1890-02">1890-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-02-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Alexander Supan</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ Finally after 42 years, the hope will probably be realised of clarifying the fate of Dr Leichhardt and his companions! Some months ago, a Mr Alexander M'Phee at Lagrange Bay ¶  heard through the Ab...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">90.02.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Alexander Supan</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The letter is undated. The first paragraph and a half was published, with some stylistic changes but without a date, in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Petermann's geographische Mitteilungen</seg>; see B90.05.04. The issue in which it appeared closed on 3 May 1890 so M's letter must have arrived in Gotha before that. Mail between Australia and Europe took 6 to 7 weeks at this period which would suggest that M probably sent the letter by late February 1890, which is consistent with the presence of McPhee and Jun Gun in Melbourne in late January 1890 (see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>
                     <seg style="">, 27 January 1890, p. 9)</seg>.<seg style=""> </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Endlich nach 42 Jahren wird wohl die Hoffnung erfüllt werden, das Geschick Dr Leichhardt's u. seiner Gefährten aufzuklären! Vor einigen Monaten hörte ein Mr. Alexander M'Phee an der Lagrange-Bay durch die Eingebornen zweier Stämme, deren jede Sprache er erlernt, von einem Weissen, "Jun Gun", der viele Tagereisen entfernt südöstlich sich unter den Autochthonen befinden sollte. Er brach, von Eingebornen geleitet u. von keinen Weissen begleitete, nach der Stätte auf, fand einen sehr hellfarbigen Mann aber von ächtem australischen Typus, welchen er mit nach Melbourne brachte. Dies Ereigniss würde unbedeutungsvoll sein, hätte Mr McPhee nicht von den ältesten Leuten des Stammes, — dem Jun-Gun angehört, — mit mancher Umständlichkeit erfahren, dass Solche von deren Nachbaren, in der Wüste weiter südöstlich lebend, vor langer Zeit gehört, es seien 2 Weisse u. 2 bekleidete Schwarze mit Pferden vom Nord-Osten kommend in dortiger Gegend verdurstet; die Pferde seien zuerst umgekommen, dann weiter vordringend die beiden Weissen, jeder in verschiedener Richtung nach Wasser suchend, u. Einer nach dem Andern verschmachtend! Der Stamm, noch weiter inland, sah noch die Parthie zu Pferde nach den Aussagen von Jun-Gun's Freunden u. Verwandten, welche Letztern aber nur die Weissen auffanden nach deren Tode. Diese Wüsten-Gegend ist fast ohne Wasser, da sich nur ein wenig davon findet in vereinzelten Felslöchern, welche jedoch ohne Hülfe der Eingebornen nicht im schnellen Suchen eines Verzweifelten aufzufinden wären. Die Wilden behaupten weiter, dass noch eine Axt der Verunglückten bei dem Nachbarstamme vorzufinden sei, ferner Gebeine, noch Überreste vom Geschirr der Pferde, u. wohl noch Anderes von den armen Verunglückten. Gewiss wären jetzt noch Knochen der Pferde aufzufinden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist nun die Absicht der Victoria-Abtheilung der Kgl. geogr. Gesellschaft von Australien, </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sofort</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Mr McPhee nach der Todes-Stätte Leichhardt's und seiner Gefährten auszusenden, mit Hülfe des dort lebenden Stammes vollständige Nachfragen anzustellen, Gegenstände die noch von den Umgekommenen vorhanden sind zu sammeln, und eine Stein-Pyramide als Denkmal einer trauervollen aber historischen Örtlichkeit zu errichten. So können wir wohl erwarten, dass gegen Ende dieses Jahres volles Licht auf das Geschick u. aber auch auf die grossartigen Resultate unseres berühmten Landsmannes wird geworfen sein, der also schon vor 40 Jahren ⅔ oder ¾ des Austral. Continents mit nur einer leichten Parthie u. ohne Cameele von O. nach W. durchschritt! Einige der Mitglieder des von mir 1865 zusammengerufene Damen-Committees, welches die Aufsuchungs Expedition unter MacIntyre aussandte, sind noch unter den Lebenden, u. für diese Damen, welche mit so regem Eifer und tiefer Sympathie damals, aber leider in einem Jahre fast beispielloser Dürre, die Nachforschungen anstellen liessen, wird die endgültige Lösung dieser trübseligen Frage ebenso erhebend (u. belohnend) sein, als für die Geographen der ganzen Welt und namentlichen denen der Landes-Genossen Leichhardts ein melancholisches aber auch anerkennungsvolles Andenken bewahrt werden wird!</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Next paragraph added in pencil.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Würden Sie, hochgeehrter Herr Hofrath, so freundlich sein, auch von </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geographischer</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Seite meinen (eben an Sie abgesandten) zweiten Census der Pflanzen Australiens mit einiger </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Vollständigkeit</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> in Ihren schönen "Mittheilungen" besprechen zu lassen? Es ist eins der Resultate 43 jähriger ununterbrochener oft gefahrvollen Forschungen, nach 7 jährigen europäischen Vorbereitungen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>Finally after 42 years, the hope will probably be realised of clarifying the fate of Dr Leichhardt and his companions! Some months ago, a Mr Alexander M'Phee at Lagrange Bay<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>WA.</p>
               </note> heard through the Aborigines of two tribes, whose languages he learned, of a white man, "Jun Gun", who was said to be located among the autochthones many days journey to the southeast. He set out for the place accompanied by Aborigines and not by whites, found a very lightly coloured man but of real Australian type, whom he brought with him to Melbourne.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The details to this point match the account in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg> (see n. 1). The remainder of the paragraph has information also in McPhee's letter to the editor (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 5 February 1890, p. 9).</p>
               </note> This event would be insignificant, had not Mr McPhee ascertained with some labouriousness from the oldest people of the tribe to which Jun-Gun belonged, that such of their neighbours living in the desert further to the southeast heard a long time ago there were 2 Whites and 2 clothed Blacks with horses coming from the northeast into that region, dying of thirst; the horses had perished first, then both the whites advanced further, each seeking after water in a different direction, one after the other perishing! The tribe still further inland, even saw the party on horseback according to the statements of Jun-Gun's friends and relatives, but the latter only discovered the Whites after their death. This desert region is almost without water, because there is only a little of it in isolated rock holes, which, however, would not be discovered in a rapid search by a desperate person without help from the Aborigines. The savages further maintain that an axe of the victims is still to be found with a neighbouring tribe, further bones, besides remnants of horse harness and probably still other things of the poor victims. Certainly bones of the horses would still be found now.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is now the intention of the Victorian section of the Royal Geographical Society of Australia,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. Australasia.</p>
               </note> to send Mr McPhee out <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">immediately</hi>
               </seg> to the place of death of Leichhardt and his companions, to make complete enquiries with assistance of the tribe living there, to collect objects of the deceased that are still available and to erect a stone pyramid as a memorial of a sad but historical locality.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>McPhee met the Council of the Victorian Branch of the RGSA on 14 February 1890, but he withdrew from leading such an expedition. However, his account resulted in Thomas Elder financing the ill-fated expedition led by David Lindsay. See Lewis (2013), pp. 182-90, which includes images of Jun Gun.</p>
               </note> So we can probably expect that towards the end of this year full light will be thrown on the fate, but also on the magnificent results of our celebrated countryman, who thus as long as 40 years ago traversed ⅔ or ¾ of the Australian continent with only a light party and without camels from east to west. Some of the members of the Ladies Committee established by me in 1865,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ladies' Leichhardt Search Committee.</p>
               </note> that sent out the search expedition under Macintyre, are still among the living, and for these ladies, who had the search instigated with such zealous ardour and deep sympathy at that time, but unfortunately in a year of almost unprecedented drought, the conclusive solution of this sad question will be just as uplifting (and rewarding) as for the geographers of the whole world and especially to those of the fellow compatriots of Leichhardt, a melancholy but also an appreciatory memory will be preserved!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Would you be so kind, highly esteemed Councillor, to have my second Census of Australian plants<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B89.12.03.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> (just sent off to you) reviewed with the same <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">completeness</hi>
               </seg> from the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">geographical</hi>
               </seg> side in your fine <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen</seg>?<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The review, by Drude, appeared in 'Geographischer Litterature-Bericht für 1891', </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Petermann's geographische Mitteilungen</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 37, </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Beilage</seg>
                     <seg style="">, p. 90. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> It is one of the results of 43 years of uninterrupted, often dangerous exploration after 7 years of European preparation!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
