<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 13th October, 1890. ¶ The Honourable Sir Thomas Elder, K.C.M.G., M.L.C., etc., etc. ¶  ¶ It is my pleasing duty to inform you, dear Sir Thomas, that at a meeting of the Victorian Council of...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-10-13a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>90.10.13a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 13th October, 1890. ¶ The Honourable Sir Thomas Elder, K.C.M.G., M.L.C., etc., etc. ¶  ¶ It is my pleasing duty to inform you, dear Sir Thomas, that at a meeting of the Victorian Council of...</title>
               <date when="1890-10-13">1890-10-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1890/90-10-13a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Thomas Elder</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 13th October, 1890. ¶ The Honourable Sir Thomas Elder, K.C.M.G., M.L.C., etc., etc. ¶  ¶ It is my pleasing duty to inform you, dear Sir Thomas, that at a meeting of the Victorian Council of...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">90.10.13a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Thomas Elder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions of the Royal Geographical Society of Australasia, Victorian Branch</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 8, part 2 (March 1891), pp. 41-3 (B91.03.05). The text is appended to a report of a meeting of the Council of the Victorian Branch held on 6 October 1890. The Council, 'having discussed and come to an agreement respecting the principal items in connection with the fitting out and dispatch of an expedition into Central Australia', agreed that 'the resolutions adopted by this meeting be embodied in a letter to Sir Thomas Elder, to be signed by the President [i.e. M] and approved of by a sub-committee, consisting of the President, Messrs. Panton, Newbery, Scarr and [Macdonald]'. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note>Melbourne, 13th October, 1890.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Honourable Sir Thomas Elder, K.C.M.G., M.L.C., etc., etc.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is my pleasing duty to inform you, dear Sir Thomas, that at a meeting of the Victorian Council of the Royal Geographical Society of Australasia, held on the 6th October inst., it was resolved that for the expedition which, in accordance with your wishes and through your munificence, is to be sent out for the main purpose of completing the exploration of the Continent of Australia, the best route would be to start from the Peake Station, on the Overland Telegraph Line, in order to penetrate in the first instance as far as possible midway through the large unexplored space contained between the track of your expedition of 1875 on the south side, and the Musgrove<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Musgrave?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Ranges and Forrest's track of 1874 on the north side. The camels, which we expect you will kindly place at the disposal of the expedition, may be picked up on the way to Peake Station.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The expedition having penetrated in a westerly direction towards Queen Victoria Springs, thence to Mount Weld, long. 122° 20' E. lat. 28° 40' S., and having thus established a new geographical line across the continent, would then turn northwards towards Weld Springs, crossing Giles' track of your expedition of 1876; would then advance as far as Mount Macpherson, at the head of the Oakover River, the point reached by Gregory's expedition of 1861, where, if necessary, replenishment of provisions might be effected.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Resuming the journey in an easterly direction through the second large patch of unexplored territory, the party would again endeavour to keep away as far as possible from any hitherto known point, and would proceed easterly between Lake Macdonald of Tietkins' expedition<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>William Tietkens.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> of 1889, and Termination Lake<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now Lake Gregory, WA.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> of Augustus Gregory's expedition of 1856. During this part of the journey, by making assiduous enquiries through aboriginal interpreters the fate of Dr. Leichhardt and of his companions might perhaps be cleared up. This achievement we trust will fall to the share of your contemplated expedition. All this could probably be accomplished by moderately swift movements within one season, and thus the largest blanks on the map of Australia would be filled up to a considerable extent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Should the season and other circumstances prove favourable, it would then be highly desirable to continue the party in the field for some months longer, as during the extra three or four months nearly double the work of exploring the country at several points on both sides of the direct route could be accomplished, and contingent upon the condition of the men and camels admitting of a longer stay in the field, the blank space on the map to the east and between Lake Termination and the telegraph line, could also be explored.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Council would further respectfully submit to you the advisability of the exploring party being ready for its start from the Peake Station not later than the beginning of March, 1891, in order that full advantage could be taken of the coming season. In the event of these suggestions meeting with your approbation, subject to whatever alterations you may deem fit, we venture to ask the favour of an answer by cable,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Elder was visiting Europe at this time.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> so that early preparations for the new enterprise can be made.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As regards the constitution of the exploring party, bearing in view your wish that it should be thoroughly scientific, the Council beg to submit for your favourable consideration the following appointments:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1st. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Leader of the Expedition and principal surveyor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">2nd. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Second in Command and assistant surveyor, acting also as Geologist, unless that duty should devolve on some other officer of the party.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">3rd. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Medical Officer, who probably could also act as botanist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">4th. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Zoologist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">5th. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Photographer, unless one of the other members of the party could act as such.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">6th. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Overseer and Storekeeper.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The number of men required for ordinary duties, such as camel driving, cooking and various field work, could be determined hereafter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Council has refrained from entering into a detailed estimate of the cost likely to be involved by carrying out the plan as sketched above, but my colleagues, as well as myself, wish to offer at the very outset their assurance that due economy will be studied throughout the arrangements, so far as may be compatible with efficiency.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Next we beg to bring under your favourable notice, that after consultations with the other branches of the Royal Geographical Society of Australasia, this Council is unanimously in favour of the appointment of Mr. Charles Winnecke to the leadership of your Expedition, but wishes to mention also the names of Mr. Ernest Giles, Mr. David Lindsay, F.R.G.S., Mr. Carruthers, and Mr. Stanley Milroy, the latter highly eligible for the post of Second in Command, on account of his extensive surveying experience in Central Queensland.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the event, Lindsay was appointed leader.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Allow me finally to convey to you the assurance of this Council, that nothing shall be left undone on our part to make the results of the intended enterprise commensurate with the expectations of its noble initiator and sustainer.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Regardfully always yours,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferdinand von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>President of the R.G.S.A., Victorian Branch.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
