<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>13/7/85 ¶  ¶ The last post, highly esteemed Professor, brought me your friendly letter of 31 May and also the accompanying circular letter. ¶  It probably does not require my assurance that I will gla...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-07-13-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>85.07.13</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>13/7/85 ¶  ¶ The last post, highly esteemed Professor, brought me your friendly letter of 31 May and also the accompanying circular letter. ¶  It probably does not require my assurance that I will gla...</title>
               <date when="1885-07-13">1885-07-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-07-13-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Curvembryonateae</term>
               <term>Elymus arenarius</term>
               <term>Stackhousiaceae</term>
               <term>Monochlamydeae</term>
               <term>Candolleaceae</term>
               <term>Pittosporeae</term>
               <term>Tremandreae</term>
               <term>Amyliferae</term>
               <term>Myoporinae</term>
               <term>Meliaceae</term>
               <term>Aroideae</term>
               <term>Psamma</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Adolf Engler </name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">13/7/85 ¶  ¶ The last post, highly esteemed Professor, brought me your friendly letter of 31 May and also the accompanying circular letter. ¶  It probably does not require my assurance that I will gla...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">85.07.13</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Adolf Engler </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Privat</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">13/7/85</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die letzte Post, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, brachte mir Ihren freundlichen Brief v. 31 Mai u. auch das begleitende Circular-Schreiben. Es bedarf wohl nicht meiner Versicherung, dass ich Ihrem schönen Unternehmen gern nützlich sein werde, soweit ichs vermag. Pflanzen-Familien, die Australien ganz oder fast ganz angehören, will ich gern bearbeiten, z. B. die Myoporinen, Tremandreen, Pittosporeen, Candolleaceen, Stackhousiaceen. Die neue Ausgabe meiner "select plants", welche für die Colonial-Ausstellung in London erscheinen wird, könnte ja auch Ihrem Werke zu gut kommen; u ich würde es auch erlauben, unter Angabe der Quelle, dass Abbildungen aus meinen hiesigen Werken in Xylography copirt würden, wie es bei Schnitzleier schon begann. An <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">einem</hi>
               </seg> Felsen scheitern manche derartiger Unternehmungen, daran dass der Plan <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">zu grossartig</hi>
               </seg> und zu <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">weitgreifend</hi>
               </seg> gefasst wird. Mir scheint, ein Werk wie Lindley's vegetable Kingdom wäre das beste Vorbild mit Ausdehnung der Illustrationen etwa wie bei Maout u Decaisne. Ein Werk wie Baillon's ist schon veraltet ehe es zu Ende kommt (êntre nous); u <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">wann</hi>
               </seg> kommt es zu Ende? Ist es besser, ein kleineres Werk zu liefern, und es durch neue Auflagen neu zu erhalten? <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Zu</hi>
               </seg> grosse Werke sind auch viel zu kostbar für das allgemeine Publicum u nicht tragbar auf Reisen. So wird es mit Prof Kirchhoff's geogr Werck "Unser Wissen von der Erde" sein. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mir scheint, dass für genera doch wohl Jeder B. &amp; H. oder auch noch den immer ausgezeichneten Endlicher zu Rathe ziehen würde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Eine</hi>
               </seg> besondere Schwierigkeit entsteht, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">diese</hi>
               </seg>: welche Sequenz soll beobachtet werden in der Anordnung der Familien? Ich habe nach vielen Nachdenken und endlosen Vergleichen zu keinem anderen Resultat kommen können, als dass das Syst von D.C. oder das umgekehrte Original-System von Jussieu das <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">beste</hi>
               </seg> bleibt, nur müssen die <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name> oder Apetalae vertheilt werden anderweitig ausser Coniferen. Ich kann mich auch noch gar nicht mit dem Gedanken befreunden, dass die Coniferen den Filices nahe stehen. Man beobachte doch nur die Keimung. Hat sich die Beobachtung über die Entwicklung eines prothallus mit Archegonien im Embryoschlauch wirklich bestätigt? Liegt nicht vielleicht eine sehr verzeihliche Missdeutung vor, wie bei der Idee, dass die Lichenen aus einer Zusammensetzung von Algene u. Pilze bestanden? <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> sind gewiss in der Lage gewesen, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">selbst</hi>
               </seg> diese Beobachtungen zu prüfen; mir hat es an Zeit u besonderer Übung zu <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">solchen</hi>
               </seg> Untersuchungen, ja auch den besten Instrumenten gefehlt. Geben Sie mir doch gütig Ihre Ansicht auch hierüber, denn ich bin immer offen für Belehrung, u. auch gern bereit meine Anschauungen zu ändern nach zu länglichen Beobachtungen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sehen Sie sich, bester Freund, doch auch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">noch einmal ruhig meinen Census an</hi>
               </seg>, u. sagen Sie mir gütig, was der darin angenommenen Anordung entgegensteht; bis zum gewissen Grade ist sie loyal für D.C. Wäre nicht etwas Ähnliches im Embryosak anderer Dicotyledenen zu entdecken?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben mich ausserordentlich durch die Original-Belege der Aroideen verpflichtet; <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">die</hi>
               </seg> haben Werth für Alle Zeiten. Demnächst soll auch wieder ein Packet au[s]erlesener australischer Pflanzen an Ihr Museum abgehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Ermittlung der Gattungen nach einem kurzen Schlüssel nützt nicht viel, da man dann zum Stillstand kommt, u. nichts über die Art weiss, wie man dies beim Gebrauch von Baillon's Monographien empfindet. Die Berechnung der Arten ist auch eine schwierige u. gewagte, seit die meisten Naturforscher überhaupt gar keine Stabilität von Arten anerkennen. In der That wäre es gut, wenn man die Fixität der Arten nicht mehr anerkennt auch den Ausdruck von Species ganz aufzugeben u. nur von Formen zu reden, oder Bastarden oder Varietäten. Welche Divergenz in der Calculation der Arten der Meliaceen selbst in wenigen Jahren, seit H. &amp; B. u dann A de Candolle die Arten-Zahl berechneten! H. &amp; B. schrieb ich von Anfang an, dass Species … <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">notae</hi>
               </seg> gesagt werden müsse; denn in vielen Gattungen wird der Zuwachs ja noch enorm sein, z. B. aus Central Africa den Sunda-Inseln, Neu Guinea, selbst Brasilien u andern central-amerikanische Ländern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Vorläufer</hi>
               </seg> eines grösseren Werks wäre — so scheint es mir — am Besten <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">jetzt</hi>
               </seg>. Am Ende Jahrhunderts oder in Beginn des nächsten, könnte dann eher etwas <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Erschöpfendes</hi>
               </seg> geliefert werden</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ganz der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Freundschaftlich</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Würden Sie nicht gelegentlich ein Schema der Verwandtschaft der Pflanzen-Familien nach <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihren</hi>
               </seg> eignen reichen Erfahrungen geben? Ich habe auch Baillon um die Aufstellung eines Systems nach seinen eignen Ideen gebeten. Absolut lässt sich freilich die Stellung mancher Familien nicht fixiren in einreihiger Linie, wie solche für Bücher nöthig ist, da ja die Verwandtschaft radial bleibt. Das ist aber das Schöne der Anlage eines bot. Systems in einem Garten, wie ich es B. de Juss schon 1857 hier nachahmte, dass man den vielseitigen Affinitäten gerecht werden kann. In meinem "Census" werde ich gelegentlich noch einige kleine Änderungen machen in Bezug auf die verwandtschaftliche Stellung einiger Familien; aber ich denke doch, dass im Allgemeinen ich nicht viel zu ändern habe, u. an der Verschmelzung der perigynae u epigynae halte ich fest. Schade, dass B. &amp; H. meinen Rathe in 1862 nicht folgten, die Monochlamydeen den andern Familien zuzustellen nach respectiven Erfordernissen. Man sieht die Nothwendigkeit dafür recht bei den Curvembryonaten (od. Amyliferen).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Würden Sie gütig einige Körner frisch von <name key="Psamma">Psamma</name> in Ihrem nächsten Brief beifügen, <name key="Elymus%20arenarius">Elymus arenarius</name>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">habe</hi>
               </seg> ich hier naturalisirt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auf geldliche Zahlung für etwaige Beitrage wurde ich keine Ansprüche machen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Soll die Synonyme der Gattungen auch vollständig berücksichtigt werden</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">13/7/85</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last post, highly esteemed Professor, brought me your friendly letter of 31 May and also the accompanying circular letter.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note> It probably does not require my assurance that I will gladly be of use to your excellent enterprise, as far as I am able. I will gladly work up plant families, which belong entirely or almost entirely to Australia, for example the <name key="Myoporinae">Myoporinae</name>, <name key="Tremandreae">Tremandreae</name>, <name key="Pittosporeae">Pittosporeae</name>, <name key="Candolleaceae">Candolleaceae</name>, <name key="Stackhousiaceae">Stackhousiaceae</name>. The new edition of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select Plants</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B85.12.03.</p>
               </note> that will appear for the Colonial Exhibition in London,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Colonial and Indian Exhibition, London, 1886.</p>
               </note> could certainly also be beneficial to your work and I would also permit, with acknowledgement of the source, illustrations from my local works to be copied in xylography,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. wood engraving.</p>
               </note> as it has already begun at the engraver's. Several undertakings of such a kind foundered on <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg> rock, in that the plan was conceived too <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">grandiosely</hi>
               </seg> and too<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline"> far reachingly</hi>
               </seg>. It seems to me a work such as Lindley's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Vegetable Kingdom</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lindley (1847).</p>
               </note> would be the best model with expansion of the illustrations somewhat like Maout and Decaisne.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Le Maout &amp; Decaisne (1868).</p>
               </note> A work such as Baillon's<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Baillon (1867-95)<seg style="">.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> is already obsolete before it comes to an end (entre nous) and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">when</hi>
               </seg> will it be finished? Is it better to produce a small work and to keep it updated by new editions? <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Too</hi>
               </seg> large works are also much too costly for the general public and not easy to carry on journeys. So it will be with Prof. Kirchhoff's geographical work <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Unser Wissen von der Erde</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kirchhoff (1886-1907).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It seems to me that for genera each one would probably consult H. &amp; B.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham &amp; Hooker (1862-83).</p>
               </note> or even the always outstanding Endlicher.<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Endlicher (1836-40).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">One</hi>
               </seg> particular difficulty arises, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">this</hi>
               </seg>: what sequence is to be observed in the arrangement of the families? After much thought and endless comparison I have been able to come to no other result than that the system of D.C.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Possibly A. P. de Candolle (1816-21).</p>
               </note> or the inverted original system of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Jussieu</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Jussieu (1789).</p>
               </note> remains the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">best</hi>
               </seg>, only the <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name> or Apetalae must be divided in some other way without the Conifers. I can also still not reconcile myself at all with the idea that the Conifers stand near the Filices. After all only the germination was observed. Is the observation about the development of a prothallus with archegonium in the embryo tube really confirmed? Is there not perhaps a very excusable misinterpretation, as with the idea that the lichens consist of a combination of algae and fungi? <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">You</hi>
               </seg> certainly have been in the position to check these observations <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">yourself</hi>
               </seg>. I lack the time and the special experience for <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">such</hi>
               </seg> investigations, indeed even the best instruments. Do kindly give me your opinion about this, as I am always open to instruction, and also gladly prepared to change my views according to prolonged observations.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Do <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">calmly look over my </hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <hi rend="underline">Census</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B83.03.04.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline"> again</hi>
               </seg>, best of friends, and kindly tell me what is opposed to the arrangement adopted in it. Up to a point it is loyal to D.C. Would not something similar be discovered in the embryo sac of other dicotyledons?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have put an extraordinary obligation on me by the original documents of the <name key="Aroideae">Aroideae</name>;<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Possibly Engler (1884).</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">which</hi>
               </seg> have merit for all time. Shortly a packet of selected Australian plants is to again go off to your museum too.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The determination of genera according to a short key is not much use, because one then comes to a standstill and knows nothing about the species as one feels in using Baillon’s monograph.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not identified.</p>
               </note> The determination of species is also a difficult and bold one, since the majority of naturalists recognise absolutely no stability at all of species. In fact it would be good if the fixity of species was no longer recognised even giving up the expression of species completely and only speaking of forms, or bastards or varieties. What a divergence in the calculation of species of <name key="Meliaceae">Meliaceae</name> even in a few years, since Hooker &amp; Bentham and then A. de Candolle determined the species number! I wrote to Hooker &amp; Bentham from the beginning that species … <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">notae</hi>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. known.</p>
               </note> must be said because in many genera the growth will still be really enormous, e.g. from Central Africa, the Sunda Islands, New Guinea, even Brazil and other Central American countries.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">precursor</hi>
               </seg> of a larger work would — it seems to me — be best <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">now</hi>
               </seg>. At the end of the century or at the beginning of the next, a somewhat <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">exhaustive one</hi>
               </seg> could then be produced.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Entirely yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Would you not give some time a scheme of relationship of plant families according to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> own rich experiences? I have also asked Baillon<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> to put forward a system according to his own ideas. Absolutely of course the place of many families does not allow fixing in a straight line, as is necessary for books, because the relationship certainly remains radial. But that is the beauty of the layout of a botanical system in a garden, as I imitated B. de Jussieu here as early as 1857, that one can do justice to the manifold affinities. In my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Census</seg> I will at times make in addition some small changes in respect to the relational position of some familes, but I do think that in general I have not much to change and I hold fast to the merging of the perigynae and epigynae. A pity that Bentham &amp; Hooker did not follow my advice in 1862 to distribute the <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name> to the other families according to the respective requirements.<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to G. Bentham, 24 January 1862.</p>
               </note> One sees the necessity for this properly in the <name key="Curvembryonateae">Curvembryonateae</name> (or <name key="Amyliferae">Amyliferae</name>).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Would you kindly add some grains fresh from <name key="Psamma">Psamma</name> in your next letter. I <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">have</hi>
               </seg> naturalised <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Elymus%20arenarius">Elymus arenarius</name>
               </seg> here.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would make no claims for monetary payment for any possible contributions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Shall the synonyms of genera be completely considered as well.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Amyliferae">Amyliferae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Aroideae">Aroideae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Candolleaceae">Candolleaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Curvembryonateae">Curvembryonateae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Elymus%20arenarius">Elymus arenarius</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Meliaceae">Meliaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Monochlamydeae">Monochlamydeae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myoporinae">Myoporinae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pittosporeae">Pittosporeae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Psamma">Psamma</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stackhousiaceae">Stackhousiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Tremandreae">Tremandreae</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
