<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>8/6/85 ¶  ¶ Today you have pleased me greatly, dearest Sir, although it torments me to hear that you already think about the end of your highly beneficial career. ¶  Chevreul has just recently continu...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-06-08-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>85.06.08</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>8/6/85 ¶  ¶ Today you have pleased me greatly, dearest Sir, although it torments me to hear that you already think about the end of your highly beneficial career. ¶  Chevreul has just recently continu...</title>
               <date when="1885-06-08">1885-06-08</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-06-08-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Myoporinae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">8/6/85 ¶  ¶ Today you have pleased me greatly, dearest Sir, although it torments me to hear that you already think about the end of your highly beneficial career. ¶  Chevreul has just recently continu...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">85.06.08</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Ferdinand von Krauss</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotations by Krauss: (1) 'Empf. 27. Juli Rep. 20. Aug.' [Received 27 July Replied 20 Aug.] (letter not found): (2) 'Als Geschenk durch die Linn. Soc. in London v. v. Müller Index perfectus ed C. Linnei species plantarum Collatore Ferd. de Müller. Melbourne 1880.' [As presentation through the Linnean Society in London from von Mueller …]: (3) <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'Eucalyptographia 1, 2.5.7 erhalten [received]'.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.6665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The works mentioned by Krauss are B80.04.04, B79.13.11 and B80.13.14. </p>
               </note>8/6/85.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Heute haben Sie mich aufs Innigste erfreuet, theuerer Herr, obwohl es mich quält zu hören, dass Sie an das Ende Ihrer segensreichen Laufbahn schon denken. Chevreul hat 97 Jahr alt noch kürzlich seine Vorlesungen an der Universität Paris forgesetzt. Humboldt war ja auch zum 90stn Jahre geistes frisch u körperlich stark; Bentham u Hooker arbeiteten aufs Anstrengendste zum 84 Jahr, so können ja auch Sie Muth fassen, nur müssten Sie sich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ruhe</hi>
               </seg> gönnen, u. behaglich auf das Geschaffene Ihrer schönen Anstalt hinabschauen u. Ihre Kräfte schonen. Wahrlich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg> haben genug gethan, u. können nun doch auch sich selbst u den Ihren leben!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass der arme Dr Wilkie plötzlich in Paris starb anfangs April, ist Ihnen vielleicht bekannt geworden, da eine verheirathete Schwester der Frau Dr Wilkie vor einigen Jahren in Stuttgart lebte mit ihren Kindern. Er opferte sich offenbar seiner Familie auf, da die 3 prächtigen Töchter in Paris der Studien der Musik, des Gesangs u. der Malerei sich zum Vergnügen widmeten, was den hoch betagten seit nahe 50 Jahren an das austr Clima gewohnten Mann in die kälte Nacht-Luft Nordfrankreichs zu oft gebracht hat, so dass er der Lungen Enzündung unterlag! Mit ihm ist einer meinen edelsten Freunde, doch in dessen Haus ich seit mehr denn 30 Jahren aus u ein ging, dahin! Die Wittwe u. Töchter werden nun wohl bei Verwandte in Schottland für Erste bleiben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herrn Messner, als besonderen Landsmann und einen der angenehmsten Menschen den man sich nur denken kann werden Sie ebenso lieb gewonnen haben als ich ihn hochschätze. Ich freue mich schon recht auf seine Rückkehr! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass Sie mich durch die neue <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sarcophila</hi>
               </seg> oder Pennatula mit dem weltberühmten Anatomen u Physiologen Hr. Prof Kölliker in Berührung brachte, erregt meine hohe Freude, u bin ich Ihnen u dem verehrten Manne aufs dankbarste verpflichtet meinen Namen auch in der Gruppe der Meerfeder-Thiere vereinigt zu haben. Wenn ich diesem erhabenen Gelehrte in irgend einer Weise eine Freude bereiten könnte, so soll es gern geschehen!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wenn ich bedenke, wie von der allgemeinen Welt Darwin, den auch ich als <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Beobachter</hi>
               </seg> verehre, förmlich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">vergöttert</hi>
               </seg> wird, so fühle ich die Ungerechtigkeit gegen solchen Herren, in der Natur Wissenschaft als Kölliker u Owen, deren solides Forschen bleibenden Werth hat u unumstossbare Resultate giebt, während doch nur ein kleiner Theil des Darwin’s Theorien haltbar bleiben. Der 80 jährige Owen ist noch so frisch, so gütig, so geistigstark noch; mir hat er in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">inniger Freundschaft</hi>
               </seg>, obwohl wir uns im Leben nie trefen, stets nahe gestanden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein Skelett nach <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">einem</hi>
               </seg> Knochen herzustellen, ist die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Errungenschaft</hi>
               </seg> eines Cuvier, eines Owen, eines Kölliker, das überstrahlt blösse Theorien.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auch Hr Dr Fischer bitte ich für seine neue Dedication, diesmal unter den Ophidea, meinen besten Dank zu sagen, u freundlichsten Gruss zu entbieten. In diesem Jahr giebt es besonders schwere Arbeit bei mir. Die Obliegenheiten für die London Colonial Ausstellung mit ganz für mich unzulängliche Mitteln, die Hülfe für Organisation der Neu Guinean Expedition; die Präsidentur unserer geogr. Gesellschaft hier, die Herausgabe einer neuen erweiterten Ausgabe des Werkes "select plants", die Vollendung der mit 80 Quarto Tafeln illustrirte Monographie der Myoporinen, die Ausarbeitung eines Schulbuchs für Benennung der mehr denn 1800 Vascular-Pflanzen Victorias, strengen mich neben der enormen Correspondenz aufs Übermannenster an; so dass Sie mir guter u edler Freund, nicht zürnen dürfen, wenn ich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihnen</hi>
               </seg> gegenüber, dem ich aufs Tiefste verpflichtet bin, so lässig erscheinen. Im nächsten Jahr, deo volente, werde ich wohl etwas freier sein, u da der liebe Hr Messner mir noch genauer sagen kann, was Sie gebrauchen, so soll Ihnen dann recht viel zukommen</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was ich eben an wanzenartigen Hemipteren auftreiben kann, soll Ihnen gleich per Post zukommen, auch bald die Fehlenden Hefte der Eucalyptographie u manches Andere.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun halten Sie sich ja lange noch frisch u munter, u bleiben Sie fürder gewogen Ihrem</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Die Coleopteren &amp;c <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">kaufte</hi>
               </seg> ich von Mr French. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Holz-Ex. hoffe ich mich bald absenden zu können</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ein Wuerttemberger, Hr Bäuerlin, ist von mir für die Neu Guinea Expedition als Pflanzen Sammler gewählt</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von Sarcoptilus bisher nur 1 Ex. gefunden<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Von Sarcoptilus bisher nur 1 Ex. gefunden <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is written on the flap of an envelope</seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">8/6/85</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Today you have pleased me greatly, dearest Sir, although it torments me to hear that you already think about the end of your highly beneficial career.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> Chevreul has just recently continued his lectures at the University of Paris at 97 years of age. Humboldt was certainly even in his 90th year intellectually fresh and strong in body; Bentham and Hooker worked most strenuously at 84 years, so you can certainly also pluck up courage, but you would have to allow yourself <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">rest</hi>
               </seg> and look down contentedly on the achievements of your fine institution and conserve your strength. Truly <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg> have done enough, and are certainly able now also to live for yourself and your family!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That poor Dr Wilkie suddenly died in Paris at the beginning of April is perhaps known to you, because a married sister of Mrs Wilkie lived some years ago in Stuttgart with her children. He obviously sacrificed himself for his family, since the 3 splendid daughters in Paris devoted themselves to the pleasures of music study, of singing and of painting, which has brought the highly aged man,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Wilkie was 69 when he died.</p>
               </note> who was used to the Australian climate for nearly 50 years, into the cold night air of northern France too often, so that he succumbed to inflammation of the lungs! With him has died one of my most noble friends, indeed in whose house I went to and fro for more than 30 years! I suppose the widow and daughters will now remain at first with relatives in Scotland.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will have become as fond of Mr Messner<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Frederick Messner arrived in Victoria in April 1863 aboard <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg> and made a successful career in business. In 1884 he decided to re-visit his home town, Stuttgart, and M provided him with an introduction to Krauss; see M to F. von Krauss, 20 August 1884 (in this edition as 84-08-20a).</p>
               </note> as a special compatriot and one of the most pleasant men whom one can think of as I highly respected him. I am already looking forward very much to his return!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That you have brought me in contact with the world famous anatomist and physiologist Professor Köllicher through the new <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sarcophila</seg> or<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pennatula</seg>, arouses my great pleasure and I am most gratefully obliged to you and the esteemed man for having united my name with the group of sea pen animals as well.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Kölliker (1885) named the pennatulid <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Pteroides mülleri</seg> in M's honour, from a specimen forwarded to him by Krauss; see Lucas (2013). </p>
               </note> If I could give pleasure to this eminent savant in any kind of way it shall gladly be done!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>When I consider how Darwin, whom even I admire as an <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">observer</hi>
               </seg>, is positively <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">idolized</hi>
               </seg> by the world in general, I feel the injustice towards such men in the natural sciences as Kölliker and Owen, whose solid research has lasting value and gives incontrovertible results, whilst only a small part of Darwin's theory remains tenable. The 80-year-old Owen is still so bright, so kind, so intellectually vigorous; to me he has always stood in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">intimate friendship</hi>
               </seg>, although we have never met.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>To reconstruct a skeleton from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="font-weight: bold; "> </seg>bone, is the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">achievement</hi>
               </seg> of a Cuvier, of an Owen, of a Kölliker, that outshines mere theories.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Also please give Dr Fischer my best thanks for his new dedication this time among the snakes<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. G. Fischer named <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Hoplocephalus muelleri</seg> in Fischer (1885), p. 109. See Darragh (1996), Lucas (2013).</p>
               </note> and present most friendly compliments. In this year there is particularly heavy work at my place. The obligations for the London Colonial Exhibition<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Colonial and Indian Exhibition, London, 1886.</p>
               </note> with quite insufficient funds for me, the assistance for organisation of the New Guinea expedition, the presidency of our Geographical Society here, the publication of a new enlarged edition of the work <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select plants</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B85.12.03.</p>
               </note> the completion of the monograph of the <name key="Myoporinae">Myoporinae</name> illustrated with 80 quarto plates,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B86.08.05.</p>
               </note> the preparation of a school text for naming of more than 1800 vascular plants of Victoria,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B86.04.05.</p>
               </note> together with the enormous correspondence fatigue me most overpoweringly, so that you, good and noble friend, will not be angry with me, if I seem so remiss towards <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>, to whom I am obligated most deeply. In the next year, deo volente,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">God willing.</p>
               </note> I will probably be somewhat more free and, since dear Mr Messner can tell me even more exactly what you need, shall then send very much to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What I can just find of bug-like Hemiptera shall be sent to you immediately through the post, also soon the lacking parts of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptographia</seg> and some others.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now keep hale and hearty for a long time and remain favourably disposed towards your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">purchased</hi>
               </seg> the Coleoptera from Mr French.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Some years earlier, M offered French's collection to the British Museum, but there is no evidence of its having been purchased; see M to R. Owen, 30 October 1878.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope to be able to send the wood specimens soon.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A Wuerttemberger, Mr Bäuerlin,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">W. Bäuerlen.</p>
               </note> is selected by me as plant collector for the New Guinea expedition. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Up to now only 1 specimen of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Sarcoptilus</seg> found.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myoporinae">Myoporinae</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
