<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>26/2/1885. ¶  ¶ Though honoring the confidence, my dear niece, with which you approach me, and altho' I appreciate the kindly feelings, which you show to improve my household, — yet it would be a grea...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-02-26-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M100A, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>85.02.26</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>26/2/1885. ¶  ¶ Though honoring the confidence, my dear niece, with which you approach me, and altho' I appreciate the kindly feelings, which you show to improve my household, — yet it would be a grea...</title>
               <date when="1885-02-26">1885-02-26</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-02-26-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Louise Wehl</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">26/2/1885. ¶  ¶ Though honoring the confidence, my dear niece, with which you approach me, and altho' I appreciate the kindly feelings, which you show to improve my household, — yet it would be a grea...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">85.02.26</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Louise Wehl</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RB MSS M100A, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">26/2/1885.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Though honoring the confidence, my dear niece, with which you approach me, and altho' I appreciate the kindly feelings, which you show to improve my household, — yet it would be a great disappointment to you, to come to this great city. I have lived here now more than 30 years, and have found that in most cases young Ladies could much easier establish a domesticity for themselves in the country than in the city. You would not believe it, unless you saw it yourself here, what a number of young Ladies have grown old here and remained alone in life, though highly educated, charming in their manners and endowed with personal beauty! How is this? — because in a great city the calls on every one are so exorbitant for support of endless things, from charities to pleasures, from churches to arts, that seldom engagements are made, unless the independence of family-life is secured by<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">property</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>already existing. This want of prosperity deters most people to add to their responsibility in great centres of population. Very different it is in country-districts; and the less such are populated, the better it is for the young people. So, I act in due regard to your likely welfare, if I most strongly advise you, not to give up the humble independence, which you so honorably established for yourself. — Even if I was endowed with worldly riches, I would give the same advise. But let me recommend to you, to petition Mr Todd for a position near your dear mother;<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M's sister, Clara Wehl. Louise Wehl<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>had joined the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>SA<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Government service in 1882<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(see M<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to L. Wehl, 10 October 1882). She was<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>postmistress at Appila,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1882-4, some 240 km north of Adelaide<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>thus over 600 km from her mother Clara's residence at Millicent<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(Dowe et al.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(2020), p.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>12).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>you will then not feel so lonely, can see her on sundays, and she can aid you in accomplishing the best for your worldly welfare. It was wrong of the Lady, who counselled you, to disturb the peace of your mind! As regards my own habitation, it is only an office with four small rooms, all of which are overfilled with books, collections and office-concerns. So I keep only a groom in my simple household. I never invite any one, and only one meal daily is prepared, as there is no space for domestic concerns. I wanted for some time to add one room, so that at all events one private room might be in the poor place; but I have not even the means for that, as only lately I paid off the mortgage on the building. My income is so heavily taxed by my scientific intercourse with all parts of the world, that I have nothing whatever either to build or furnish any place. Had I received the slightest help from any one, when I "struggled for existence" in the bot. Garden, I could have had the happiness of some of my near relatives visiting me. In the garden was at least after 17 years a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>good two-storied House completed by me. You must also remember, my dear niece, that at my time of life I have very seldom any time for any pleasure; so I could not go out or even come to see you except at long intervals, if you stayed with friends in Melbourne; and if I had any spare-means, I feel sure you would like me rather to give them to your poor mother or for the education of your younger sisters and brothers.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Clara Wehl had twelve children who survived to adulthood.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Think me not unkind, but allow me to speak to you from a lifelong experience with the same candor, which you evinced towards me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With my sincerest wishes for your welfare</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I am sure, I have not bowed<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to any young Ladies for many years.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
