<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[…] My journey was very interesting and in spite of the fact that it was always through the desert, yet I have brought back handsome results principally of plants. My companions were my second son Ott...</title>
            <author>Federico Philippi</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-00-00c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>85.00.00c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Federico Philippi</author>
               <title>[…] My journey was very interesting and in spite of the fact that it was always through the desert, yet I have brought back handsome results principally of plants. My companions were my second son Ott...</title>
               <date when="1885">1885</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1885/85-00-00c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Prosopis siliquastrum</term>
               <term>Cereus atacamensis</term>
               <term>Gourlica chilensis</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/b36df9ae-c30a-4503-96cf-51ff0c109bce">Chenopodiaceae</term>
               <term>Margyricarpus</term>
               <term>Borragineae </term>
               <term>Cynanthereae</term>
               <term>Leguminosae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/16cc4011-deab-4472-b9b0-377d3b26d1db">Solanaceae</term>
               <term>Coniferae</term>
               <term>Gramineae</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/b89f18f9-06fb-4b01-b3c2-d7908f43e484">Juncaceae</term>
               <term>Polylepis</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/2ed7e3fa-8568-4c33-85fa-02fba53fe739">Rosaceae</term>
               <term>Verbenae</term>
               <term>Malveae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[…] My journey was very interesting and in spite of the fact that it was always through the desert, yet I have brought back handsome results principally of plants. My companions were my second son Ott...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">85.00.00c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Federico Philippi</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 16 December 1885, p. 11. <seg style="">The extract was introduced: ‘Neue Forschungsreise in Süd-Amerika. Herr Baron Dr. F. von Müller, in Melbourne, hat uns den nachstehenden Auszug aus einem Briefe des Professors Dr. Federico Philippi, in Santiago (Hauptstadt von Chile), gütigst zur Verfügung gestellt und bemerkt dabei, dass seines Wissens noch kein Reisebericht dieses thatkräftigen Forschers in deutscher Sprache erschienen ist. </seg>Der interessante Bericht lautet:’ [New research journeys in South America. Baron Dr F. von Mueller in Melbourne has kindly placed the following extract from a letter of Professor Federico Philippi in Santiago (capital of Chile) at our disposal and in addition remarked that to the best of his knowledge no report of the journey of this energetic researcher has yet appeared in German. The interesting report runs:]</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">[…] Meine Reise war höchst interessant, und trotzdem dass sie stets durch die Wüste ging, habe ich doch eine hübsche Ausbeute mitgebracht, hauptsächlich an Pflanzen. Meine Begleiter waren mein zweiter Sohn Otto und der Sub-Director des Museums, Herr Rahmer. In Copiapó liess ich 13 Maulthiere kaufen und ein Leitpferd, und am 2. Januar reisten wir von dort ab, von einem Diener, einem Maulthiertreiber und einem Wegweiser begleitet;, unser Gepäck war auf 5 Thiere gepackt, die anderen dienten als Relais. Wir ritten 3 Tage lang nach Osten, bis zum Salzsee Maricunga, der etwa 4,O0O M. hoch liegt. Von hier hatten wir 2 kurze Tagereisen nach Norden, dann ging es stets nach Osten, über den ersten Kamm der Cordilleren weg, auf der höchsten Stelle etwa 5,600 M. hoch, bis wir am 16. Januar Antofagasta de la Sierra erreichten, ein Oertchen von etwa 14 bis 16 Häusern und Kirche, von kaum 40 Personen bewohnt, Indiern, die aber alle spanisch sprechen, und ihre Muttersprache, das Atacamenno. vergessen zu haben scheinen. Der Ort liegt auf 22° 55' südl. Br und 68° 11' 25" westl. L. v. Grenwich, 3,570 M. über dem Meere, in einem hübschen Thal, welches in einen Trachytstrom eingeschnitten ist; es war früher bolivianisch, ist aber durch den letzten Vertrag für einstweilen an Chile abgetreten. Die Leute können immer noch nicht begreifen, dass sie keine Bolivianer mehr sind. Von Maricunga an trafen wir keine Wohnung mehr bis Antofagasta.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Nach sechstägigem Aufenthalt ging es weiter; die Mulas hatten sich erholt und etwas herausfressen können, und wir benutzten die Zeit zur Jagd, Sammeln und Trocknen. Unser Weg ging nun nordwärts, stets auf der Hochebene lang, die von manchem Bergzug durchzogen ist, und mussten wir über verschiedene derselben klettern. Am 23. Januar verliessen wir Antofagasta, und am 4. Februar erreichten wir San Pedro de Atacama, 22° 55' südl. Br. und 68° 11' 25" westl. L., 2,720 M. hoch gelegen. San Pedro de Atacama zählt 2,000 Einwohner, und liegt in einem ziemlich bedeutenden Wald, von Algarrobo (<name key="Prosopis%20siliquastrum">Prosopis siliquastrum</name> var) und Channar (<name key="Gourlica%20chilensis">Gourlica chilensis</name>) und Birnbäumen; die Bäume stehen entfernt von einander, sind aber zum Theil recht gross, bis 1 M. im Durchmesser, und können Sie sich denken wie uns der Anblick des Waldes erfreute, da wir am 3. Januar den letzten Baum gesehen hatten. Bei Atacama gedeiht noch Luzerne und Weizen, von deren Bau die Leute meist leben, auch beschäftigen sich die meisten als Maulthiertreiber. Hier gibt es auch Läden, die zum Theil ziemlich gut assortirt sind, und konnten wir verschiedene Vorräthe erneuern. Zwischen Antofagasta und Atacama passirten wir blos einen Weiler am 2. Februar, sonst ist die ganze Gegend unbewohnt. Viele Einwohner Atacama's sprechen noch Atacamenno.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Am 17. Februar ging es weiter, stets nach Norden und im Innern der Cordillera; aber von hier an trafen wir doch fast alle Tagereisen eine Hütte oder mehrere. Wir passirten das Etablissement von Ascotan, 21° 42' südl. Br., 68° 14' 10" westl. L., und 3,750 M. über dem Meere, an der Fahrstrasse von Caracoles nach den Silberminen von Huanchaca gelegen, und wo Borax gewonnen wird. Das nächste Nachtlager ist gar 4.200 M. hoch gelegen. Von Amincha aus wandten wir uns wieder nach Westen, bis zur Laguna del Huasco, 3,869 M. hoch, am Westrande des Plateau gelegen, von wo wir hinabstiegen nach Pica, in der ehemals peruanischen, jetzt chilenischen Provinz Tarapacá, welches wir am 2. </seg>März früh erreichten, nach zwei Monate langem Ritt. <seg style="">Im Monat März bereisten wir noch die Provinz Tarapacá, und Anfangs April kehrten wir wieder hierher zurück.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Die Vegetation des Hochplateau ist ärmlich; an den wenigen Wasserläufen gibt es Gramineen und wenige Juncaceen; auf den Abhängen gibt es höchstens bis 1 M. hohe Büsche. Die Hauptfamilien sind <name key="Cynanthereae">Cynanthereae</name> 94 Sp., Gramineen 43, Legumin. 29, Solan. 28, Coniferen 18, Chenopod. und <name key="Verbenae">Verbenae</name> je 15, Malvae und Borragineen je 12 Arten; der Rest vertheilt sich auf 48 Familien. Farren fanden wir blos 3 Arten. Diese Zahlen beziehen sich auf die ganze Ausbeute; aber Tarapacá liefert fast nichts, so dass beinahe alles aus die Wüste kommt. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Interessant war mir eine Sp. <name key="Polylepis">Polylepis</name>, neu, welche bei 4,000 M. Höhe noch einen ziemlich dicken Baum bildet, aber niedrig, der den Bewohnern ihr Holz zu Thüren und Hausrath liefert; dies Genus der Rosaceen (<name key="Margyricarpus">Margyricarpus</name> verwandt) findet sich in der ganzen Hochebene, stets als Baum. An anderen Stellen der Hochebene dient der bis 30 Cm. starke, sehr feste Stamm von <name key="Cereus%20atacamensis">Cereus atacamensis</name> als Bauholz; ich könnte von Atacama einen hübschen Stamm in's Museum schicken. Ueber die Hälfte der mitgebrachten Pflanzen find neu, 209 Sp., darunter 10 neue Genera, zum Theil sehr interessant. Die ganze Reise verlief sehr glücklich, ohne jeden Unfall, blos das Leitpferd ging verloren.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">P.S. Die ganze Hochebene von Antofagasta an besteht aus Trachytlava, welche auf rothem (Secundär) Sandstein aufliegt, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>und liegen auf ihr eine Menge erloschener Vulcane, deren 3 höher sind als der Chimborazo, aber niedriger als der Aconcagua. Characterisch sind auch die Salares, grosse Ebenen, theils mit Steinsalz bedeckt, theils Tümpel mit Salzwasser zeigend, die oft eine Längenausdehnung von vielen Tagereisen haben. Diese Salares erstrecken sich vom 26° 30' südl. Br. bis an den Titicacasee. Wahrscheinlich kam das Salz der Salares aus dem rothen Sandstein, wenigstens finden sich auf den Salares ebensolche Selenitstücke, wie sie in Adern des rothen Sandsteines in ungeheurer Menge vorkommen. In den Salares findet sich auch oft knollenartig und nesterweis Hydroboracit, der zur Boraxgewinnung benützt wird.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[…] My journey was very interesting and in spite of the fact that it was always through the desert, yet I have brought back handsome results principally of plants. My companions were my second son Otto and the sub-director of the Museum, Mr Rahmer. In Copiapó I had 13 mules purchased and a leading horse and on 2 January we departed from there accompanied by a servant, a muleteer and a guide. Our luggage was packed on five animals and the others served as relays. We rode for three days to the east up to the salt lake Maricunga that lies about 4,000 m high. From here we had two short days’ journey northwards, then continued constantly eastwards over the first ridge of the Cordillera, on the highest place about 5,600 m high, until we reached Antofagasta de la Sierra on 16 January, a little place of about 14 to 16 houses and a church, inhabited by scarcely 40 people, Indians, but who all spoke Spanish and appear to have forgotten their mother tongue, Atacamenno. The place lies at 22° 55’ south latitude and 68° 11’ 25” west longitude from Greenwich, 3,570 m above sea-level, in a pretty valley, which is cut into a stream of trachyte. It was formerly Bolivian but was ceded to Chile for the present by the last treaty. The people still cannot yet comprehend that they are no longer Bolivians. From Maricunga on we met no more dwellings until Antofagasta.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After a six-day stop we went on. The mules had recovered and were able to fatten somewhat and we used the time for hunting, collecting and drying. Our track now went northwards, constantly along the high plain, which is traversed by many a mountain range and we had to climb over various of them. On 23 January we left Antofagasta and on 4 February we reached San Pedro de Atacama, situated at 22° 55’ latitude south and 68° 11’ 25” longitude west, 2,720 m. high. San Pedro de Atacama numbers 2,000 inhabitants and lies in a rather significant forest of Algarrobo (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Prosopis%20siliquastrum">Prosopis siliquastrum</name>
               </seg> var.) and Channar (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Gourlica%20chilensis">Gourlica chilensis</name>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Typesetter’s error for </seg>
                     <seg style="">Gourliea chilensis</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>) and pear trees. The trees stand distant from one another, but are in part very large up to 1 m in diameter and you can imagine how the view of the forest pleased us, because we had seen the last tree on 3 January. Lucerne and wheat still thrive at Atacama, from the cultivation of which the inhabitants mostly live. The majority are employed as muleteers as well. Here there are also shops, which in part are rather well stocked and we could renew various provisions. Between Antofagasta and Atacama we passed merely one hamlet on 2 February, otherwise the whole region is uninhabited. Many inhabitants of Atacama still speak Atacamenno.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On 17 February we went further always northwards and into the interior of the Cordillera, but from here on we did meet almost on every day’s journey a hut or several. We passed the establishment of Ascotan, 21° 42 south latitude, 68° 14’10” west longitude and 3,750 m above sea-level, situated on the cart road from Caracoles to the silver mines of Huanchaca and where borax is extracted. The next night’s lodging is situated fully 4,200 m high. From Amincha we turned again westwards up to Laguna del Huasco, 3,869 m high, situated on the west edge of the plateau, from whence we descended to Pica in the former Peruvian, now Chilean, province of Tarapacá, which we reached on the morning of 2 March after a two-month-long ride. We still were travelling over the Province of Tarapacá in March and at the beginning of April we returned here again.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The vegetation of the high plateau is sparse. On the few water courses there are <name key="Gramineae">Gramineae</name> and a few <name key="Juncaceae">Juncaceae</name>; on the slopes there are bushes at most one metre high. The main families are <name key="Cynanthereae">Cynanthereae</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Typesetter’s error for </seg>
                     <seg style="">Synanthereae</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> 94 species, <name key="Gramineae">Gramineae</name> 43, Legumin. 29, Solan. 28 <name key="Coniferae">Coniferae</name> 18, Chenopod. and <name key="Verbenae">Verbenae</name> each 15, Malvae and Boragineae each 12 species, the remainder divided into 48 families. We found merely three species of ferns. These numbers refer to the whole results, but Tarapacá produced almost nothing, so that nearly everything comes from the desert. Interesting for me was a species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Polylepis">Polylepis</name>
               </seg>, new, which at 4,000 m high still forms a rather thick but low tree that provides the inhabitants with their wood for doors and household furniture. This genus of the <name key="Rosaceae">Rosaceae</name> (related to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Margyricarpus">Margyricarpus</name>
               </seg>) is found in the whole high plain, always as a tree. In other places on the high plain the very solid trunk of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cereus%20atacamensis">Cereus atacamensis</name>
               </seg> upto 30 cm thick serves as timber. I was able to send a handsome trunk from Atacama to the Museum. Over half the plants brought back are new, 209 species, among them 10 new genera, in part very interesting. The whole journey turned out well, without any accident, merely the leading horse was lost.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>P.S. The whole high plain from Antofagasta on consists of trachyte lava that lies on red (Secondary) sandstone, and lying on it a number of extinct volcanoes of which three are higher than Chimborazo but lower than Aconcagua. Characteristic also are the Salares, large plains, partly covered with rock salt, partly pools showing salt water, which often have a linear dimension of many days’ journey. These Salares extend from 26° 30’ south latitude up to Lake Titicaca. Probably the salt of the Salares came from the red sandstone, at least such selenite pieces are found on the Salares as occur in huge numbers in veins of the red sandstone. In the Salares hydroboracite clumps and nests are also often found, which are used for borax extraction. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Borragineae%20">Borragineae </name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cereus%20atacamensis">Cereus atacamensis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Chenopodiaceae">Chenopodiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Coniferae">Coniferae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cynanthereae">Cynanthereae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gourlica%20chilensis">Gourlica chilensis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Gramineae">Gramineae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Juncaceae">Juncaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Malveae">Malveae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Margyricarpus">Margyricarpus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Polylepis">Polylepis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Prosopis%20siliquastrum">Prosopis siliquastrum</name>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Rosaceae">Rosaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Solanaceae">Solanaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Verbenae">Verbenae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
