<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tönning Ferry, 10 August 1840. ¶ My dear Ferdinand, ¶  ¶ While waiting for Häsler ¶  to come I am getting the letter ready, and right at the beginning I want to tell you some quite enjoyable news. Fri...</title>
            <author>Iwanne Müller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/40-08-10-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Private hands.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>40.08.10</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Iwanne Müller</author>
               <title>Tönning Ferry, 10 August 1840. ¶ My dear Ferdinand, ¶  ¶ While waiting for Häsler ¶  to come I am getting the letter ready, and right at the beginning I want to tell you some quite enjoyable news. Fri...</title>
               <date when="1840-08-10">1840-08-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/40-08-10-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Tönning Ferry, 10 August 1840. ¶ My dear Ferdinand, ¶  ¶ While waiting for Häsler ¶  to come I am getting the letter ready, and right at the beginning I want to tell you some quite enjoyable news. Fri...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">40.08.10</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Iwanne Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Private hands.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope front: 'Hr. Ferdinand Müller | in | Husum | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Frei</hi>
                     </seg>.' [Prepaid.]</p>
               </note>Tönninger Fähre 10. August 1840.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mein lieber Ferdinand! — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Erwartung dass Häsler kommen wird mache ich den Brief fertig, und will Dir gleich im Anfang eine recht erfreuliche Nachricht mittheilen. Freitag vor 8 Tagen hat uns Fortuna im Vogelschiessen die Königin ins Haus geführt. Ernst Mertens das Glückskind schoss erst den Schwanz und nachher den ganzen Rumpf von der Stange, und Clara war die Königin beide waren so vergnügt, sie sprangen den ganzen Tag herum, und haben auf dem Ball den letzten Tanz mitgemacht. den ersten mussten sie ganz allein tanzen. wirklich ein wichtiges Königspaar Ernst 7 und Clara 6 Jahre alt. Wenn Mutter das doch gewusst hätte, die hätte sich gewiss schrecklich dazu gefreut. — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eigentlich hätte ich schon eher schreiben müssen, aber da Oncel und die Cousinen nicht lange mehr hier bleiben wollten, so hab ich die Zeit in ihrer Gesellschaft zugebracht. Donnerstag sind sie mit einer Helgolander Golle von hier abgefahren und heute Morgen um 7 fährt ein Dampfschiff von Helgoland nach Hamburg worauf sie sich begeben werden, und von Hamburg wollen sie noch andere Verwandten auf 14 Tage besuchen. Es kommt uns jetzt ordentlich still vor, denn lebhaft waren sie alle drei. — Ferner kann ich dir noch mittheilen aus einem Brief von Madame Lund den ich vor kurzem erhielt "das Agnes Fischer Hr Stellerbeck in ihre Netze gefangen, und ihn zu ihrem Bräutigam auserwählt hat. Sie sei überglücklich".</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun lieber Bruder rückt das Pferdemark auch her, vor Mittwoch über 8 Tage haben wir es hier. Oncel sagte gestern zu mir ich möchte Dir schreiben, dass er keine Zeit hätte Dich mit unserm Wagen zu holen, du möchtest also Hr Becker dem Contracte zufolge sagen, dass Oncel wünschte Du kämest folgenden Montag mit Häsler hierher, wir freuen uns schon alle recht dazu, Dich auf längere Zeit wiederzusehn. — </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Oncel ist jetzt bei der Rabsenferndte<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Rapsernte?</p>
               </note> begriffen, seine Zeit ist daher sehr beschränkt. — Denk Dir lieber Ferdinand kein Haarbreit hätte gefehlt, und Oncel wäre zu Tode gekommen, ein Bullochse in Dithmarschen hat ihn unter gehabt, und er befindet sich jetzt so schlecht, alle Glieder thun ihn weh, so dass er heute das Bett hüten muss. — Unser Dampfschiff fährt jetzt auf einmal wieder so plötzlich wie es weggeblieben, ist es auch wiedergekommen. Für uns ist es ein grosser Werth dass es hier ist, indem keine Brücke ist, und wir alles fahren was dahin soll. — Frau Consulin ist von ihrer Reise noch nicht wieder zurück und sie haben jetzt eine Wirthschaftsmamsell erhalten ein sehr nettes Mädchen. — Kaufmann Haacks Mamsell habe ich auch kennen gelernt. — Lieber Bruder, du hast wohl zwei paar weisse wollene Strümpfe bringe die Montag mit, wenn du es denn willst, kannst du sie mit unsern Strümpfen grau gefärbt kriegen, denn weiss sieht doch gar zu schlecht aus. Denk Dir den Tag darauf wie Du meinen Brief erhielst worin ich schrieb das Hr Cap. Suensen bedenklich krank wäre ist er schon gestorben, nun können wir über unsere 7 Mark 8 Schilling auch einen Strich machen. — Bei Schlachter Detlefsen ist ein neues Comptoir errichtet Jansen und Lascow die künftigen Schwäger haben sich beide etablirt, und Jansen wird Demoisel Lascow auch wohl bald heirathen. — Nun lieber Ferdinand wollen wir das andere mündlich besprechen Nun Adieu, lebe bis dahin recht wohl, sei herzlich gegrüsst von uns allen, und sei versichert dass sich auf Deine Ankunft herzlich freut</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Deine </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dich liebende Schwester</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Iwanne Müller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Tönning Ferry, 10 August 1840.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dear Ferdinand,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>While waiting for Häsler<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The coachman who operated the service between Tönning and Husum.</p>
               </note> to come I am getting the letter ready, and right at the beginning I want to tell you some quite enjoyable news. Friday a week ago at the popinjay shoot Lady Luck led the Queen into our home. Ernst Mertens, the lucky child, first shot the tail and later the whole rump from the pole, and Clara was the queen. Both were so gay, they skipped around all day, and at the ball they joined in the last dance. The first one they had to dance all on their own, truly an impressive royal couple — Ernst 7 and Clara 6 years old. If only mother could have known about this, I am sure she would have been terribly pleased.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I really should have written to you sooner, but as Uncle<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not Johann Ferdinand Mertens but another, unidentified relative.</p>
               </note> and the cousins did not want to remain here very much longer, I spent the time in their company. They left here on Thursday with a Helgoland boat, and this morning at 7 a steamboat goes from Helgoland to Hamburg, on which they will go, and from Hamburg they want to visit other relatives. The place seems rather quiet now, as all three of them were pretty lively.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I can tell you further from a letter I received recently from Madam Lund 'that Agnes Fischer has caught Mr. Stellerbeck in her nets, and has chosen him to be her bridegroom. She is overjoyed'.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And now, dear brother, the horse market is drawing near, by Wednesday week we have it here. Uncle said to me yesterday, that I should write to you that he will have no time to pick you up with our wagon, you should therefore tell Mr Becker<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Albert Becker.</p>
               </note> in accordance with your contract, that Uncle wishes you to come here with Häsler on the following Monday. We are all happy in anticipation of seeing you again for a longer period.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Uncle<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Johann Ferdinand Mertens.</p>
               </note> is now in the middle of the rape harvest and has therefore little time. — Just imagine, dear Ferdinand, not a hair's breadth and Uncle would have been killed. A bullock in Dithmarschen had him down, and now he feels so poorly, all his limbs are aching, and he had to stay in bed today.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Our steamer has suddenly started going again, it returned as abruptly as it stopped away. It means a lot to us to have it back, as there is no bridge and we have to drive everything that has to go there. — The Consul's wife<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mrs Lexow, see also I. Müller to M, 25 April 1841.</p>
               </note> has not yet returned from her journey and they have got a housekeeper now, a very nice girl. I have also met grocer Haack's housekeeper.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dear brother, I think you have two pairs of white woollen stockings, bring them along on Monday, and if you want to, you can have them dyed grey with our stockings, because white really does look too bad. Just imagine, the day after you got my letter in which I wrote that Captain Suensen was seriously ill, he had already died, now we can write off our 7 Mark 8 Schillings. They have erected a new office at butcher Detlefsen's, Jansen and Lascow, the future brothers-in-law, have established themselves well, and it looks as if Jansen will marry Miss Lascow soon.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now, dear Ferdinand, we will talk about the rest in person. Now adieu, keep well until then, sincere greetings from us all, and be assured that the one looking happily forward to your arrival is</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your loving sister</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Iwanne Müller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
