<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nübel, 31 July 1842. ¶ Good brother, ¶  ¶ Thank God, a quarter of a year is gone! And in spite of my dislike of being here I must honestly confess that it has passed quickly for me. It must be that I ...</title>
            <author>Iwanne Müller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/42-07-31-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M106.3, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>42.07.31</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Iwanne Müller</author>
               <title>Nübel, 31 July 1842. ¶ Good brother, ¶  ¶ Thank God, a quarter of a year is gone! And in spite of my dislike of being here I must honestly confess that it has passed quickly for me. It must be that I ...</title>
               <date when="1842-07-31">1842-07-31</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/42-07-31-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Nübel, 31 July 1842. ¶ Good brother, ¶  ¶ Thank God, a quarter of a year is gone! And in spite of my dislike of being here I must honestly confess that it has passed quickly for me. It must be that I ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">42.07.31</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Iwanne Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M106.3, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Nübel den 31stn Juli 1842.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Guter Bruder! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gottlob, ¼ Jahr ist dahin, und bei alle dem das ich hier nicht sein mag, muss ich aufrichtig gestehn, das es mir schnell entflohen ist, es muss doch daher kommen, das man immer so in Thätigkeit ist — u will ich mich freuen, wenn die übrige Zeit auch so eilt. — Ich habe jetzt eine Bitte an Dich lieber Ferdinand, nämlich die, das Du Mertens wenn du zum Pferdemarkt in Tönning kommst bittest, zu Mai für mich eine Stelle womöglich in einen grossen Putzladen aufzusuchen, denn Wirtschaftsmamsell zu sein ist mir so verhasst, dass ich mich jetzt nur mit dem Gedanken Putzarbeiterin zu werden herumtrage, und bin ich dann nur noch 1 Jahr in einem Putzladen gewesen, dann will ich mich schon selbst helfen, und Bertha kann mit, wenn sie will. — Ich denke Mertens werden nichts dagegen einzuwenden haben, da ich Lust und Genie dazu habe, u das ist doch auch weit angenehmer, als Jahrelang andern Leuten, das Essen zu machen u vom Morgen bis zum Abend herumzuarbeiten, so komme ich zum Mai hier weg, wo ich dann hinkomme, weiss ich denn ob ich es da besser bekomme, kommt man bei vornehmeren, nein dann will ich lieber ich weiss nicht was thun, als nach Vornehmeren gehn, da muss man immer in Angst sein, das ist das einzigste was mir hier gefällt, das es hier nicht so steif ist, kurz um Wirtschafterin bleibe ich nicht, das ich hier ein Jahr bin freut mich, insofern das ich für einen anständigen bürgerlichen Hausstand gut kochen u backen kann, u mehr gebrauche ich nicht, denn es wird sich nicht noch mal ein Prinz in mir verlieben, ja Ferdinand, lache nur, nun hast Du meine aufrichtige Meinung, und das kannst Du Mertens nur sagen, das einzige bedenkliche was bei der Sache ist, ist das, das es noch etwas kosten wird, aber hier schleise ich ja auch was auf, die 5 <seg style="color: #000000; ">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Reichsthaler symbol.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>sind beinahe alle, und wenn das Jahr um ist, werden die 20 <seg style="color: #000000; ">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">Reichsthaler symbol</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>auch wohl auf sein, und dann die Reisekosten dazu, was kommt da denn heraus. — So leicht wird auch wohl keine passende Stelle in einen Putzladen zu bekommen sein, deshalb bitte ich Dich aber es nun mit Mertens abzumachen so haben sie Zeit genug bis Mai, und können sich, sollten sie es etwa nicht gerne sehn, nicht mit dergleichen entschuldigen, dies lieber Junge, ist nun mein liebster Wunsch, würde der auch vernichtet, was soll ich dann machen. Ich wollte erst selbst [an] Mertens schreiben, aber das ist doch nicht so, als wenn jemand darum spräche — Du wirst auch äusserst selten hören, das eine Mamsell sich glücklich fühlt, allenthalben sind sie geplagte Geschöpfe, auch Beckers Mamsell wird es nicht besser gehn. — Nun thue für mich was Du kannst, ich will es Euch überlassen. — Lieber Ferdinand ich schreibe die nächste Woche an Mertens, und will ihnen es denn wohl zu verstehen geben recht nachdrücklich, — u warum mag ich hier nicht sein, weil gerade das woran ich so viel Gefallen und wozu ich so grosse Lust habe, weil ich das alles hier entbehren muss, nun kommt die Erndte Zeit, morgen geht es schon an, dann sind die Mädchen mit auf dem Felde, und ich bin allein in der Küche, ich sehe alle Tage wie ein Schornsteinfeger aus. Lieber Ferdinand, Du denkst nun doch nicht, das ich Dir was vorklagen will, das ist keineswegs der Fall, ich schreibe es nur damit Du einsiehst das ich nicht unrecht habe Putzmacherin zu werden, da ich doch so sehr dafür bin. — Ich muss Mertens so ungern ich es thue, auch schreiben das sie mir 5 <seg style="color: #000000; ">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="">Reichsthaler symbol.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>zuschicken, denn ich mag wirklich nicht darum bei Pastors fragen, u ich wollte auch doch gerne ein altes Umschlage Tuch herhaben wenn es des Morgens manchmal kalt ist, so komme ich in Verlegenheit, das kannst Du dann mit nach Husum nehmen und von da pr. Gelegenheit weiter besorgen und dann (packst Du mir da ein bischen Schokolade, oder sonst eine Kleinigkeit bei ein, nicht wahr, es braucht nur wenig zu sein. Nun wollte ich Dich noch um einen kleinen Rath gegen Zahnschmerzen fragen, denn ich habe schon ein paar mal welche gehabt, und auch gegen meine Haare, denn die gehn mir in dieser Zeit so sehr aus. — Ich habe auch viele Anliegen nicht wahr? — Nun bekömmst Du auch ein paar Pflanzen wieder, die Blaue, und Gelbe, sind Gartenblumen, vielleicht kannst Du davon Gebrauch machen, das lange Gewächs steht zwischen Gras und Unkraut. — Nun ist mein Papier gleich wieder voll, ich eile zum Schluss, weil ich auch noch nähen wollte, u will ich alles dem lieben Gott überlassen, dass er es nach meinem Wunsche einrichten möge, denn hat er es anders beschlossen, so wird doch nichts daraus, und so muss ich mich darin fügen. So wünsche ich Dir lieber Ferdinand, ein recht vergnügtes Pferdemarkt in Tönning u bitte ich nach demselben gleich zu schreiben, u alles neue u was Du da zu hören bekommst, ich bin nun schon neugierig auf Deinen Brief. So lebe wohl, u glücklich, und denke zuweilen mit brüderlicher Liebe an </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Deine Schwester.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Iwanne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Nübel, 31 July 1842.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Good brother,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Thank God, a quarter of a year is gone! And in spite of my dislike of being here I must honestly confess that it has passed quickly for me. It must be that I am constantly occupied. I shall be happy if the rest of my time here hurries by just as fast.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And now I have a request to put to you, dear Ferdinand. When you go to Tönning for the horse market, would you please ask the Mertens to find a position for me for May in a milliner's shop, a large establishment if possible. I hate being a housekeeper, and just keep going with the thought that I will become a milliner. Once I have been in a milliner's shop for one year I will be able to work for myself, and Bertha can come with me if she wants to. I don't think the Mertens will have any objections, seeing that I have enthusiasm and genius for it. And it is much nicer than preparing food for other people and slaving around from morning to night. How do I know, whether I will be better off when I leave here in May? If one goes to people of rank, — no! — I would rather do I don't know what, than to work for the upper class, there one would always have to live in fear. That is the only thing I like about this place, it is not so formal. In one word: I will not remain a housekeeper! To be here for a year is good in so far as I will be able to cook and bake well for a decent middle class household. I don't need more than that. It is not likely that a prince will fall in love with me one day! Yes, Ferdinand, you go ahead and laugh, but there you have my honest opinion, and that is what you can tell Mertens, too. The only problem with it is, that it will cost a bit more. But then I wear out quite a bit of clothing here, the 5 Reichsthaler Courant are almost gone. By the time the year is over the 20 Reichsthaler Courant will probably have been used up, too. Add to that the travelling expenses, — where does that leave us?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Probably it will not be all that easy to find a suitable position in a milliner's shop. That is why I am asking you to settle it now with the Mertens, that will give them ample time till May and they will not be able to use anything like that as an excuse, if they should not be in favour of the idea.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This then, my dear boy, is now my dearest wish. I don't know what I would do, if that, too, were to be destroyed. I was going to write to the Mertens myself at first, but then that is not the same as someone pleading your cause in person. You will hear only very rarely that a housekeeper is happy, they are always harassed creatures, Becker's<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Benjamin Becker.</p>
               </note> housekeeper won't be any better off either. Anyway, do for me what you can, I will leave it to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dear Ferdinand, I am going to write to Mertens myself next week, and then I will give them to understand — quite emphatically — why I don't want to be here, because here I am deprived of everything I enjoy and want to do. Now harvest time is coming, it starts already tomorrow, the girls will have to go along, out into the fields, and I am left all alone here in the kitchen, every day I look like a chimney sweep. Dear Ferdinand, I hope you don't think I am just whinging. That is not the case at all. I am only writing this so you will understand that I am not wrong in wishing to become a milliner, when I want it so very much.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As much as I dislike having to do this, I must also write and ask Mertens to send me 5 Reichsthaler Courant, for I really don't want to ask the Minister for it. Also I would like to have an old shawl here, because sometimes, when it is cold in the mornings, I am placed in an awkward position. You can take it with you to Husum and send it on from there when convenient. And you will pack some chocolate or some other little things like that in with it, won't you? — it need not be much. Also I want to ask you for a bit of advice against toothache, because I have had it a few times. About my hair, too: I am losing such a lot lately. I do have a lot of requests, don't I?!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herewith you are also getting a few more plants. The blue and the yellow ones are garden flowers, maybe you can make use of them. The tall plant was growing amongst grass and weeds.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My paper is nearly filled once more, now I hurry to finish, because I still wanted to do some sewing. I will leave everything to the good God, that he may arrange everything according to my wish, because if he has decided otherwise, nothing will come of it anyway, and I will have to submit to it.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I wish you, dear Ferdinand, an enjoyable horse market and ask you to write immediately afterwards and tell me all the news you hear. I am already curious, waiting for your letter. Keep well and happy, and remember occasionally in brotherly love</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your sister</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Iwanne.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
