<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg, 7 May 1843. ¶ Dear Müller, ¶  ¶ At long last! — you will say, when you receive these lines. My long silence had the appearance as if the correspondence between us had collapsed. I can, howeve...</title>
            <author>Albert Schütt</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/43-05-07-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M102.2, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>43.05.07</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Albert Schütt</author>
               <title>Hamburg, 7 May 1843. ¶ Dear Müller, ¶  ¶ At long last! — you will say, when you receive these lines. My long silence had the appearance as if the correspondence between us had collapsed. I can, howeve...</title>
               <date when="1843-05-07">1843-05-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/43-05-07-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg, 7 May 1843. ¶ Dear Müller, ¶  ¶ At long last! — you will say, when you receive these lines. My long silence had the appearance as if the correspondence between us had collapsed. I can, howeve...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">43.05.07</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Albert Schütt</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M102.2, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS envelope front: 'Herrn F. Müller | Wohlgeb | Addresse Herr Apotheker Becker | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Husum</hi>
                     </seg> | <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">Franco</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <seg style="">'</seg>.</p>
               </note>Hamburg d: 7 May [1]843.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Müller!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Endlich, werden Sie gewiss beim Empfang dieser Zeilen rufen, da mein langes Stillschweigen das Ansehn hatte als wenn die Correspondens zwischen uns auffliegen sollte, jedoch kann ich Ihnen versichern das es mir bis jetzt unmöglich gewesen im geringsten an schreiben zu denken da Stoff zum Schreiben für mich hinreichend da ist, wie auch Sie selbst erleben werden wenn der Brief durch gelesen ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Geschäft ging es diesen Winter sehr ruhig her, selbst das Frühjahr schien durch aus nicht geeignet den Apothekern &amp; Aertzten Gelegenheit zu geben sich dem Publicum nützlich machen zu können, dieses dauerte bis Mitte März, plötzlich aber kam Leben, Grippe gastrisches Fieber weckte Apotheker &amp; Aertzte aus ihrem Winterschlaf und meine Receptur stieg von 20 schnell bis auf 70 Recepte dieser dauerte nun bis May unverändert fort dazu hatte ich das Unglück das unser Lehrling weg kam, weil derselbe nicht ehrlich; - - - da stand ich nun, Gesell und Lehrling in einer Person, (nemlich die Anfangs Gründe der Pharmacie repitiren, Kapsel machen — Tutenkleben etc Sie kennen ja auch alle diese schönen Arbeiten practisch, und wissen wie angenehm mir solche gewesen, das mir nun die Lust zum Schreiben vergangen und von einem Tage bis zum andern die Beantwortung Ihres lieben Briefes verzögert wurde. können Sie sich leicht denken, da überhaupt meine Schreiblust nicht weit her ist. Bei Windter hab ich wenn ich Ihrem Briefe trauen darf Lorbeeren geerndtet und auch als Augenartzt mich hervorgethan, allerdings hoffe ich schon Michaelis alle Hindernisse beseitigen und zur Universität gehen zu können um der Pharmacie valet zu sagen und ein Jünger Aesculaps zu werden, ich nehme zu diesem Zweck wöchendlich eine lateinische Stunde doch darüber später etwas Detallierteres. nächsten Sonntag werde ich die Botanische Excursion mit machen und hoffentlich im nächsten Brief eine Pflanze mit einschliessen Von Bürgermeister Paulsens Sohn der in meiner Nähe bei Hr Beinhauer Gebr in der Lehre ist habe ich erfahren das in Husum ein grosses Feuer gewesen nemlich bei Kauf-Heureck (wird ja wohl seine Finanzen dadurch etwas verbessert haben?) Etwas neues kann ich von Hr Hermes mittheilen gewiss wird es Hr Becker interessiren, seine Familie hatte eine passende Frau mit Vermögen für ihn gefunden, hier über zufrieden lässt er sich auch gleich mit dem jungen Mädchen von ungefähr 54 Jahr verloben ohne sie vorher gesehen zu haben weil ihm die Glänzende Aussicht wird studiren zu können, da sie ihm das Geld dazu geben wolle, allein mit dem Vermögen ist es nicht weit her es ist im ganzen nur 4000 Mark also ein sehr beneidenswerthes Glück.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie ist Ihre Excursion in Ostern ausgefallen, ist Ihre Mühe belohnt?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Haben Sie die Güte Schmidt recht herzlich zu grüssen und mich bei ihm zu entschuldigen, dass ich seinen lieb. Brief bis jetzt noch nicht beantwortet, ich aber so bald nur irgend Zeit sey mich anschicken werde meine Seumsäligkeit<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Saumseligkeit.</p>
               </note> nach zu kommen überhaupt bitte alle Bekannten sowie Hr Becker nebst Familie recht herzlich zu grüssen,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auch theilen Sie mir mit wie die goldene Hochzeit Ihrer Grosseltern aus gefallen Sie sind doch recht vergnügt gewesen, überhaupt vergessen Sie das Schreiben nicht und nehmen es nicht übel wen ich mit der Beantwortung zögere seien Sie fest überzeugt das ich desto öfter Ihrer gedenke, nochmals bitte ich alle zu grüssen so wie lieb zu behalten </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. H. A. Schütt</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Eiligst</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg, 7 May 1843.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Müller,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At long last! — you will say, when you receive these lines. My long silence had the appearance as if the correspondence between us had collapsed. I can, however, assure you, that until now it has been impossible for me to even think of writing, though I had plenty to write about, as you will see, when you have read this letter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Business has been very quiet this winter, and even spring did not seem inclined to provide an opportunity for pharmacists and doctors to make themselves useful to the public. This lasted till mid-March, when things suddenly got lively. Influenza &amp; gastric fever woke pharmacists and doctors from their hibernation, and my prescriptions rapidly rose from 20 to 70. And thus it continued unchanged until May. In addition I had the misfortune that our apprentice had to go, as he was dishonest. There I was, journeyman and apprentice rolled into one, i.e. repeat the basic beginnings of pharmacy, making capsules, glue paper bags, etc, — you know all these lovely jobs from practical experience, and know how attractive I found them, so that I did not feel much inclined to write. And replying to your kind letter<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> was put off from one day to the next. I am sure you know what I mean, as I am not much of a letter writer anyway.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If I can believe your letter, I have earned laurels with Windter, and have also excelled as eye specialist. Of course I hope that by St Michael's Day<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">29 September.</p>
               </note> I will already have overcome all obstacles and be able to go to university and bid farewell to pharmacy to become a disciple of Aesculapius, and towards this end I take weekly Latin lessons, but more details about that later.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Next Sunday I will take part in a botanical excursion and hope that I can enclose a few plants with my next letter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I heard from Mayor Paulsen's son, who is apprenticed to Beinhauer Bros not far from me, that there was a big fire in Husum at Kauf-Heureck (he will probably have improved his finances somewhat by it?) I have some news about Mr Hermes — I am sure Mr Becker<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Probably Ernst Becker who, to judge by the envelope from an earlier letter, A. Schütt to M, 10 March 1843, was already managing the Husum pharmacy for his uncle Albert Becker, even if he did not formally take it over until the following year?</p>
               </note> will be interested —, his family found him a suitable woman with money, content with this he agrees at once to become engaged to the young lady of around 54, without even having seen her first, because he has great expectations of being able to study, as she would give him the money for it. However, the fortune turns out not to be up to much, only 4000 Mark, a very enviable happiness!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>How did your excursion at Easter turn out? Were your troubles rewarded?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Be so kind and give my regards to Schmidt and make my apologies to him, because I have not yet answered his kind letter, but I will make up for my negligence and get on to it just as soon as I can make the time. Give my regards to all acquaintances generally and Mr Becker and family in particular.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Let me know, how the celebrations for your grandparents' golden wedding anniversary turned out, did you enjoy yourself? Don't forget to write and don't take offence, when I am tardy with my replies. Rest assured that I am thinking of you all the more often. Once more, convey my regards to everybody and keep in your favour</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. H. A. Schütt</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">In great haste.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
