<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rendsburg, 13 October 1844. ¶  ¶ This morning, beloved brother, our Bertha set out on her journey to Hamburg. At 8 o'clock she left with the diligence ¶  for Neumünster and will then get to Altona wit...</title>
            <author>Iwanne Müller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/44-10-13-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M106.8, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>44.10.13</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Iwanne Müller</author>
               <title>Rendsburg, 13 October 1844. ¶  ¶ This morning, beloved brother, our Bertha set out on her journey to Hamburg. At 8 o'clock she left with the diligence ¶  for Neumünster and will then get to Altona wit...</title>
               <date when="1844-10-13">1844-10-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1840-9/1840-4/44-10-13-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Rendsburg, 13 October 1844. ¶  ¶ This morning, beloved brother, our Bertha set out on her journey to Hamburg. At 8 o'clock she left with the diligence ¶  for Neumünster and will then get to Altona wit...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">44.10.13</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Iwanne Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M106.8, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Rendsburg d. 13tn October. 1844. — </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Diesen Morgen, geliebter Bruder! hat unsere Bertha ihre Reise nach Hamburg angetreten, um 8 Uhr ist sie mit der Deligence nach Neumünster gefahren, und wird sie mit den zweiten Bahnzug nach Altona kommen, wo sie dann um 6 Uhr weiterreisen wird. Bertha dachte schon ihren Kaffee bei Barhaas zu trinken, aber etwas später wird es denn doch. — Leider war am Sonnabend keine Gelegenheit nach Laenstedt und die Reise kann nicht länger aufgeschoben werden, daher rieth ich Bertha, nur die Reise nach Hw Sames aufzugeben. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nun sitze ich denn ganz allein, und was könnte ich dann besseres thun, lieber Ferdinand, als Deinen lieben Brief beantworten, und mich eine Weile mit Dir unterhalten, denn ich habe heute recht viel zu erzählen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin ganz entzückt, wenn ich daran denke, Dich guter Bruder <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mehrere Tage</hi>
               </seg> bei uns zu sehen, nur möchte ich Dich bitten, wenn es sich so einrichten liesse, nicht wieder diese geräuschvolle Zeit zu wählen, am liebsten wäre es uns nach Pfingsten, es ist freilich noch sehr lange, und geht es nicht, doch zu Ostern, damit wir auch recht Genuss von der Zeit haben. Und dann sollst Du alles wissen, was zum Schreiben zu weitläuftig ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zum Winter engagieren wir uns 3 Lehrlinge. 1 junges Mädchen haben wir schon so halb u. halb, dann bekommen wir für 1 Jahr 20 <seg style="color: #000000; ">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Reichsthaler symbol.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>zu, haben wir dann 3, so haben wir doch Miethe u. Feurung frei, billiger wollen wir es nicht gerne, denn es kommen ohnehin Putzarbeiterinnen genug. — Am Freitag Abend waren wir ins Theater, es wurde der Sohn der Wildnis gegeben. Ach, wenn Du Gelegenheit hast dieses Stück zu sehen, so lass sie nicht vorbei gehen, ich habe mich selten so gut amüsirt, als den Abend. Wir gehen in der Loge, im Parterre ist es zu gemischt, Müllers gehen aber im Parterre, und ich hatte Freitag den hohen Genuss, sie da zu sehen. — Wenn Du mir versprichst, nichts an Mertens zu plaudern, will ich Dir was erzählen. Theodors Companjon, Herr Stever, hat uns besucht, u da unser Logis so unansehlich von aussen ist, und auch der Laden ein wenig beschränkt,so will er nicht, das wir länger als bis Ostern hier bleiben, und uns selbst eine andere Wohnung besorgen, und sollen wir uns dann Mobilien bei den Tischlern miethen. Dies ist uns auch recht lieb, und wie viel ist es doch werth, das wir männliche Stütze, und einen guten Rath dabei haben werden. na, das sollte Müller wissen, das Herr Stever uns aufgesucht hat, und hielt auch er es so viel besser für uns, nur schalt er uns tüchtig aus, das wir keine schönere Wohnung gemiethet haben, es waren aber keine andere miethsfrei. Er sagte, wir müssten Schläge haben, ich habe ihn ausgelacht; ½ Jahr ist nicht ewig. — Ich freue mich immer unendlich, wenn ich von vernünftigen Leuten höre, das sie unsere Ansichten theilen, sie sagen es geradezu, über uns herrscht nur eine Stimme, aber über Müllers — Viele. — Theodor ist wegen Schulden verklagt, denk Dir, nun sagt er, wir haben ihn ruiniert, wir hätten so wenig Kostgeld gegeben. Die Menschen lachen über seine Dummheit, denn jeder weiss ja, wie lange wir da gewesen sind, und noch dazu im Sommer, wir haben doch immer für Feurung mitbezahlt. Gottlob, das wir es so weit überstanden haben. Ja es ist wirklich angenehm so seine freie, eigene Existenz zu behaupten, brauchten wir nur nicht immer von neuem Geld aufzunehmen, aber es ist auch noch der Anfang, und im Anfang hat man noch zu kämpfen. Ich denke 100 <seg style="color: #000000; ">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Reichsthaler symbol.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>werden genug sein, 100<seg style="">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mark symbol.</p>
               </note> hat Bertha noch ausserdem, so kann denn für 400 <seg style="">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mark Symbol</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>einigermassen Auswahl angeschafft werden, es gehört sehr viel dazu, ich könnte gerne mein ganzes Capital dazu gebrauchen. — Bei Sommerfeld in Schleswig haben wir ungefähr für 40 <seg style="">
                  <note type="frame"/>
               </seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Mark Symbol</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Blumen aufgegeben. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Grimm ist hier auch schon gewesen, wir haben ihn ersucht, uns nicht so oft zu besuchen, denn das giebt gleich Gespräche. Allgemein sagen die Leute, wie schrecklich, ich sei mit Hr. Grimm versprochen. — Klupps nehmen wir nicht mit, es sei denn, das wir mal eingeführt würden, auch wegen der Trauer, um unsern guten Grossvater, wollen wir fürs erste nicht tanzen. — Du fragst nach meinem befinden, lieber Ferdinand. Diese Woche bin ich recht wohl gewesen, die vorige aber, hatte ich mir durch eine starke Erkältung, schreckliche Zahnschmerzen zugezogen, das ich in 5 Nächten keine Ruhe hatte, und dabei solch reissen in Kopf und Ohr, da nahm ich meine Zuflucht zu einer spanischen Fliege, die auch bald die gewünschte Erleichterung verschaffte. Ich habe so viel Weinstein an den Zähnen, weisst Du dafür wohl einen Rath. — Ich sehe mein Papier ist zu Ende, und damit muss es dann auch mein Brief sein. — So wünsche ich Dir schliesslich ein recht herzliches Lebewohl, lieber<seg> Φερδινανδ.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Deine Iwanne. —</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich erwarte nun auch bald einen eben so reichhaltigen Brief von Dir. — Darf ich hoffen ? —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich benütze Dein Couvert, lieber Ferdinand, indem mein Papier percha ist. — Adieu. —</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Rendsburg, 13 October 1844.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This morning, beloved brother, our Bertha set out on her journey to Hamburg. At 8 o'clock she left with the diligence<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A mail coach taking passengers, which ran to a set timetable. At the time a train ran from Kiel via Neumünster to Altona. The dilligence ran from Rendsburg to Neumünster, where Bertha changed to continue her journey by train.</p>
               </note> for Neumünster and will then get to Altona with the second train, from where she will journey on at 6 o'clock. Bertha thought of taking her coffee break with Barhaas, but it will get in a little later than that. Unfortunately there was no opportunity to get to Laenstedt<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Not found in any gazeteer. Probably a misspelling by Iwanne for Luhnstedt near Rendsburg.</p>
               </note> and the journey can not be delayed any longer. That is why I advised Bertha to give up the trip to see Rev. Sames.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Now I am sitting here all alone and I could not think of anything better to do, dear Ferdinand, than to answer your dear letter, and to chat with you for a while, for I have a lot to tell you today.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am really delighted at the thought of having you, dear brother, with us for <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">several days</hi>
               </seg>, only I would like to ask you, if it could be arranged so that you don't choose again this noisy period. We would like it best after Pentecost, which is of course still a very long way off, or, if that does not suit, then for Easter, so that we can really relish your time with us. And then you shall hear everything that takes too long to write.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Towards the winter we will take on three apprentices. We already have one young girl sort of half and half, then we will receive 20 Reichsthaler Courant for one year. Once we have three it means we will have rent and heating free. We don't want it any cheaper, there will be enough women coming as milliners' labourers as it is.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>On Friday night we went to the theatre, they performed 'The Son of the Wilderness'.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Halm (1843), first performed 1842: see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Oxford Companion to German Literature.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Oh, if you get the opportunity to see this play, don't pass it by! Rarely have I been so well entertained as on that evening. We take a box, it is too mixed in the stalls. But the Müllers<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Theodor Müller and his wife.</p>
               </note> take the stalls, and on Friday I had the great gratification of seeing them there.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If you promise not to repeat it to the Mertens, I will tell you something. Theodor's companion, Mr. Stever, has visited us, and because our lodging looks so shabby on the outside and the shop is also a little on the small side, he does not want us to stay here any longer than till Easter and will look for other lodgings for us himself, and we should then hire furniture from the cabinet makers. That suits us very well, too; how good it is that we will have male support, and good advice into the bargain. If Müller but knew that Mr. Stever visited us! He also thinks it is much better for us like this, but he gave us a good scolding, that we did not rent better lodgings for ourselves. But there was nothing else rent-free. He said we ought to be spanked, but I just laughed at him. Half a year is not for ever!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It always pleases me no end, when I hear from sensible people that they share our opinions; they say straight out that there is only one opinion about us, but about Müller there are many. Theodor is being sued for debts. Just imagine, now he says that we have ruined him, because we paid so little board. People laugh about his stupidity, because everybody knows how long we stayed there, and during summer, too, and we paid towards heating costs. Thank God that we have got through that alright. Yes, it is really pleasant to lead one's own free existence. If only we did not have to borrow money again and again,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">From the phrasing this might mean using her capital, rather than borrowing in the usual sense.</p>
               </note> but this is only the beginning, and in the beginning one always has to fight. I think 100 Reichsthaler Courant should be enough, in addition Bertha still has another 100 Mark, so for 400 Mark we can buy a reasonable selection; it takes so much! I could easily spend my whole capital.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We delivered nearly 40 Mark worth of flowers near Sommerfeld in Schleswig.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr. Grimm has been here, too. We have asked him not to visit so often, because there will immediately be gossip. People are already saying: how terrible, that I am promised to Mr. Grimm!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We don't go to clubs, unless we make our debut some time. But because we are in mourning for our good grandfather we don't want to go dancing at present.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You ask how I am, dear Ferdinand. This week I have been really well, but last week I had a terrible toothache as the result of a chill, and after not getting any rest for five nights, and having with it such intense pain in my head and ear I finally resorted to a Spanish fly, which soon brought the hoped-for relief. I have so much tartar on my teeth. Can you give me any advice on what to do about it?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I see that my paper is finished, so my letter must end as well. To conclude I wish you a very sincere God's speed, dear Ferdinand.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your Iwanne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">But now I expect just as much news in a letter from you soon. May I hope? — I use your envelope, dear Ferdinand, because my paper is parchment. — Adieu.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
