<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Honorable The Chief Secretary. ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ We have the honor to solicit the assistance and co-operation of the Government of Victoria, in the contemplated exploration of the interior of Australia ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1859/59-09-22-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>L59/9758, unit 757, VPRS 1189 inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>59.09.22</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>The Honorable The Chief Secretary. ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ We have the honor to solicit the assistance and co-operation of the Government of Victoria, in the contemplated exploration of the interior of Australia ...</title>
               <date when="1859-09-22">1859-09-22</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1859/59-09-22-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>John O'Shanassy</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">The Honorable The Chief Secretary. ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶ We have the honor to solicit the assistance and co-operation of the Government of Victoria, in the contemplated exploration of the interior of Australia ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">59.09.22</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To John O'Shanassy</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">L59/9758, unit 757, VPRS 1189 inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Honorable The Chief Secretary.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We have the honor to solicit the assistance and co-operation of the Government of Victoria, in the contemplated exploration of the interior of Australia by a party fitted out in, and maintained by this Colony.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We respectfully submit that although much has been done to advance our Geographical knowledge of Australia a vast field is still left open for the exertions and enterprize of future explorers.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In our desire to provide such means and to devise such plans as will enable the Victorian Exploring party to remain two years at least, and if possible three years in the field, we entertain the hope that the great object of traversing the unknown interior in its <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">widest-distances</hi>
               </seg>, will be accomplished without any unnecessary hazard or peril to human life.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A great stimulus, as you are aware, has been given in Victoria to the cause of exploration, by the munificent offer by an unknown donor of £1000 for exploration purposes, on the condition that £2000 should be raised by private subscription within twelve months.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We are happy to be in the position to inform you that all classes throughout the Colony have warmly responded to this noble offer, and that, having thus become entitled to this gift of £1000, we have now at command a sum exceeding £3700 —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We are aware that the present Government obtained a vote of £3000, last session of Parliament, for the introduction of Camels, and that it is their intention that these should be available for the exploration of the interior; but, to render the services of the camels really valuable, and to carry out our proposed plan of exploration, it will be necessary that a large Depôt be formed at Cooper's Creek, recently ascertained by Mr Augustus Gregory to be the continuation of the Victoria River of Sir Thomas Mitchell.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The establishment and maintenance of this Depôt, upon which the success of all our efforts must essentially depend, will necessitate a very considerable outlay.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The funds in hand from private sources might, indeed, be sufficient to equip a small party, for a few months labour in the field, but the result could not be otherwise than unsatisfactory. And we respectfully urge that an unsuccessful result would not only be a source of great public disappointment, but would be altogether unworthy of the commercial wealth, energy, and public spirit, of Victoria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Having been in communication with men of wealth and intelligence in all parts of the Colony, we are warranted in stating that the public generally heartily concur in the contemplated exploration, while, at the same time, they are of opinion that the great national importance of the cause demands national funds for its execution, and that it would be vain to expect any efficient result, or any large success, from private resources alone.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We deem it unnecessary to submit a detailed statement of the probable expenditure required. The whole arrangements of the scheme will altogether depend upon the amount of assistance that may be obtained from Parliament, but we believe that the sum of £6000, in addition to the amount already raised from private sources, will be sufficient to carry out the objects we have in view, and to maintain the exploring party in a state of efficiency for a period of at least two years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Assuming that £6000 will be voted by Parliament, the whole party would probably consist of twelve men, six to guard the Depôt, and six to be employed in the field. The salaries of the officers and men would amount to about £4,400 for two years. Purchase of twenty four horses, outfit for the party including stores and transport for one year, may be estimated at £3,600. Additional stores and transport for second year £1,500. Total, £9,500 —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As we believe that the Government are fully alive to the practical advantages likely to arise from our extending our knowledge of the interior, and by opening it up for the progress of civilization — advantages in which assuredly Victoria must largely share from its central position — we consider it unnecessary to press upon your attention all those commercial and scientific considerations which we believe fully warrant us, on public grounds, to solicit the cooperation of the Government, and the support of Parliament.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We beg, therefore, most respectfully to request that you will be pleased to place the sum of £6000 on the estimates for 1860, in aid of the exploration of Central Australia, and thereby to supplement the sum of £3,700 raised by private subscription for the same object.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">We have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your most obedient servants</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>John Hodgson M.L.C.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>John Macadam M.D., M.L.A.,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>David E. Wilkie M.D. M.L.C.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">22nd September 1859<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">O'Shanassy minuted on 22 September: 'Report for the use of Parliament when the Estimate on Exploration is under consideration.' The letter was copied for the Legislative Assembly on 17 October 1859. Another handwritten copy, dated 4 July 1861 and prepared as a supporting document for a deputation from the Royal Society of Victoria’s Exploration Committee that was to see the then Chief Secretary, Richard Heales, the next day, is at MS 13071 Royal Society of Victoria Exploration Committee records, box 2088B/5, pp. 53-5, La Trobe Australian Manuscripts Collection, State Library of Victoria, Melbourne.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
