<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[I permitted myself in the expectation of the granting of my request to also enclose  ¶  ¶ a quantity of insect pins. Dr. C. von Felder.]...</title>
            <author>Karl Scherzer</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1859/59-12-18-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>59.12.18</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Karl Scherzer</author>
               <title>[I permitted myself in the expectation of the granting of my request to also enclose  ¶  ¶ a quantity of insect pins. Dr. C. von Felder.]...</title>
               <date when="1859-12-18">1859-12-18</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1859/59-12-18-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
               <term>Times, Times</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>form text</term>
               <term>Internet link</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="16">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="84">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[I permitted myself in the expectation of the granting of my request to also enclose  ¶  ¶ a quantity of insect pins. Dr. C. von Felder.]...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">59.12.18</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Karl Scherzer</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS is a printed letter with 'Novara-Expedition.' printed on the front. The letter has been signed by Scherzer. The postscript is a handwritten inscription beneath the signature.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS found inserted in a copy of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Victoria Votes and Proceedings of the Legislative Council, Session 1850, Bills</seg>.</p>
               </note>
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times, Times; ">
                  <seg style="color: #000000; ">Trieste, December 18th, 1859.</seg>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Sir</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have great pleasure in informing You that the Imperial Austrian Expedition of Circumnavigation of which I enjoyed the honour to be a member, has safely arrived home in August last, after having visited during the whole cruise 21 different places, viz: Gibraltar, Madeira, Rio Janeiro, Cape of Good Hope, St Paul and Amsterdam, Ceylon, Madras, Nicobar islands, Singapore, Batavia, Manila, Hongkong, Canton, Macao, Shanghae, Pouynipet (Caroline islands), Stewart islands, Sydney, Auckland (New Zealand), Society islands and Chile.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The serious political state of affairs in Europe, which we learned only at our arrival in Valparaiso,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Chile.</p>
               </note> decided the Commander in Chief of the Imperial Expedition, Commodore B. de <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Wuellerstorf</seg>, to give up all further projects of exploration and to return direct to Europe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This resolution, although caused by the noble and anxious desire to be present and ready when the threatened country should want to call him and those entrusted to his leadership to another field of activity, — yet could not fail to produce, especially amongst the naturalists on board, some disappointments, for it destroyed all our hopes with respect to the continuation of our most interesting cruise.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In this sad disposition I applied to Commodore <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Wuellerstorf,</seg> that I might be permitted to return home with one of the Royal Mail Steamers by the way of the Isthmus of Panama, under the condition to wait at Gibraltar for the arrival of the frigate Novara, who sailed on the 11th of May direct for the straits round Cape Horn.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>This request was granted to me with that kindness and obligingness which the members of the scientific commission were witnessing during the whole cruise from the part of the Commander in Chief of the Expedition, and afforded me the most favourable opportunity to see a great number of interesting places along the West-Coast of South America, between Valparaiso and Panama, to spend more than a fortnight at Lima and to be moreover able to render yet some services to science, while the Novara herself was already under sail on her way home.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At Gibraltar I met again the frigate and returned on board of her to Trieste, where we all safely arrived on the 26th of August a. c.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>this year.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The whole cruise lasted 849 days, out of which 551 days have been spent at sea and 298 days on shore. The number of miles sailed during this period amounts to 60,914 english miles. Our different collections of objects of natural history, embracing all three kingdoms of nature, are considerable; they fill more than a hundred large cases and are now about to be prepared, arranged and exhibited in the "Augarten", one of the former Imperial summer-residences at Vienna.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Commodore <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Wuellerstorf</seg>, as well as the different members of the scientific commission on board the Imperial frigate, are now busily engaged in publishing the rich literary material, which they have gathered with the kind assistance of their learned friends in the different parts of the globe they visited, and they are most generously supported in their endeavour by the Imperial government and H. I. R. Highness the Archduke <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Ferdinand Maxmillian</seg>, under whose noble auspices the Expedition was undertaken.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The nautical, astronomical, meteorological and magnetical observations and results, in fact everything relative to the physical geography of the sea, shall be published by Commodore <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Wuellerstorf</seg> himself or under his auspices.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With regard to the different branches of natural history, the zoological part shall be published by Messrs <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Frauenfeld </seg>and<seg style="font-variant: small-caps; "> Zelebor</seg>, the geological part by Dr. <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Hochstetter,</seg> the botanical and medical part by Dr. <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Schwarz.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My own department embraces ethnography and political economy; in short, man, in all his relations to the external world. I have been moreover entrusted with the publication of the descriptive part of our cruise, compiled from the extensive Journals of the Commodore and my own. This book, written in a popular style and intended for a large circulation will be illustrated with several hundred drawings selected from more that two thousand sketches of the album of our artist, and is intended to be translated into different languages.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is the wish of H. I. R. Highness the Archduke <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Ferdinand Maxmillian</seg> that all those gentlemen in the different parts of the world, who have so heartily received the Novara-Expedition, and by their amiable concurrence have so much contributed to its success, shall be presented with copies of the popular work as well as of the scientific one, which latter shall be published in separate volumes, and most probably completed in the course of three or four years.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Scherzer (1861-2), published in English as Scherzer (1861-3), <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is the popular account; a technical report was published under the series title<seg style="font-style: italic; "> Reise der österreichischen Fregatte Novara um die Erde in den Jahren 1857, 1858, 1859 unter den Befehlen des Commodore B. von Wülerstorf-Ubair</seg>, see (<ref target="https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.1597"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0000ff; ">
                        <seg style="color: #0000ff; ">
                           <hi rend="underline">https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.1597</hi>
                        </seg>
                     </ref>) with specialist reports under the authorship of individual writers or volume editors, including those mentioned above. Schwarz, mentioned above, published the medical volume, part 6 of the series, but did not publish on the botany, although a cryptogamic botanical volume was edited by Fenzl and appeared in 1870 as part 3. M's copies of these works, if he acquired them, are no longer in the library of the Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By the above communications You will perceive that my task is a most difficult and complicated one, and for this reason will be surely kind enough to excuse, when I request You to assist me in the different publications which I am about to prepare, by furnishing me as soon as possible with a short account of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">most recent events of importance</seg> at your place, together with the newest statistical tables, comprising population, productions, commercial movement, exports, imports, etc. etc. etc.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The surest way for any letter, package, or parcel to reach me is to direct it to the care of the Imperial Austrian Admiralty at Trieste, which will also be so kind to advance for me all the expenses that may have occurred by the shipping and forwarding.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In conclusion, I can only repeat that I shall always feel most happy to be in any way of some service to You in this part of the world, and expecting to hear soon from You, I beg to believe me with true esteem,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">your most grateful</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dr Karl Scherzer</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich erlaubte mir in Erhoffung der Gewährung meiner Bitte auch eine Quantität Insectnadeln beizuschliessen. Dr C. v Felder </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">[I permitted myself in the expectation of the granting of my request to also enclose <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>a quantity of insect pins. Dr. C. von Felder.]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
