<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>4.8.1880 ¶ Dear Mr De Candolle. ¶  ¶ I must express my thanks for your attention in sending me your "Phytography"; ¶  another volume you have added to the important publications that have made your na...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-08-04-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Bibliothèque des Conservatoire et Jardin botaniques, Geneva.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>80.08.04</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>4.8.1880 ¶ Dear Mr De Candolle. ¶  ¶ I must express my thanks for your attention in sending me your "Phytography"; ¶  another volume you have added to the important publications that have made your na...</title>
               <date when="1880-08-04">1880-08-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-08-04-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Monocotyledoneae</term>
               <term>Dicotyledoneae</term>
               <term>Acotyledoneae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>table</term>
               <term>note</term>
               <term>multi-row cell</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="56">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="44">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Alphonse de Candolle</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">4.8.1880 ¶ Dear Mr De Candolle. ¶  ¶ I must express my thanks for your attention in sending me your "Phytography"; ¶  another volume you have added to the important publications that have made your na...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">80.08.04</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Alphonse de Candolle</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Bibliothèque des Conservatoire et Jardin botaniques, Geneva.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">4/8/80</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Cher M. De Candolle.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Il est de mon devoir d'exprimer mes remerciments pour l'attention, que vous avez eue en m'envoyant votre "Phytographie"; ce qui est un autre volume, que vous avez ajouté aux importantes publications, qui ont rendu votre nom illustre. La raison pour laquelle dans les "native plants" j'ai donné les nomes des auteurs et leur oeuvres en les citant complétement c'est parce que ce livre est principalement fait pour les écoles de Victoria, ou les précepteurs ne comprendraient pas les abreviations de ce genre.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dans l'allusion, que vous faites à la "Flora Australiensis" je vois, que ma collaboration est entièrement ignorée. Vous devez donc penser, que j'ai eu une part insignifiante dans l'élaboration, et je m'en contenterais, si j'etais un individu privé. Mais comme mes moyens propres ainsi que ceux de mon Departement furent devoués a cet objet, il serait très injuste pour le Gouvernement de Victoria, si je consentais a ce, qu'on crut, que la Flora Australiensis (melius Australiana) fut l'ouvrage de M. Bentham seulement. Cet homme illustre écrivit tout le texte, mais <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">deux-tiers</hi>
               </seg> du material (echantillons preéxaminées) furent fournis par moi même. Mes collections Australiennes sont deux ou trois fois plus grandes, que celles de Kew. J'ai envoyé de 1862-1877 à Kew comme un emprunt mon herbier normal d'environs 70 grandes caisses, remplies de 90,000 échantillons complétement arrangées, qui par moi même priorément ont été examines, et que j'ai recuillis depuis 1847 avec l'aide d'amis et d'hommes payés; pour obtenir ces collections j'ai voyagé à cheval et à pied 28,000 milles anglaises! Enfin 30,000 échantillons ont été procurés et graduellement ajoutés par moi, depuis que les volumes de la Flora Australiensis parurent successivement, ce qui fait, qu'environ 650 espèces ont été ajoutés dans les "fragmenta", parmi lesquelles etaient plusieurs genres et quelques orders naturels. M. Dyer dans son recent discours à l'Institut colonial a reconnu ma part dans l'ouvrage.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dans votre liste des grands herbiers je vois, que celui de Melbourne n'y est pas. Il est le plus grand dans l'hémisphère australe (et pour l'Australie largement unique?), contenant des plantes de toutes les parties du globe, lesquelles j'ai obtenues moi même depuis 1840 ou en faisant des achats et des échanges. Je calcule, que le nombre d'échantillons (qui ne sont pas doubles) sont environ 300,000, desquels il y en a 120,000 Australiens et 180,000 extra-australiens. Il n'est pas facile de déterminer, combien d'espèces cette vaste collection contient réellement. Le nombre des espèces australiennes et<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">est.</p>
               </note> d'environ 10,500, i.e.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <table n="Table1">
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <name key="Dicotyledoneae">Dicotyledoneae</name>
                     </p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">7000</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; "
                        rows="3">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 36pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">}</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; "
                        rows="3">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">considerées très-conservativement.</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <name key="Monocotyledoneae">Monocotyledoneae</name>
                     </p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">1600</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <name key="Acotyledoneae">Acotyledoneae</name>
                     </p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <p rend="letter"
                        style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">1900</p>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Les Algae (par example) ont été augmentées dejà depuis Harvey de 600 à environ 800 principalement par Sonder d'après mes contributions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>La collection privé, que J. Drummond avait faite pour lui même, passa après sa mort en ma possession. On peut voir dans les "fragmenta", que les trois quarts des collecteurs botaniques de l'Australie ont envoyé leur "specimens" a moi, quoique j'ai permis successivement, qu'on en garda les duplicates à Kew. J'ai aussi reçu de Sir Jos. Hooker de nombreux exemplaires de R. Brown et A. Cunningham, et j'ai obtenu une collection complète du Dr Milligan, ainsi que beaucoup des plantes de Sieber, la plupart de celles de Preiss et toutes celles de Leichhardt. Dans mon Muséum les plantes de Australie, celles de Nouvelle Zélande et celles de la Polynésie sont apart; mais toutes les autres ont été inserées et arrangées (selon le système Candolleen) pour former une seule collection compacte. Mon Museum contient des plantes de Areschoug (Scandinavia et Algae), Aucher-Eloy, Ayres (Mauritius), Sir H. Barkly (Jamaique &amp; Essequibo), Beccari (Sumatra), Boivin (Réunion), Bourgeau, Chickering (Amerique du Nord), Cosson, Cuming (Philippines), Durieu (Algerie), D'Albertis (Nouvelle Guinée), Eaton (Amerique boreale), Traill-Green (N. Amer.), Ecklon (toute sa collection d'Allemagne, ainsi que la plupart de cette du Sud de l'Afrique), Falconer (Indes), Fortune (Chine), Franqueville, Glaziou (par Hooker), Griffith (Indes), Hance (Hong-Kong &amp; Chine), Haast (Nouvelle Zélande), Hauck (Algues) Harvey (Algues), Van Heurck, Heer (Suisse), Hillebrand (Filices de Hawaia), Hohenacker, Hooker (collections diverses et extensives), Hooker &amp; Thomson (Indes), Hepp (lichenes), Kurz (grand collection Indienne), Kotschy, Labrador (Latrobe)<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Labrador (Latrobe) <seg style="font-style: italic; ">interlined above</seg> Lehmann (Melastomées &amp;c.).</p>
               </note> Lehmann (Melastomées &amp;c.), Lénormand (Algues), Leighton (LIchenes) Lindheimer (Texas par Asa Gray), Maillard, Meller (Madagascar), Lindberg (Musci), MacOwen, M'Ken (Natal), Stuart-Mill (Grande Bretagne, seulement trois collections, une des quelles m'a été donnée par sa niéce suadente Hookero), Miquel (Inde Hollandaise), Nonneprediger (Brezil), Moritzi (Venezuela), J. Mueller (Lichenes), Pancher (Nouvelle Caledonie), Parlatore (Italie), Parry (Amerique du Nord), Philippi (Chili), Regel (Russie), Riedel (Brezil par Regel), Rochel (Banat), Sartwell (Amerique boreale), Samson (Chine), Salzmann (Bahia), Scheffer (Myrsinées, Palmae &amp;c.), Shuttleworth, Schimper (Abyssinie, par Hochstetter), Short (Amerique du Nord), Sonder (particulierement une très-grande collection des Monocotylédones), Steetz (toute sa très-grande collection privée), Thuemen (Fungi), Teyesman (Java &amp;c.), Thwaites (Ceylon), Todaro (Sicilie), Travers (Nouvelle Zeelande et l'isles de Chatham), Vieillard (Nouvelle Caledonie par Lénormand), Wallich, Welwitsch (ouest de l'Afrique par le Comte Ficalho), Wight (Indes), Zeyher (Afrique australe), &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Je pourrais ajouter plusieurs autres nomes de Botanistes et de Collecteurs, mais ce que je dis peut suffire a vous montrer, que mon herbier est extensif. En effet, je calcule, que mon Musée contient 40000 espèces <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">bien-fondées</hi>
               </seg>, sans compter celles de l'Australie, de la Nouvelle Zelande et de l'Oceanie. Comme vous savez la plus grande partie des plantes Australiennes est endemique. Cela donne un grand total de 50000 espèces approximativement.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vous aurez peut être l'occasion d'utilizer ceci avec d'autre notes pour une contribution pour quelque supplement à votre precieuse "phytographie", ou bien vous pourriez le trouver d'un interêt suffisant pour le publier dans un des nombreux journeaux, qui sont a votre disposition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Avec tous les égards et respects je reste votre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. de Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">4.8.1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Mr De Candolle.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I must express my thanks for your attention in sending me your "Phytography";<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A. de Candolle (1880).</p>
               </note> another volume you have added to the important publications that have made your name famous. The reason why I have, in the "Native Plants",<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.06.04.</p>
               </note> given the names of authors and their works with full citations is that this book is principally intended for the schools of Victoria, where the teachers would not understand abbreviations of this kind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I see that in your allusion to the "Flora Australiensis", my collaboration is completely ignored. You therefore must think that I had an insignificant part in its preparation, and I should be content with that, if I were a private individual. But as both my own means and those of my Department were devoted to this work, it would be most unjust to the Government of Victoria, were I to allow it to be believed that the Flora Australiensis (better Australiana) was the work of Mr Bentham alone. This illustrious man wrote all the text, but <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">two-thirds</hi>
               </seg> of the material (pre-examined specimens) were furnished by me. My Australian collections are two or three times larger than those of Kew. From 1862 to 1877 I sent to Kew on loan my standard herbarium of about 70 large crates, filled with 90,000 completely arranged specimens previously examined by me, which I have gathered since 1847 with the help of friends and paid men; to obtain these collections I travelled on horseback and on foot 28,000 English miles!<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Eduard Regel in his review of de Candolle’s book (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora</seg>, vol. 32, 1883, pp. 93-4) similarly criticized de Candolle for treating <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora australiensis</seg> as Bentham’s work alone; and when de Candolle wrote complaining of this, Regel responded by reiterating at greater length and in more detail his view that to portray M as just another collector who had contributed to the work, as de Candolle had done, did M a great injustice (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora</seg>, vol. 33, 1884, pp. 62-3).</p>
               </note> Finally, 30,000 specimens have been procured and gradually added by me since the volumes of the Flora Australiensis successively appeared, which means that about 650 species have been added in the "Fragmenta", among them several genera and some natural orders. Mr Dyer in his recent speech at the Colonial Institute recognized my part in the work.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Thiselton-Dyer (1880); M had seen the version published as Thiselton-Dyer (1880b) and commented upon it in M to W. Thiselton-Dyer, 7 July 1880.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In your list of large herbaria, I see that Melbourne's is not included. It is the biggest in the southern hemisphere (and largely unique for Australia?), containing plants from all parts of the globe that I have obtained since 1840 myself or through purchases or exchanges. I calculate that the number of specimens (which are not duplicates) is about 300,000, of which 120,000 are Australian and 180,000 extra-Australian. It is not easy to determine how many species this vast collection really contains. The number of Australian species [is] about 10,500, i.e.</p>
            <table n="Table2">
               <row>
                  <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                     <table n="Table3">
                        <row>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">
                                 <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                                 <name key="Dicotyledoneae">Dicotyledoneae</name>
                              </p>
                           </cell>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">7000</p>
                           </cell>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; "
                                 rows="3">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 36pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">}</p>
                           </cell>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; "
                                 rows="3">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">
                                 <seg style="">
                                    <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                                 </seg>considered very conservatively.</p>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">
                                 <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                                 <name key="Monocotyledoneae">Monocotyledoneae</name>
                              </p>
                           </cell>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">1600</p>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">
                                 <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                                 <name key="Acotyledoneae">Acotyledoneae</name>
                              </p>
                           </cell>
                           <cell style="padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; padding-left: 0.075in; padding-right: 0.075in; padding-top: 0in; padding-bottom: 0in; border: none; ">
                              <p rend="letter"
                                 style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
                                 xml:lang="en">1900</p>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The Algae (for example) have already been increased since Harvey<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Harvey (1858-63).</p>
               </note> from 600 to about 800 principally by Sonder from my contributions.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The private collection that Drummond made for himself passed after his death into my possession. One can see in the "Fragmenta" that three-quarters of the botanical collectors of Australia have sent their "specimens" to me, though I have successively allowed the duplicates to be kept at Kew. I received from Sir Jos. Hooker numerous specimens of R. Brown and A. Cunningham,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The Robert Brown (1773-1858) specimens were almost certainly duplicates extracted from the portion of Brown's herbarium that Kew received in 1876 as a bequest from J. J. Bennett, to whom Brown had left his collection. Allan Cunningham bequeathed his private herbarium to Robert Heward who presented it to Kew in 1862, and it is possible that the Cunningham specimens that M received from <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Hooker were duplicates extracted from this collection.</p>
               </note> and I obtained a complete collection from Dr Milligan, likewise many of Sieber's plants, the majority of Preiss's, and all Leichhardt's. In my Museum the plants of Australia, those of New Zealand and those of Polynesia are apart; but all the rest have been inserted and arranged (according to the Candollean system) to form a single compact collection. My Museum contains the plants of Areschoug (Scandinavia and Algae), Aucher-Eloy, Ayres (Mauritius), Sir H. Barkly (Jamaica &amp; Essequibo), Beccari (Sumatra), Boivin (Réunion), Bourgeau, Chickering (North America), Cosson, Cuming (Philippines), Durieu (Algeria), D'Albertis (New Guinea), Eaton (north America), Traill-Green (N. Amer.), Ecklon (his whole German collection, along with most of that of South Africa), Falconer (India), Fortune (China), Franqueville, Glaziou (through Hooker), Griffith (India), Hance (Hong-Kong &amp; China), Haast (New Zealand), Hauck (Algae), Harvey (Algae), Van Heurck, Heer (Switzerland), Hillebrand (filices of Hawaii), Hohenacker, Hooker (diverse and extensive collections), Hooker &amp; Thomson (India), Hepp (lichens), Kurz (large Indian collection), Kotschy, Labrador (Latrobe)<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">M presumably meant</seg> Latrobe (Labrador). The Moravian minister Peter La Trobe, brother of Victoria's Lieutenant-Governor, C. J. La Trobe, had access to the 'beautiful collection of the plants' that had been brought together by the Moravian missionary B. G. Kohlmeister during the many years that he lived in Labrador; see W. Hooker (1840), vol. 1, p. 194. Perhaps M somehow acquired part, at least, of this collection?</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0.1598in; "
                     xml:lang="en">As in this case and in those of J. S. Mill and Miquel, and almost certainly in the case of the Hookers and others, the parenthetical name after the description of the collection does not necessarily denote the field collector, but may denote the cabinet collector through whose collections the specimens reached M. For a general discussion of the ambiguity inherent in such references, see Lucas &amp; Lucas (2014).</p>
               </note> Lehmann (Melastomeae &amp;c.), Lénormand (Algae), Leighton (Lichens), Lindheimer (Texas through Asa Gray), Maillard, Meller (Madagascar), Lindberg (Musci), MacOwen,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">P. MacOwan.</p>
               </note> M'Ken (Natal), Stuart-Mill<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. J. S. Mill. See M to H. Taylor, 23 September 1876 (in this edition as 76-09-23d).</p>
               </note> (Great Britain, only three collections, one of which was given to me by his niece by Hooker persuaded), Miquel (Dutch Indies), Nonneprediger (Brazil), Moritzi (Venezuela), J. Mueller (Lichens), Pancher (New Caledonia), Parlatore (Italy), Parry (North America), Philippi (Chile), Regel (Russia), Riedel (Brazil through Regel), Rochel (Banat), Sartwell (north America), Samson (China), Salzmann (Bahia), Scheffer (Myrsinaceae, Palmae &amp;c.), Shuttleworth, Schimper (Abyssinia, through Hochstetter), Short (North America), Sonder (particularly a very large collection of Monocotyledons), Steetz (the whole of his very large private collection), Thuemen (Fungi), Teyesman<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. E. Teijsmann.</p>
               </note> (Java &amp;c.), Thwaites (Ceylon), Todaro (Sicily), Travers (New Zealand and the Chatham Islands), Vieillard (New Caledonia through Lenormand), Wallich, Welwitsch (west Africa through Count Ficalho), Wight (India), Zeyher (south Africa), &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I could add several other names of Botanists and Collectors, but what I say can suffice to show you that my herbarium is extensive. Indeed, I calculate that my Museum contains 40,000 <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">well-founded</hi>
               </seg> species, without counting those of Australia, New Zealand and Oceania. As you know, the greatest part of the Australian plants is endemic. That gives a grand total of 50,000 species approximately.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Perhaps you will have occasion to use this with other notes for a contribution for some supplement to your valuable "phytography", or you could even find it of sufficient interest to publish it in one of the numerous journals that are at your disposal.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With all regards and respect, I remain yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Acotyledoneae">Acotyledoneae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dicotyledoneae">Dicotyledoneae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Monocotyledoneae">Monocotyledoneae</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
