<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queensland Laboratory ¶ Brisbane 29th January 1880 ¶ Esteemed Baron ¶  ¶ In reference to your esteemed letter of 18 January 1880 ¶  I have to mention together with New Year good wishes that the name B...</title>
            <author>Karl Staiger</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-01-29-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>80.01.29</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Karl Staiger</author>
               <title>Queensland Laboratory ¶ Brisbane 29th January 1880 ¶ Esteemed Baron ¶  ¶ In reference to your esteemed letter of 18 January 1880 ¶  I have to mention together with New Year good wishes that the name B...</title>
               <date when="1880-01-29">1880-01-29</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-01-29-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
               <term>Times</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>form text</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Queensland Laboratory ¶ Brisbane 29th January 1880 ¶ Esteemed Baron ¶  ¶ In reference to your esteemed letter of 18 January 1880 ¶  I have to mention together with New Year good wishes that the name B...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">80.01.29</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Karl Staiger</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times; ">Queensland</seg> Laboratory<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Laboratory <seg style="font-style: italic; ">written</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">over printed</seg> Museum <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted.</seg>
                     <seg style=""> Karl Staiger is identified as correspondent since he was of German origin and was Queensland's Government Analytical Chemist at this time.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg rend="form%20text" style="color: #2f5496; font-family: Times; ">
                  <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Brisbane </seg>
               </seg>29th Januar 1880<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">All Communications to be Addressed to the Secretary of the Board of Trustees. All Parcels to be addressed to the Curator <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is printed at the head of MS and crossed out.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Werther Herr Baron.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Beziehung von Ihrem Werthen 18/1 80. habe ich nebst Neujahrs Glück-wünschen zu erwähnen dass der Name Barramunda blos zu dem Fisch Osteoglossum Leichardti gehört. Dieser Fisch ist blos im Dawson River zu finden u. wurde von Leichhardt entdeckt. Der Fisch selbst ist wunderhübsch. <seg style="">Grau am Rücken weiss am Bauch u. Seiten mit Carmin gefärbten ½" grossen Tupfen u. diese haben in ihrem Zentrum einen schwarzen Flecken. </seg>Er ist etwa 18"-24" lang hat grosse Schuppen u. ist ausgezeichnet zu essen. Er wird mit Fliegen gefangen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der zweite sogenannte Barramunda wird in Rockhampton gefangen, wo er das Hauptnahrungsmittel der Krokodile ausmacht, wie ich bei eigner Erfahrung weiss. Grosse Fische, etwa 80 lb schwer sind nicht essbar, weil zu strohig. Allein Fische von 3"-8" sind wirklich ausgezeichnet. Der Fisch, grau am Rücken u. Weiss an den Seiten, nicht sehr ausgezeichnet für Schönheit. Er bildet den Hauptfisch für Rockhampton. Allein manchmal finden die Fischerleute die Fische u. das Netz dazu im Magen von einem Krokodil. Der Fisch hat ein Habitat das sich von Kalkutta bis nach Rockhampton erstreckt u. an allen Flussmündungen gefunden wird, so lange es zwischen den Wendekreisen ist. Südlicher von Rockhampton wird er niemals gefunden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Genus nahme ist Labrax (Seebarsch) also ein Perca (Barsch).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der dritte, sogenannte Barramunda ist Ceratodus u. wird blos im Mary u. Burnett River gefunden. Sein Fleisch ist wie das von dem Salmon, röthlich, deshalb ist er mehr als Burnett Salmon bekannt, trotzdem dass er nicht ein Fisch ist u. blos das unterste Glied der Reptilien ausmacht. Er wird mit Angeln gefangen, da Netze wegen versunkenen Baumstämmen unbrauchbar sind. Der Fisch ist nichts für einen Fischer da er sehr faul ist u. kaum ein Gefühl für eine Angel hat. Er muss deshalb mit Gewalt emporgezogen werden, er wehrt sich nicht u. es ist gerade als wie wenn man ein Stück Stein heraufziehen würde. Wenn nicht zu gross ist er ausgezeichnet zu essen, u. ich habe ihn längst, ehe Krefft ihn benannte, als Salmon gegessen, ohne zu wissen woher er kam u. somit einen Fisch der ein ganz neues Genus ist allein man scheert sich mehr für Essen als was […] man weit im Innern ist.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Text ends at bottom of page, without valediction; there may have been additional text that is now missing.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Queensland Laboratory</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Brisbane 29th January 1880</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Baron</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reference to your esteemed letter of 18 January 1880<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found; but see M to F. von Krauss, 18 January 1880.</p>
               </note> I have to mention together with New Year good wishes that the name Barramunda<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Barramundi.</p>
               </note> only belongs to the fish <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Osteoglossum leichhardti</seg>. This fish is only found in the Dawson River and was discovered by Leichhardt. The fish itself is wonderfully pretty. Grey on the back, white on the stomach and sides with carmine coloured ½ inch sized spots and these have a black blotch in the their center. It is about 18"– 24" long has large scales and is excellent to eat. It is caught with flies.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The second so-called Barramunda is caught in Rockhampton, where it makes up the principle food of the crocodile, as I know from my own experience. Large fishes, about 80 lb weight are not edible, because too tough. But fishes from 3"–8" are really excellent. The fish, grey on the back and white on the sides, not very excellent for beauty. It forms the main fish for Rockhampton. But sometimes the fishermen find the fish and the net for it in the stomach of a crocodile. The fish has a habitat that extends from Calcutta to Rockhampton and is found at all river mouths, as long as they are between the Tropics. It is never found southwards from Rockhampton. The generic name is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Labrax</seg> (Sea Barsch<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Sea bass or Sea perch.</p>
               </note>) therefore a Perch (Barsch).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The third so-called Barramunda is <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Ceratodus</seg> and is only found in the Mary and Burnett Rivers. Its flesh is like that of the salmon, pinkish, therefore it is more known as the Burnett Salmon, notwithstanding that it is not a fish and makes up merely the lowest member of the reptiles. It is caught by angling, because nets are unusable on account of sunken tree trunks. The fish is nothing for a fisherman because it is very lazy and scarcely has a feeling for a hook. Therefore it must be pulled out with force, it does not put up a fight and it is just as if one was pulling up a stone. If not too large it is excellent to eat and I have eaten it as salmon long ago, before Krefft named it, without knowing from where it came and therefore a fish that is a new genus but one cares more for eating than what is […] far in the interior.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
