<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>7/7/80. ¶  ¶ I felt very honoured, noble sir, to receive your kind letter ¶  and so to enter into direct communication with a highly celebrated contemporary and what is more that you write completely ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-07-07c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RA 14.6, Heimatmuseum Schloss Schönebeck, Vegesack, Bremen.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>80.07.07c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>7/7/80. ¶  ¶ I felt very honoured, noble sir, to receive your kind letter ¶  and so to enter into direct communication with a highly celebrated contemporary and what is more that you write completely ...</title>
               <date when="1880-07-07">1880-07-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-07-07c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>hyperlink</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>Internet link</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Gerhard Rohlfs</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">7/7/80. ¶  ¶ I felt very honoured, noble sir, to receive your kind letter ¶  and so to enter into direct communication with a highly celebrated contemporary and what is more that you write completely ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">80.07.07c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Gerhard Rohlfs</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RA 14.6, Heimatmuseum Schloss Schönebeck, Vegesack, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Bremen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">7/7/80.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Recht geehrt fühle ich mich, edler Herr, Ihre gütige Zuschrift zu erhalten, und so mit einem hochberühmten Zeitgenossen in directe Verbindung zu treten; und dazu kommt noch, dass Sie ganz in meinem Interesse schreiben, und mich in Meyer's Conversations-Lexicon ehren wollen. Ich habe eben erfahren, dass eine biographische Notiz im Supplement zu diesem Werke, mich betreffend, bereits erschienen ist. Da aber das Werk mir eben nicht zur Hand ist, u Sie vielleicht für die neue Ausgabe einige Worte mehr über mein Wirken mitzutheilen wünschen, so nehme ich mir die Freiheit, ihnen einen Abdruck einer Lebensskizze von mir, die Herr J. Arn. Knapp gütig entwarf, Ihnen hiermit zuzusenden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um diesen Abriss meiner wissenschaftlichen Lebens-Ereignisse vollständig to machen, sende ich Ihnen einige Notizen über mein Wirken während der letzten drei Jahre.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Den Marquis u die Marquisin de Toverena besuche ich von Zeit zu Zeit; es sind ausgezeichnete Verehrer von Ihnen, gerade wie Sie verdienen solche in hohen Stellungen ganz besonders zu haben. Die arme Marquisin ist recht leidend, nicht nur durch Brustbeschwerden (chronischen Bronchial-Catarrh) sondern auch durch die Trübsal, das einzige u so hochbegabte Kind verloren zu haben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe die Aufschriften der Briefe gesehen, welche Sie durch den Marquis an australische Geographen befördern lassen; ich erinnere nicht, dass eine bedeutende Persönlichkeit von Ihnen übersehen ist. Wenn ich Ihnen noch anderweitig zu irgend einer Zeit nützen kann, so bitte ich Sie, über meine Dienste unzögernd zu gebieten.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit Ehrerbietung</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich sende den 10 Band der "fragmenta", da auf den Titelblatte alle mir bis 1877 erwiesene Auszeichnungen notirt sind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Im Jahre 1877 bereiste ich Westaustralien, ritt von Champion Bay zur Shark Bay, dann zu den übern Gewässern des Irwin u Greenough Flusses, später reiste ich durch verschiedene Theile des Darling-Range, dann mit Abwagen zur Geographe-Bay u überland zu King George Sound. Der Zweck dieser 1500 Meilen langen Reisen war, die Verbreitung der südlichen Pflanzen West Australiens nordwärts kennen zu lernen, und auf besonderen Wunsch der Regierung dort einen Rapport über die südlichen Forsten des Colonial-Territoriums zu liefern. Letzterer erschien in England im vorigen Jahre "Forest Resources of Western Australia" mit 20 Quart-Platten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An dieses Werk schliesst sich mein "Descriptive Atlas of the Eucalypts" an, von welchem die 7tn Decade fast beendet ist. Diese Monographie der in vielfacher Beziehung wichtigsten Baum-Gattung der Erde wird etwa 120 Arten bildlich umfassen, da ich eine Anzahl weniger wichtigen Species nur im Text berühren werde. S. Königl Hoheit, der Prinz von Wales, hat es mir gnädig erlaubt, ihm das Werk zuzueignen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Der 11te Band der fragmenta ist ziemlich weit vorgeschritten, der 1ste Theil des "Native plants of Victoria", in dem ich das System von De Candolle selbstständig in einigen Stücken änderte, wurde auch schon vor 2 Jahren beendigt, und ich bin nur durch die Anfertigung der zahlreichen Holzschnitte gehindert, die beiden andern Theile zu Tage zu fördern. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die 2te Decade der "Vegetable fossils" ist fast vollendet, drei Abhandlungen über die Pflanzen Nord-West Australiens aus de<seg style="">n Sammlungen der Reisende John &amp; Alex Forrest sind ausgearbeitet. Über die Pflanzen von Giles's 3ter u 4ter Central-australischen Reise habe ich im Trimen's Journal of Botany berichtet. Von Wittsteins "Analyse von Pflanzentheilen auf ihre organischen Bestandtheile" habe ich eine engl. Übersetzung geliefert mit vielen Supplemental-Notizen von mir selbst. </seg>Von meinem Werke "select plants for industrial culture" ist in Calcutta eine erweiterte Ausgabe auf Kosten der indischen Regierung erschienen hauptsächlich um anzubahnen dass ausserindische Bäume dort mehr in die Forstcultur gezogen werden, und um durch vervielfältige Cultur von alimentar Pflanzen, den Schrecken der Hungersnöth bei misrathener Reiserndte vorgebeugt werde. Die Regierung von New South Wales lässt jetzt auch eine neue Ausgabe dieses Buches drucken, zu welchem ich aufs Neue Zusätze gemacht habe. Es ist das einizige<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">einzig.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Werk in der Literatur der Welt, welches in gedrängter Kürze das Wichtigste über alle bekannten Nutz-Pflanzen der aussertropischen Zonen bringt, u es ist wahrscheinlich, dass zum Besten für Auswanderer und Colonisten man es in mehrere Sprachen übertragen wird. Das Erscheinen des Werkes in Indien ist eine Ehre, die keinem australischen Literaten<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Litteraten.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> bisher wieder fuhr, da kein anderes volles original Werk aus dem Austral-Welttheil bisher irgendwo reproducirt wurde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vielleicht sollte ich noch bemerken, dass ich eine Übersetzung von Prof. Rasmussens dänischen Aufsatz über Echinococcus Cyste, von Naegeli's Beobachtungen über Contagium Pilze (ganz im Auszug) u andere Abhandlungen für das Australian medical Journal lieferte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hr Dr Sonder, Baron Thümen, Prof Agardh, Prof Joh. Müller, u Pastor Kalchbrenner habe ich in letzteren Jahren ziemlich viel Material zugewandt für die Weiter Special Forschung an Cryptogamen des fünften Welttheils.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zur Ichthyologie und andere Theilen der Zoologie liefern meine fortgesetzte Sammlungen immer etwas neues Material für die Fauna Australiens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit zäglicher Bescheidenheit zage ich fast, nun noch hinzugesetzen, dass Ihre Majestät, die gnädige Königen von England, mich zum Commandeur des St Michael &amp; St George Ordens erhob, eine Ehre die bisher keinem andern Gelehrten zu Theil wurde. So hat auch Ihr gnädiger Herrscher zu Weimar so wie der Grossherzog von Baden mich mit einer Ordensauszeichnung geehrt, u mehrere wissenschaftliche Vereine haben in den letzten Jahren mich auch noch in ihre Mitte als Ehrenmitglied aufgenommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Möge mir Kraft verbleiben, den auf meine fürdern Arbeiten gesetzten Hoffnungen gerecht zu werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ob es mir gelingen wird, die Mittel für eine neue Suchung nach Spuren von Leichhardt für Giles zusammen zu bringen, ist noch unentschieden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Dedicationen der Hauptgebirge u neuer Flusse auf Al Forrest's Karte seiner letzten Reise geschehen mehrfach auf meinen Antrieb.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">7/7/80.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I felt very honoured, noble sir, to receive your kind letter<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Letter not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and so to enter into direct communication with a highly celebrated contemporary and what is more that you write completely in my interest and want to honour me in Meyer's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Conversations-Lexicon</seg>. I have just ascertained that a biographical note concerning me has already appeared in the supplement to this work.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See entry in the third edition of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Meyers Konversations-Lexikon. 16: Ergänzungen und Register</seg>
                     <seg style="font-weight: bold; ">, </seg>
                     <ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/view/bsb11371373?page=557"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">
                        <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0563c1; ">p. 547</seg>
                     </ref> (1878).</p>
               </note> However, because the work is just not at my disposal and you perhaps wish to communicate some more words about my work for the new edition, I take the liberty of sending you herewith a reprint of a sketch of my life kindly drawn up by Mr J. Arn. Knapp.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Knapp (1877).</p>
               </note> In order to make this summary of the scientific events of my life complete, I am sending you some notes about my work during the last three years.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The entry in the fourth edition (1885-92) differs slightly from the earlier one, and adds <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptographia</seg> to the major publications, but does not include detail from the notes M provided, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Meyers Konversations-Lexikon</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">11. Band: Luzula - Nathanael</seg>, <ref target="https://www.retrobibliothek.de/retrobib/seite.html?id=111576"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">
                        <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0563c1; ">p. 864</seg>
                     </ref>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I visit the Marquis and the Marchioness de Toverena<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Alessandro de Goyzueta, Marquis of Toverena, and his wife.</p>
               </note> from time to time. They are outstanding admirers of you, just as you deserve quite particularly to have this in high places. The poor Marchioness is suffering very much, not only through chest troubles (chronic bronchial catarr) but also through the affliction of having lost her only so highly talented child.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have seen the addresses of the letters that you have had forwarded to Australian geographers by the Marquis; I do not recall that an important personage has been overlooked by you. If otherwise I can be of use to you at any time, I ask you to command my service unhesitatingly.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With respect your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I am sending the 10th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B78.03.10.</p>
               </note> because all the distinctions conferred on me up to 1877 are noted on the title page.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the year 1877 I travelled all over Western Australia. I rode from Champion Bay to Shark Bay, then to the upper waters of the Irwin and Greenough Rivers, later I travelled through various parts of the Darling Range, then with the coach to Geographe Bay and overland to King George Sound. The object of this 1500-mile-long journey was to get to know the distribution of the southern plants of Western Australia northwards, and to produce a report on the southern forests of the colonial territory at the particular request of the government there. The latter was published in England last year <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Forest resources of Western Australia</seg> with 20 quarto plates.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.13.10.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Descriptive atlas of the Eucalypts</seg>, of which the 7th decade is almost finished,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.13.11, B80.13.14.</p>
               </note> follows on this work. This monograph of the tree genus, in many respects the most important on earth, will include about 120 species pictorially, because I will touch on a number of less significant species only in the text. His Royal Highness, the Prince of Wales, has graciously permitted me to dedicate the work to him.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The 11th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg> is quite far advanced, the 1st part of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Native plants of Victoria</seg>, in which I changed the system of De Candolle independently in some parts, was also finished as early as two years ago<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B79.06.04.</p>
               </note> and I am only prevented by the making of the numerous wood engravings from bringing the other parts to light. The 2nd decade of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Vegetable Fossils</seg> is almost complete,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The final part of the second decade was published as B82.05.02, and included in the consolidated volume B83.13.04.</p>
               </note> three papers on the plants of North-West Australia from the collections of the explorers John and Alex Forrest are finished.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B81.03.02, B81.13.04, B83.08.01.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have reported on the plants of Giles's third and fourth Cental Australian journeys in Trimen's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of Botany</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B77.10.01, B77.11.03.</p>
               </note> I have produced an English translation of Wittstein's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Analyse von Pflanzentheilen auf ihre organischen Bestandtheile</seg> with many supplemental notes of my own.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B78.06.09.</p>
               </note> A new enlarged edition of my work <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Select plants for industrial culture</seg> was published in Calcutta at the cost of the Indian Government,<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B80.13.07.</p>
               </note> principally in order to bring it about that non-Indian trees are grown more there in forest culture, and to prevent the horror of famine through failure of the rice harvest by diversified culltivation of food plants. The Government of New South Wales has now printed a new edition of this book as well,<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B81.01.04.</p>
               </note> to which I have made additions again. This is the only work in the literature of the world that presents succinctly the most important facts about all known useful plants of the extra-tropical zone, and it is probable that it will be translated into several languages for the benefit of emigrants and colonists. The publication of the work in India is an honour that no Australian author has ever had, because no other full original work from the Australian part of the world has been reproduced anywhere so far.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Perhaps I should also remark that I <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>produced a translation of Professor Rasmussen's Danish essay on Echinococcoccus cysts, of Naegeli's observations on contagious fungi (completely in summary) and other papers for the Australian Medical Journal.<note xml:id="ftn18" type="footnote" n="18">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B69.01.01 and continuations as 69.02.01 and 69.03.01; B78.11.03; <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>eight other publications appeared in that journal before 1880, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>including one other translation, 76.12.02.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the last few years, I have procured for Dr Sonder, Baron Thümen, Professor Agardh, Professor Joh. Müller and Pastor Kalchbrenner rather much material for further special research on cryptogams of the fifth continent.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My continued collections in ichthyology and other parts of zoology are always producing some new material for the fauna of Australia.<note xml:id="ftn19" type="footnote" n="19">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Darragh (1996), Lucas (2013), <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Lucas (2013a), and Lucas (2014).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With timid modesty I almost lack courage now to add that Her Majesty, the gracious Queen of England, raised me to Commander of the Order of St Michael and St George,<note xml:id="ftn20" type="footnote" n="20">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Queen Victoria to M, 24 May 1879.</p>
               </note> an honour that till now was bestowed on no other scholar. Also your gracious ruler at Weimar as well as the Grand Duke of Baden honoured me with an award of an Order,<note xml:id="ftn21" type="footnote" n="21">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Order of Vigilance or of the White Falcon (Weimar) (see Carl Alexander, Grand Duke of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach, to M, 17 December 1874); Order of the Zähringen Lion (Baden) (see Friedrich I, Grand Duke of Baden, to M, 10 October 1879 (in this edition as 79-10-10b)).</p>
               </note> and several scientific societies have in the last few years also taken me into their midst as honorary member.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May my strength continue to do justice to the hopes put on my future work.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Whether I will suceed in bringing together the means for Giles for a new search for traces of Leichhardt is still not decided.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The dedications of the main ranges and new rivers on Al Forrest's map of his last journey occurred repeatedly at my instigation.<note xml:id="ftn22" type="footnote" n="22">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See map with B81.13.04; a more detailed version is available online at <ref target="http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-232134183"
                          rend="Internet%20link"
                          style="color: #0563c1; ">
                        <seg rend="Internet%20link" style="color: #0563c1; ">http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-232134183</seg>
                     </ref> (accessed 25 May 2020). Forrest's journal (A. Forrest (1880)) contains details of names bestowed; some are udoubtedly M's suggestions, for example, 'Mt Krauss, after the Director of the museum of Stuttgart' (p. 24) and 'this river the Negri, after Commander Christopher Negri, of Turin' (p. 27).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
