<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne 16/8/80. ¶ Commander Alessandro de Goyzueta ¶ Marquis of Toverena ¶ Italian Consul General &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. ¶  ¶ According to reports that have appeared in the recent European scientific journals...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-08-16-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Versamento IV Busta 243. Fascicolo 1435. “19/5. Eucalyptus. Semi.", Direzione generale dell'agricoltura, Ministero dell'Agricoltura, Industria e Commercio, Archivio Centrale dello Stato, Rome.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>80.08.16</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne 16/8/80. ¶ Commander Alessandro de Goyzueta ¶ Marquis of Toverena ¶ Italian Consul General &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. ¶  ¶ According to reports that have appeared in the recent European scientific journals...</title>
               <date when="1880-08-16">1880-08-16</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-08-16-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eucalyptus amygdalina</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus coccifera</term>
               <term>Melaleuca ericifolia</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus globulus</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus rosrata</term>
               <term>Eucalyptus Gunnii</term>
               <term>Pinus Canariensis</term>
               <term>Pinus Haleppensis</term>
               <term>Pinus Lambertiana</term>
               <term>Pinus Gerardiana</term>
               <term>Pinus longifolia</term>
               <term>Pinus Massoniana</term>
               <term>Pinus silvestris</term>
               <term>Pinus australis</term>
               <term>Pinus Hartwegii</term>
               <term>Pinus sabineana</term>
               <term>Pinus balsamea</term>
               <term>Pinus insignis</term>
               <term>Pinus Pinaster</term>
               <term>Pinus resinosa</term>
               <term>Pinus serotina</term>
               <term>Pinus excelsa</term>
               <term>Pinus Fraseri</term>
               <term>Pinus Laricio</term>
               <term>Pinus Cembra</term>
               <term>Pinus rigida</term>
               <term>Pinus mitis</term>
               <term>Pinus pinea</term>
               <term>Pinus Taeda</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Alessandro de Goyzueta</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne 16/8/80. ¶ Commander Alessandro de Goyzueta ¶ Marquis of Toverena ¶ Italian Consul General &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. ¶  ¶ According to reports that have appeared in the recent European scientific journals...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">80.08.16</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Alessandro de Goyzueta</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Versamento IV Busta 243. Fascicolo 1435. “19/5. Eucalyptus. Semi.", Direzione generale dell'agricoltura, Ministero dell'Agricoltura, Industria e Commercio,</seg> Archivio Centrale dello Stato, Rome.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne 16/8/80.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">M. le Comandeur Alessandro de Goyzueta,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">dei Marchesi de Toverena,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Consul General de l'Italie</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>D'après des rapports, qui ont paru dans les journaux scientifiques d'Europe d'une date récente, il paraitrait, que les plantations d'Eucalyptus Globulus dans la Campagne Romaine auraient beaucoup souffert à cause des fortes gélées de ces derniers hivers, ce qui fait qu'on ne pense pas devoir continuer à faire ces plantations sur une grande échelle. Ces nouvelles m'induisent à m'adresser a vous, Mons. le Marquis, qui êtes le représentant digne de Gouvernement Italien dans l'Australie, parce que j'ai été un des premiers à suggerer, que la Campagne pourrait être délivrée de la malaria, en plantant des Eucalyptus extensivement, et j'en fournit les semences il y a plusieurs années a l'occasion de la première visite à Rome de sa Grâce l'Archevêque de Melbourne.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Je vous ais cette communication maintenant en remarquant, qu'il est très probable, que les jeunes Eucalyptes ont étés extensivement detruites <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">parce qu'ils n'etaient pas abrités</hi>
               </seg> par des arbres plus forts, lesquels seraient particulièrement nécessaires pour empêcher, que la bise des vents froids ne soit trop forte; les jeunes Eucalyptes supporteraient plusieurs dégrés de froid beaucoup mieux abrités par des plantations qu'exposés à la violence du vent. En outre dans tout ce que j'ai écrit et plus complètement dans mon Atlas des Eucalyptus, j'ai indiqué, que pour des regions plus froides <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">l'Euc. amygdalina</hi>
               </seg> devrait être choisi, cette espèce s'élevant ici dans les montagnes à des élévations plus considérables que l'E. Globulus, et ce qui est très important pour les regions fievreuses près de Rome, c'est que cet arbre produit la <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">plus d'huile volatile antiseptique</hi>
               </seg>. Cependant dans les localités ou il y a une humidité stagnante, qui ne pourrait pas être facilement déssechée, E. rostrata et E. Gunnii seraient préférables, ces deux arbres se trouvant mieux dans les terrains marécageux que d'autres espèces d'Eucalyptus plus élevés, quoiqu'ils ne grandissent pas si vite que l'Euc Globulus. Un des arbres les plus importants pour la Campagne serait l'<seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">E. coccifera</hi>
               </seg>, car il est nonseulement sub-alpine en Tasmanie, mais aussi riche en huile volatile que l'Euc. amygdalina.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Si les terrains étaient subsalins, on devrait choisir <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name> pour des plantations sanitaires, cet arbre touffu réussit dans les endroits salins humides, son feuillage contenant la même huile anti-miasmatique que les Eucalyptes. Enfin, si la culture de l'Eucalyptus, qui donnait tant à espérer après l'avoir essayée devait être abandonnée dans la Campagne alors quoi que je n'ai pas l'intention d'importuner avec mes conseils, j'indiquerais, comme je l'ai déjà fait pour la Hollande, que des <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">centaines de milliers des Pins</hi>
               </seg>, qui contienent le plus de <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">terebinthine</hi>
               </seg> soient plantés dans la Campagne, parceque les émanations d'huiles volatiles des arbres conifères sont <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">aussi sanitaires</hi>
               </seg> que celles des Eucalyptus, quoique les Pins ne croisent pas si vite, l'huile des conifères développant copieusement comme celle des Eucalyptus, de l'Ozone et du Dioxyde d'Hydrogène, agents qui detruisent les germes de la malaria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dans le cas ou cette proposition serait trouvée digne d'attention, on devrait nécessairement choisir les arbres de l'ordre des Conifères, qui sont les plus riches en térébinthine, et moi-même en effet j'ai établi tout atour de la ville de Melbourne de grandes plantations de Pins, considérant que cela empecherait ou diminuerai les fièvres malignesmes. Je recommenderais donc outre les Pins Italiens (<name key="Pinus%20Haleppensis">Pinus Haleppensis</name>, P. Pinaster, P. pinea, P. silvestris, et peut-Ietre aussi P. Cembra et P. Laricio) plus particulièrement le <name key="Pinus%20australis">Pinus australis</name> de l'Amerique du Nord, lequel conviendrait à la Campagna ou dans d'autres régions fièvreuses d'Italie étant un des pins les plus riches en terébenthine et parce qu'il réussit dans les localités marecageuses, il constitue, principalement les forêts du "Pine-Barrens". Les autres Pins de l'Amerique du Nord, qui méritent d'être cultivés pour assainir sont: P. balsamea, P. Fraseri, P. resinosa, P. Taeda, P. mitis, P. serotina (ce dernier particlulièrement pour les endroits marécageux) et <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">P. rigida</hi>
               </seg>, qui est très résineux. Pour la vitesse de croissance <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">P. insignis</hi>
               </seg> de Californie est digne de remarque et le noble P. Lambertiana et aussi P. sabineana du même pays, pourraient être aussi plantés avec avantage pour l'hygiène. Il y a aussi les Pins de l'Himalaya dont la culture pourrait être essayée comme ayant plus de térébenthine, tels que: P. longifolia, P. Gerardiana et P. excelsa. On pourrait de même en choisir d'autres de pays différents comme P. Canariensis, que croit très vîte P. Hartwegii du Mexique P. Massoniana du Japon, et plusieurs des Cyprès. Le feuillage tombant dea arbres coniféres n'occasionne pas generalement de la putréfaction comme celui d'autres arbres et c'est c que fait les forêts de Pins sont aussi salubres, que celles d'Eucalyptus, quoique les Pins n'absorbent pas si bien l'humidité que les Eucalyptes, qui surpassent en ceci les autres espèces de végétation arboricente; ces derniers pourraient être entremêlés avec les Pins. Des semences de tous les arbres nommés peuvent être obtenues facilement et bon marché chez les marchands.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>En terminant, je me permets d'espérer, que le Gouvernement de votre royaume, qui d'une manière si attentive encouragea ces plantations dans la Campagne verra tout de même ses efforts couronnés avec un succès complet, en banissant les fièvres de voisinage de votre métropolis, et achèvera ainsi ce que les Souverains de Rome ont manqué d'accomplir pendant les 2000 dernières années.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Veuillez agréer, M. le Marquis, l'assurance de ma plus haute estime.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Votre devoué</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>le Baron Ferd. de Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne 16/8/80.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Commander Alessandro de Goyzueta</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Marquis of Toverena</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Italian Consul General &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>According to reports that have appeared in the recent European scientific journals, it would appear that the plantings of <name key="Eucalyptus%20globulus">Eucalyptus globulus</name> in the Roman Campagna have suffered greatly from the strong frosts of these last winters, which is making people think they ought not to continue making these large-scale plantings.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Reports not identified.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> This news induces me to address myself to you, Marquis, the worthy representative of the Italian Government in Australia, because I was one of the first to suggest that the Campagna could be freed from malaria by planting Eucalyptus extensively, and I furnished the seeds several years ago on the occasion of the first visit to Rome of his Grace the Archbishop of Melbourne.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Barclay-Lloyd (1994).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I now make that communication to you by remarking that it is very likely that the young Eucalypts were extensively destroyed <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">because they were not sheltered</hi>
               </seg> by stronger trees that would be necessary particularly to prevent the blast of cold wind being too strong; the young Eucalypts would survive several degrees of cold much better, sheltered by plantings, than exposed to the violence of the wind. Moreover, in all that I have written, and more completely in my Eucalyptus Atlas,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalyptographia</seg>
                     <seg style=""> (B79.13.11 and later parts).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> I have indicated that for colder regions <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Euc. amygdalina</hi>
               </seg> ought to be chosen, this species growing here in the mountains at more considerable elevations than E. Globulus and, what is very important for the fever-ridden regions near Rome, this tree produces <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">most volatile antiseptic oil</hi>
               </seg>. However, in localities where there is a stagnant humidity that cannot be easily dried, E. rosrata and E. Gunnii would be preferable, these two trees being better in marshy terrains than other, taller species of Eucalyptus, even though they do not grow as quickly as Euc. Globulus. One of the most important trees for the Campagna would be <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">E. coccifera</hi>
               </seg>, for it is not only subalpine in Tasmania but also as rich in volatile oil as Euc. amygdalina.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If the terrains were sub-saline, <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name> should be chosen for sanitary plantings; that bushy tree succeeds in damp saline places, its foliage containing the same anti-miasmatic oil as the Eucalypts. Finally, if the cultivation of the Eucalyptus, which gave so much to hope for after having tried it, is to be abandoned in the Campagna, then although I do not intend to pester with my advice, I would indicate, as I have already done for Holland,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Reference not identified.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">hundreds of thousands of the Pines</hi>
               </seg> that contain most <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">turpentine</hi>
               </seg> should be planted in the Campagna, because the emanations of volatile oils from coniferous trees are <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">as sanitary</hi>
               </seg> as those of the Eucalyptus even though the Pines do not grow so quickly, the oil of the conifers developing Ozone and Hydrogen dioxide, agents that destroy the germs of the malaria, copiously like that of the Eucalyptus.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Should this proposition be found worthy of attention, trees of the order of Conifers should necessarily be chosen that are richest in turpentine, and I myself have established all around the city of Melbourne large plantings of Pines, considering that that would prevent or diminish malignant fevers. I should thus recommend, beyond the Italian Pines (<name key="Pinus%20Haleppensis">Pinus Haleppensis</name>,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>P. halepensis?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> P. Pinaster, P. pinea, P. silvestris<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>P. sylvestris?</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and perhaps also P. Cembra and P. Laricio), more particularly the <name key="Pinus%20australis">Pinus australis</name> of North America, which would suit the Campagna or other fever-ridden regions of Italy being one of the pines richest in turpentine, and because it succeeds in marshy localities it is the principal constituent of the forests of the "Pine-Barrens".<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An extensive area in New Jersey, USA.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Other North American Pines that merit being cultivated for sanitary purposes are: P. balsamea, P. Fraseri, P. resinosa, P. Taeda, P. mitis, P. serotina (this last particularly for marshy places) and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">P. rigida</hi>
               </seg>, which is very resinous. For speed of growth, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">P. insignis</hi>
               </seg> from California is worthy of remark and the noble P. Lambertiana and also P. sabineana from the same country could also be planted with advantage for hygiene. There are also the Pines of the Himalaya the cultivation of which could be tried as having more turpentine, such as P. longifolia, P. Gerardiana and P. excelsa. Others from different countries could likewise be chosen such as P. Canariensis, which grows very quickly, P. Hartwegii from Mexico, P. Massoniana from Japan, and several Cypresses. The foliage dropping from coniferous trees generally does not occasion putrefaction like that from other trees and this is what makes Pine forests as salubrious as those of Eucalyptus, although Pines do not absorb humidity as well as do Eucalypts, which in this surpass other species of arborescent vegetation; these latter could be intermingled with the Pines. Seeds of all the trees named can be easily and cheaply obtained from the merchants.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In closing, I allow myself to hope that the Government of your kingdom, which in such an attentive manner encouraged these plantings in the Campagna, will all the same see its efforts crowned with complete success by banishing fevers from the neighbourhood of your metropolis, and will thus achieve what the rulers of Rome have failed to accomplish during the last 2000 years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Accept, Marquis, the assurance of my highest esteem,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Baron Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20amygdalina">Eucalyptus amygdalina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20coccifera">Eucalyptus coccifera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20globulus">Eucalyptus globulus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20Gunnii">Eucalyptus Gunnii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20rosrata">Eucalyptus rosrata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Melaleuca%20ericifolia">Melaleuca ericifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20australis">Pinus australis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20balsamea">Pinus balsamea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Canariensis">Pinus Canariensis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Cembra">Pinus Cembra</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20excelsa">Pinus excelsa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Fraseri">Pinus Fraseri</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Gerardiana">Pinus Gerardiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Haleppensis">Pinus Haleppensis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Hartwegii">Pinus Hartwegii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20insignis">Pinus insignis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Lambertiana">Pinus Lambertiana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Laricio">Pinus Laricio</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20longifolia">Pinus longifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Massoniana">Pinus Massoniana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20mitis">Pinus mitis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Pinaster">Pinus Pinaster</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20pinea">Pinus pinea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20resinosa">Pinus resinosa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20rigida">Pinus rigida</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20sabineana">Pinus sabineana</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20serotina">Pinus serotina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20silvestris">Pinus silvestris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pinus%20Taeda">Pinus Taeda</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
