<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ [Mr Otto Leichhardt advises Baron Mueller, who, as is known, has rendered great service most resolutely and most fortunately for the determination of the dark and very painful end of our great fell...</title>
            <author>Otto Leichhardt</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-04-22c-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>80.04.22c</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Otto Leichhardt</author>
               <title> ¶ [Mr Otto Leichhardt advises Baron Mueller, who, as is known, has rendered great service most resolutely and most fortunately for the determination of the dark and very painful end of our great fell...</title>
               <date when="1880-04-22">1880-04-22</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1880/80-04-22c-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="58">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="42">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ [Mr Otto Leichhardt advises Baron Mueller, who, as is known, has rendered great service most resolutely and most fortunately for the determination of the dark and very painful end of our great fell...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">80.04.22c</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Otto Leichhardt</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     </seg>Letter not found. For the text given here, see 'Leichhardt's hinterlassene Briefe' [Leichhardt's posthumous letters], <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Australische Zeitung</seg>, 13 July 1880, p. 1. <seg style="">The text is introduced as follows:'Durch die Freundlichkeit des Hrn. Baron von Müller in Melbourne ist uns ein Brief des Neffen unseres grossen australischen Reisenden Dr. L. Leichhardt, des Hrn. Otto Leichhardt in Altona mit der Bitte zugegangen, den Inhalt desselben zu veröffentlichen. Da derselbe eine Angelegenheit betrifft, die uns australische Deutsche sehr nahe angeht, indem sie uns auf eine Dankespflicht aufmerksam macht, die wir dem grossen und tief zu beklagenden Leichhardt schulden und zugleich ein Mittel an die Hand giebt, dieselbe endlich abtragen zu helfen, so ist es uns eine angenehme Pflicht, derselben nachzukommen.' </seg>[Through the kindness of Baron von Mueller in Melbourne a letter of the nephew of our great Australian traveller Dr L. Leichhardt, Mr Otto Leichhardt in Altona, has reached us with the request to publish its contents. As it relates to a cause that concerns very nearly all of us Australian Germans, directing our attention to a duty of thanks that we owe to the great and deeply lamented Leichhardt and at the same time puts us in the way of finally helping to repay it, so it is our pleasant duty to discharge it.]</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[Hr. Otto Leichhardt zeigt dem Hrn. Baron Müller, der bekanntlich auf das entschiedenste und glücklichste für die Ermittlung des dunklen und tiefschmerzlichen Endes unseres grossen Landsmannes sich verdient gemacht hat, durch den genannten Brief vom 22. April d. J. an, dass es ihm, in Verbindung mit dem Professor Neumeyer gelungen sei, die hinterlassenen, höchst interessanten Briefe seines Onkels, des Dr. L. Leichhardt zu dem Zweck herauszugeben, für den im Verkaufe gelösten Ertrag, ihm ein schlichtes Denkmal in dessen Geburtsorte Trebatsch in der Mark Brandenburg errichten zu lassen. Diese Briefe beginnen mit seiner Studienzeit in Göttingen und gehen lückenlos bis zum 21. Febr. 1848, wo er bekanntlich seine letzte Reise durch den australischen Continent antrat, von der er nicht wieder zurückkehren sollte. Schon Humboldt und Ritter beabsichtigten, diese Briefe, die sie "für wertvolle Kleinode" erklärten, herauszugeben, indess der Versuch missglückte damals. Jetzt nun ist es dem Neffen des Verewigten möglich geworden, die Originalbriefe zu erhalten. Nach dem Leien derselben fasste er den Beschluss, die Herausgabe derselben zu übernehmen. Er sagt darüber wörtlich: "Ich wurde von den lebhaften Schilderungen darin und von den tiefen philosophischen, psychologischen und naturwissenschaftlichen Kenntnissen, die mein Onkel darin niedergelegt hat, nicht wenig ergriffen." Hr. Prof. Neumeyer, der bekanntlich mehrere Jahre in Melbourne wohnte, hat die Uebersetzung der Briefe ins Deutsche übernommen und wird ein einleitendes Vorwort dazu schreiben und eine geographische Karte hinzufügen, während der Vater des Herrn Herausgebers, der einzige noch lebende Bruder des Verewigten, eine, treue und ziemlich ausführliche Lebensbeschreibung den Briefen beigeben wird. Die deutsche Ausgabe dieser Briefe sollte, etwa um Pfingsten herum, im Buchhandel erscheinen, während die englische Ausgabe zur Ausstellung in Melbourne fertig sein wird. Der Herausgeber bittet in der Ueberzeugung, dass das Andenken an den hochverdienten Reisenden grade in Australien, wo an unbekannter Stelle seine Gebeine ruhen, noch sehr lebhaft sein möchte, das Erscheinen dieser Briefe anzukündigen, zum Ankaufe derselben zu ermuntern und dadurch dazu beizutragen, dass dem Verstorbenen endlich ein ehrendes Denkmal gesetzt werden mag, das er recht sehr verdient hat.]</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               </seg>[Mr Otto Leichhardt advises Baron Mueller, who, as is known, has rendered great service most resolutely and most fortunately for the determination of the dark and very painful end of our great fellow-countryman, by the said letter of 22 April this year that he, in association with Professor Neumeyer,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Georg Neumayer.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> has been successful in publishing the posthumous, highly interesting letters of his uncle, Dr L. Leichhardt, for the purpose of having erected a simple memorial to him in his birthplace Trebatsch in the Mark Brandeburg from the proceeds realised in the sale. These letters begin with his time as student in Göttingen and go uninterrupted to 21 February 1848, when, as is known, he entered on his last journey through the Australian continent, from which he was not to return again. Already Humboldt and Ritter intended to publish these letters, which they declared 'a valuable treasure', however the attempt at that time was unsuccessful. Now it is has become possible for the nephew of the deceased to get the original letters. After the loan of them he resolved to undertake the publication of them. He says about it literally 'I was not a little moved by the lively depictions in them and by the deep philosophical, psychological and natural historical knowledge that my uncle had set down in them'. Professor Neumeyer, who, as known, lived for many years in Melbourne, has undertaken the translation of the letters into German and will write an introductory forward for it and add a geographical map, while the father of the publisher, the sole living brother of the deceased, will add a true and rather detailed biography to the letters. The German edition of these letters should appear in the book trade about Whitsun,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leichhardt (1881).</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> whereas the English edition will be ready for the Exhibition in Melbourne.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>International Exhibition, Melbourne, 1880-1. The proposed English edition was not published.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> The publisher asks in the conviction that the memory of the highly deserving traveller just in Australia, where his skeleton rests in an unknown place, may be still very vivid, to advertise the appearance of these letters, to encourage the sale of them and in contributing to it thereby finally a memorial in honour of the deceased may be set up, which he has richly deserved.]<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg style="">The article concludes with the following comments:</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3937in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Diese Aufforderung an die Australier und namentlich an die Deutschen, wird keine vergebene sein, und Namens der edelen Sache ersuchen wir die geehrten Vorstände aller deutschen Vereine in allen australischen Kolonien eben so dringend als freundlich dies Gesuch zu unterstützen, Listen auszulegen oder in Umlauf zu setzen, in welche die ihre Namen eintragen, welche diese Briefsammlung, sei's die englische oder deutsche Ausgabe, zu kaufen wünschen und uns dann aufgeben zu wollen, wie viele Exemplare jeder Verein zu beziehen wünscht. Wir werden uns dann mit dem Herausgeber durch Hrn. Baron von Müller zur Beziehung derselben in Verbindung setzen. Der Preis des Werkchens ist uns nicht angegeben, doch kann derselbe offenbar nur ein geringer sein. </seg>Ebenso sind wir bereit, alle sonstigen Bestellungen darauf anzunehmen.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.3937in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">[This appeal to the Australians, and especially to the Germans, will not be in vain and in the name of the noble cause we request the honourable committees of all German societies in all Australian Colonies to support this request as urgently as favourably, to display or circulate lists in which those, who wish to purchase this collection of letters, be it the English or German edition, enter their names and then to give us how many copies each society wishes to obtain. We will then contact the publisher through Baron von Mueller. The price of this little work was not indicated to us, but obviously it can be only a low one. Likewise we are ready to accept all other orders for it.]</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
