<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Botanical Gardens Melbourne, ¶ 14. July 1854. ¶ Sir William. ¶  ¶ Your kind communication, dated 9. Apr 1854, reached me yesterday, and it would be difficult to say, with how much pride and gratificat...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1854/54-07-14-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Director's letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 141.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>54.07.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Botanical Gardens Melbourne, ¶ 14. July 1854. ¶ Sir William. ¶  ¶ Your kind communication, dated 9. Apr 1854, reached me yesterday, and it would be difficult to say, with how much pride and gratificat...</title>
               <date when="1854-07-14">1854-07-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1854/54-07-14-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Eucalyptus </term>
               <term>Casuarina</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Botanical Gardens Melbourne, ¶ 14. July 1854. ¶ Sir William. ¶  ¶ Your kind communication, dated 9. Apr 1854, reached me yesterday, and it would be difficult to say, with how much pride and gratificat...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">54.07.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Director's letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 141.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Botanical Gardens Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14. July 1854.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir William.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Your kind communication, dated 9. Apr 1854, reached me yesterday, and it would be difficult to say, with how much pride and gratification it has been received. In fact, Sir William, you overvalued in a high degree the results of my humble labors and all I hope and desire will only be, that for the many errors, which your mastereye soon will discover, I may be excused by you under the kind consideration, that I was but scantily supplied with books and quite destitute of any authentic specimens, until Dr Sonder a few weeks ago sent me about 400 of Preiss specimens.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Short &amp; Sinkora (1988), pp. 485-6.</p>
               </note> Some assistance will be hereafter, besides your own de[c]isive remarks, afforded to me in the comparison of my in Europe compiled collection, containing about 8000 species from various parts of the globe. This collection I can receive every day, and certainly it will facilitate much the examination of the plants under cultivation in our establishment.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to W. Hooker, 22 September 1854 (in this edition as 54-09-22a).</p>
               </note> I am preparing just now for a short trip to the Port Phillip heads to collect more algae, to add perhaps a little of this interesting tribe of plants to the magnificent work, that we may expect from so high a authority as Prof. Harvey. I need not say, that I should feel delighted to meet him here, altho I fear I shall be deprived of this pleasure, as it appears that Dr Harvey intends to proceed from Adelaide to Hobarttown and thence to Sydney.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">For Harvey's Australian itinerary, see Ducker (1988).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have just packed up again about 400 sp., a few of them new, for your brill[i]ant collection. A smaller set has been kindful by the late Governor forwarded to you, belonging to the herbarium of this year. His Aid de Camp<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Robert Carey.</p>
               </note> received also a packet of seeds and some manuscripts. The larger collection from last year together with the manuscript of considerable lenght I hope reached you long ago.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The larger collection … long ago <seg style="font-style: italic; ">is annotated with</seg>
                     <seg style=""> </seg>X<seg style="">s </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">probably by W. Hooker.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Again I forwarded by the overland mail a set of manuscripts about 6 weeks hence.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It was not in my power to send, the seeds, added this time to the specimens, at a more early period, as I was obliged to leave part of the Murray and Alpine plants behind; the latter to be forwarded by a vessel, I received but very recently. This delay as well as my duties for the Paris Exhibition, have impeded the progress of my writings this winter considerably, however I send all the manuscripts that I possibly could get ready, now again. I have much to regret, that not to each description has been added a corresponding specimen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After leaving the Grampians I found the Murray vegetation so much advanced, that altho' on my way to the alps I was enabled to note many species down, known to me previously, yet it was utterly useless to procure any of the early annual specimens in their parched state. In a few instances I brok fragments of from the solitary specimens in my normal collection. Yet in the course of time, I trust, I shall be able to supply you perfectly with all within my reach. I am for this present want of some specimens very glad, that Dr J. Hooker contemplates going for a few days to Dr Sonder, who can doubtless help to fill up many vacuum in your collection. Dr Sonders collection is also so rich in South African plants, that doubtless your far famed son, not will have to regret the short loss of time, and two so careful observers as Dr Hooker and Dr Sonder; both besides Algologist[s], can doubtless learn much from each other, and it will be a very pleasent thought to me, should I have been the humble means of forming a new connecting link between the British and continental botanists.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had suggested that J. Hooker visit Sonder to look at his Australian collection; see M to W. Hooker, 18 October 1853. J. Hooker and N. Lindley toured Europe from August to October 1855. No evidence has been found that Hooker and Sonder met in 1855. See Huxley (1918), vol. 1, p. 435.</p>
               </note> Dr Sonder sent me a few days ago some copies of the notes on the Cryptogamic plants of the former collections, which will be most instructiv to me. — I am surprised to see so many algae appear to be new, certainly a great stimulus to collect on a larger scale of them hereafter. Sometimes however I find it very difficult to collect on a large scale, when for instance the difficulty of the country in the alps hardly permitted me to force my way through them, leading only a solitary pack horse. Unforseen circumstances obliged me again to travel about the Snowy mountains for months alone! — and it is certainly unjust of Mr Swainson, when he alludes to the ample means of my last years travelling, when I had for the greater part of the time not the benefit of a solitary attendant, which he enjoyed during all his stay in this colony.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Swainson thought M was better equipped than himself: '… as the Colonial Botanist has had the requisite facilities at his disposal for ascertaining this fact [that parts of Victoria contained valuable timber] during his extensive excursions he will doubtless have suceeded far better than myself in developing the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">economical </seg>properties of the Victorian timber trees.' See Swainson (1854).</p>
               </note> It is much to be deplored, that a man of such eminence as a Zoologist should devote his time to other branches of Natural history in Australia, where more insects as plants are new. And I am sorry, that neither my friendly warnings nor my remonstrations could bring him from the unfortunate idea, that the laws of distinction in Entomologie, the laws of distinction of individuals, could be safely applied to classification of plants, which are a complex of individuals fixed to a soil of not allways equal composition and situation and climate. Certainly no one should feel more sorry as myself, if to Mr Swainsons well deserved fame his botanical labours in Australia should prove detrimental.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Not even my laying before him Walpers extracts of Miquels splendid monographia of the <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>e,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Miquel (1848).</p>
               </note> of the existance of which he was unaware, could induce him to mitigate his offensive statement, that all, that hitherto was written on this genus was utterly useless! — Of his drawings I saw only a few when paying him a visit at Dandenong; I am unable to say what became of them, but believe that they are of little practical use on account of incompleteness. His boxes with specimens and seeds of Eucalypti and <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>e I received only one day before my departure to the interior, and opening at once the tin case that contained them I observed, that they had not been perfectly dried before and were consequently greatly damaged. I send however half of the seeds this time.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's misgivings about Swainson's botanical report were shared by Lieut. Governor La Trobe, who wrote in his despatch covering the report and that of M, 'Mr Swainson's services were secured by me, with the sanction of the Legislative Council, for the limited period of one year, with the special object of enabling him to examine and report upon the varieties and qualities of the family Eucalyptidae, or Gum Trees, in this Colony ... the result … I must leave it for more competent judges to decide.' (National Archives, London, CO 309/19, ff.191-194: despatch 187, La Trobe to Duke of Newcastle, 24 November 1853).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After praising M's Report, W. Hooker commented: 'I wish I could say as much in favor of Mr Swainson's Report, of which the Governor himself speaks doubtfully. It is matter of congratulation, however, that the term of Mr Swainson's engagement with the Colony had expired.' (National Archives, London, CO 309/29 ff. 323-4, W. Hooker to Duke of Newcastle, 6 March 1854). He also commented to F. Peel: 'Mr Swainson's Report is a very [lame] concern.' (National Archives, London, CO 309/29 f. 331, 6 March 1854).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In introducing Swainson (1854), Hooker commented: 'The late Lieutenant-Governor, Mr. La Trobe, in his great desire to promote the cause of botany, appointed also another naturalist, W. Swainson Esq., well known as a distinguished zoologist and most able draughtsman, to study and report on the timber of the colony, chiefly <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Eucalypti</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>e</seg>. By favour of his Grace the Duke of Newcastle the Report is now before us and it is as brief as it is startling in some of its statements. (p.186). … This singular document concludes with a catalogue of Latin and English names, numbering 213 species of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>e</seg>, "several," as the author tells us "including other species," all new, and all described by Mr. Swainson "without a single book to refer to"!' (p. 190).</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also Maroske &amp; Cohn (1992).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am delighted to learn from you, Sir, how generously the noble Mr Bentham has acted in placing his splendid collections into those localities, where they best may be appreciated. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have to thank you, Sir William, for reprinting my last report<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">B54.04.01, prefaced by W. Hooker with the following editorial note: 'We cannot too highly appreciate the services rendered to Botanical Science by Mr. La Trobe, late Lieutenant-Governor of Victoria, in this appointment of so able and indefatigable a Botanist as Dr. Müller to the office in question; and we can only hope that his example will be followed by other Colonial Governors, and with equal prospect of usefulness.'</p>
               </note> and for the attention paid to me in transmitting to me copies of it as well as of your valuable account of the Argan tree<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">W. Hooker (1854).</p>
               </note> The seeds, of which I thankfully acknowledge the receipt, have been distributed all over the country, but observing that its oil was already rancid, I fear that they will not grow. The increase of the plants useful for our garden lays much on my heart May I solicit, Sir William, that you would kindful send us as many seeds as you can spare of Cap-Australian;<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Cap-Australean?</p>
               </note> South Europe, China and other plants, that are in some degree useful and will endure our climate without protection. I should desire for instance to experiment with The[a]<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition </seg>— obscured by binding strip.</p>
               </note> but we possess not a single species.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I trust, Sir William, that this hasty lines will reach you enjoying healths and happin[ess]<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition </seg>— obscured by binding strip.</p>
               </note> and that you will continue your favour to your </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">most obedient servant Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Casuarina">Casuarina</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20">Eucalyptus </name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
