<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Suggestions for the advancement and completion of descriptive botany. ¶  ¶ At the time, when I am writing these lines in the continent most distant from Europe, the naturalists of all civilised countr...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1854/54-09-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>54.09.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Suggestions for the advancement and completion of descriptive botany. ¶  ¶ At the time, when I am writing these lines in the continent most distant from Europe, the naturalists of all civilised countr...</title>
               <date when="1854-09">1854-09</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1854/54-09-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
               <term>tab alignment</term>
               <term>even tabulation</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Fürnrohr</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Suggestions for the advancement and completion of descriptive botany. ¶  ¶ At the time, when I am writing these lines in the continent most distant from Europe, the naturalists of all civilised countr...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">54.09.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Fürnrohr</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see B55.04.01.</p>
               </note>Andeutungen zur Förderung und Vervollständigung </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="de">der beschreibenden Botanik.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zur Zeit, in welcher ich diese Zeilen in dem von Europa entferntesten Erdtheile niederschreibe, werden die Naturforscher jedes civilisirten Staates wieder ihre jährlichen Zusammenkünfte halten. Nur diejenigen, welche in fernen Landen allein dastehend des Antheils an diesen trefflichen Vereinen beraubt sind, werden es vermögen, die nachhaltigen und unabsehbaren Vortheile, welche aus diesen Versammlungen für die Wissenschaft hervorgehen, im volleren Umfange zu würdigen. — Neue Verbindungen werden angeknüpft, Ideen ausgetauscht, Wetteifer angeregt, ruhende Kräfte aufs Neue belebt. — Indessen wird es keineswegs von mir hier beabsichtigt, Vortheile, welche ja so offenbar sind, weiter darzulegen, sondern ich möchte vielmehr nur wagen, die geneigte Aufmerksamkeit dieser Versammlungen auf die Möglichkeit einer noch weitern Ausdehnung ihres Wirkungskreises hinzulenken. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die mühsamsten und mit dem besten Willen unternommenen Untersuchungen in der Natur, welche in ihren wunderbaren Formen und Gesetzen doch wohl nur mit grössten Erfolge "im Freien" sich erforschen lässt, scheitern nur zu oft an der Schwierigkeit oder Unausführbarkeit, in fremden Ländern die hinlänglichen Materialien zum Vergleiche und aus der Literatur zusammen zu bringen; sei es, weil die Notizen über exotische Pflanzen oder Thiere durch die Annalen aller civilisirten Nationen zerstreut und mit Schwierigkeit zu erlangen sind, oder sei es, weil Original-Exemplare zum Vergleiche fast gänzlich ausserhalb des Bereiches eines Einzelnen liegen. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dennoch scheint es mir, dass die aus diesen Verhältnissen hervorgehenden Hindernisse sich wenigstens in Bezug auf Literatur grösstentheils beseitigen liessen, und das namentlich die alljährigen Versammlungen der Naturforscher hiezu ebenso passende als Erfolg versprechende Gelegenheiten bieten und zwar durch jährliche Lieferung von Supplementen zu den neuern grossen Werken.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Denn obwohl jeder neue Band von De Candolle's Prodromus als Zierde der botanischen Literatur mit Jubel begrüsst wurde, so ist es doch selbst den kundigsten Arbeitern nicht immer gelungen, alle Zweifel aufzuklären und die so wünschenswerthe Vollständigkeit zu erringen, und ich zweifle nicht, dass jeder Pflanzenkenner, dem bedeutende Sammlungen zu Gebote stehen, ergänzende und aufklärende Beiträge selbst zu den neuesten Theilen jenes Meisterwerkes liefern könne. Aus dieser Überzeugung habe ich es gewagt, ein mehr ausgedehntes Zusammenwirken der Botaniker in den Jahres-Versammlungen in Anregung sowie folgende Punkte in Vorschlag zu bringen: </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">1.<space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass in den Sectionsversammlungen für Pflanzenkunde die Anwesenden aus ihren Herbarien solche Exemplare begleitet von entsprechenden Notizen vorlegen möchten, aus welchen sich für den jüngst erschienenen Band des Prodromus von De Candolle Nachträge entnehmen liessen, — Nachträge welche durch die Sanction der Versammelten hohe Autorität erlangen würden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">2. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass diese Supplemente und Berichtigungen durch den Sections-Secretär für Botanik dem Monographen mitgetheilt werden möchten, damit derselbe seine Arbeit zu der nach dem heutigen Stande der Wissenschaft höchsten Vollkommenheit erhebe. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">3. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass die verehrten Mitglieder ebenfalls den Theil ihrer Sammlungen, welcher den für De Candolle's Prodromus zunächst erwarteten Familien angehört, dem anwesenden Bearbeiter derselben oder in seiner Abwesenheit einem zu erwählenden Rathe vorlegen möchten. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">4. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass die Mitglieder dieses Rathes das Neue oder Wichtige solcher Sammlungen oder etwaige Notizen dem Bearbeiter übersenden und von demselben diese Materialien bei der nächstjährigen Versammlung zurückerhielten. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unstreitig würden manche Sammlungen auf diese Weise eine höhere wissenschaftliche Geltung erlangen, und dem Monographen würde durch die Ansammlung einer mehr mannichfaltigen Formenreihe seine Untersuchungen eher erleichtert als erchwert werden. Gerade die Ordnung der Proteaceen welche wir jetzt in Meisner's Meisterhand wissen, einer Ordnung, welche ausschliesslich exotische und oft ganz locale Arten umfasst, ist es wahrlich ohne Mithülfe Vieler nicht leicht, die Species in den für genügende Begrenzung nothwendigen mehrfachen Entwickelungstufen und Abänderungen zu erlangen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich würde gezaudert haben, meine Stimme für ein mehr gemeinsames Zusammenwirken der Botaniker im angedeuteten Sinne zu erheben, wäre mir nicht gerade hier, gewissermassen im wissenschaftlichen Exile, die Wichtigkeit und Ausführbarkeit des Angedeuteten klarer geworden, als Denjenigen, welche mit reichlichen Hülfsmitteln umgeben, sich unserer gemeinsamen Wissenschaft gewidmet haben. Und gewiss sind wir Alle von dem innigen Wunsche durchdrungen, dass die Zahl der vielen unzulänglichen Arten, welche entweder aus unvollständigen Materialien oder aus der Unzulänglichkeit der ersten Definition hervorgegangen sind, nicht noch weiter vervielfältigt werde.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Melbourne, im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>September 1854.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Dr Ferd. Müller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">Suggestions for the advancement and completion of descriptive botany.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>At the time, when I am writing these lines in the continent most distant from Europe, the naturalists of all civilised countries will once more hold their annual meetings. Only those who, alone in distant countries, are deprived of participation in these excellent associations, can fully appreciate the lasting and immeasurable advantages for science that result from these gatherings. New connections are established, ideas exchanged, competition is spurred on, dormant vigour is freshly revived. However, I do in no way intend to further expound advantages, that are clearly evident; rather, I would like to take the liberty to direct the gracious attention of this high assembly to the possibility of further extending their sphere of influence. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The most laborious researches in nature, undertaken with the best of intentions, which in all its wondrous forms and laws can after all be most successfully explored only 'in the field', all too often founder on the difficulty or impossibility to accumulate in foreign countries adequate materials for comparison and from literature, be it, because the papers on exotic animals and plants are dispersed through the annals of all civilised nations and difficult to obtain in their entirety, or be it, because authentic specimens for comparison are almost completely outside the reach of an individual.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nonetheless, it seems to me, that obstacles arising out of these situations could, — at least as far as literature is concerned, — be removed for the major part, and that especially the annual meetings of naturalists offer a suitable opportunity that promises success by annual publication of supplements to the newer larger works.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Although each new volume of De Candolle's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A. P. de Candolle (1823-73).</p>
               </note> has been greeted with joy as an ornament to botanical literature, even the most knowledgeable workers have not always succeeded to clear up all doubts and achieve the so desirable perfection. I do not doubt that every botanist, who has significant collections at his disposal, could produce supplementary and elucidating contributions even to the latest parts of this masterwork. Out of this conviction I have taken the liberty to kindle a more extensive co-operation between botanists at the annual meetings and to suggest the following points:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">1. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That in the section meetings for botany the participants should table such specimens from their herbaria, accompanied by appropriate notes, from which supplements for the most recently published volume of De Candolle's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus</seg> could be compiled, — supplements, which, by sanction through the assembled, would acquire great authority. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">2. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That these supplements should be communicated to the monographer through the secretary of the section for botany, in order that he could elevate his work to the greatest perfection according to today's standards of science.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">3. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That the honorable members should also lay that part of their collections, belonging to the next family expected to be treated, before the relevant worker, if present or, in his absence, before an elected council.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">4. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That the members of this council should send to the prospective author whatever is new or important together with any notes, these materials to be returned by the worker at the following year's meeting.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unquestionably many collections would obtain a greater scientific standing this way, while the monographer would find his researches made easier rather than impeded by such a collection of more diverse forms. Especially in the family of the Proteaceae, which, as we know, is currently in the master hand of Meisner, a family which comprises exclusively exotic and often very localised species, it is truly not easy without the assistance of others to obtain the species necessary for adequate species limitation in all their various stages of development and varied forms.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I would have hesitated to raise my voice for a greater general co-operation between botanists as indicated above, had not the importance and feasibility of the proposal become clearer to me, especially here, so-to-speak in scientific exile, than it would be for those who, surrounded by abundant resources, have dedicated themselves to our common science. Surely we are all filled with the sincere desire, that the number of the many inadequate species, resulting either from incomplete materials or from the inadequacy of the original description, should not be multiplied further.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">September 1854.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dr Ferd. Mueller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
