<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Omeo, 16. December 1854. ¶  ¶ After a prosperous journey over the central part of the Australian Alps arriving at this locality, I will occupy an leisure hour or two to acquaint you briefly with the b...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1850-9/1854/54-12-16a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 147.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>54.12.16a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Omeo, 16. December 1854. ¶  ¶ After a prosperous journey over the central part of the Australian Alps arriving at this locality, I will occupy an leisure hour or two to acquaint you briefly with the b...</title>
               <date when="1854-12-16">1854-12-16</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1850-9/1854/54-12-16a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Prasophyllum fimbriatum</term>
               <term>Stackhousea pulvinaris</term>
               <term>Veronica serpillifolia</term>
               <term>Brachycome decipiens</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/6ff19de8-52c8-40d8-bff2-438bc1569102">Calystegia marginata</term>
               <term>Ranunculus Gunnianus</term>
               <term>Alchemilla vulgaris</term>
               <term>Grevillea Victoriae</term>
               <term>Orites diversifolia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d220a5e5-85ef-4c59-838d-c50bc0660f7a">Pentachondra pumila</term>
               <term>Ranunculus cuneatus</term>
               <term>Ranunculus Millani</term>
               <term>Anemone introloba</term>
               <term>Barbarea vulgaris</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/c772cb5d-c5be-4758-b8b0-d9c0526e164f">Calystegia sepium</term>
               <term>Pimelea axillaris</term>
               <term>Drosera Arcturi</term>
               <term>Pimelea sericea</term>
               <term>Boronia bijuga</term>
               <term>Carex Preissii</term>
               <term>Pimelea nivea</term>
               <term>Schidiomyrtus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/4b1753ef-2865-4e4e-aea4-78af79ea8589">Geum urbanum</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/318a5dd0-f2d7-48d0-8492-6962be3e3fce">Utricularia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/c56af135-4b41-483c-b494-b7b5449f81ea">Leucopogon</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/39f4b1bf-ab8e-4905-8da9-5f8845b481b0">Ozothamnus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/f6e788ed-c72a-45db-bb78-95ff5b9a6d7e">Pomaderris</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/b155ec53-c9e9-4842-827c-f846469aee63">Ligustrum</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/7eb7217b-8056-4250-ac9d-28130c8d3311">Oreobolus</term>
               <term>Ionidium</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/8da80305-cdda-47f2-8dfe-022414169601">Sphagnum</term>
               <term>Calluna</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/480f9a3b-d9ce-4612-9dc4-09543a0b0648">Epacris</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/f1a5a5e8-cacc-436a-b717-e20750f80a71">Richea</term>
               <term>Lilac</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/e9ec15ee-ab15-4650-9501-19fecd730d61">Pigea</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/9c45bdc8-58d7-4dec-91a3-b03c01aa9f61">Viola</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>William Hooker</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Omeo, 16. December 1854. ¶  ¶ After a prosperous journey over the central part of the Australian Alps arriving at this locality, I will occupy an leisure hour or two to acquaint you briefly with the b...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">54.12.16a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To William Hooker</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, Directors' letters, vol. LXXIV, Australia letters 1851-8, letter no. 147.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">For a copy of most of this letter see B55.13.09. W. Hooker's editorial changes have only been noted where they change the sense of the MS.</p>
               </note>Omeo, 16. December 1854.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After a prosperous journey over the central part of the Australian Alps arriving at this locality, I will occupy an leisure hour or two to acquaint you briefly with the botanical part of my last researches. Altho' I wrote to you only about a month ago, when returning from Mount Wellington (in Gipps Land) I may hope, that an other communication now will not be altogether unacceptable, as Dr. Jos. Hooker's mastermind and diligent hands are now occupied in the elucidation of Tasmania’s Flora, for which a few observations on the plants lately gathered here may prove useful. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The want of time does hardly permit me to enter into any other statements but botanical; still I shall briefly mention, that I, as the first and only white man, ascended now the two heighest summits in the Bogong Range, probably the loftiest in this continent, which will receive the names Mount Hotham and Mount LaTrobe, if his excellency the Lieutn. Governor should be pleased to sanction them. To other Snowy mountains, which my bearings will connect with those included already in the trigonometrical Survey of Australia, I beg leave to give in decent veneration to so many great men, the names "Hookers plateau, Mount Leichhardt, Kennedys height, Mitchells Highland, and Clarke's peak." The boiling water point was on the tops of Mt. Hotham and Mt. LaTrobe equally 198°F. (75°R) although the former exceeds the altitude of the other in a few hundred feet.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Printed version note by J. Ball: '75° Réaum = 200.75° Fahr It may therefore be presumed that the scale of his thermometer was not accurate, and it is impossible to derive any secure conclusion from such an observation. According to Professor J. D. Forbes, the reduction is very simple, being in the simple arithmetical ratio of 570 feet, (as I recollect) to 1° of Fahr. for each degree below 212° for average pressure. This would give for 198° Fahr. an altitude above the sea of 7980 English feet, but for 75° Reaum. only 6413 feet.'</p>
               </note> This equality was of course oweing to the variation in the atmospherical pressure whilst the two observations took place.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The vegetation of this so prominent mountains can not boast of so many peculiarities, as I anticipated to find; repetitions of Tasmanian forms or of such as I had already observed in other parts of the Australian Highland were by far prevailing. Notice deserves chiefly a dwarf ranunculaceous plant, perhaps an anemone,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version has</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">'Caltha'</seg>; see M to W. Hooker, 22 January 1855.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Presumably <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Caltha introloba</seg> (B55.13.03, p. 98).</p>
               </note> with sagittate-heartshaped leaves of which the lower extremities are inflexed in a most remarkable manner! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>And as the contemplation of everything, however insignificant, in nature can only inspire us with humble admiration of the wisdom of the divine being, so teaches also this plant that nothing in the creation is arranged without its ful reason. This Anemone has been provided with the gift of drawing the lobes of its leaves inwards, because it is growing only on the margin of the now smelting snow, in which it must be buried much longer than half a year. It was ripening at this time its fruit, and the white-sepaled flowers must be already developed like those of the snowdrops, when yet everything around is cloathed in snow. The icecold water, which flows over its root and against which the petioles are secured by a slimy tegument of decayed tissue can not reach the fresh green of the leaves by the singular direction which they assume. The furrowed scape is either very short or the always solitary flower sessile.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">—<seg style=""> </seg>If an Anemone I shall call it <name key="Anemone%20introloba">Anemone introloba</name>. It is accompanied by two species of <name key="Oreobolus">Oreobolus</name>, by a Drosera with long creeping root allied to D. Arcturi (growing out of <name key="Sphagnum">Sphagnum</name>) by a white flowering <name key="Richea">Richea</name>, <name key="Pentachondra%20pumila">Pentachondra pumila</name>, <name key="Ranunculus%20Millani">Ranunculus Millani</name>, a very fragrant Stackhousea<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed version has</seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">'Stackhousia'</seg>.</p>
               </note> (hardly rising above the ground S. pulvinaris) and other truely alpine plants. <name key="Orites%20diversifolia">Orites diversifolia</name>, (if not a distinct sp. for I saw it never with toothed leaves) is frequent over the snowy regions of these mountains, as well as the <name key="Calluna">Calluna</name>-like shrub, which may be a kind of <name key="Schidiomyrtus">Schidiomyrtus</name>. Of an umbelliferous genus described by Dr Hooker I possess now the first specimens; knowing it alone from Walpers work<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Walpers (1848-71) vol. 1, p. 342. The genus referred to is probably <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Doplaspis</seg>. See J. Hooker (1847) p. 468.</p>
               </note> I can not at present remember its name. A Ranunculus, I presume your Ranunc. cuneatus, grows not only along with Ran. Gunnianus but also frequently enough in an altitude considerably below that species. You may imagine, Sir William, what a hearty wellcom our old acquaintance, <name key="Alchemilla%20vulgaris">Alchemilla vulgaris</name>, had, when I saw a few individuals of it again here in the very heart of the Alps, namely at the sources of the Mitta Mitta, not having seen this plant again since the last 7 years, when I left my native home: with yet greater fondness I laid aside all obtainable specimens of a Veronica, not unlike V. serpillifolia, which grew here (and but here) as well as <name key="Geum%20urbanum">Geum urbanum</name> and <name key="Barbarea%20vulgaris">Barbarea vulgaris</name> promiscuously with Alchemilla. A white-flowering <name key="Viola">Viola</name> with cordate leaves assists in the imitation of European plants but does not venture to ascend to the heigh localitites with so inclement a climate, to which the other penetrate A peculiar <name key="Leucopogon">Leucopogon</name> and two or three <name key="Epacris">Epacris</name> form also additions to the Victoria-Flora. From the lower country I obtained <name key="Calystegia%20marginata">Calystegia marginata</name>, which I think, is more than a small-flowering variety of C. sepium;<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">printed text replaces</seg> which I think, is ... of C. sepium <seg style="font-style: italic; ">by</seg> which I think is only a small flowered variety of C. sepium.</p>
               </note> farther a blue <name key="Pigea">Pigea</name> or <name key="Ionidium">Ionidium</name> not unlike an <name key="Utricularia">Utricularia</name>, from the seeds of which I hope you will raise a fine additional pot plant for your garden. <name key="Carex%20Preissii">Carex Preissii</name>, a <name key="Pomaderris">Pomaderris</name>, and an <name key="Ozothamnus">Ozothamnus</name>, not previously found here, are identical with V.DL sp. but a charming Boronia (B. bijuga)<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The name <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Boronia%20bijuga">Boronia bijuga</name>
                     </seg> has not been found (APNI, accessed 28 November 2019). M described, in B55.09.03, p. 100, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">B. algida</seg> from these mountains, to which it is restricted in Victoria. See J. Willis (1972). </p>
               </note> and a Pimelea (P. axillaris) seem to belong exclusively to this mountains. I have convinced myself now also, that the true "locus natalis" of <name key="Grevillea%20Victoriae">Grevillea Victoriae</name>, which I saw here in all its glory, is the alps! But the fruit was only developing and I could not obtain a grain of seed from it. What an introduction to Kew Gardens, this plant, a plant that requires no protection in England and will grow along with <name key="Ligustrum">Ligustrum</name>, Honeysuckle and <name key="Lilac">Lilac</name>! — Of a rufous Prasophyllum, may be P. fimbriatum, I could not find more but a solitary specimen. In vain I was searching for the splendid Pines of Tasmania, for <name key="Pimelea%20nivea">Pimelea nivea</name>, sericea and so many other plants, which adorn the mountains of that island. I hope to be more lucky at Mount Cosciusko, for which I now am steering. To the Cobboras I shall in passing by pay a visit again. My return to Melbourne is fixed to be in March, for I wish to deprive myself not of the society of our noble friend Dr Harvey. How happy I would be, could I find letters there then from you. </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I remain, Sir William, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your most devoted srvt</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir W. J Hooker Kt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">&amp;c &amp;c &amp;c.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Brachycome%20decipiens">Brachycome decipiens</name> I saw not here also in Omeo.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Alchemilla%20vulgaris">Alchemilla vulgaris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anemone%20introloba">Anemone introloba</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Barbarea%20vulgaris">Barbarea vulgaris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Boronia%20bijuga">Boronia bijuga</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Brachycome%20decipiens">Brachycome decipiens</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Calluna">Calluna</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Calystegia%20marginata">Calystegia marginata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Calystegia%20sepium">Calystegia sepium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Carex%20Preissii">Carex Preissii</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Drosera%20Arcturi">Drosera Arcturi</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Epacris">Epacris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Geum%20urbanum">Geum urbanum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Grevillea%20Victoriae">Grevillea Victoriae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ionidium">Ionidium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leucopogon">Leucopogon</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ligustrum">Ligustrum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Lilac">Lilac</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Oreobolus">Oreobolus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Orites%20diversifolia">Orites diversifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ozothamnus">Ozothamnus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pentachondra%20pumila">Pentachondra pumila</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pigea">Pigea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20axillaris">Pimelea axillaris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20nivea">Pimelea nivea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pimelea%20sericea">Pimelea sericea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Pomaderris">Pomaderris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Prasophyllum%20fimbriatum">Prasophyllum fimbriatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ranunculus%20cuneatus">Ranunculus cuneatus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ranunculus%20Gunnianus">Ranunculus Gunnianus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ranunculus%20Millani">Ranunculus Millani</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Richea">Richea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Schidiomyrtus">Schidiomyrtus</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Sphagnum">Sphagnum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stackhousea%20pulvinaris">Stackhousea pulvinaris</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Utricularia">Utricularia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Veronica%20serpillifolia">Veronica serpillifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Viola">Viola</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
