<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hamburg 2 March 1871 ¶ My dear friend, ¶  ¶ You have without doubt already waited a long time for news about the Mueller consignment. The crate had already been several weeks in my house, but by what ...</title>
            <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1870-9/M71-03-02 Sonder-Krauss.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M71.03.02</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Wilhelm Sonder</author>
               <title>Hamburg 2 March 1871 ¶ My dear friend, ¶  ¶ You have without doubt already waited a long time for news about the Mueller consignment. The crate had already been several weeks in my house, but by what ...</title>
               <date when="1871-03-02">1871-03-02</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1870-9/M71-03-02 Sonder-Krauss.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Krauss</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Hamburg 2 March 1871 ¶ My dear friend, ¶  ¶ You have without doubt already waited a long time for news about the Mueller consignment. The crate had already been several weeks in my house, but by what ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M71.03.02<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; "/>
            </p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Wilhelm Sonder to Ferdinand von Krauss<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; "/>
            </p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde, Stuttgart.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-weight: bold; ">To proof. — Box 3, folder 2, orange folder '1870-71'.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Krauss: 'R. d. 10. April. | d. 21. Mai d. Brief v. Müllers v. 9. Febr. zur Ansicht geschickt.' [Replied 10 April. Mueller's letter of 9 February 1871 sent to be viewed on 21 May]; see F. von Krauss to W. Sonder, 10 April 1871, and M to F. von Krauss, 9 February 1871. Re M's letters for viewing by the Minister, see G. von Silcher to F. von Krauss, 10 June 1871.</p>
               </note>Hamburg d. 2 März 1871</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Mein liber Freund,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben ohne Zweifel schon längere Zeit auf Nachrichten über die Müller'sche Sendung gewartet, die Kiste ist auch schon mehrere Wochen in meinem Hause, doch auf welche Weise Ihnen dieselbe zukommen lassen? Auf der Eisenbahn will man sich nicht verpflichten, in irgend einer Zeit die Kiste nach Stuttgart zu liefern, Sie wissen, dass die letzte sich an 8 Wochen unterwegs aufgehalten hat u erst auf Reclamationen von meiner Seite auf dem Bahnhof in Hildesheim aufgefunden wurde. Was wollen Sie nun, haben u wissen Sie ein Mittel, die Beförderung rascher zu besorgen, ich bin die Kiste gerne los. Oder soll ich einige Gegenstände in kleineren Abtheilungen durch die Fahrpost befördern, u die Bücher durch die Buchhandlung. Unter letzteren sind wohl einige, die Ihnen Vergnügen machen werden z. b. ein cabinets Werk über die Landschnecken von Australien, die Verhandlungen der Gesellschaft von Neuseeland. Dann sind 2 Kisten da, eine mit Käfern u eine mit Schmetterlingen, beide, die sich trocken gestellt, gut erhalten, verschiedene kleinere Kisten in den Packeten die ich nicht geöffnet habe, zoologische Gegenstände, ein [Packen] Spongien u. s. w. Kann man die Schmetterlinge u Käfer durch die Post senden? Vielleicht wenn sie wegen des Feststeckens nachgesehen werden. Doch das verstehe ich nicht u aus der Hand zu geben ist mir zu gefährlich, Sie wissen auch warum. Nun [warten]<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Conjectural reading, MS damaged.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Sie. Es ist allerdings jetzt der [Krieg]<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Conjectural reading, text destroyed, MS damaged.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>vorbei, aber wer sagt uns, dass jetzt die Bahnen nicht noch mehr benutzt werden. — Sie fragen aber gewiss, weshalb ich die Kiste nicht schon früher abgeschickt habe. Der Grund, lieber Freund, ist kein erfreulicher. Vom 26 Decbr bis jetzt ist mein Haus ein Lazareth gewesen, erst erkrankte ich selbst u durfte über 3 Wochen nichts vornehmen, dann traten die Pocken auf, eine meiner Töchter war die erste, dann 2 meiner Leute, endlich auch meine Frau. Den Hausknecht musste ich ins Krankenhaus schicken u.s.w. Das war eine böse Zeit. Aber Gottlob, es ist jetzt alles vorbei, alles ist ohne Narben u sonstige Uebel vorübergegangen, worüber natürlich Frau u Kinder erfreut sind. Wenn Sie nun böse auf mich gewesen sind, so müssen Sie solches auf die Franzosen übertragen, denen wir hier die Pocken u andere<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Krankheiten verdanken, die wir Ihnen<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>ihnen.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>aber bei ihrem Abzuge wieder mit auf den weg geben wollen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unser Freund in Melbourne schreibt mir in seinem vorgestern eingetroffenen Brief, dass er wieder eine Sendung für Sie bereite. Er ist im Ganzen aber wieder niedergeschlagen, da er noch immer gegen seinen Widersacher kämpfen muss, der als Verwandter eines der Minister grossen Anhang hat, obgleich er ein Säufer ist. Ich habe ihm Mittheilung gemacht, über das was Sie mir über unsere oder eigentlich Ihre Bemühungen in Betreff seiner Beförderung schrieben. Er besteht, obgleich er meine Mittheilung noch nicht hatte, wiederum darauf, dass die Sache von grösster Wichtigkeit für ihn sei, oder richtiger eine Lebensfrage in Bezug auf sein besseres Fortkommen u seine Zukunft. Er glaubt, dass er bei Erweiterung dieser seiner Aussichten noch mehr für Ihr Museum wirken könne, ich glaube dass ich Ihnen schon persönlich darüber meine Muthmassung gesagt. Doch Alles hängt ja in Stuttgart von höheren Interessen ab, die erst angeregt u gesichert sein müssen, ich habe ihm auch geschreiben, er möge Ihnen nur alles überlassen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was sagen Sie zu den Pariser Gelehrten, die mit den Deutschen keinen Verkehr mehr haben wollen und ihre Diplome zurückschicken. Das ist doch mehr als dumm. Man sagt, die Dänen seien die Affen der Franzosen, jetzt muss man aber sagen, es ist das Umgekehrte der Fall, denn die Dänen haben den Franzosen obiges vorgemacht! Schimper in Strassburg, ein geborener Deutscher, soll auch fürchterlich auf Deutschland schimpfen, wird sich aber auch fügen müssen. In den nächsten Tagen will ich aus Scherz an einen alten Bekannten in Frankreich schreiben, mich soll verlangen, was der sagt. —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Unser guter Herr von Martens ist doch wohl; ich will ihm nächstens meine kleine Arbeit über die neuen australischen Algen schicken, die jetzt in den Verhandlungen unsres naturwissenschaftlichen Vereins veröffentlicht werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich will wünschen, dass Sie und die Ihrigen gut durch diesen kalten Winter gekommen sind.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit freundlichem Grusse</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Sonder</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Hamburg 2 March 1871</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">My dear friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You have without doubt already waited a long time for news about the Mueller consignment. The crate had already been several weeks in my house, but by what means to have it come to you? One would not rely on the railways to deliver the crate to Stuttgart at any time. You know that the last one loitered eight weeks on the way<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and was found on the Hildesheim railway station only after a complaint on my part. What do wish now? Do you know and have a means of attending to the dispatch more quickly? I'll be glad to get rid of the crate. Or should I dispatch some objects in smaller sections by parcel post and the books by the book trade? <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Among the latter are some that will probably delight you, e.g. a cabinet edition on the land snails of Australia, the proceedings of the society of New Zealand. Then there are two boxes, one with beetles and one with butterflies, both are dry and well preserved, various smaller boxes in the packets that I have not opened, zoological specimens, a packet of sponges and so on. Can the butterflies and beetles be sent by post? Perhaps if they are checked with regard to the securing. But I don't understand that and to pass that over to me is too dangerous. You also know why. Now [wait]. It is true the [war]<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Franco-Prussian war, 1870-71.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is now over, but who said to us that the railways can still no longer be used. — <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>However, you will certainly ask why I have not already sent off the crate earlier. The reason, dear friend, is not a welcome one. From 26 December until now my house has been an infirmary, firstly I became ill and for three weeks could not undertake anything, then the small pox broke out, one of my daughters was the first, then two of my servants, finally my wife as well. […]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Our friend in Melbourne writes to me in his letter received yesterday<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that he is preparing a consignment for you. However, in general he is depressed again, because he must still fight against his opponent, who has important adherents as a relative of one of the ministers<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>although he is a drunkard.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn7" n="8">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">William Ferguson</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is not known to have been related to a Government minister. By 1859 he was gardener for John Henry Brooke, who held office as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">President of the Board of Land and Works and Commissioner of Crown Lands and Survey1860-1in the Heales administration; but<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">ceased to be a member of Parliament in 1864 and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">had left Australia in 1867. Ferguson had been employed as Gardener to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">the wealthy merchant and landowner<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">Hugh<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">Glass</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>at Flemington House from 1863 until his appointment as Oversee of Forests and Crown Lands Bailiff in September 1869 and then Curator of the Botanic Gardens in November of the same year (J. McKean to M, 3 November 1969, and notes thereto.)</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>M had also described Ferguson as a drunk in letters to Joseph Hooker, for example M to J. Hooker, 6 November 1870</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 70-11-06a), but no evidence has been found, as alleged by M in that letter, that Feerguson had been fined in October 1870 for drunkenness in Melbourne streets.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        </seg>
                     </p>
                     <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; font-weight: bold; "
                        xml:lang="en">(check notes in my old filing cabinet in the library, I have the name there. Also in the journal, I do not recollect the exact title, some horticultural society in Geelong). I don't think he was related to a Minister? Wasn't that Guilfoyle later on?</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-weight: bold; color: #C00000; "
                        xml:lang="en">The Minister was John Henry Brooke, but 1) he left Melb in 1867, 2) Ferguson wasnot employed by him up top that time, he was Gardener for Hugh Glass at Flemington House from 1863.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </p>
                     <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have informed him about what you wrote to me about our or really your efforts in respect to his preferment.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn8" n="9">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Marginal annotation by Krauss marked with a cross: 'zum Baronen' [as a Baron].</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Although he has not yet had my communication, he insists again that the matter is of the greatest importance for him, or more correctly a question of life in respect to his success and his future. He believes that he can no longer work for your museum with the extension of the latter of his prospects. I think I have already spoken to you personally about my conjecture. But all really depends on the higher interests in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Stuttgart, which must first be roused and assured. I have also written to him he should just leave everything to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-indent: 0.3333in; "
               xml:lang="en">[…]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
