<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Botanic Garden ¶ Melbourne 13 August 1873 ¶ Dear Father, ¶  ¶ After a long period of uncertainty about my future, I can inform you today that since 1 July I have been out of the botanical garden, and ...</title>
            <author>Georg Luehmann</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1870-9/M73-08-13-nonsf.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Private hands.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M73.08.13</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Georg Luehmann</author>
               <title>Botanic Garden ¶ Melbourne 13 August 1873 ¶ Dear Father, ¶  ¶ After a long period of uncertainty about my future, I can inform you today that since 1 July I have been out of the botanical garden, and ...</title>
               <date when="1873-08-13">1873-08-13</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1870-9/M73-08-13-nonsf.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="47">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="53">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Johann Christian Luehmann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Botanic Garden ¶ Melbourne 13 August 1873 ¶ Dear Father, ¶  ¶ After a long period of uncertainty about my future, I can inform you today that since 1 July I have been out of the botanical garden, and ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M73.08.13</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Georg Luehmann to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Johann Christian<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Luehmann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Private hands.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Botanic Museum</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne, 13 August 1873</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Lieber Vater!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nach längerer Zeit der Ungewissheit über meine Zukunft <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>kann ich Dir heute mittheilen, dass ich seit den 1sten Juli aus dem botanischen Garten fort bin, und dafür jetzt ausschliesslich im botanischen Museum, wo ich früher allerdings auch mitzuthun hatte und daselbst wohnte, angestellt bin. Wie ich Dir schon früher mittheilte, hat mein Vorgesetzter, Baron von Müller, sich schon seit längerer Zeit schlecht mit der Regierung gestanden und letztere hat es durchgesetzt dass er nichts mehr mit dem Garten zu thun haben sollte. Er ist jetzt officiell "Regierungs Botaniker", oder Professor der Botanik, und um ihm den sauren Bisher t... zu versüssen hat man seinen Gehalt von 610 auf 800 Pfund Sterling des Jahrs erhöht, wovon Einer allerdings mit einem mässigen Appatit leben kann!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich dachte dass ich selber auch etwas besser gestellt werden wurde aber meine Hoffnungen sind zu Wasser geworden. Im Uebrigen habe ich aber eine angenehme Beschäftigung, besonders da mein Chef mich die ganze Woche ungestört lässt und nur das Sonntags herkommt. Mit meiner Gesundheit steht es auch Gottlob gut.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Groener wohnt jetzt auch in demselben Hause mit mir was mir höchst angenehm ist, er lässt freundlichst grüssen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Willst Du so gut sein mir das nächste Mal wenn Du nach Hamburg kommst 3 Exemplar von Petermann's neuesten Karten von Australien zu besorgen?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Du musst dieselben auf Leinen geklebt nehmen. Man kann diese Karten hier nicht haben und die englischen Karten sind lange nicht so gut. Die Karten welche ich wünsche sind glaube ich die grössten welche publicirt sind, etwa 4 Fuss lang 3 Fuss breit. Du wirst die richtigen wohl bekommen wenn Du nach einem grossen Buchhändler Laden gehst und dieselben in Wandkarten Form forderst. Ich sende Dir einliegend 1 Pfund; sollten dieselben mehr kosten so legst Du das Geld wol aus oder schickt weniger wie 3. Wenn die Karten auf Leinen geklebt sind so werden sie weniger leiden, und das Porto nicht sehr viel betragen wenn sie als Buch Packete gehen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoffend dass Ihr Euch alle in besten Wohlsein befindet schliesse ich mit herzlichen Grüssen an Mutter und Geschwister.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Dein<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dich liebenen Sohn</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. G. Lühmann</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Botanic Garden</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne 13 August 1873</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Father,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>After a long period of uncertainty about my future, I can inform you today that since 1 July I have been out of the botanical garden, and am now employed exclusively in the botanical museum, where I admittedly also used to assist and live there. As I have already told you, my superior, Baron von Müller, has been in a bad relationship with the government for a long time and the latter has made it clear that he should have nothing more to do with the garden. He is now officially "Government Botanist", or professor of botany, and in order to sweeten the sour [...], his salary has been increased from 610 to 800 pounds sterling per annum, on which one can certainly live with a moderate appetite!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I thought that I myself would be a little better off, but my hopes have turned to water. However, I have a pleasant occupation, especially as my boss leaves me undisturbed all week and only comes here on Sundays. Thank goodness my health is also good.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Groener now lives in the same house with me, which is most pleasant for me, he sends his kindest regards.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Will you be so good as to get me three copies of Petermann's latest maps of Australia the next time you come to Hamburg?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You must take them pasted on linen, you cannot get these maps here and the English maps are not nearly as good. The maps I want are, I think, the largest that are published, about 4 feet long and 3 feet wide. You will probably get the right ones if you go to a large bookseller's shop and ask for them in wall map form. I am sending you 1 pound enclosed; if they cost more, duly pay the money or send less than 3. If the cards are pasted on linen, they will suffer less, and the postage will not be very much if they go as book packages.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoping that you are all in the best of health, I close with warm greetings to mother and brothers and sisters.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>loving son</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. G. Lühmann</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
