<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>No. 19. ¶ Kew, June 15/74 ¶ My dear Sir Henry. ¶  ¶ […] ¶  ¶ I have had more than ever to do with the Colonial Office of late, and especially with the W. Indian Colonies, St. Helena and the Straits Se...</title>
            <author>Joseph Hooker</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1870-9/M74-06-15Hooker-Barkly.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RBG Kew, archives, Letters from Joseph Hooker vol. 1, Ada-Bar, ff. 225-8.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>74.06.15</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Joseph Hooker</author>
               <title>No. 19. ¶ Kew, June 15/74 ¶ My dear Sir Henry. ¶  ¶ […] ¶  ¶ I have had more than ever to do with the Colonial Office of late, and especially with the W. Indian Colonies, St. Helena and the Straits Se...</title>
               <date when="1874-06-15">1874-06-15</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1870-9/M74-06-15Hooker-Barkly.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Henry Barkly</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">No. 19. ¶ Kew, June 15/74 ¶ My dear Sir Henry. ¶  ¶ […] ¶  ¶ I have had more than ever to do with the Colonial Office of late, and especially with the W. Indian Colonies, St. Helena and the Straits Se...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">74.06.15</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">Joseph Hooker to Henry Barkly</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">RBG Kew, archives, Letters from Joseph Hooker vol. 1, Ada-Bar, ff. 225-8.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">This volume consists mainly of transcriptions, most in the form of typescript carbon copies, of Joseph Hooker's letters. There is no indication in the volume as to the date or author of the transcriptions, or the location of the originals, (presumably if they exist they are with Barkly's archive, if that exists) and the Archivist at Kew in June 2000 has no knowledge of the provenance of the volume. Folios 152-260 are to Sir Henry Barkly, October 1865 to November 1876, with one of 18 August 1866 (possibly an enclosure) to Charles Meller (see below) and 261-3 to Lady Annie M Barkly, July-Aug 1867. There are some gaps in the text and a few possible misreadings. Apparent typing errors ('fir' for 'for', 'Ericeoe' for Ericeae' etc) seem to increase in letters after 1873, with more blanks; some of which have been filled in in black type (which must have been done before binding) or occasionally ink. Many letters have been annotated or asterisked in red ink and in pencil. Each letter in the Barkly series has been numbered. The subjects of the early letters are Hooker's various difficulties with the Board of Works 'under a department of Govt. already tired of scientific expenditure on Kew' (19 January 1866; f. 154), and Meller's journey to and health, conduct, and position at Mauritius, which apparently gave cause for concern. <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(Meller, Charles James, c. 1836, Surrey-1869, Sydney. Surgeon and naturalist on David Livingstone's African expedition, Superintendent, Botanic Gardens, Mauritius, 1865. [Desmond].) Letters 1872-4 deal with subjects including the Ayrton affair, the engagement of W T Dyer, the progress of the Cape Flora (especially with reference to Sonder's dilatoriness), visitors to Kew, unusual weather patterns, a trip abroad in an effort to overcome whooping cough (4 June 1874; f. 222), the "Challenger" visiting the Cape, physiological botany: "Mr Darwin's brilliant (unpublished) discoveries on [the digestive processes of] Drosera" (October 24 1873:f. 214); the Ashantee (sic) War; the defeat of the Government Ministry: "The ignorance of all parties respecting the feeling of the country is the most curious feature of the whole […] dislike was cumulative, and cumulated in most of the public offices rejoicing to see the backs of their Chiefs, let who will succeed them" (23 February 1874; ff. 217-28); a scheme for the instruction of Kew's gardeners in botany, physics, meteorology, chemistry, and plant distribution and economics (14 October 1873; f 211), the Royal Society, and in virtually all letters, the arrival, condition and discussion of plants sent from the Cape by Barkly.</p>
               </note>No. 19.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">sic, not 'with' or 'and has'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Kew, June 15/74</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My dear Sir Henry.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>[…]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have had more than ever to do with the Colonial Office of late, and especially with the W. Indian Colonies, St. Helena and the Straits Settlements, and Lord C. threatens me with Gibraltar where he talks of establishing a good Garden. He kindly wishes<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>sic.</p>
               </note> me to accept K.C.M.G. the other day, but I declined. I was recommended for it some 5 or 6 years ago, when it was refused, ungraciously as I thought. My principal reason for now declining was that my R.S. friends thought that the title being quite unknown in scientific circles, and my two predecessors being made K.C.B.s, the C.O. should have offered me the highest title of the Order or nothing (a proposition which would <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">scare</hi>
               </seg> the official intellect). The C.M.G. was offered me long ago, but not till after Mueller had it, and of course I could not then accept it, and all the more as Mueller's claims had been referred to me, and I need not add been strongly recommended. I suppose that you originated it in his case. I want the C.O. to give it now to Thwaites and Hector, but doubt if they will. If they want to recognize scientific services by this Order, they should do it handsomely, and not content themselves with sticking the P.R.S in the middle of the classes. Personally I am not desirous of changing my designation, nor is Mrs. Hooker of being called "My Lady". We<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>sic.</p>
               </note> refused Knighthood long ago. For the sake of the Science I represent it would perhaps be well that I accepted, and I certainly should prefer the St. M. &amp; G. to any other Order, as a testimony to my services to the Colonies, now of 34 years duration, but I have no time and little inclination towards such matters, and it will soon be too late, as my aversion to take a title increases with the years<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">In letter No 23, 14 September 1874, (ff. 237-40) Hooker writes: 'Thanks for the kind things you say about the K.C.B. etc. I do not think the offer is at all likely to be made, and I can truly say that I have personally no wish for it, though for the sake of Kew and my family I suppose I ought to be [sic] — no less than on its own account. A large-minded man should be pleased and proud, but minds like mine get preoccupied with what is on hand. It is a great pity that the M.G. and. S.I. were not originally made chapters of the Bath, and that there were not a few Honorary members of each who might be excused from taking the title. At my age I extremely dislike the idea of dropping my familiar appellation for any other. I know too that the moment "Sir" is added I shall be inundated with "attentions" that no merit would have obtained, and this is to me revolting.' In a P.S. to his letter of 5 March 1875, he writes:</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>'I must tell you, though it is hardly fair, the C.O. have made my dear old friend G. MacLeay a K.C.M.G. in mistake for his father — and gazetted him as a "late Colonial Secretary and First Speaker of the House" in N.S.W — The old man who is here meant died 20 years ago. George got a C.M.G for having accompanied Sturt as a volunteer, and has done no earthly thing but get rich since then — never served the Government in any capacity.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The C.O. has played ducks and drakes with that order and I have vigorously remonstrated against their having made Butler of N.Z. a C.M.G. for <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>
                     </seg> but publishing a book on the Birds of the group (a good one I grant) — and left Hector, the most distinguished scientific man in N.Z., who has worked for 20 years under the C.O., and established 3 Govt. Departments, Geological, Meteorological &amp; Telegraph, besides what he did for the N. American Colonies — is left out in the cold. [sic 'left … left'] It is too bad.'</p>
               </note> […]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
