<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>And metadata details added: Johann Luehmann to father, I don't know where it is located. ¶ Botanic Museum ¶ Melbourne, 19 April ¶  ¶ 1877 ¶ Lieber Vater ¶  ¶ Es machte mir ¶  ¶ viele Freude Deinen lie...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/mentions/1870-9/M77-04-19-proofed.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier/>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>And metadata details added: Johann Luehmann to father, I don't know where it is located. ¶ Botanic Museum ¶ Melbourne, 19 April ¶  ¶ 1877 ¶ Lieber Vater ¶  ¶ Es machte mir ¶  ¶ viele Freude Deinen lie...</title>
               <date when="1877-04-19">1877-04-19</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/mentions/1870-9/M77-04-19-proofed.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>Normal</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name/>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">And metadata details added: Johann Luehmann to father, I don't know where it is located. ¶ Botanic Museum ¶ Melbourne, 19 April ¶  ¶ 1877 ¶ Lieber Vater ¶  ¶ Es machte mir ¶  ¶ viele Freude Deinen lie...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; break-before: page; text-align: end; font-weight: bold; color: #C00000; "
               xml:lang="en">And metadata details added: Johann Luehmann to father, I don't know where it is located.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Botanic Museum</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 19 April<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1877</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Lieber Vater</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es machte mir<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>viele Freude Deinen lieben Brief vom 17 Januar zu empfangen und zu vernehmen dass Ihr Euch bei guter Gesundheit befindet. Recht leid thut es mir indess zu hören dass meine liebe Schwester Anna, welche ich meiner Theilname zu versichern bitte, sich in Ihrem Ehestande nicht glücklich<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>fühlt. Ich zweifle nicht dass Du Dein Bestes thun wirst und gethan hast Ihre Lage zu verbessern und das Leben angenehm zu machen.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es freut mich zu vernehmen dass Jacob ein geschickter und tüchtiger Handwerker geworden ist, denn ein solcher hat fast überall in der Welt keine Schwierigkeit sein Brot zu verdienen.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ob es thunlich hierher auszuwandern mag ich noch nicht mich<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>bestimmt aussprechen; überhaupt möchte ich nicht gern Jemanden unter irgend welchen Umständen aus der Heimat auszuwandern auffordern, und später Verantwortlichkeit auf mich laden. Ich habe noch nicht Zeit gehabt mich nach der Lohgerberei hier näher zu erkundigen, da ich nicht persönlich mit irgend einem Lohgerber bekannt bin. Ein guter Freund von<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>mir, ein Deutscher, der einer der ersten Musiklehrer in der Stadt ist, lässt seinen Sohn die Gerberei erlernen, und dieser ist der Meinung dass es hier ein sehr gutes Geschäfte ist. Der Lohn für einen guten Gehülfen ist £3.- (drei Pfund Sterling) die Woche, und es soll nicht schwer sein Arbeit zu erhalten.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Besonders geschickte Arbeiter erhalten mehr (bis zu £5.-) aber natürlich muss man sich hier erst Local Kenntniss erwerben, besonders da hier, so viel ich weiss, nur Mimosa Rinde, keine Eichenrinde verwandt<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>wird. Ich werde bis zur nächsten Post nähere Erkundigungen einzuziehen suchen, besonders von den Deutschen Gerbereien davon es hier glaube ich zwei giebt. Ich sollte denken dass die Gerberei sich hier gut bezahlte da wir<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>hier Häute und ebenfalls Mimosa<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Rinde in Menge ausführen.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Weiter in Lande kann man vielleicht mit verhältnissmässig<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>geringen Capital das Geschäft anfangen. An den kleineren Goldfeldern z. B. wo ich früher war, wurden<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>die Ochsenhäute weggeworfen, weil sich der Transport nach Melbourne nicht lohnte und gegerbtes Leder musste doch herbeigeschafft werden. Vielleicht könnten Jacob und ich später zusammen ein Geschäft anfangen,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>da ich mir eine gute Kenntniss des Landes angeeignet habe, auch in geschäftlicher Hinsicht. Jedenfalls<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>sollte Jacob vorher erst etwas Englisch lernen und wahrscheinlich würde es auch von grosser Wichtigkeit für<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>ihn sein in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>England, wenn auch nur für kurze Zeit, zu arbeiten, um das englische Verfahren zu erlernen so dass er hier gleich ordentlich auftreten kann.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wie schon bemerkt werde ich mir alle Mühe geben während das nächsten Monats Erkungigungen einzuziehen und werde ihm dann selber schreiben.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich dachte ich hätte Dir schon früher über meine eigenen Verhältnisse Näheres berichtet, oder dass Du es doch von Herrn Baumann erfahren hättest. Wie Du weisst war ich zuerst hier in dem Botanischen Garten, wie es daran in den meisten grossen europäischen Städten besonders aber an Universitäten giebt. Der damalige Director des Gartens, Herr Baron von Mueller (noch jetzt mein Vorgesetzte) ist einer der ersten Gelehrten seiner Zeit und als wissenschaftlicher Mann berühmt, aber er war durchaus kein prakischer Mann nur wusste es<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>nicht anzufangen dem Melbourner<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Publikum in der Anlage des Gartens und in der wichtigen Verwaltung zu<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>gefallen, und wurde deshalb Jahre lang immer in der Zeitungen angegriffen. Dabei ist er ein vershrobener Kopf der keinen guten Rath annehmen auch keinen geschickten Gärtner unter sich Freiheiten einräumen wollte sondern immer nur seinem<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>eigenen Kopfe folgte. Indessen sein Ruf als Gelehrter hielt ihn für lange Zeit, bis er endlich der Directur des Gartens enthoben wurde. Man liess<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>ihm aber seine Stellung als Regierungs Botaniker mit vollem Gehalt, als welcher<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>er die Pflanzen<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>von Australien untersucht und beschreibt und auf alle dahin gehörende Fragen Auskunft ertheilt. Für<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>die getrockneten Exemplare von allen Pflanzen, welche nothwendig dazu sind zum<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Vergleich, war schon früher ein eigenes Haus gebaut und diese Sammungen sind unter meiner Aufsicht. Ich habe dieselben zu ordnen und sonst schriftliche Arbeiten zu machen.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Leider habe ich kein besonderes Talant für Planzenkunde und das Studium zu spät im Leben angefangen um es zu sehr weit darin zu bringen. Sonst ist meine Stellung an und für sich eine ganz angenehme wenn ich nur Aussicht hätte jemals ein ordentliches Einkommen zu haben. Ich habe <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>jetzt einen Gehalt<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">[next page missing]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Botanic Garden</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>19 April 1877</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Father,</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It gave me great pleasure to receive your dear letter of 17 January and to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>learn<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that you are in good health. However, I am very sorry to hear that my dear sister Anna, whom I would like to assure of my sympathy, does not feel happy in her married state. I have no doubt that you will do your best and have done your best to improve her situation and make her life pleasant.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am glad to learn<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that Jacob has become a skilful and capable craftsman, for such a one has no difficulty in earning his bread almost anywhere in the world.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I cannot yet say<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>definitely<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>whether it is<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>feasible to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>emigrate<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>here; in any case, I would not like to ask anyone to emigrate from their homeland under any circumstances, and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>later<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>burden myself with the responsibility. I have not yet had time to enquire more closely about tanning here, as I am not personally acquainted with any tanners. A good friend of mine, a German, who is one of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the first music teachers in the city, has<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>his son learning<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>tanning, and he<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is of the opinion that<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>it is a very good business here. The wages for a good journeyman<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are £3 (three pounds sterling) a week, and it is said to be not difficult to get work. Particularly skilled workers get more (up to £5.-) but of course<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>first<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>one has to acquire local knowledge, especially as I understand that only mimosa bark is used here, not oak bark.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I will try to find out<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>more<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>detailed<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>information by next post, especially from<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the German tanneries, of which I think there are two here.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I should think that tanning<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>here<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>would<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>pay well, as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>here<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>we export hides and also mimosa bark in quantity.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Further inland, it may be possible to start a business with relatively little capital. At the smaller goldfields,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for example, where I was previously, the ox hides were thrown away because<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>transport<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to Melbourne<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>did not pay<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>yet<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>tanned leather had to be brought<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>there.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Perhaps<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Jacob and I could start a business together later, as I have acquired a good knowledge of the country, also from a business point of view. In any case, Jacob should first learn some English and it would probably also be of great importance for him to work in England, even if only for a short time, in order to learn the English procedure so that he can act properly here straight away.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As I have already said, I will make every effort to collect<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>information<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>during the next month and will then write to him myself.</p>
            <p rend="Normal"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I thought I would have told you more about my own circumstances earlier, or that you would have<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>found out<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>from Mr Baumann. As you know, I was first here in the Botanical Garden, as there are in most large European cities, but especially at universities. The director of the garden at that time, Baron von Mueller (still my superior) is one of the first scholars of his time and famous as a scientific man, but he was by no means a practical man,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>just<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>did not<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>know<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to please the Melbourne public in the layout of the garden and in the important administration, and was therefore<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for years<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>always attacked in the newspapers.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>In addition he is a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>queer-headed fellow<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>who will<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>not accept good advice, nor did he want to concede freedom to any<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>skilful gardener<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>under him, but<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>always<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>just<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>followed<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>only<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>his own mind. However, his reputation as a scholar kept him for a long time, until he was finally relieved of the directorship of the garden. However, he was allowed his position as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>government botanist, as he investigates and describes the plants of Australia and provides information on all questions pertaining to them.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>A separate house was build earlier for the dried specimens of all plants, which are necessary for comparison, and these collections are under my supervision. I have to arrange them and do other written work.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Unfortunately, I have no particular talent for botany and started my studies too late in life to go very far in it. Otherwise, my position is quite pleasant in itself, if only I had the prospect of ever having a decent income. I now have a salary [next page missing]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
