<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne 17. Nov. 1878. ¶ To his Excellency Sir G. Bowen, ¶ G.C.M.G., Governor of Victoria. ¶ Sir. ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of a copy of a despatch received by your Excellency...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1878/78-11-17-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>M78/57, unit 31, VPRS 1096, VA 466 Governor's inward correspondence, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>78.11.17</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne 17. Nov. 1878. ¶ To his Excellency Sir G. Bowen, ¶ G.C.M.G., Governor of Victoria. ¶ Sir. ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of a copy of a despatch received by your Excellency...</title>
               <date when="1878-11-17">1878-11-17</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1878/78-11-17-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>George Bowen</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne 17. Nov. 1878. ¶ To his Excellency Sir G. Bowen, ¶ G.C.M.G., Governor of Victoria. ¶ Sir. ¶  ¶ I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of a copy of a despatch received by your Excellency...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">78.11.17</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To George Bowen</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">M78/57, unit 31, VPRS 1096, VA 466 Governor's inward correspondence, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">There is a copy of this letter at CO 447/30, Order of St. Michael and St. George, 1878, vol. I, Despatches, warrants, letters &amp;c, Victoria no. 488, enclosure to despatch no. 217 of 22 November 1878, Public Record Office, London.</p>
               </note>Melbourne 17. Nov. 1878.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To his Excellency Sir G. Bowen,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">G.C.M.G., Governor of Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of a copy of a despatch received by your Excellency from the Right hon. the Minister<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Minister <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted and replaced with </seg>Secretary<seg style="font-style: italic; "> presumably by H. Pitt the Governor's Private Secretary.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> of State for the colonies, accompanied by copies of letters from Sir Jos. Hooker and the honorable Sir<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">the honorable Sir <seg style="font-style: italic; ">deleted and replaced with </seg>Mr<seg style="font-style: italic; "> presumably by H. Pitt the Governor's Private Secretary.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> R. G. W. Herbert, respecting the completion of the first series of volumes of the Australian Flora,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78).</p>
               </note> on which Mr G. Bentham has been engaged under my constant cooperation for the last 16 years.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See G. Bowen to M, 7 October 1878, enclosing a copy of a circular dated 19 August 1878 sent by the Secretary of State, M. Hicks Beach, to the Governors of Britain's seven Australasian colonies (unit 32A, VPRS 1087, dispatches of the Secretary of State to the Governor, vol. 32, part 2, July-December 1878, Public Record Office, Victoria). The circular includes copies of the letters from J. Hooker to R. Meade, Under Secretary at the Colonial Office, 24 July 1878 (in this edition as M78-07-24), and R. Herbert to J. Hooker, 9 August 1878 (RBG Kew, Colonial floras, ff. 90-1) to which M refers. (A copy of the circular is held at the PRO London, CO 854/19, Colonial Office, Circular Despatches 1878, 9309/78 Australia, ff. 176-7.)</p>
               </note> It is most gratifying to observe, that the Right Hon. Sir Mich. Hicks-Beach appreciates so highly the services thus rendered to the British and Colonial Empire of her Majesty, by which efforts the foundation work on the plants of one of the five great divisions of the globe is recently brought to a close. Every one must share the admiration, expressed by the distinguished Director of the Royal bot. Garden of Kew for Mr Benthams exertions, to elucidate the plants of the whole Australian continent, and this all the more as he at his venerable age has continued with youthful enthusiasm to work not merely with my aid on the plants of the greatest of the Queens Dominions, but has been engaged all the time also with Sir Joseph Hooker on an equally extensive work, namely the plant-genera of the whole globe.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham &amp; Hooker (1862-83).</p>
               </note> Both works involved the almost daily tracing of microscopic minutiae and an amount of detail-studies, which must have deprived him, whom we all recognize as the greatest phytographer of the day, of all repose even at the evening of a long and labourious life,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker, in his note of appreciation of the honor of CMG conferred on G. Bentham, wrote to C. Cox, 27 May 1879: 'he is in his 80th year I believe &amp; works at Kew daily! Summer and winter!' (PRO London, CO 447/34, Order of St Michael and St George, vol. 2, 1879, Misc. Offices no. 8687).</p>
               </note> and I trust, that this great man, while he is still spared us, will receive for his brilliant services the fullest imperial recognition. In justice to the colony, of which your Excellency is the vice-regal ruler, I may be permitted to observe more fully, what share Victoria has had in the issue of this certainly unique work, after Sir Jos. Hooker referred already in generous terms to my own efforts for rendering known the vegetable treasures of a continent nearly as large as Europe, inhabitable in all its zones, and rich in an endemic vegetation of much industrial value.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In frankly setting forth my own engagements for the Flora of Australia, it is not done with any desire to earn any praise or reward whatever, but merely to show, that I endeavoured to acquit myself honorably of a task, which I commenced when I arrived 31 years ago (in 1847) in Australia, after the needful prior University education for the specialities of such work. Since then uninterruptedly engaged in Australia, I have extended the lines of my personal field-observations to between 27,000 and 28,000 miles, involving much of the toils, privations and dangers of early geographic exploration but affording me also unusual experience; the material thus accumulated by myself and supplemented by amateur-collectors or departmental emissaries exceeds one hundred thousand specimens from all parts of the Australian continent as far as hitherto mapped, embracing about 2/3 of all the localities recorded in the Flora Australiana. The whole of these enormous collections, nearly all examined by myself, were transmitted since 1862 gradually on loan to the illustrious main-author of the Flora, after my own successive observations on the species had to a great extent been recorded in the ten volumes of the "fragmenta phytographiae Australiae" and in some minor descriptive works, while the utilitarian value of many of the Australian plants was traced in my chemical laboratory, tested by my experimental cultures in the bot Garden of Melbourne, recorded in distinct publications and brought gradually at the successive great exhibitions before the commercial and technological world.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The first literary foundation of the Flora of Australia was laid (in 1810) by Robert Brown, the celebrated Naturalist of Flinders Expedition in his "prodromus,"<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>R. Brown (1810).</p>
               </note> comprising several thousand plants either of his own collections or those of others, chiefly of Sir Joseph Banks. Valuable scattered memoirs of many authors, now mostly numbering with the death,<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">dead?</p>
               </note> have followed, Mr Bentham's own early contributions dating as far back as 1837, all scattered except the researches of a number of men of science of several nations on the plants of West-Australia, collected by Prof. Lehmann<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Lehmann (1844-7).</p>
               </note> into two volumes, and except also two splendid and illustrated volumes by Sir Jos. Hooker on the plants of Tasmania.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">J. Hooker (1860).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It was a rare facility, enjoyed by Mr Bentham, to be able to compare the original material chiefly among the great treasures at Kew, which the enlightened statesmanship of a great nation caused to be accumulated and there to be turned to unrivalled scientific account. In facilities like these I could only have participated by one or more visits to England, had it fallen to my sole share to elaborate connectedly the Flora of the fifth continent, a vast territory in the sole possession of Britain. It is now my intention, as announced by Mr Bentham in the preface to the 7th volume,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78), vol. 7, p. v.</p>
               </note> — if providence grants me life and health and if my researches should continue to obtain the needful fair and intelligent support —, to issue supplemental volumes for the description of those plants, discovered gradually since the Flora was issued;<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No supplements were published.</p>
               </note> for the first volumes particularly extensive additions have been obtained through the geographic disclosures of vast regions of the interior during late years. It will furthermore be needful to edit separate volumes on mosses, lichens, fungi and algae,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No cryptogamic volumes were published.</p>
               </note> though of these the latter are to a great extent already elaborated by the late Professor Harvey in his five illustrated volumes, the result of his two years travels along the Australian coast.<note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Harvey (1858-63). For Harvey's expedition see Ducker (1988).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>If I have at some perhaps undue length entered into this exposition, the Right honorable the Secretary of State will kindly consider, that I have made the study of plants of all Australia an object of life, that I have sacrificed for it nearly all that is dear to us in the world, and that it is with some pardonable pride when I own to have lived through the greater portion of the century of main-discovery of natural history and to have helped to unfold largely the vegetable objects, which nature with prodigal richness has strewed over the grandest possession of the British crown.<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The copy held in London is accompanied by a minute paper bearing, among others, the following minutes: 'There is nothing I presume to be done on this. Dr Mueller expresses a hope that Mr Bentham "will receive for his excellent services the fullest Imperial recognition" — Dr Von Muellers own name has been more than once brought under notice in connection with a KCMG. [WD]' and 'Sir G Bowen makes no recommendation. I think they both deserve to be noted for consideration — Dr Mueller for KCMG &amp; Mr Bentham for CMG. [JB] 14/1.' and 'Note them for consideration, [for] the next Birthday Gazette. RGWH Jan 18.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M was Gazetted as KCMG in the Supplement to the London Gazette of Friday 23 May (24 May 1879), p. 3597, and Bentham as CMG on p. 3598. The Governor of Victoria was notified by telegram, 23 May 1979: 'Von Mueller appointed K.C.M.G. — Bentham C.M.G.— &amp; Colonel Scratchley C.M.G.' In the draft letter (17 May 1879, CO 447/34 (M8452/79)) to Queen Victoria recommending various appointments to the Order, the reference to M is: 'Dr Ferdinand von Mueller, C.M.G. He has spent his life in most successful and valuable investigations of the natural history of Australia.'</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For Bentham for CMG, the description reads: 'For Services — together with Dr. von Mueller — in collecting and illustrating the Flora of Australia'.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>your Excellencys very obedient</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
