<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ I am currently attempting to equip a new geographical expedition for further exploration in Central Australia, should I succeed in raising the necessary pecuniary means. My intention is to have the...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1870-9/1878/78-12-14-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>78.12.14</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ I am currently attempting to equip a new geographical expedition for further exploration in Central Australia, should I succeed in raising the necessary pecuniary means. My intention is to have the...</title>
               <date when="1878-12-14">1878-12-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1870-9/1878/78-12-14-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ernst Behm</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ I am currently attempting to equip a new geographical expedition for further exploration in Central Australia, should I succeed in raising the necessary pecuniary means. My intention is to have the...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">78.12.14</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Ernst Behm</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Mittheilungen aus Justus Perthes' Geographischer Anstalt</seg>, vol. 25 (1879), p. 117 (B79.03.03), headed: 'Baron Ferd. von Mueller schrieb uns am 14. December aus Melbourne' [Baron Ferd. von Mueller wrote to us on 14 December from Melbourne]. Behm had succeeded Petermann as editor of the journal following the latter's suicide on 25 September 1878.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich mache eben den Versuch, eine neue geographische Expedition für weitere Forschung in Central-Australien auszurüsten, falls es mir gelingt, die nöthigen Geldmittel zusammenzubringen. Meine Absicht ist, unter Giles' Befehl aus den Hintergegenden Carpentaria's mit Kameelen das Land in der Richtung von Lake Amadeus durchstreifen zu lassen, auf dem Wege die fruchtbaren Basalttriften am oberen Victoria-Flusse und an der Sturt's Creek, die ich selbst mit Gregory 1855 und 1856 bereiste, durch sichere Reiselinien mit den Stationen an der Überland-Telegraphen-Linie in Verbindung zu bringen. Der grosse Landsee Lake Amadeus kann dann auch in seiner noch unbekannten nordwestlichen Ausdehnung verfolgt werden, zumal da es mir nicht genügend scheint, sein Dasein allein von dem Wasserabfluss aus den Petermann- und Rawlinson-Gebirgen und dem Gills Range abzuleiten; vielmehr kommt es mir als wahrscheinlich vor, dass ungekannte Gebirgszüge oder Berghöhen ihre südöstlichen Gewässer zum nordwestlichen Theil des Amadeus-See's ergiessen. Dann drängt sich mir auch der Gedanke auf, dass Leichhardt's Todesstätte westlich von der grossen Telegraphen-Linie zu suchen sei, denn die Heerdenbesitzer von Queensland sind jetzt schon über die Grenze in Südaustral-Territorium eingedrungen, und das reiche Weideland östlich von der Telegraphen-Linie ist so vielfach durchkreuzt, ohne die geringsten Spuren des seit 30 Jahren verschollenen deutschen Naturforschers aufzudecken. Vielleicht — indessen — ist diess Mr. Alex. Forrest vorbehalten, der sich eben rüstet, um von Nickol-Bai aus, wo er mit seinem berühmten Bruder neue Triangulationen vollendete, ganz Nordwest-Australien bis nach Port Darwin geographisch zu bereisen. Die beiden Feldmesser Mess. Carey begleiten ihn.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am currently attempting to equip a new geographical expedition for further exploration in Central Australia, should I succeed in raising the necessary pecuniary means. My intention is to have the country from the hinterland of Carpentaria<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Gulf of Carpentaria.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> roamed through with camels in the direction of Lake Amadeus<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">NT.</p>
               </note> under Giles's command, to connect on the way through safe lines of travel the fertile basalt pastures on the upper Victoria River and on Sturt’s Creek, which I myself travelled through with Gregory in 1855 and 1856,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">During the North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> with the stations on the Overland Telegraph line. The large inland lake, Lake Amadeus, can then also be followed in its yet unknown northwesterly extension, particularly since it seems to me not sufficient to infer its presence solely by the outflow of water from the Petermann and Rawlinson Ranges and the Gills Range.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">George Gill Range, NT.</p>
               </note> Moreover it occurs to me as probable that unknown ranges of hills or mountain heights pour out their southeasterly waters to the northwest part of Lake Amadeus. Then the thought forced itself upon me that Leichhardt's place of death is to be sought west of the great telegraph line, since the cattle owners of Queensland have now already penetrated over the border into the South Australian Territory,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Australia’s Northern Territory was at this time administered by South Australia.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> and the rich pastureland east of the telegraph line is so many times crossed without revealing the slightest trace of the German naturalist lost sight of for 30 years. Perhaps, however, Mr Alex. Forrest, who is now preparing to travel from Nickol Bay,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">WA.</p>
               </note> where he completed new triangulations with his celebrated brother,<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">John Forrest.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> through the whole of Northwest Australia to Port Darwin, has kept this in reserve. Both the surveyors, Messrs Casey, will accompany him.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
