<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Tönning, April 1849] ¶ My most dearly loved Clara, ¶  ¶ I, too, sit down to bring you a bit of news from your beloved home country, as I am sure you will be interested in everything that happens. I a...</title>
            <author>Marie Mertens</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/Mentions/1814-49/M49-04-00-draft.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M99.6, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>M49.04.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Marie Mertens</author>
               <title>[Tönning, April 1849] ¶ My most dearly loved Clara, ¶  ¶ I, too, sit down to bring you a bit of news from your beloved home country, as I am sure you will be interested in everything that happens. I a...</title>
               <date when="1849-04">1849-04</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/Mentions/1814-49/M49-04-00-draft.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>not final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="48">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="52">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Clara Müller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">[Tönning, April 1849] ¶ My most dearly loved Clara, ¶  ¶ I, too, sit down to bring you a bit of news from your beloved home country, as I am sure you will be interested in everything that happens. I a...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">M49.04.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Marie Mertens to Clara Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M99.6, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Undated letter on the second and third pages of a single folded sheet that also contains letters from J. F. Mertens dated 9 April 1849 and August 1849 addressed to M and Bertha and Clara Müller.</p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Easter 1849 fell on 8 April. The contents of the letter suggest it was written shortly after Easter.</p>
               </note>Meine innigstgeliebte Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auch ich setze mich hin, um Dich ein wenig aus der lieben Heimath zu erzählen, da Dir doch gewiss Alles was passiert, interessiert. Bald wäre ich nicht im Stande gewesen dies zu thun, weil ich von einer schweren und gefährlichen Krankheit heimgesucht bin, von welcher ich auch gewiss nicht wieder genesen wäre, wenn nicht der alliebende Vater im Himmel seine Hand schützend über mich gehalten hätte, und mir liebende Eltern und Geschwister gegeben hätte, die mit aufopfernder Liebe meiner geflegten und warteten. Diese meine Krankheit was nemlich die Gehirnentzündung. An einem Donnerstage, ungefähr 7 Wochen vor Ostern wurde ich in der Schule krank, und hatte an dem Tage das ordentliche kalte Fieber. Aber in der Nacht wurde es schlimmer, so dass der Arzt 4 mal geholt werden musste, und am Freitage auch 4 mal kam. Die Besinnung verliess mich bald; ich wurde zu Ader gelassen, bekam Blutigel, Senfpflaster und Spanische Fliegen. Aber ungeachtet dass diese Mittel gut wirkten, änderte sich mein Zustand nicht, so dass die beiden Ärzte Dr Thomsen und Dr Junges vor den 8ten Tag keine Hoffnung auf Wiedergenesung machen konnten. Bis zu diesen Tag sollte und musste ich nemlich schwitzen, und weil noch immer kein Schweiss kam, so musste ich am nächsten Donnerstag Abende in ein warmes Bad, nach welches ich denn auch in der Nacht stark zu schwitzen kam. Jetzt freilich ausser Gefahr zeigte sich doch noch keine Besserung, so dass ich noch 6 Wochen im Bette bleiben musste. Nun bin ich doch schon den ganzen Tag auf, und fühle mich so ziemlich frei von Schmerzen, aber so stark bin ich doch noch nicht wieder, wie früher; mein ganzer Körper ist so abgemagert, und meine schon so dicken Arme sind jetzt wieder die früheren dünnen. Aber das hat keine Noth, das will wohl von selbst wieder gut werden, wir wollen nur den lieben Gott danken, der mich aus der Gefahr errettet, und mir meine Gesundheit wieder gegeben hat. Recht viele Arbeit macht uns nun noch mein Haar. Du kannst Dir denken wie unordentlich das lange Haar wohl bei 6-7 wöchentlichem, unverwährendem im Bette liegen wird; dazu kommt aber noch das Blut, welches von den Blutigeln hineingelaufen ist, und die Wasserblasen, welche mir in meiner Krankheit immer auf den Kopf gelegt sind, und von welchen mein Haar förmlich steif geworden ist, so dass es fast nicht anders möglich war, als das es abgeschnitten werden musste. Aber die liebe Mutter übernahm es, es nach und nach zu ordnen, so dass es jetzt bis auf eine Kleinigkeit geordnet ist. O, wie oft habe ich an Dich, meine gute Clara, gedacht, wie Du mir auch bei kleinen Krankheitsanfällen immer so treu Gesellschaft leistetest, und mein Gemüth aufzuheitern suchtest; vernimm noch jetzt meinen innigsten Dank dafür. — Es hat mich recht gerührt, wie theilnehmend alle Leute waren, fast Jedermann in Tönning erkundigte sich nach meinem Befinden, und es verging kein Tag, an dem meine Freundinnen Helene Schubart, Doris und Emilie Lempelius, Therese Tetens u.s.w. sich selbst nach mir erkundigten, und jetzt, da ich besser bin, besuchen sie mich. Mir wurden so viele Erquickungen geschickt von den Leuten, und die lieben Klanders aus Husum schicken Fische, allerlei Conditor Sachen, und viele Apfelsinen. Überhaupt von den Letzteren habe ich recht reichlich gehabt, denn die lieben Eltern erfreuten mich immer mit welche. Wir müssen sie hier nur so theuer bezahlen, 3-4 Mark das Stück. Ihr pflückt sie wohl nur so vom Baume, nicht wahr? Während meiner Krankheit habe ich ja natürlich nicht zur Schule können, und habe sie deshalb ja lange versäumt, was mir sehr leid thut, aber ich habe ja noch ein ganzes Jahr nach sie zu besuchen, und so muss sich da ja helfen. Ich bin nemlich nicht mit Ernst diesen Ostern confirmirt, sondern habe bloss vor meiner Krankheit mit nach den Pastoren zum Zuhören gegangen, welches ja sehr lehrreich und nützlich ist. Mit unserer Schule wird vielleicht wieder eine Veränderung vorgenommen, indem wir wohl wieder alle unsere Stunden bekommen werden. Louise geht in der Mittelklasse, und hat jetzt genug mit Schreiben Lernen u. dergl. zu thun. Bist Du schon confirmirt, liebes Clärchen? Du kannst wohl schon ganz fertig Englisch sprechen, nicht? Ja, denke nur nicht das wir hier zurück bleiben, denn auch ich lerne jetzt die englische Sprache, und würde wohl mit Dir palliren,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">parlieren.</p>
               </note> wenn Du hier wärst. Unser englischer Lehrer heisst Simonsen, und ist der Mann von Christiane Boyens. Nun, was macht Ihr Lieben denn, hoffentlich erfreut Ihr Euch in dem schönen Klima einer dauerhaften Gesundheit, welches ja der Zweck Eurer Reise, und das höchste Erdengut ist. Was macht denn die liebe Bertha? Gleich wie sie ist auch ihre Freundin Louise Lescow in Rendsburg verlobt. Hat sie sich schon verheirathet? Wenn sie verheirathet ist, ziehst Du wohl mit ihr in ihr Haus, nicht wahr? Ach, wir sind so begierig von Euch etwas zu hören, und sehen jeden Posttag nach einem Briefe von Euch Lieben aus, aber noch immer will keiner kommen. Von allen, die Du kennst, von Therese Tetens, Helene Schubart u.s.w. soll ich viele herzliche Grüsse bestellen, sowie auch von der lieben Grossmutter. Sie ist noch immer content, und gedenkt Eurer mit Liebe, und es vergeht fast kein Tag, an dem sie nicht von Euch spräche. Der liebe Gott erhalte sie uns noch recht lange. Viele Grüsse an Deinen lieben Bruder Ferdinand, Bertha und ihren Verlobten Gustav Schedlich, und sei auch Du herzlich gegrüsst von </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Deiner</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dich ewig liebenden</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Marie.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">[Tönning, April 1849]</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">My most dearly loved Clara,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I, too, sit down to bring you a bit of news from your beloved home country, as I am sure you will be interested in everything that happens. I almost would have been unable to so, because I was afflicted with a severe and serious illness, from which I would surely not have recovered, if our all-loving Father in Heaven had not stretched out his protecting hand over me and had not given me loving parents and brothers and sisters, who cared for me and waited on me with devoted love. This disease was encephalitis. On a Thursday about 7 weeks before Easter I became ill at school and had ordinary shivery fever that day. But during the night it got worse, so that the doctor had to be called in 4 times, and another 4 times on Friday. I soon lost consciousness. I was bled, got leeches, mustard plaster and Spanish Flies. Yet even though these remedies are efficacious, my condition did not change. It was not until the eighth day that the two doctors, Dr Thomsen and Dr Junges, could give any hope for recovery. Up to that day I was supposed to and had to sweat, and because no perspiration occurred, I was placed in a warm bath on the next Thursday evening. After that I started to sweat heavily during the night. Although now out of danger, I showed no improvement. I had to stay in bed for another 6 weeks. Now I am already up all day and fairly free from pain, but am not nearly as strong as before. My whole body is so wasted away, and my arms, previously already so plump, are again as thin as they used to be. But that is no problem, it will no doubt remedy itself. We must thank the good Lord, who has rescued me from danger and has given me back my health. Only my hair still causes a lot of trouble. You can imagine, how tangled long hair gets with 6-7 weeks constant bed-rest. Add to that the blood that ran into it from the leeches, and the fluid from the blisters which were constantly placed on my head<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Probably from the Spanish Flies.</p>
               </note>, it made my hair quite stiff. There seemed no other option but to have it cut off. However, my dear mother<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Magdalene Mertens.</p>
               </note> took it upon herself to work through it bit by bit, so that by now it is all tidy again except for just a little patch.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>O, how often I have thought of you, my dear Clara, how you always used to keep me faithful company even during small illnesses and tried to cheer me up. Please accept now my belated thanks for that.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I was quite touched, how sympathetic all the people were. Nearly everybody in Tönning asked how I was, and not a day passed without my girlfriends Helene Schubart, Doris and Emilie Lempelius, Therese Tetens etc. enquiring after me. Now that I am better, they come and visit me. I was sent so many refreshments by people, the dear Klanders of Husum send fish, all sorts of pastries and many oranges. I have generally had an abundance of the latter, my dear parents always spoiled me with some. Only, they are so expensive to buy here, 3-4 Mark each. I suppose, you just pick them off the trees, don't you?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Of course I was unable to attend school during my illness, and I am very sorry to have missed so much. But then I still have a whole year of schooling left, so it will work out all right. I was not confirmed with Ernst at Easter recently, but before I got ill I just went along with him to the Pastor's to listen in, which of course is very instructive and useful. There may perhaps be another change with our school in that we will probably get all our lessons back again. Louise goes to the middle class, and is kept sufficiently busy with learning to write and similar. Have you been confirmed yet, dear Clara? You can probably speak English quite well by now, can you? Well, just don't think that we are backward here, because I am also learning the English language now, and could probably talk with you, if you were here. Our English teacher's name is Simonsen, he is the husband of Christiane Boyens.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Well, what are you all doing now? I hope you enjoy continuous good health in the beautiful climate which, after all, is the purpose of your voyage, and the greatest good on earth. How is dear Bertha? Like her, her friend Louise Lescow in Rendsburg also is engaged.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.1665in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.1665in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bertha Müller had become engaged to Carl Schedlich, a fellow passenger on the voyage from Germany to Australia. However, after a short time she broke off the engagement.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> Has she got married yet? When she is married, you will probably move into her house with her, won't you? O, we are so eager to hear from you, and every mail day we are on the look-out for a letter from you dear ones, but still none will come. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am to send you many kind regards from everybody you know, from Therese Tetens, Helene Schubart, etc., and also from our dear grandmother, she is still happy and thinks of you all with love. Hardly a day passes, when she does not talk of you. Many regards to your dear brother Ferdinand, Bertha and her fiancé Gustav Schedlich, and sincere regards to you also from </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">your always loving</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Marie.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
