<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne 24/2/93. ¶  ¶ Highly respected Professor Ascherson, your circular just arrived here, which gives the news of the high honour shown to me at Genoa, to be elected to the International committe...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-02-24-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>93.02.24</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne 24/2/93. ¶  ¶ Highly respected Professor Ascherson, your circular just arrived here, which gives the news of the high honour shown to me at Genoa, to be elected to the International committe...</title>
               <date when="1893-02-24">1893-02-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-02-24-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Nasturtium terrestre</term>
               <term>Nasturtium palustre</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/1e2b993b-1a98-4e75-99d6-3e86dd1227ae">Ranunculus</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/9a43620b-f968-4a2c-8617-bf02c5e76fcd">Anemone</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Paul Ascherson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne 24/2/93. ¶  ¶ Highly respected Professor Ascherson, your circular just arrived here, which gives the news of the high honour shown to me at Genoa, to be elected to the International committe...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">93.02.24</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Paul Ascherson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne 24/2/93.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eben, hochgeehrter Herr Professor Ascherson, langt Ihr Circular hier an, welches von der zu Genua mir erwiesenenen hohen Ehre die Kunde giebt, in das internationale Committee für systematische Pflanzen-Benennungen gewählt zu sein, und nehme ich mit grossem Dank für das mir erwiesene Vertrauen diese Wahl in die Commission nicht nur an, sondern werde mich auch besonders bestreben bei dieser wichtigen Angelegenheit meinen hohen Collegen wirklich nützlich zu sein. Diese Stellung giebt mir ja auch Gelegenheit, die Gründe noch weiter zu entwickeln und zu besprechen, welche mich nach so langer Erfahrung bei der Ausarbeitung meiner eignen phytographischen Werke leiteten.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Bezug auf die besonderen Fragen, welche in Ihrem Genua-Circular gestellt sind, möchte ich vorschlagen:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">1, dass ein Subcommittee für engere Berathungen erwählt werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">2, dass dies Subcommittee bestehe aus M. A. De Candolle, Sir J. Hooker, Prof Baillon, und entweder Prof Saccardo (für Cryptogamie) oder Prof. Coulter (für Americanische Consultation) mit Ihnen selbst als Secretair. Mir scheint eine Subcommission von 5 genügend zu sein, denn mehr Mitglieder würden die practischen preliminaren Berathungen zu weitläufig machen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">3, dass dies Sub-Committee alle Mitglieder der Commission ersuche, eine volle Exposition deren Ansichten über die zu berathenden Fragen einzusenden, dass nach solchen vollen schriftlichen Vorlagen ein Plan von der Sub-Committee ausgearbeitet werde, und dieser vorläufige Plan den 30 Mitgliedern für weitere Erwägung zukäme, wonach dann eine finale Ausarbeitung dem Sub-Committee möglich sein würde, um solche einem specialen botanischen internationalen Congress vorzulegen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">4, dass die Wahl des Ortes, in welchem dieser Congress zu halten wäre, vom Sub-Committee bestimmt werde, so wie auch der passende Zeitpunct.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Um der Sub-Committee die Deliberationen und Ihnen die Correspondenz zu vereinfachen und zu erleichtern, möchte es wünschenswerth sein, den 30 Mitgliedern eine Reihe categorischer Fragen zu stellen formulirt und exemplificirt, z. B. Ob Tournefort, der eigentliche Begründer der Pflanzen-Genera, ganz zu übergehen sei, ob wenigstens als (T.) Anerkennung verdiene, oder ob wie ich mit Asa Gray, Baillon &amp;c wünschte, als erste und älteste systemat. Gattungs-Autorität zu betrachten sei (e.g. <name key="Ranunculus">Ranunculus</name>, <name key="Anemone">Anemone</name> &amp;c. Im letztere Falle bliebe die Annahme für die Species doch 1753, und nur solche Genera aus der Zeit vor L. würden angenommen werden, als durch die binare Benennung confirmirt wurden. So auch könnte eine Frage lauten, ob der erste Art-Name anzunehmen sei, obwohl solcher in den meisten Fällen auf Irrthümer in der Gattungs Auffassung beruht, und eine solche Annahme dem wahren Prioritäts-Recht widerspricht; e. c.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>exempli causa.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <name key="Nasturtium%20terrestre">Nasturtium terrestre</name> (1812) oder N. palustre (1821) obwohl Leysser 1761 und Withering erst 1776 schrieb.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Ferner, ob es gerechtfertigt sei, dass bei der Transposition von Arten aus einem genus in ein anderes irgend einem Anderem, als dem der die erste Indication gab, die Autorität zufiele für Arten deren richtige Auffassung vollkommen bekannt waren, also selbverständlich in das neue Genus oder andere G. übergingen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Andere Fragen möchten sein. Verwerfung von Gattungs Namen ohne Indication von Arten selbst in Zeiten nach Linné, wenn auch die Nothwendigkeit durchaus nicht vorliegt, dass der neue Doppel Name gedruckt sei, da solche Andeutungen manchmal wie Scopoli, R Br und andere solche gaben ganz genugen Es möchte auch zu erwägen sein, ob die Sub-Committee auch einige Zoographen zu Rath ziehen solle, um für die systematischen Benennungen in der ganzen le</seg>
               <seg style=""> </seg>
               <seg style="">What is this? Did he mean e.g.?benden Natur eine Gleichförmigkeit in den Principien anzubahnen. Vor Allem kommt es aber darauf an, dass alle Bestimmungen auf volles </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Gerechtigkeits</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Gefühl beruhen, wenn solche dauernden Bestand haben sollen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne 24/2/93.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Highly respected Professor Ascherson, your circular just arrived here, which gives the news of the high honour shown to me at Genoa, to be elected to the International committee for systematic plant nomenclature, and I not only accept this election to the committee with great thanks for the trust shown to me, but also will strive especially in this important matter to be really useful to my distinguished collegues. This position also certainly gives me opportunity to develop even further and to discuss the reasons which guided me after such long experience in the elaboration of my own phytographic works.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In reference to the particular questions which are put in your general circular, I would like to suggest:</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>1, that a sub-committee be elected for closer consultation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>2, that this sub-committee consist of M. A. De Candolle, Sir J. Hooker, Professor Baillon and either Professor Saccardo (for cryptogams) or Professor Coulter (for American consultation) with yourself as secretary. It seems to me a sub-commitee of 5 is sufficient, because more members would make the practical preliminary consultation too lengthy.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>3, that this sub-committee request all members of the committee to send in a full exposition of their views about the questions to be discussed, that after such complete written presentations a plan be worked out by the sub-committee and this provisional plan come to the 30 members for further consideration, after which it would be possible to submit a final elaboration by the sub-committee to a special international botanical congress.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>4, that the choice of the place in which this congress would be held will be determined by the sub-committee as well as the suitable time. In order to simplify and make the deliberations of the sub-committee and the correspondence easier for you, it may be desirable to put a series of categorical questions to the 30 members, formulated and exemplified, for example, whether Tournefort, the actual founder of plant genera, is to be ignored completely, whether at least that (T.) deserves recognition, or whether, as I with Asa Gray, Baillon &amp;c wish, he is to be regarded as the first and oldest systematic authority of genera (e.g. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Ranunculus">Ranunculus</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Anemone">Anemone</name>
               </seg> &amp;c). In the latter case the acceptance for species remains really 1753 and only such genera would be accepted from the time before Linnaeus as were confirmed by binomial nomenclature. So also could a question be whether the first species name be accepted, even if in most cases it is based on an error in the generic conception and such an acceptance contradicts the true right of priority, for example <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Nasturtium%20terrestre">Nasturtium terrestre</name>
               </seg> (1812) or <seg style="font-style: italic; ">N. palustre</seg> (1821) although Leysser 1761 and Withering 1776 wrote them first.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leysser (1761); Withering (1776). See Bentham (1863-78), vol. 1, p. 66 for a discussion of the oldest name in </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Nasturtium</seg>
                     <seg style="">, and hence whether </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">terrestre</seg>
                     <seg style=""> or </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">palustre</seg>
                     <seg style=""> has priority as the specific epithet.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Further, whether it is justified that in the transfer of species from one genus into another the authority for species whose correct conception was completely known passed to somebody other than he who gave the first indication, thus of course turned into the new genus or other genera.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Other questions may be: Rejection of generic names without indication of species even in times after Linné, even if the necessity is not by any means known that the new double name be printed, because such mentions sometimes like Scopoli, Robert Brown<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Robert Brown (1773-1858).</p>
               </note> and others were given quite sufficiently. It may also be considered whether the sub-committee should also consult some zoologists, to initiate uniformity in the principles for systematic nomenclature in the whole of living nature. What matters above all is that all determinations are based on complete feelings of justice, if such are to have permanence.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anemone">Anemone</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Nasturtium%20palustre">Nasturtium palustre</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Nasturtium%20terrestre">Nasturtium terrestre</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ranunculus">Ranunculus</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
