<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>South-Yarra, ¶ 14/8/93. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Under Secretary. ¶ Sir....</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-08-14a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>V93/5332, unit750, VPRS 3992/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>93.08.14a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>South-Yarra, ¶ 14/8/93. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Under Secretary. ¶ Sir....</title>
               <date when="1893-08-14">1893-08-14</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-08-14a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Thomas Wilson</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">South-Yarra, ¶ 14/8/93. ¶ T. R. Wilson Esqr ¶ Under Secretary. ¶ Sir....</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">93.08.14a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Thomas Wilson</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">V93/5332, unit750, VPRS 3992/P inward registered correspondence, VA 475 Chief Secretary's Department, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">South-Yarra,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">14/8/93.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">T. R. Wilson Esqr</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Under Secretary.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication, dated 11 Aug,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See T. Wilson to M, 11 August 1893 (in this edition as 93-08-11b).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>informing me, that his Exc. the Governor in Council has been pleased to appoint Mr G. Renner an Officer of the fifth Class in the Gov Botanist's branch<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The file contains a copy of the letter from the Public Service Board, 20 July 1893, declaring that G. Renner,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'who was, on the 25th March 1892, transferred temporarily to the Mines Department, be retransferred to the Government Botanist's Branch of the Chief Secretary's Department'. On 30 September 1893, Wilson minuted to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the Department's chief finance clerk,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>James<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Killen:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'If I recollect rightly Mr Renner was actually transferred (that is<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">permanently</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>transferred &amp; not merely lent) to the Mines last year, &amp; has been sent back to us because they wished to reduce their Exp. In other words, I might have declined taking him back &amp; have left the Mines to provide for him till a permanent place could be found. Am I correct?'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The reply appears as annotations<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on the minute: against<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <hi rend="underline">permanently</hi>
                        </seg>'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is written<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'No — Temporarily', and at the end of the minute,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'I do not think you could properly have done this. Col. Couchman's letter is correct.'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>minute was mistakenly filed with an unrelated letter, M to T. Wilson, 29 September 1893 (in this edition as 93-09-29a).</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>second<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>comment refers to an<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>editorial in the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(Melbourne), 29 September 1893, p. 4, criticizing the transferring of Renner to the Government Botanist's branch and subsequent correspondence, including a letter from T. Couchman, Chairman of the Public Service Board. Relevant clippings are included in the file.</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>editorial began:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'A curious illustration of the blissful condition of the Public Service came out last night in the Assembly, in the course of a discussion on the Estimates. A new clerk at £188 a year has been put into the Government Botanist's department, and the total cost of that office, in spite of general retrenchment, has therefore jumped up from £1479 in 1893-93 to £1607 in 1892-94. The circumstance was so peculiar that the Premier was asked for an explanation. He gave it. The clerk was formerly engaged in the Mining department. There was nothing for him to do there, and he was shifted over to Dr. von Mueller to botanise with the baron pending a distressed country being able to find something for him to do. The man of many herbs has no more need of him than Mr. Howitt has, but it would never do to have a civil servant "without a local habitation" as well as a name; and so, according to the Premier, the gentleman is considerately put to ruralise amongst the plants a little while, until somebody can somewhere find something for him to do by way of partially earning his salary.'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The editorial went on with criticisms about an overcrowded Public Service in a time of economic hardship. The editorial provoked a reply (<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>, 30 September 1893, p. 10) from the Chairman of the Public Service Board, T. Couchman:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'The Public Service Board regrets to observe on perusing your leading article of this morning that you still persist in misrepresenting its action. The clerk referred to was an officer of the Government Botanist's branch. Owing to slackness of work he was temporarily transferred to assist in the Forestry branch of the Mines department. When his services were no longer required there he was sent back to the botanist, pending other arrangements, as was practically explained by the hon. the Premier in Parliament last night.'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The Editor of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>responded:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'Mr. Patterson stated in the Legislative Assembly that the clerk in question, having nothing to do in the Mining department, had been put into the Government Botanist's branch until work could be found for him. Mr. Couchman admits that this is the case. He is there in addition to the staff of last year, and Mr. Patterson told the Assembly that he is not wanted there, but merely put there because there is no other post at present open. Where, then, is the misrepresentation?'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The exchange was accompanied by a letter from<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'A Gardener'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to the Editor:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'In your leading article this morning, you state that a "clerk was formerly engaged in the Mining department. There was nothing for him to do there, and he was shifted over to Dr. von Mueller to botanise with the baron pending a distressed country being able to find something for him to do. The man of many herbs has no more need of him than Mr. Howitt has," &amp;c., the fact being that the baron has so much need of the clerk that at present, and for some time past, he has paid an extra clerk out of his own salary.'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The file also includes a letter from T. Couchman to the Premier, 30 September 1893, concerning the newspaper clippings:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'I beg to invite your attention to the accompanying marked portion of a Leading Article, published in the Age Newspaper of yesterday's date, and Board's reply published in this morning's issue. The officer referred to is Mr G. Renner, and I beg to ask whether it is your desire that his services should be dispensed with, and if so, from what date.'<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>On 11 October Wilson minuted:<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>'CS says "[see] votes"'. Renner had been transferred to the Mines Department in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>March<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1892; see M to T. Wilson, 31<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>March<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1892<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>92-03-31b).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the public service, and I have transmitted a copy of your communication accordingly to Mr Renner.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I have the honor to be,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir, your obedient servant</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Gov. Botanist.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">I am of course glad for the additional aid afforded thus to my establishment.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
