<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 31/1/93. ¶  ¶ In acknowledgement of your letter of 22/12/92, ¶  highly esteemed Professor, I express my thanks to you for the notification of a new contribution of dried plants to the colle...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-01-31-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>93.01.31</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 31/1/93. ¶  ¶ In acknowledgement of your letter of 22/12/92, ¶  highly esteemed Professor, I express my thanks to you for the notification of a new contribution of dried plants to the colle...</title>
               <date when="1893-01-31">1893-01-31</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-01-31-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Dilleniaceae</term>
               <term>Mylitta</term>
               <term>Todea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Adolf Engler</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 31/1/93. ¶  ¶ In acknowledgement of your letter of 22/12/92, ¶  highly esteemed Professor, I express my thanks to you for the notification of a new contribution of dried plants to the colle...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">93.01.31</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Adolf Engler</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Berlin.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne, 31/1/93.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Anerkennung Ihres Schreibens vom 22/12/92, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, spreche ich Ihnen meinen Dank aus für die Ankündigung eines neuen Beitrags von getrockneten Pflanzen zu den Sammlungen meiner Anstalt, wodurch ich allerdings noch weiter in Schuld gerathe bezüglich Ihres Museums, was um so bedrückender für mich ist, als meine Mittel für Austausch seit längerer Zeit so sehr beschränkt sind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Schon in einem früheren Briefe setzte ich Ihnen die jetzigen Verhältnisse meines Departements auseinander; will aber noch einmal jetzt darauf zurückkommen. Selbst aus den täglichen Zeitungen wird Ihnen die Finanzlage der Colonie Victoria während der letzten 2 oder 3 Jahre bekannt geworden sein, u. diese unglücklichen Verhältnisse haben namentlich seit dem Beginn des Jahres 1892 grosse Beschränkungen auch in meiner Anstalt herbeigeführt. Mein Haupt-Augenmerk in einer jungen winterlosen Colonie muss selbstverständlich bei den hiesigen Erfordernissen den ruralen Interessen gewidmet sein; in der That phytographische Arbeiten sind fast Nebensache. — So habe ich denn seit sehr langer Zeit keinen Sammler mehr im Felde, u. was ich durch Amateure erlange, sind meistens nur einzelne Stücke, oft nur Fragmente. Ich selbst habe nicht mehr Zeit für Sammel-Reisen so spät im Leben nach 46 jährigem ununterbrochenen Hiersein. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die überzähligen Exemplare im Herbarium sind in fast allen Fällen längst erschöpft, und was noch etwa da ist zum Weggeben, harrt mühesamer zeitnehmender Benennung. Wenn ich nun auch in Ausnahmsfällen, wie bei den Dilleniaceen, an das normale Hauptherbarium gehen lasse, um für einer speciellen Monographen etwas abzunehmen, so finde ich, dass die typischen Exemplare, welche durch Jahrhunderte die Belege zu meinen phytographischen Werken sein sollen, mutiliert werden, oder dass der Kreis der Formen für Varietäten oder Localitäten gebrochen wird. Die Befolgung eines solchen gewissermassen plündernden Prinzips müsste selbstverständlich zur Entwerthung des ganzen "Main-Herbarium" führen! Dann fehlt mir die für extensive Durchsicht u methodische Aufsuchung von noch etwaigen Doubletten die nothwendige Hülfe, denn meine eigne Zeit ist so besetzt, dass ich nie Ferien nehmen kann u selbst auch jeden Sonntag u Festtag durch lange Stunden durcharbeite, was bei meinem vorgerückten Alter, bei einer jährlich etwa 3000 Briefe erfordernden <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">eigenhändigen </hi>
               </seg>Correspondenz und bei anderen vielseitigen Amtspflichten stets recht angreifend für mich ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie machen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">mir</hi>
               </seg> den Vorwurf, dass in Ihrem bot. Museum die Pflanzen-Arten gesammt Australiens so unvollständig vertreten sind. Ich bin aber mit manchen anderen auch Deutschen u auch hohen bot. Wissenschafts Anstalten ebenfalls im Austausch-Verkehr, leider auch hier u. da verschuldet jetzt und ich bin doch überzeugt, dass eine sehr bedeutende Anzahl australischer u oft seltner Species durch mich im Lauf der Jahre zu Ihrer Anstalt gelangte, kann insoweit aber keiner Vollständigkeit anstreben bei einer Vegetation, die reicher wie die von ganz Europa ist! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mein Ehrgefühl hat mir stets angewiesen, Jedem im Leben gerecht zu werden, u. wenn ich mich bedrängt sah in meinen wissenschftl. Obliegenheiten aus Mangel an Mitteln, trotztdessen dass ich nie speculirte, auf Familien Leben u gesellige Erfreuungen verzichtete, u das letzte was ich von Privat Vermögen hatte, aufgeopfert habe, selbst ohne Reservation meiner 1839 begonnenen Privatsammlungen u Bibliothek, so habe ich versucht doch ein "quid pro quo" zu liefern; — sei es durch Senden meiner Werke, sei es durch grosse Massen unpräparirter Algen, sei es durch Senden von solchen kostbaren höchst seltenen Prachtstücken wie Riesen-Todeen frei abgeliefert dort, auch in Kiel, <name key="Mylitta">Mylitta</name>, Sämeraien &amp;c. Es ist ja durchaus nicht nöthig, dass für erhaltene Herbarien auch als Gegengabe <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Herbarien</hi>
               </seg> gesandt werden müssen; u. bisher ist Jeder damit zufrieden gewesen, wenn ich etwas anderes als Gegengabe wählte oder wählen musste.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Kaufbar sind getrocknete Pflanzen auch für mich hier nicht, einfach aus dem Grunde, weil in diesen Colonien bei dem theueren Leben u theueren Reisen es Niemand bezahlbar finden würde, käufliche Pflanzen-Sammlungen herzustellen, zumal da die weite Übersendung auch die Kosten noch sehr vermehren würde. In letztere Beziehung habe ich seit einiger Zeit in meinem Verkehr mit allen Theilen der Erde die Methode gewählt, durch die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Post</hi>
               </seg> eine Anzahl <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">kleiner Packete</hi>
               </seg> zu senden, was freilich hier jedes auf ½ lb beschränkt. Es ist die einfachste, schnellste, sicherste u billigste Art des Sendens <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">von hier</hi>
               </seg>, u sie hat von noch den Vortheil, dass selbst wenn auch nur wenig zur Hand ist, ich es sofort verschicken kann. So habe ich denn nun für Sie 9 kleine Päckchen packen u auf die Post geben lassen, was freilich nur etwa 180 Arten repräsentirt. Sie werden gewiss den guten Willen anerkennen. Es soll mehr folgen, so wie mehr zu <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">haben</hi>
               </seg> ist! Da dies aber meistens von Umständen abhängt in Bezug auf jährliches Amateur-Sammeln, bitte ich Sie nun ganz besonders, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">weiteres Senden hierher von dort einstweilen einzustellen, bis Sie selbst finden, dass Sie für das von mir Erhaltene ein vollständiges Äquivalent haben</hi>
               </seg>; sonst würden Sie meine Ängstlichkeit noch mehr vergrössern in Bezug auf meine Verpflichtungen zu Ihnen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bedenken Sie auch, da Sie selbst eine so bedeutende Staats-Stellung einnehmen, dass ich seit 1847 naturalisirter Unterthan der englischen Krone bin, und dass es von mir erwartet wird, immer in erster Instanz das grosse brittische National Etablissement von Kew zu versorgen, u dass das brittische Museum auch auf mich Anspruch macht officiell.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich denke, dass diese erneuete Exposition meinen Standpunkt auch bei Ihnen nur ganz klar machen wird, u Sie werden meine Offenheit gewiss ehrenhaft finden. Jedenfalls würde ich es sehr bedauern, wenn das freundliche Verhältniss zu dem ersten Sitz der Pflanzenkunde in der Hauptstadt Deutschlands nicht ein ebenso befriedigendes bliebe, als es so lange mit Al. Braun, Eichler u Ihnen selbst gewesen ist!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">In grösster Hochachtung Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ergebenster</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hoffentlich ist Ihre Reise nach Spanien für Sie eine genussreiche u lehrende gewesen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In den dortigen Anmerkungen des "Census" war offenbar die Transposition zu anderen Generibus häufiger dort vorhandener Arten missverstanden.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 31/1/93.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In acknowledgement of your letter of 22/12/92,<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> highly esteemed Professor, I express my thanks to you for the notification of a new contribution of dried plants to the collections of my institute, though through it I fall even further into debt in respect of your museum, which is so much the more depressing for me as for a long time my means for exchange have been so very limited.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Already in a previous letter I explained the present circumstances of my department to you, but will again now revert to it. Even from the daily newspapers the financial situation of the Colony of Victoria during the last 2 or 3 years will have been known to you, and these unfortunate circumstances have caused large reductions in my institute as well, particularly since the beginning of 1892. My special attention in a young winterless colony in the present exigency must of course be devoted to the rural interests, in fact phytological work is almost a secondary consideration. — So for a long time then I have no longer had a collector in the field, and what I get through amateurs are mostly only single pieces, often only fragments. I have no more time myself for collecting expeditions so late in life, after an uninterrupted presence of 46 years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The surplus specimens in the herbarium in almost all cases are long ago exhausted, and what is still there by any chance to give away awaits laborious, time-consuming naming. Even if now in exceptional cases, as in the case of the <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name>, I go to the normal main herbarium to take something away for one of the special monographers, I find that the typical examples which are to be the record of my phytographical work for centuries are mutilated or that the range of forms for varieties or localities is broken.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In M to A Engler, 20 April 1888 (in this edition s 88-04-20a), Engler was asked to reserve the <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name> for him to monograph in Engler &amp; Prantl (1897-1915). However, in M to A. Engler, 31 May 1892, pressure of work was given as an explanation of not having written it. M to A. Engler, 28 June 1982 (in this edition as 92-06-28a) indicates that M intended to send specimens of this group for the use of Gilg who wrote the monograph, but nothing from M is cited by Gilg (1895); see notes to that letter.</p>
               </note> The consequence of such a to some degree plundering principle must of course lead to the debasement of the whole "main herbarium"! Then I lack the necessary assistance for extensive inspection and methodical search for any possible duplicates, because my own time is so occupied that I can never take holidays and also even work through long hours through every Sunday and holiday, which at my advanced age, with an annual correspondence requiring about 3000 letters <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from my own hand</hi>
               </seg> and with other manifold official duties is always very exhausting for me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You blame <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">me</hi>
               </seg> that the plant species of the whole of Australia are so incompletely represented in your bot. Museum. But I also have exchange dealings with many other German and also great bot. scientific institutions as well, but also unfortunately here and there now indebted; and yet I am convinced that a very significant number of Australian and often rare species reached your institution through me in the course of time, but in this respect cannot aim at completeness in the case of a vegetation that is richer than that of the whole of Europe! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My sense of honour has always directed me to do justice to everyone in life, and if I saw myself pressed in my scientific obligations from lack of means, even though I never speculate, deny myself family life and social pleasures, and have sacrificed the last of what I had of my private means, even without reservation my private collections and library begun in 1839, I have nevertheless tried to give a "quid pro quo"; be it through sending my works, be it through large masses of unprepared algae, be it through the sending of such valuable, very rare splendid pieces as giant <name key="Todea">Todea</name>s delivered free there, even in Kiel, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Mylitta">Mylitta</name>,</seg> seeds &amp;c. It is certainly not at all necessary that for receiving herbaria, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">herbaria</hi>
               </seg> must be sent as a return present as well; and previously everyone has been satisfied with it, if I chose or had to choose something else as a return gift.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Here it is not possible even for me to purchase dried plants, simply because in these colonies with the expensive living and expensive travel no-one would find it payable to make plant collections for sale, especially since the far shipment would also increase the costs even more. In regard to the latter, I have for some time in my dealings with all parts of the world chosen the method of sending a number of <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">small parcels</hi>
               </seg> through the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">post</hi>
               </seg>, which admittedly are restricted to ½ lb here. It is the simplest, quickest, safest and cheapest way of dispatch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">from here</hi>
               </seg>, and it has the advantage that even if only little is available, I can send it off immediately. So I have then had packed 9 small parcels for you now and will have them given to the post, which of course only represents about 180 species. You will certainly acknowledge my good intention. More will follow, as soon as more is to be <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">had</hi>
               </seg>! But since this mostly depends on circumstances respecting annual amateur collecting, I ask you now quite particularly, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">to discontinue further shipments from there to here until even you find that you have a complete equivalent for that received by me</hi>
               </seg>; otherwise you would increase my anxiety even more in respect of my obligations to you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Also consider, since you occupy such a significant state position yourself, that I have been a naturalized subject of the English Crown since 1847 and that I am expected in the first instance always to supply the great British national establishment at Kew, and that the British Museum also makes demands on me officially.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I think that this renewed exposition will just make clear my standpoint even in your case and you will find my frankness certainly honest. In any case I would regret it very much if the friendly relation to the first seat of plant study in the capital of Germany did not remain just as satisfactory as it has been for so long with Al. Braun, Eichler and you yourself!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With greatest respect your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>most humble</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I hope your journey to Spain has been a very enjoyable and instructive one for you.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the annotations to the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Census</seg> made there, obviously the transposition to other genera of species commonly existing there is misunderstood.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Dilleniaceae">Dilleniaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Mylitta">Mylitta</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
