<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 8/1/93. ¶  ¶ By the last weekly post, highly esteemed Professor, I expressed my deepest gratitude to the  ¶  ¶ Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences directly for the enormous honour that was gi...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-01-08-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Kungl. Vetenskapsakademien, Stockholm.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>93.01.08</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 8/1/93. ¶  ¶ By the last weekly post, highly esteemed Professor, I expressed my deepest gratitude to the  ¶  ¶ Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences directly for the enormous honour that was gi...</title>
               <date when="1893-01-08">1893-01-08</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-01-08-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Osmunda</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/3bbd2c34-3d4f-4cb2-85f0-168b1e58b3c8">Bergia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d50ddb57-69c1-4be7-b4fe-f1d8a1594f98">Todea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="60">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="40">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Veit Wittrock</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 8/1/93. ¶  ¶ By the last weekly post, highly esteemed Professor, I expressed my deepest gratitude to the  ¶  ¶ Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences directly for the enormous honour that was gi...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">93.01.08</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Veit Wittrock</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Kungl. Vetenskapsakademien, Stockholm.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne, 8/1/93.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch letzte Wochen-Post, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, sprach ich der Kgl. schwed. Akademie der Wissenschaften direct meine tiefen Dankgefühle aus für die überaus grosse Ehre, welche mir durch die Wahl zum Membr. extran. erwiesen ist, eine Auszeichnung, welche ich zu den höchsten Errungenschaften meines Lebens zähle! Gewiss bin ich </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihnen</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style="">, edler Herr, für diese hohe Gunst grossentheils verpflichtet, und ich möchte daher auch Ihnen speciell meine Danksagung darbringen. Ich werde mich bemühen, die mir gewordene Auszeichnung auch durch Beiträge zu Ihren Sammlungen anzuerkennen, so wie sich von Zeit zu Zeit dazu die Gelegenheit bietet. Getrocknete Pflanzen-Exemplare kann ich in kleinen Packeten am besten durch successive "Mails" senden. Auch will ich nach einer <name key="Todea">Todea</name> suchen in entfernten Waldthälern an Bächen, so gross wie solche sich noch finden lässt. Die letzte, welche ich von den 10 von mir hier in 45 Jahren erlangten Riesen-Exemplaren noch hatte, ist bereits für Prof. Goodale verpackt, als eins der Dankzeichen für meine Wahl — auch in 1892 — an die Stelle von Maximowicz in die grosse amerikanische Akademie. — Ostern ist die beste Zeit, solche Farne mit schweren Stämmen herauszuheben, da dann die Schluchten etwas trockner sind. Ich werde auch nach meiner kürzlichen Wahl in die Kgl. Akademie in Copenhagen, eine Farnsendung dahin im australischen Spätherbst machen; die Stämme kommen dann bei Ihnen in frostfreier Zeit an u. die jungen Triebe haben sich hier um Ostern noch nicht gebildet. <name key="Todea">Todea</name> neben der europäischen <name key="Osmunda">Osmunda</name> ist ein merkwürdiges Object für dortige Gärten. Der Wuchs ist sehr langsam, u. daher das Alter grosser Stämme bei Jahrhunderten zu zählen.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich bin Ihnen zum besonderen Danke verpflichtet, mir den ersten Band der wichtigen Acta Ihres schönen Gartens gesandt zu haben. Es sind eine Menge schöner Abhandlungen, auch prächtige Abbildungen. Ein Portrait von Bergius hatte ich noch nie gesehen, obgleich ich selbst schon vor vielen Jahren 2 <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name>-Arten entdeckt u. beschrieben habe. Ich will versuchen, Ihnen frische <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name> Samen zu verschaffen. Ich sehe, dass Sie bisher überhaupt wenige austral. Pflanzen im Garten haben.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend, der Ihre,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Das Diplom der Akademie ist ein herrliches Document! Ich habe unter Ihrer Adresse dem jungen Grafen Axel. Wachtmeister den Druck des Melb. Columbus-Festes gesandt. Dieser geistreiche u. hochgebildete Edelmann wird gewiss nach seiner Rückkehr von Indien auch bald wieder Stockholm besuchen.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 8/1/93.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>By the last weekly post, highly esteemed Professor, I expressed my deepest gratitude to the <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences directly for the enormous honour that was given to me by the election to foreign membership, an award that I will number among the highest achievements of my life!<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. See Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences to M, 9 November 1892.</p>
               </note> Undoubtedly for the most part I am indebted to <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>, noble Sir, for this high favour, and I would therefore like specially to offer you my expression of thanks. I shall endeavour to acknowledge the award bestowed on me also by contributions to your collections as the opportunity offers from time to time. I can send dried plant specimens in small parcels best through successive 'mails'. I also want to look for a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
               </seg> in distant forest valleys on creeks, as large as they are still to be found. The last that I still had from the ten giant specimens obtained by me here in 45 years is packed ready for Professor Goodale, as one of the tokens of thanks for my election — also in 1892 — to the place of Maximowiz in the great American Academy.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Foreign Honorary Members of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences were 'not to exceed seventy-five' and were 'elected as vacancies occur' (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Proceedings</seg>, vol. 27, pp. 457, 460). M was elected at the Academy's meeting on 15 June 1892 in the place of Carl Maximowicz, a member of the Academy from October 1888, who had died in February 1891; see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Proceedings</seg>, vol. 28, p. 290.</p>
               </note> Easter is the best time to lift out such ferns with heavy trunks, as then the gullies are somewhat drier. I shall also send a consignment of ferns in the late Australian autumn to the Royal Academy in Copenhagen after my recent election into it;<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M had been elected a Foreign Member of the Royal Danish Academy of Sciences in 1890; see M to H. Zeuthen, 3 June 1890 (in this edition as 90-06-03b).</p>
               </note> the trunks then will arrive at your place in frost-free time and the young shoots have not yet formed here at Easter. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
               </seg> together with the European <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Osmunda">Osmunda</name>
               </seg> is a remarkable object for gardens there. The growth is very slow, and therefore the age of large trunks is to be numbered as hundreds of years.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am particularly obliged to you for having sent me the first volume of the important <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Acta</seg> of your beautiful gardens.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Acta horti <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name>ni, </seg>
                     <seg style="">with the alternative title </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Meddelanden från Kongliga Svenska Vetenskaps-Akademiens Trädgård Bergielund</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 1, 1891. </seg>
                     <seg style="">The first part of the volume is dated 1890 and consists of an article, Wittrock (1890), outlining the history of the <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name>n Foundation, including a biographical sketch of the botanist Bergius.</seg>
                     <seg style=""> Wittrock was director of the garden. A copy of the 8-part first volume is in the library of the Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne. </seg>
                  </p>
               </note> There are a lot of fine papers, also splendid illustrations. I had never seen a portrait of Bergius, although many years ago I myself discovered and described two <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name>
               </seg> species. I want to try to supply you with fresh <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name>
               </seg> seeds. I see that up to now you really have few Australian plants in the garden.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">The diploma of the Academy is a splendid document! Under your address I have sent the young Count Axel Wachtmeister the printing of the Melbourne Columbus celebration.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">An account of the festival organized by the Victorian Branch of the Royal Geographical Society of Australasia to mark the fourth centenary of Columbus's landing in America was published in the Society's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions</seg>, vol. 10 (1893), pp. 101-17. The article contained M's address, B93.03.02. A preprint of the account was ready for distribution late in 1892, see B92.13.19. </p>
               </note> This intelligent and highly educated nobleman will undoubtedly visit Stockholm again soon after his return from India.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Bergia">Bergia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Osmunda">Osmunda</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Todea">Todea</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
