<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ An interesting question that perhaps has never before been explained, noble friend, might get its answer through you with the opportunity and means that stand at your disposal in this direction. It...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-11-00i-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>93.11.00i</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ An interesting question that perhaps has never before been explained, noble friend, might get its answer through you with the opportunity and means that stand at your disposal in this direction. It...</title>
               <date when="1893-11">1893-11</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1890-6/1893/93-11-00i-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="57">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="43">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ludwig Wittmack</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ An interesting question that perhaps has never before been explained, noble friend, might get its answer through you with the opportunity and means that stand at your disposal in this direction. It...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">93.11.00i</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Ludwig Wittmack</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is the second item in '</seg>
                     <seg style="">Sprechsaal' [Discussion Room],</seg>
                     <seg style="color: #ff0000; "> </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora</seg>
                     <seg style="">, vol. 43 (1894), p. 32 (B94.01.06). </seg>The correspondent is determined from the structure of the opening sentence, which indicates that this was addressed personally to Wittmack, the editor of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora</seg>. Issues of the journal are not dated but the structure is consistent and this is the first of 24 issues for the year, that is, the first issue for January 1894. The letter is thus dated to late November 1893 as the latest likely date that it could have been sent to have been included in this issue.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine interessante Frage, welche vielleicht noch nie erläutert ist, edler Freund, möchte durch Sie wohl ihre Lösung bekommen, bei den Gelegenheiten und Mitteln, welche Ihnen gerade in dieser Richtung zu Gebote stehen. Es ist diese: Leiden Samen, welche aus warmen Zonen in kältere Länder so geschickt werden, dass solche in der kalten Jahreszeit ankommen? Es ist wohl denkbar, dass Samen von Pflanzen frostfreier Länder leiden können, wenn bei unrichtiger Zeit des Eintreffens solche Samen bedeutenden Kältegraden unterworfen werden. Mag dies auch zum Teil die Ursache sein, warum so oft Samen tropischer Pflanzen in den Gewächshäusern kalter Länder nicht zur Keimung kommen, oder ist Schaden schon entstanden, wenn solche Samen in ungeheizten Magazinen aufbewahrt werden? Sollten noch keine Beobachtungen in dieser Richtung vorliegen, so wäre es wohl des Versuchs wert, Samen von Tropen-Pflanzen der Gefrier-Kälte längere Zeit auszusetzen, und dann zu ermitteln, ob die Keimkraft bei allen, bei einigen oder bei keinen gelitten habe. Nach einigen Experimenten dort werden Sie gewiss in der Gartenflora darüber berichten. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Sie ehrend und Ihnen alles Gute wünschend, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Melbourne</seg>.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An interesting question that perhaps has never before been explained, noble friend, might get its answer through you with the opportunity and means that stand at your disposal in this direction. It is this: Do seeds that are sent from warm zones to colder countries such that they arrive in the cold season, suffer? It is certainly conceivable that seeds of plants from frost-free countries could suffer, if such seeds are subject to significant degrees of cold at the incorrect time of arrival. May this even be the cause in part, why so often seeds of tropical plants do not germinate in glasshouses in cold lands, or has damage already resulted, if such seeds are stored in unheated storehouses? If still no observations in this direction exist, then it would probably be worth trying exposing seeds of tropical plants to the freezing cold for a longer time and then ascertaining whether the germinating power has suffered in all, in some or in none. After some experiments there you will surely report on them in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Gartenflora</seg>.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Honouring you and wishing you well,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Melbourne.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Wittmack added a response below the letter:</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 9pt; margin-left: 0.5in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">Vorläufige Antwort. Theoretisch müsste man annehmen, dass die Samen, wenn sie trocken sind, durch die Kälte nicht leiden. Indess ich will Versuche machen und bitte mir gefl. Samen zu schicken. L. W. [Preliminary Answer. Theoretically one has to assume that the seeds, if they are dry, do not suffer through the cold. However, I will undertake trials and ask to kindly send me seeds.]</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A response from Ed. Richter was published in the next issue, p. 54, reporting that acorns were not shipped unless the weather was mild, and that frozen acorns turned brown inside.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
