<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Clarendon, 30 Oct. 1881. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron! ¶  ¶ I take the liberty of sending you with this mail a further parcel of plants, which were collected in a radius of 2-3 miles. In the previous list ...</title>
            <author>Otto Tepper</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-30-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M39, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>81.10.30</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Otto Tepper</author>
               <title>Clarendon, 30 Oct. 1881. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron! ¶  ¶ I take the liberty of sending you with this mail a further parcel of plants, which were collected in a radius of 2-3 miles. In the previous list ...</title>
               <date when="1881-10-30">1881-10-30</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-30-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Stackhousia linarifolia</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/935e755a-18f3-4e1a-804a-4380de9057e5">Cymodocea antarctica</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/83d92c86-0107-4c54-9eea-2a24c3fc810d">Santalum acuminatum</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/d9da1629-db49-4496-aa9c-0c4bf428303f">Erodium cicutarium</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/7875b303-cd9e-40dd-9894-304dbe0c29b9">Styphelia humifusa</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/666b73e7-176a-4074-aa42-6c48e2a73379">Banksia ornata</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Clarendon, 30 Oct. 1881. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron! ¶  ¶ I take the liberty of sending you with this mail a further parcel of plants, which were collected in a radius of 2-3 miles. In the previous list ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">81.10.30</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Otto Tepper</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M39, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Clarendon, 30. Oct 81.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter Hr Baron!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit dieser Post erlaube ich mir Ihnen ein weiteres Packet Pflanzen zu übermitteln, welche in einem Radius von 2-3 Miles gesammelt wurden. In der vor. Liste vermisse ich Nos. 33, 58, 58; sind dieselben weiterer Untersuchung vorbehalten worden?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No.74. Styphelia sp. (in Frucht) hatte bereits abgeblüht u. kommt nur sehr vereinzelt im Sand-Scrub vor. In Bezug auf <name key="Styphelia%20humifusa">Styphelia humifusa</name> scheint es mir, als ob unter der Benennung <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">zwei</hi>
               </seg>, wenn nicht drei verschiedene Pflanzen begriffen wären, sehr verschieden im Habitus. Eine davon, wie ich glaube, die typische Pflanze, hat bei weitem breitere und längere Blätter u. nicht so dicht stehend als die andern, auch sind die Früchte von sphäroidischer Form, meistens dunkel gestreift. Eine der beiden Andern kriecht wie die Erstere, hat aber sehr schmale und dicht gestelte Blättchen, während die Früchte meistens globuler u. cylindrisch-globuler, kleinere u. härter sind. Beide Arten kommen in sandigem Boden oft neben einander vor, wo diese Unterschiede sehr deutlich hervortreten. Die letzte Art ist stets aufrecht und steif u. hat harte, fast ungeniessbare Früchte. Dieselbe scheint hier herum nicht vorzukommen, war aber in der Peninsula auf gewissen Stellen nicht selten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit den Stackhousien geht es mir ähnlich. Die typische <name key="Stackhousia%20linarifolia">Stackhousia linarifolia</name> tritt als kleine Pflanze in offenen Feldern, etc., auf, stirbt nach der Fruchtreife, wie mir scheint vollkommen ab, da die Wurzel so dünn u. trocken, zu der Periode sich findet, dass eine Wiederbelebung fast unmöglich erscheint; auch finden sich selten mehr als 1, 2 od. 3 Stengel dicht an einander gedrängt, da die Steifheit derselben keine Ausweichung zulässt. Diese findet sich hier, wie auf der Peninsula unter denselben Verhältnissen u. derselben Form.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ausser dieser findet sich aber eine andre (143), welche in der Form derselben ähnelt, aber viel höher ist u. zähreiche, nicht sehr steife konvergirende hat, alle aus einer langen, starken perennirenden Wurzel entspringend, u. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg> bis auf die Wurzel alljährlich absterben. Die Blumen sind deutlich gelb, stehen sehr dicht u. sind sehr zahlreich, besonders nahe der Spitze. Eine dritte Art, ähnlich der vorigen in Stengel u. Wurzelbildung, Höhe u. Ausdauer in gewissem Masse zeigt <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sehr</hi>
               </seg> biegsame Stengel, welche in anmuthigen <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Kurven</hi>
               </seg> sich auseinander neigen u. die Blumen alle an der unteren Seite herabhängend haben; dieselben sind hell gelb und blühen etwas später als die vorigen. Die Blätter der letzteren sind kleiner u. noch weniger zahlreich u. entfernter als bei No.2, während No.1 dieselben sehr <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dicht</hi>
               </seg> gestellt zeigt. Ich habe in Pflanzen der letzten Art von 12-20 Stengel gezählt u. kommt dieselbe auch im Scrub der Peninsula vor, aber nicht die zweite. Beiliegend ein Stengel der dritten Art (144).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Re <name key="Cymodocea%20antarctica">Cymodocea antarctica</name> bemerkten Sie, dass dieselbe doch jedenfalls perennirend sein müsse. Das mag wohl sein, in der Lokalität aber, die meinen Beobachtungen zugänglich war, schien das nicht der Fall. Denn von der Jetty aus, u. bei gelegentlichen Bootfahrten liessen sich während u. nach der Fruchtbildung, d.h. am Mutterstock, sehr grosse Exemplare zahlreich bemerken, während sich im Frühjahr kein einziges auf eben diesen Plätzen vorfand, sondern nur die jungen, anwurzelnden Pflänzchen in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">allen</hi>
               </seg> Stadien der Wurzelbildung von der ersten Wurzelkeimung bis zur Rhizombildung. Ich habe eine Serie von Abbildungen der Adelaider Royal Society geliefert, die in den diesjährigen Transactions erscheinen werden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No. 141 Erodium sp. Fand sich auf einer Stelle in den Hügeln, wo ein Feuer die Vegetation geklärt hätte u. schien mir in Blumen u. Fruchtbildung abweichend von dem europäischen und dem einheimischen E. cicutarium zu sein. No. 120 ist überall auf Berg u. Thal, in Feld u. Scrub verbreitet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Könnten Sie mir freundlichst den Namen der Hecken-Acacie oder Kangaroo Thorn's mittheilen. Dieselbe kommt in den Bergen am South Para einheimisch vor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Soweit wie ich mich erinnern kann, kommt eine Banksia mit rothen "Cones" in Scrubpartien in der Umgegend von Tilley's Swamp im Südosten (S.A.) vor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Neulich wurde mir mitgetheilt, dass die hiesigen Eingebornen <name key="Santalum%20acuminatum">Santalum acuminatum</name>, welches sich hier vereinzelt findet, "Yacca" nannten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Eine weitere Sammlung Pflanzen werde ich nächstens senden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Studium der Natur ist mir die einzige Freude u. Erholung bei den unerquicklichen Verhältnissen in denen wir Lehrer uns befinden. Wie gross Gott ist, kann nur der erkennen, oder vielmehr ahnen, der sich eingehend mit Seinen Werken beschäftigt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Hoffentlich erhalten Sie den Sak "<name key="Banksia%20ornata">Banksia ornata</name>" Früchte in gutem Zustande u. dieselben so wie Sie sie wünschen. Ich habe meistens solche verpackt, die sich an älteren Aesten, u. möglichst reifen Samen enthaltend, fanden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Meine Auslagen sind so gering gewesen, dass Sie keine Rechnung zu erwarten haben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit besten Wünschen für Ihr Wohlergehen habe ich die Ehre zu verbleiben</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ganz der Ihrige</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J.G.Otto Tepper.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Clarendon, 30 Oct. 1881.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Highly esteemed Baron!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I take the liberty of sending you with this mail a further parcel of plants, which were collected in a radius of 2-3 miles. In the previous list I found Nos. 33, 58, 58 missing; have these been held back for further examination?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No. 74. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Styphelia</seg> sp. (in fruit) had already finished flowering and occurs only as very isolated plants in the sand-scrub. Concerning <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Styphelia%20humifusa">Styphelia humifusa</name>
               </seg>, it seems to me that <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">two</hi>
               </seg> if not three different plants, very different in their habit, were included under the one name. One of them, which I think is the typical plant, has considerably broader and longer leaves that do not stand as closely together as in the others, and the shape of the fruit is spherical, usually dark striped. One of the other two creeps, like the first, but has very narrow and closely-set little leaves, while the fruit are usually globular or cylindrical-globular, smaller and harder. Both kinds occur in sandy soil, often side by side, which makes these differences particularly apparent. The third kind is always erect and stiff and has hard, almost inedible fruit. This one does not seem to occur around here, but was not uncommon in certain spots on the Peninsula.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Yorke Peninsula, SA, where Tepper used to live.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With the Stackhousiae I find myself in similar difficulties. The typical <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Stackhousia%20linarifolia">Stackhousia linarifolia</name>
               </seg> occurs as a small plant in open fields, etc., and, it seems to me, dies off completely after the fruit is ripe, as the roots at that time are so thin and dry that it seems almost impossible that they could come back to life. Also it has rarely more than 1, 2 or 3 stems standing closely crowded together, as their stiffness does not permit any divergence. It is found here as well as on the Peninsula, in the same habitat and in the same form.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Apart from this there is another one (143) that resembles the first in form but grows much taller and has numerous not very stiff convergent stems, all of them arising from a long, strong, perennial root, and it does <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> die back annually down to the roots. The flowers are distinctly yellow, stand very closely together, and are very numerous, especially near the apex. A third kind, similar to a certain degree to the preceding in stem and root formation, height and life span, produces <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">very</hi>
               </seg> flexible stems that diverge in graceful <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">curves</hi>
               </seg>, with the flowers all pendulous from the lower side. These are bright yellow and flower a little later than the other two. The leaves of this last form are smaller and even less numerous and further apart than in No. 2, while in No. 1 they are very close together. I have counted from 12 to 20 stems in plants of the third kind. It occurs also in the scrub on the Peninsula, but the second form does not. Enclosed is a stem of the third form (144).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You remarked re <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Cymodocea%20antarctica">Cymodocea antarctica</name>
               </seg> that it would have to be perennial. That may be so; however it did not seem to be the case at the locality where I made my observations.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to O. Tepper, 5 November 1881.</p>
               </note> From the jetty, and also during occasional outings on a boat, I could observe that during and after the formation of the fruit, i.e. on the parent plant, there were numerous very large specimens, while in spring not a single one could be found in the same places. Instead there were only the young rooting seedlings in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> stages of root formation, from the first germination right through to the formation of rhizomes. I have handed a series of illustrations to the Adelaide Royal Society<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Royal Society of South Australia.</p>
               </note> that will appear in this year's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Transactions</seg>.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Tepper (1882).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No. 141. <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Erodium</seg> sp. was found at a place in the hills where a fire had cleared the vegetation, and it seemed to me to differ in both flowers and fructification from the European and the local <seg style="font-style: italic; ">E. cicutarium</seg>. No. 120 is widespread everywhere in mountains and valleys, in fields and scrub.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Could you kindly let me know the name of the hedge-acacia or kangaroo thorn. It is indigenous in the mountains along the South Para.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>South Para River, SA.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As far as I can remember, a <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Banksia</seg> with red "cones" does occur in scrub areas in the vicinity of Tilley's Swamp in the south-east (S.A.).</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I was told recently that the local natives call <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Santalum%20acuminatum">Santalum acuminatum</name>
               </seg>, of which occasional plants are found here, "Yacca".</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I shall send a further collection of plants shortly.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The study of nature is my only joy and recreation in the disagreeable conditions in which we teachers find ourselves. How great God is can be recognised, or rather guessed at, only by someone who is earnestly engaged in the study of His works.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope you will receive the bag with the "<seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Banksia%20ornata">Banksia ornata</name>
               </seg>" fruit in good condition and find them as you desired. I have packed mainly those found on older branches and containing seed as ripe as possible.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My expenses were so small that you have no need to expect an account.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With best wishes for your well-being, I have the honour to remain,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Wholly Yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J. G. Otto Tepper.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Banksia%20ornata">Banksia ornata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Cymodocea%20antarctica">Cymodocea antarctica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Erodium%20cicutarium">Erodium cicutarium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Santalum%20acuminatum">Santalum acuminatum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stackhousia%20linarifolia">Stackhousia linarifolia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Styphelia%20humifusa">Styphelia humifusa</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
