<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ For a long time I have owed you a letter, noble friend, not only to thank you for the naming of several lichens, but also to express my acknowledgement to you for the sending of several of your pap...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-06-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Conservatoire et Jardin botanique, Geneva.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>81.10.06</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title> ¶ For a long time I have owed you a letter, noble friend, not only to thank you for the naming of several lichens, but also to express my acknowledgement to you for the sending of several of your pap...</title>
               <date when="1881-10-06">1881-10-06</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-06-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Coenogonium</term>
               <term>Oedogonium</term>
               <term>Peltigera</term>
               <term>Parmelia</term>
               <term>Usnea</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Jean Müller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ For a long time I have owed you a letter, noble friend, not only to thank you for the naming of several lichens, but also to express my acknowledgement to you for the sending of several of your pap...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">81.10.06</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Jean Müller</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Conservatoire et Jardin botanique, Geneva.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">6/10/81.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Seit langer Zeit schuldige ich Ihnen einen Brief, edler Freund, nicht nur um Ihnen für die Benennung mehrerer Flechten zu danken, sondern auch um Ihnen für die Uebersendung mehrerer Ihrer Schriften meine Anerkennung auszusprechen. Ganz besonders haben mich Ihre Beobachtungen über die weite Verbreitung der Microgonidien im Flechten-Reiche interessiert, und dass die unnatürliche Annahme des Paratismus von Pilzen auf Algenlagern um Flechten zu bilden somit über den Haufen gestossen ist. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leighton und Cook haben auch nie an die Möglichkeit einer so phantastischen Composition geglaubt. Der arme Cook schreibt mir gerade, dass er durch Überarbeitung von Paralysis befallen sei. Ich werde Hooker bitten, ihn einige Monate nach einem gesunden Platz Central-Amerikas zu senden, damit er auf ruhiger Seereise sich völlig erhole und mit mycologischen Schätzen beladen zurückkehre. Der arme Harvey hätte auch noch viele Jahre leben können, hätten seine Schwäger, 2 australische enorm reiche Heerden Besitzer, ihm eine Unabhängigkeit gegeben, um in einem warmen Clima sich ruhig seinen Lieblingsstudien hinzugeben!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Doch um zu den Microgonidien zurückzukehren. — Sind diese Organe in den Flechten identisch in Function und Bau mit den gleichgenannten Körperchen von <name key="Oedogonium">Oedogonium</name>, welche Antheridien bilden? Ist etwas Aehnliches durch die Microgonidia oder zuletzt Gonidia erwirkt? Was Sie über das Vorkommen von sowohl Microgonidien als Gonidien in <name key="Coenogonium">Coenogonium</name> sagen, ist sehr interessant. Ich habe es recht bedauert, besonders in letzteren Jahren, dass ich den niederen Acotyledonen nicht einen Theil meiner Zeit für wirklich untersuchende Arbeiten widmete; aber die vieljährigen Reisen liessen es zuerst nicht zu; dann kamen die schweren Direktur-Arbeiten um eine neue u. grosse Anstalt unter ungewöhnlichen Schwierigkeiten zu begründen; dann die Bearbeitung oder Durcharbeitung von etwa 8000 Cotyledonen-Pflanzen des ganzen Australlandes, u. dann war ich lange unter dem Eindruck, dass viel mehr Flechten cosmopolitar seien, als sich später herausgestellt hat. Dazu die Abwesenheit irgend eines Universalwerkes seit Acharius' Zeit, da selbst Nylander, von dem wir alle es erwarteten seine Synopsis nicht einmal halb durchführte. Und welche Fülle neuer Formen (Arten möchte ich kaum sagen) hat das letzte Dutzend Jahre zusammengeführt, um die beiden Hefte Nylanders schon ganz unvollständig zu machen. Sie werden manchmal gelächelt haben, wenn ich Ihnen ganz gewöhnliche <name key="Usnea">Usnea</name>, <name key="Peltigera">Peltigera</name>, <name key="Parmelia">Parmelia</name> Arten usw. zusandte, die ich vor 40 Jahren genau kannte nach dem damaligen Stande der Lichenologie; aber ich habe nur eine vage Idee über die Artengrenzen, welche in der Jetztzeit angenommen sind nach anderen Fructifications Prinzipien, u. da selbst gewöhnliche Flechten oft neue Standorte hier geben, um die geographische Verbreitung zu verfolgen, so halte ich am Besten, Ihnen selbst das Allergewöhnlichste zukommen zu lassen, zumal da weite Strecken Australiens, besonders die mehr centralen Gegenden ebenso arm an Flechten als an Moosen u. Pilzen sind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit den besten Wünschen für Ihr Wohlsein und die Lösung Ihrer grossen wissenschaftlichen Lebens-Aufgaben, bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Werden Sie Ihre grossen Wissenschafts-Arbeiten krönen, indem Sie uns einen Acharius der Jetztzeit liefern?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Neulich hat mich auch eine Schweizer Gesellschaft zum Mitglied erwählt, es war die geographische Gesellschaft in St. Gallen, worüber ich mich recht gefreut habe.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; text-align: end; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="de">6/10/81.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>For a long time I have owed you a letter, noble friend, not only to thank you for the naming of several lichens, but also to express my acknowledgement to you for the sending of several of your papers. Your observations on the wide distribution of microgonidia in the lichen kingdom, and that the unnatural acceptance of parasitism by fungi on the algal thallus in order to form lichens is consequently overthrown, have interested me exeedingly. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Leighton and Cook<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. M. C. Cooke.</p>
               </note> have also never believed in the possibility of such a fantastic composition. Poor Cook just wrote to me that he is attacked by paralysis through overwork. I shall ask Hooker to send him for some months to a healthy place in Central America, so that he will completely recover on the quiet sea voyage and return laden with mycological treasures. Poor Harvey would have also been able to live many more years, had his brothers-in-law, two enormously rich Australian cattle owners, given him an independence, to devote himself quietly to his favourite study in a warm climate!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>But to return to the microgonidia. — Are these organs in the lichens identical in function and form to the similarly-named bodies of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Oedogonium">Oedogonium</name>
               </seg>, which form antheridia? Is there something similar brought about by the microgonidia or ultimately gonidia? What you say about the occurrence of microgonidia as well as gonidia in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Coenogonium">Coenogonium</name>
               </seg> is very interesting. I have regretted it very much, particularly in latter years, that I did not devote a part of my time to the lower Acotyledons for really investigative work; but the many years of travelling did not at first permit it, then came the heavy directorial work to found a new and large department under unusual difficulties, then the treatment or working through of about 8,000 cotyledenous plants of the Australian continent, and then I was long under the impression that many more lichens were cosmopolitan than has later turned out. In addition the absence of any universal work since Acharius's time, since even Nylander from whom we all expected it accomplished not even half in his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Synopsis.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Acharius (1814) or Acharius (1803), both of which are in the library at MEL, at least one of the copies of the 1803 work being known to have been owned by M; Nylander (1858-69).</p>
               </note> And what abundance of new forms (species I would scarcely like to say) has the last dozen years brought together to make both the parts of Nylander already quite incomplete. You will sometimes have smiled when I sent you quite common <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Usnea">Usnea</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Peltigera">Peltigera</name>
               </seg>, <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Parmelia">Parmelia</name>
               </seg> species and so on, that I knew well 40 years ago according to the then state of lichenology, but I have only a vague idea about the species boundaries that are accepted at the present time according to other principles of fructification, and since even common lichens often give new localities here, to pursue the geographical distribution I thought it best to have even the most common of all come to you, especially since wide stretches of Australia, particularly the more central regions, are just as poor in lichens as in mosses and fungi.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With best wishes for your well-being and the resolution of your great scientific life's work, I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Will you crown your great scientific works by producing an Acharius of the present time for us?</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Recently a Swiss society has also elected me a member, it was the Geographical Society in St. Gallen, about which I am very pleased.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See Ostschweizerische geographisch-commercielle Gesellschaft to M, 2 December 1880.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Oedogonium">Oedogonium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Coenogonium">Coenogonium</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Usnea">Usnea</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Peltigera">Peltigera</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Parmelia">Parmelia</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
