<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>7/10/81. ¶  ¶ Best thanks, dear Mr Harris, for your attention to the Livistona-palms. It seems to me a pity that the bower was removed, as it had no monetary value, and the fern- and palm-groups might...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-07a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>G14439, box 20, VPRS 619 Secretary's correspondence files, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>81.10.07a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>7/10/81. ¶  ¶ Best thanks, dear Mr Harris, for your attention to the Livistona-palms. It seems to me a pity that the bower was removed, as it had no monetary value, and the fern- and palm-groups might...</title>
               <date when="1881-10-07">1881-10-07</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-07a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Joseph Harris</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">7/10/81. ¶  ¶ Best thanks, dear Mr Harris, for your attention to the Livistona-palms. It seems to me a pity that the bower was removed, as it had no monetary value, and the fern- and palm-groups might...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">81.10.07a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Joseph Harris</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="en">G14439, box 20, VPRS 619 Secretary's correspondence files, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">7/10/81.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Best thanks, dear Mr Harris, for your attention to the Livistona-palms. It seems to me a pity that the bower was removed, as it had no monetary value, and the fern- and palm-groups might thus under shelter have remained an ornament to the environs of the Exhibition-building. You will agree with me, that though they may live where they are, they would unprotected not form sightly objects. Can the bower be put up again? The palms are once rooted &amp; established where they are; if as part of the garden plants round the Exhibition-building they cannot come under whatever horticultural surveillance is available there, then certainly it would be best to take them to the well sheltered gully of the Fitzroy-Park, but that should be done with the utmost of care. These Livistonas have now made young rootlets &amp; ought to lift with a good ball of earth. Still Palms cannot be moved in an upgrown state, as you are aware, without risk. Thus after my leaving the bot Garden my 2 magnificent specimens of Ptychosperma and Livistona were ruthless destroyed, after have been 16 years ago planted by me in my Palm house, in not even so much precaution in removal being used as to cut merely the outmost roots &amp; lift the main roots slightly and then leaving the Palms on the spot in the Palmhouse, til they had formed new rootlets, with a fair chance of making the moving of the Palms to an other spot successful, without sacrificing the growth of 16 years. Wendland in Herrenhausen, when his Livistona, planted in the King of England's Palm House in Hanover 120 years ago, became too tall, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">sunk</hi>
               </seg> it an other 20 feet successfully &amp; thus preserved such a treasure. Of course, if I had not given order 6 month previous to lift the roots of the Palms, (now in the Exhibition ground) in the forests &amp; at once to fill up the earth again, so that the Palms could repair easily the damage done in loosening their roots, we could not have them transferred in a living state from backwoods of New South Wales to Melbourne.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Trusting that your skill &amp; kind interest in these palms will save them from danger, I remain regardfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. von Mueller.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Joseph Harris, MP, forwarded this letter to A. Morrah, Secretary for Lands, suggesting how the palms should be moved and that they would be best sent to the Botanic Gardens; see J. Harris to A. Morrah, 8 October 1881 (G14439, box 20, VPRS 619 Secretary's correspondence files, VA 538 Department of Crown Lands and Survey, Public Record Office, Victoria). His suggestions were accepted by the Department of Lands. At the end of October, W. Guilfoyle, Curator of the Botanic and Domain Gardens, reported that the palms had been planted in the fern gully; see, in the same file, W. Guilfoyle to A. Morrah, 31 October 1881.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Prior to this, Guilfoyle had responded to M's criticism in a memorandum to Morrah (which he mistakenly dated '17.9.81', instead of 17 October): 'The fern gully would be the most suitable place for these palms as it is well sheltered and there is an abundance of shade &amp; moisture. The specimens however are not very <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">healthy</hi>
                     </seg> looking, and there will certainly be some risk in removing them to the Gardens successfully. If I am to take them I will exercise the greatest possible care in transplanting, and do my very utmost to save them. I observe that the Baron remarks that two palms were "ruthless destroyed"! They were the most miserable things I ever beheld and had actually forced up and broken the roof of the old Palm house to the danger of other far more rare and beautiful plants. Will you kindly say whether I am to have the tree ferns and Musa also, for the Gully in Gardens. There will be no risk about <seg style="">
                        <hi rend="underline">these</hi>
                     </seg>, as they can be very easily lifted &amp; transplanted. The sooner they are all removed the better, as they are suffering for want of shelter.' Approval of Guilfoyle's requests was minuted the next day.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
