<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Beechworth, ¶  16 October 1881. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron, ¶  ¶ I have just returned home from a short journey, to report to you somewhat more precisely about the  ¶ Eucalyptus ¶  tree callled 'Turpenti...</title>
            <author>Carl Falck</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-16-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>RB MSS M1, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>81.10.16</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Carl Falck</author>
               <title>Beechworth, ¶  16 October 1881. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron, ¶  ¶ I have just returned home from a short journey, to report to you somewhat more precisely about the  ¶ Eucalyptus ¶  tree callled 'Turpenti...</title>
               <date when="1881-10-16">1881-10-16</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-10-16-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/22ad8546-8f00-4999-9b20-e40d11229ad5">Eucalyptus</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Beechworth, ¶  16 October 1881. ¶ Highly esteemed Baron, ¶  ¶ I have just returned home from a short journey, to report to you somewhat more precisely about the  ¶ Eucalyptus ¶  tree callled 'Turpenti...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">81.10.16</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Carl Falck</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">RB MSS M1, Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS found with a specimen of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
                     </seg>(MEL1606639), a collection with closed buds. MS annotation by M: 'Beantw | 22/10/81' [Answered 22/10/81]. Letter not found.</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Two separate notes by Falck found with the collection read: 'No 3. Branch from Tree one foot diameter Turpentine tree.', and 'Ich habe vergessen im Briefe zu erwähnen im welchem Alter der Turpentine zu erst blüht mehrere die diesen Baum in der Nähe haben sagen mir dass die Sapling blühen wenn sie von 8 bis 10 Jahre alt sind. C. F. Falck.' [I have forgotten to mention in the letter at what age the turpentine first flowers. Several people who have this tree near them tell me that the saplings first flower when they are 8 to 10 years old. C. F. Falck.]</p>
               </note>Beechworth Oct. 16n 1881.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochgeehrter H E. Baron!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Soeben komme ich zu Hause, von einer kleinen Reise um über den <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> Baum, hier Turpentine genannt etwas genauer zu berichten, ich glaube aber das der Brief nicht mit dem ersten (6 a.m.) morgen Zuge abgehen will, weil die Mail Abends 7 Uhr geschlossen wird. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Blüthen</hi>
               </seg> von diesem Baum konnte ich erst heute finden ich ging nach einem andern Platze wo der Boden mehr <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">reicher</hi>
               </seg> war fand mehrere von diesen Bäumen in voller Blüthe Ich schicke Ihnen bei Railway Train eine kleine Kiste mit Zweige mit Samenkapseln ein und zwei Jährig Zweige mit aufgeblüthen Blumen und geschlossenen Kapseln (Blüthen drei Tage alt) Zweige von ganz jungen, und Zweige von etwas älteren Saplings, wenn Sie gleich zur Station schicken, so werden Sie die Blüthen ziemlich frisch bekommen Die verschiedenen Zweige habe ich mit Zettel beklebt und bemerkt so kennen Sie selbst sehen die verschiedenen Alter der Blätter und Form derselben, einen jüngeren Sapling denn den wo ich die Zweige abnahm konnte ich nicht finden, höchstwahrscheinlich vom Vieh abgefressen, es war den Winter hindurch nirgends wo Gras. No 1 Zweige, sind die Spitze (der lange Zweig) der kurze Zweig der untere Ausschuss ungefähr 3 Fuss von der Erde von einem Sapling ungefähr 7 Fuss hoch ganz grade die Rinde am Stam schon fasserig oben glatt. No 2 Zweige 15 Fuss hoch, von Sapling das heisst diese Zweige sind 6 Fuss von der Erde die Oberen waren mehr oder weniger von Käfer zerfressen No 3 Zweige mit Blüthen von einem gesunden graden Baume etwa 1 Fuss Durchmesser oder 1 Fuss 3 Zoll, Blüthen aber nur unten herum sehr voll oben keine. No 4 Zweige mit Samenkapseln von einem alten hohlen Baume 3 Fuss Durchmesser. Bei diesem Art Baume fangen die Aeste schon 10 bis 15 Fuss von der Erde an, habe noch nie einen längeren Stamm gesehen ohne so niedrige Aeste, die unteren Aeste sind gewöhnlich sehr krumm gewachsen nach der Erde zu hängend immer aber sehr dünne Aeste im Verhältniss zum Stamm, <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle Aeste</hi>
               </seg> mit faseriger Rinde bewachsen mit Ausnahme der äussersten jüngsten Spitzen der Baum hat die Höhe wie die anderen <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name> um ihn herum zeichnet sich aber aus durch die Farbe der Blätter, und das eigenthümliche Roth der Rinde man kann die Blüthen sehr weit davon schon richen sehr süss, der Geruch ändert sich aber wenn die Blüthen älter werden, ich habe gefunden dass dieser Baum weit in Sommer hinein blüht, die Blüthen sehr lange hält, der Geruch der Blüthen aber in einem förmlichen Gestank übergeht schärfer wie der Blue Gum, wenn man die fasserige Rinde etwas davon in der Hand reib, so hat es den Geruch ähnlich wie Turpentine. Das Holz wird nicht zu Nutzholz hier verbraucht es spaltet nie gerade und ist sehr kurz im Grain. Ein Splitter erzählte mir man könnte einen Fenzrail vors Knie zerbrechen von diesem Turpentine tree, ich glaube aber, wenn zu Bretter zerschnitten es zeigt hübsche Adern wenn Polliert. Ich schickte einen Block mit den anderen Blöcken von hier im Jahre 1878 mit wo die Nummer XVII auf einem Ende eingestämmt ist. Der Boden wo dieser Baum wächst ist <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">armer</hi>
               </seg> Granit Boden sehr poröse. Meine Kinder haben einige Pilze aber nichst besonderes Neues, ich werde sie mit beifügen, Moose haben noch <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">keine Frucht</hi>
               </seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In Hinsicht der Seidenzucht so muss ich versuchen, dass ich auch weisse Seidenraupen bekomme, oder vielmehr Raupen die die weisse Seide spinnen, denn die habe sind alle die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">gelbe Seide</hi>
               </seg> spinnen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Freundlichst grüssend verbleibe ich als</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihr</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>ergebener</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. F. Falck.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">P.S.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bei Ihrem letzten Briefe vom 10 d. M. war ein Versuch am Couvert gemacht um selbigen zu öffnen als wie, wenn jemand den Finger unter der Ueberklappe des Couvert gesteckt hatte an der Seite, es stand rund auseinander.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">C. F. F. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Beechworth,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vic.</p>
               </note> 16 October 1881.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Highly esteemed Baron,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have just returned home from a short journey, to report to you somewhat more precisely about the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
               </seg> tree callled 'Turpentine' here. But I believe that the letter will not go with the first morning train at 6 a.m., because the mail closes at 7 o'clock at night.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I could not find <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">flowers</hi>
               </seg> of this tree until today. I went to a different place, where the soil is a little <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">richer</hi>
               </seg>, and found several of these trees in full bloom. I am sending you by rail a small box containing branches with seed capsules, one and two year old branches with open flowers and with closed buds (flowers are three days old), and branches of very young and of older saplings. If you send for them to the station at once, you will receive the flowers in fairly fresh condition. I have glued tags <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to the various branches and marked them, so you can see for yourself the various ages of the leaves and their shapes. I could not find a younger sapling than the one from which I took the branches, they were probably eaten up by cattle, there was no grass anywhere during winter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No 1: branches from the tips (the long branch), and the short branch a lower shoot about 3 feet above ground level, taken from a sapling approximately 7 feet high, completely straight, the bark on the trunk already stringy, smooth at the top. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No 2: branches from a sapling, 15 feet high, that is, these branches are from about 6 feet above ground level, the upper branches were more or less eaten by beetles.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No 3: branches with flowers from a healthy straight tree, about 1 foot in diameter, or 1 foot and 3 inches; flowers very dense, but only on the lower branches, none at the top.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>No 4: branches with fruit from an old hollow tree, 3 feet in diameter. On these sort of trees the branches start already 10 to 15 feet above ground level; I have never seen a longer trunk without such low branches. The lower branches are usually very crooked and pendulous, but always very thin in relation to the trunk. <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">All the branches</hi>
               </seg> are covered with stringy bark except the outermost, youngest tips. The tree is of the same height as the other eucalypts around it, but is distinct in the colour of its leaves and the peculiar red of the bark. You can smell the flowers already from quite a distance away, their perfume is very sweet. But the smell changes, when the flowers get older. I have found that this tree flowers well into summer. It holds its flowers for a long time, but the perfume of the flowers changes to a veritable stench, stronger than the Blue Gum. If one rubs some of the stringy bark between one's hands, it has a smell similar to turpentine. The wood is not used as commercial timber here, it never splits straight and has a very short grain. A timber splitter told me, that it is possible to break a fence rail made of this turpentine tree across one's knee. But I believe that, when cut into boards and polished, it comes up in <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>a very nice grain. I sent a block of it, together with other wood blocks from here, in 1878, with the number XVII carved into one end of it. The soil, where this tree grows, is <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">poor</hi>
               </seg> granite soil, very porous.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My children have collected a few fungi, but nothing particularly new. I will enclose them. Mosses are not yet in fruit.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In regard to silk culture, I must try and also get some white silk worms, or rather, silk worms which spin the white silk, because I have only those which spin <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">yellow silk</hi>
               </seg>. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With friendly greetings I remain</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>devoted</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>C. F. Falck.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">P. S.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>An attempt had been made to open the envelope of your last letter of the 10th inst.,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</seg>
                  </p>
               </note> as if someone had pushed his finger under the flap of the envelope at the side; there was a gaping round opening.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">C.F.F.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus">Eucalyptus</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
