<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>12/11/81 ¶  ¶ It is already after midnight, dear Mr Tepper, and I am very tired, but I'll still begin a long letter. ¶  ¶ First of all  ¶ Wurmbea ¶  (or  ¶ Wurmbsea ¶ ) ¶ , to which  ¶ Anguillaria ¶  ...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-11-12-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>State Herbarium of South Australia, Plant Biodiversity Centre, Adelaide.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>81.11.12</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>12/11/81 ¶  ¶ It is already after midnight, dear Mr Tepper, and I am very tired, but I'll still begin a long letter. ¶  ¶ First of all  ¶ Wurmbea ¶  (or  ¶ Wurmbsea ¶ ) ¶ , to which  ¶ Anguillaria ¶  ...</title>
               <date when="1881-11-12">1881-11-12</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-11-12-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Anguillaria biglandulosa</term>
               <term>Anguillaria uniflora</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/4986f096-0923-4a4b-8d65-fbb209ae0042">Eucalyptus viminalis</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/dee19e49-779c-470b-81ce-59f9303589fb">Wurmbea dioica</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/ed621f0a-383a-4add-8566-ee26494fd74f">Stackhousia</term>
               <term>Wurmbsea</term>
               <term ref="https://vicflora.rbg.vic.gov.au/flora/taxon/eac71775-0f64-4b0b-a201-2b529e9cf277">Banksia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="49">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="51">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Otto Tepper</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">12/11/81 ¶  ¶ It is already after midnight, dear Mr Tepper, and I am very tired, but I'll still begin a long letter. ¶  ¶ First of all  ¶ Wurmbea ¶  (or  ¶ Wurmbsea ¶ ) ¶ , to which  ¶ Anguillaria ¶  ...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">81.11.12</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Otto Tepper</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">State Herbarium of South Australia, Plant Biodiversity Centre, Adelaide.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter marked by Tepper: ' Reply 22.11.81'. Letter not found.</p>
               </note>12/11/81</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist schon nach Mitternacht, lieber Herr Tepper, und ich bin recht müde, aber ich will doch einen langen Brief beginnen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Zunächst <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Wurmbea (oder <name key="Wurmbsea">Wurmbsea</name>), wozu Anguillaria als Section gehört. Drei Formen sind in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihren</hi>
               </seg> Colonie zu <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>unterscheiden, welche RBr. specifisch hielt. 1. Die gewöhnliche W.(A) dioica mit meistens aber nicht immer eingeschlechtigen Blüten; 2. die seltenen A. uniflora mit 1-2 Blüthen meistens bisexual; 3. die A. biglandulosa mit meist mehreren bisexualen Blüthen und mehr glandulöser Querbinde der Sepalen; letztere ist bei Ihnen die Hauptform im Norden; ich sah sie 1851 am Flinders's Range, Elder's Range &amp;c. Wenn man aber das Material aus andern Colonien zusammenbringt, so laufen diese Formen in einander über; je nach den kälteren oder wärmeren, trockneren oder feuchteren Gründen ändert sich auch die Florzeit. Zuerst hielt ich an den 3 vermeintlichen Arten fest, nachher gab ich solche auf, u. Sir Jos. Hooker u Mr Bentham sind mir darin gefolgt in Bezug auf Anguillaria.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Lassen Sie dies u <name key="Stackhousia">Stackhousia</name> als Beispiel dienen, dass man die Formengrenzen nicht specifisch nach Beobachtungen in einer Colonie bestimmen. Was Sie sehen, sah ich vor 30 Jahren u damals theilte ich nach begrenzten Materialien auch Ihre Ansicht über den Artenbegriff. Wieder u Wieder untersuchte ich dann im Lauf der Jahre anderswo dieselben u ähnliche Formen, und kam schliesslich zu andern Ansichten. Sie werden sich um so schwerer an den Gedanken grosser Veränderlichkeit der Pflanzen Arten gewöhnen können, als Sie so viel leichter die Unterschiede der Species in der Entomologie feststellen können. Bedenken Sie aber, dass das Thierleben sich <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ungebunden</hi>
               </seg> bewegt, dass jedes Thier sich unbehindert die Bedingungen zu seinem besten Bestehen aufsuchen kann; wie anders ist es im Pflanzenleben; die Pflanze ist an den Boden gefesselt; sie kann nicht fort; sie muss sich viel grösseren Verschiedenheiten von Einflüssen fügen als das Thier! Sie accommodirt sich zu veränderlichen mineralischen Nahrstoffen,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; line-height: 107%; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nährstoffen.</p>
               </note> verschiedenen Temperaturen, Feuchtigkeitsgraden u. s.w.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist also nicht wunderbar dass Pflanzen sehr veränderlich sind; es ware dagegen miraculös wenn solche es <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">nicht</hi>
               </seg> wären! Wenn ich also als Graukopf mit geschwächten Augenlicht nicht immer in Erörterungen eingehe über Formen, die Ihnen specifisch erscheinen, mir aber Varietäten sind, so müssen Sie dies in unserer weiteren Correspondenz nicht als Mangel von Aufmerksamkeit betrachten. Wenn sich erst Varietäten gebildet haben (wie auch bei Hausthieren), so können solche abgeänderte Pflanzen in deren Verbreitung neben anderen Varietäten sich hinstellen, aber nicht unter dem Begriff selbständiger Arten. Wenn Sie einmal Gelegeneit haben, könnten Sie vielleicht diese Ideen von mir als erklärend über meine Auffassung Ihrer kritischen Pflanzen in einer einschlagenden Abhandlung nebenher berucksichtigen. Ehe ich aber dies Thema verlasse, rathe ich Ihnen sorgsam die <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">reifen</hi>
               </seg> Samen der Wurmbseen zu vergleichen; vielleicht zeigen sich dabei Unterschiede, die früher übersehen sind.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sie haben jetzt Euc viminalis um sich, so dass Sie vielleicht bestätigen können, ob ich richtig als Ursache der Melitosen-Manna das kleine gefleckte beflügelte Insekt ansehe, das in Massen unter die Rinde dieser Eucalypten sich birgt. Mir will der Name dieses niedlichen Thierchens eben nicht in das Gedächtniss kommen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In der nächsten Woche werde ich noch einige Ihrer u Pastor Kempe's Pflanzen benennen, die ich für kritische Vergleichen zurucklegte.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit bestem Grusse</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller,</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Besten Dank für die <name key="Banksia">Banksia</name> Früchte; Sie werden wohl Mühe u Ausgabe genug davon gehabt haben.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">12/11/81</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is already after midnight, dear Mr Tepper, and I am very tired, but I'll still begin a long letter.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>First of all <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Wurmbea</seg> (or <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Wurmbsea">Wurmbsea</name>
               </seg>)<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg style="">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mueller used </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Wurmbsea">Wurmbsea</name>
                     </seg> in B79.13.14, and in B84.03.06.</p>
               </note>, to which <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Anguillaria</seg> belongs as a Section. Three forms are to be distinguished in <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> Colony, which RBr regarded as specific. 1. The common <seg style="font-style: italic; ">W.</seg>(<seg style="font-style: italic; ">A.</seg>) <seg style="font-style: italic; ">dioica</seg> with mostly, but not always, unisexual flowers; 2. the rare <seg style="font-style: italic; ">A. uniflora</seg> with 1-2 flowers mostly bisexual; 3. the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">A. biglandulosa</seg> with mostly several bisexual flowers and more glandulous transverse ties of the sepals; the latter is the main form in your north. I saw it in 1851 in the Flinders Ranges, Elders Ranges &amp;c. However, if you bring together material from other colonies, these forms run into one another, the flowering time also changes each according to the colder or warmer, drier or moister ground. At first I held to the three probable species, subsequently I abandoned such and Sir Jos. Hooker and Mr Bentham have followed me in this in reference to <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Anguillaria</seg>.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Allow the former and <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Stackhousia">Stackhousia</name>
               </seg> to serve as examples, that you determine the form boundaries not specifically according to observations in one colony. What you see, I saw 30 years ago and at that time I also shared your opinion about the species concept. Again and again I investigated, then in the course of time elsewhere the same and similar forms, and came at last to other views. You will be able to grow accustomed to the idea of great variability of plant species with greater difficulty as you can determine the differences of species in entomology so much more easily. But consider that animal life moves <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">freely</hi>
               </seg>, that every animal can seek unimpeded the conditions for its best existence. How different it is in plant life. The plant is fettered to the ground. It cannot go away. It must adapt to much greater diversity of influences than the animal! They accommodate to variability of mineral nutrients, different temperatures, grades of moisture and so on.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is therefore <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> surprising that plants are very variable; on the contrary it would be miraculous if it were <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
               </seg> so! Therefore if I as a grey-haired man with weakened eyesight do not always enter into debate about forms that appear specific to you, but are varieties to me, you must not regard this as want of attention in our wider correspondence. If varieties have just formed (as also in domestic animals), such modified plants can stand in their distribution near other varieties, but not under the concept of separate species. If you have opportunity at some time, you could perhaps take these ideas from me into consideration as explaining my interpretation of your critical plants incidentally in a referring monograph. However, before I leave this theme, I advise you to carefully compare the <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">ripe</hi>
               </seg> seeds of the <name key="Wurmbsea">Wurmbsea</name>e; perhaps they will show differences that were previously overlooked.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You now have <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Eucalyptus%20viminalis">Eucalyptus viminalis</name>
               </seg> around you, so that perhaps you can confirm whether I correctly regard the small spotted winged insect that conceals itself in masses under the bark of these eucalypts as cause of the melitosa manna. The name of this pretty little creature will just not come to me.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the next week I shall name some more of your and Pastor Kempe's plants, which I laid aside for critical comparison.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With best greetings</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Best thanks for the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Banksia">Banksia</name>
               </seg> fruits; you will probably have had trouble and expense enough for them.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anguillaria%20biglandulosa">Anguillaria biglandulosa</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Anguillaria%20uniflora">Anguillaria uniflora</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Banksia">Banksia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Eucalyptus%20viminalis">Eucalyptus viminalis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Stackhousia">Stackhousia</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Wurmbea%20dioica">Wurmbea dioica</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Wurmbsea">Wurmbsea</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
