<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 5 december ¶  ¶ 1881. ¶ To the illustrious Prince Teano, President of the Geographical Society of Italy. ¶  ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶  ¶ With deep emotion I received the document, through which you infor...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-12-05b-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>81.12.05b</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 5 december ¶  ¶ 1881. ¶ To the illustrious Prince Teano, President of the Geographical Society of Italy. ¶  ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶  ¶ With deep emotion I received the document, through which you infor...</title>
               <date when="1881-12-05">1881-12-05</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1880-9/1881/81-12-05b-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Onorato Caetani, Prince Teano</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 5 december ¶  ¶ 1881. ¶ To the illustrious Prince Teano, President of the Geographical Society of Italy. ¶  ¶ Sir, ¶  ¶  ¶ With deep emotion I received the document, through which you infor...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">81.12.05b</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Onorato Caetani,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Prince Teano</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. The text given here is from<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Terzo Congresso Geografico Internazionale</seg>. Vol. 1,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Notizie e rendiconti</seg>, pp. 387-8 (B82.13.01). It is introduced by</p>
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.6666in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">In seguito ai voti emessi nell'Adunanza generale del 19 settembre furono inoltre partecipati gli omaggi del Congresso ai signori Bennet, Dickson, Wilczek, Principe Borghese e Barone Ferdinando di Müller. Quest'ultimo inviò<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>alla<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Presidenza la seguente risposta.</p>
                  <p rend="FootnoteText"
                     style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.6666in; text-indent: 0in; "
                     xml:lang="en">[Following the votes cast in the General<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Assembly<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>on<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>19<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>September, the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>congressional tributes were also<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>communicated to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Messrs Bennet, Dickson, Wilczek, Prince Borghese and Baron Ferdinand<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>von<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Müller. The latter sent the following reply to the Presidency]<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                  </p>
               </note>Melbourne, 5 december<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>1881.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">To the illustrious Prince Teano, President of the Geographical Society of Italy.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Sir,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With deep emotion I received the document, through which you inform me in such graceful terms, that the great Congress of Geographers held at Venice has honored me, on the proposition of the illustrious Commandeur Cristoforo Negri, by a vote of acknowledgement for services rendered to Australian Geography.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Negri had addressed the congress in the following terms (p. 361):</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.6666in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">Ho</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>l’</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">onore di fare al Congresso una doppia proposta</seg>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                           <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>….</seg>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.6666in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">La seconda e questa: che il Congresso manifesti altresi le sue grazie ai generosi mecenati delle esplorazioni polari ed africane Bennett, Dickson, Wilczek e Borghese. A questi nomi proporrei che il Congresso aggiungesse quello del barone Ferdinando di Muller, da trent'anni promotore indefesso di tutte le esplorazioni australiane, e della acclimatazione di piante utili alimentari, medicinali, tessili e coloniali di ogni continente. Piaceri poi agli onorevoli uditori il sapere altresi, che questo illustre geografo di modeste fortune, il quale ha contribuito con sacrifici propri a tutte quante le esplorazioni di Australia dopo di Leichardt, ha voluto anche concorrere alia nostra antartica italiana, di cui non abbiamo mai abbandonato il pensiero, quantunque in attualità non ne eseguiamo che un esperimento.</p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.6666in; text-indent: 0in; "
                        xml:lang="en">[I have the honor to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>make<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>a double proposal<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the Congress ...The second is this: that the Congress also manifests its thanks to the generous patrons of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>polar and African exploration,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Bennett, Dickson, Wilczek and Borghese. To these names I<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>propose<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that the Congress add that of Baron Ferdinand<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>von<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Muller, who for thirty years has been the tireless promoter of all Australian explorations, and of the acclimatization of useful food, medicinal, textile and colonial plants<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>every continent.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>May it<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>then<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>please<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the honorable listeners<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to know,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>as well,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>that this illustrious geographer of modest fortune, who has contributed with sacrifices of his own to all the explorations of Australia after Leichardt<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[i.e. Leichhardt], has also wanted to contribute to our Italian antarctic, of which we have never abandoned<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the thought<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>although in actuality we<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>are only carrying out an experiment.]<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The 'patrons' named are<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>[James]<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Gordon Bennett<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Jr (1841-1918), publisher<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">New York Herald</seg>, who sponsored explorers both in Africa and the Arctic; Baron Oscar Dickson (1823-97), sponsor of Arctic exploration; Count Johann Nepomuk Wilczek (1837-1922), Arctic explorer and sponsor;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Prince Giovanni Borghese (1855–1918), sponsor of African exploration.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Though in the course of an uninterrupted stay during more than a third of a century in this part of the world it fell to my lot, to promote and even call forth the researches of many geographic explorers, and though<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I had occasion to share personally in scientific travels through much country previously unknown, including the greater portion of the Australian Alps, — yet I feel, that the special tribute paid me at so grand a forum of geographic science, as that which assembled under your leadership in Venice, is due more to the feelings of generosity of your highly illustrious colleague, than to achievements, which I would wish to have been far more extensive and brilliant. Among the honors, bestowed on me so graciously by the scientific world through several decennia, this special approbation of my efforts expressed by the assembled geographers in the ancient island-city is to me as touching and encouraging as it is unique in my life. Let me cherish an earnest desire, to promote new efforts for shedding additional light on the vast Australian territory, which mainly during my own colonial career I saw disclosed to geography, to<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>civilisation<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and to settlement. It is a sublime feeling, to enjoy the privilege of contributing to the world's knowledge and especially to widen the realms of geography, within which on new areas human industry and happiness are to dwell! Through feelings of this kind I can appreciate the enthusiastic zeal, with which the united Italian Empire under the aegis of your enlightened Sovereign and of the Italian Royal Princes and under the auspices of the geographic Society of Rome strives to carry the Italian flag to the remotest southern polar regions for the completion of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">map of the world</seg>,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Negri<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>was at this time trying<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>unsuccessfully<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to organize<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>an<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Antarctic exploring expedition under the naval officer Giacomo Bove.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>for which lofty object an Italian has made the mightiest strides among all mortals nearly four centuries ago!<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3347in; text-indent: -0.3347in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Alluding to the voyage of Christopher Columbus in 1492.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>If in this new event of historic significance to approach by ships (plated with iron and propelled by steam as triumphs of this industrial age) the long-forbidden south, thence to proceed onward by sledges and furthermore by aeronautic reconnoiterings to the hidden reclusions around the south-pole for wide topographic and geologic exploration, for the ascent of its giant mountains, for the gradual transfer of vegetable and subsequent animal organisms from all other alpine regions of the world to the lifeless extreme south, — for the establishment of permanent meteorologic observatories on the antarctic continent, — for the development of extensive fisheries in wide seas unfurrowed yet for industrial enterprises, and — perhaps even for the formation of south-polar colonies, — if for all this, which animates from the throne to the cottages your great Italian Nation, entwined in these noble efforts with the active cooperation of a rising far southern state, — I can aid from Australia even only to the slightest extent by pushing here subsidial measures, then one of the brightest aspirations left to me in life will be fulfilled, and I may then rest content as perhaps worthy of the great and singular mark of distinction, bestowed on me by the renowned Congress of geographers of Venice so unexpectedly and so graciously.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Allow me, most illustrious Prince and President, to remain with profound and regardful obedience<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Your<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. von Muller.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
