<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> ¶ In the meantime, I have been able to collect many new and undescribed, or otherwise interesting plants, and to obtain many valuable observations on the geography of plants. Of the former I shall no...</title>
            <author>Julius Haast</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-03-00-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.03.00</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Julius Haast</author>
               <title> ¶ In the meantime, I have been able to collect many new and undescribed, or otherwise interesting plants, and to obtain many valuable observations on the geography of plants. Of the former I shall no...</title>
               <date when="1863-03">1863-03</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-03-00-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility"> ¶ In the meantime, I have been able to collect many new and undescribed, or otherwise interesting plants, and to obtain many valuable observations on the geography of plants. Of the former I shall no...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">63.03.00</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">From Julius Haast</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Yeoman and Australian acclimatiser</seg>, 11 April 1863, p. 433. The article was reprinted in <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 14 April 1863, p. 7. The letter is introduced: 'The following are extracts made from a private letter lately received by Dr. Mueller from Mr. Haast, the Government geologist of New Zealand, giving some account of his late successful expedition to the west coast of the middle island [i.e. New Zealand's South Island]'.</p>
               </note>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the meantime, I have been able to collect many new and undescribed, or otherwise interesting plants, and to obtain many valuable observations on the geography of plants. Of the former I shall not fail to send you your share for your collections.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You see that my usual good luck has not left me, as I have succeeded in finding a pass through the Alps. This pass is about the most curious object known to me in physical geography, being only 1,600ft. high, whilst for hundreds of miles there is scarcely a snow-saddle to be found, whilst here only the mountain-chain is broken through, the sides about 10,000ft. high, being covered with snow and glaciers.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See also M to J. Haast, 1 April 1863 (in this edition as 63-04-01a).</p>
               </note> You may form some idea of our joy (my party consisted of five besides myself) when, after having marched for about 79 miles through a primeval forest, and after having crossed numbers of rapid rivers, we were at last able to bathe our feet in the waves of the ocean on the west coast. During our journey I had a narrow escape. Trusting too much to a projecting root I slipped, and fell in a deep rent between two rocks on a sharp block of stone. I was by myself, with no one near me to render me any assistance, and thought my leg was broken. Excessive pain made me faint. I recovered after about two hours, and succeeded in extricating myself, finding, to my great joy, that I had escaped with a severe laceration of the muscles and skin of my leg, which healed up after two days of comparative rest, wading during that time through glacial rivers. Such is the life of an explorer. . .</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> I have left orders in Christchurch to forward to you my rather long report to Government, which is to be printed immediately.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="">A 'preliminary report', J. Haast (1883), was published in the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Lyttelton times</seg>
                     <seg style=""> on 1 April, and it may have been to this that Haast was referring.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Haast's full report with a map and geological section was 'not laid on the table' of the Canterbury Provincial Council until 18 August 1863 and was evidently not printed: copies could not be found by either the National Library of New Zealand or Archives New Zealand. The report and map survive in Archives New Zealand, Christchurch Regional Office as '<seg style="">R20592639 - CH287 - CP608a/PPC 21 - Session 20 - Papers and Returns - Report, map and section by the Provincial Geologist shewing result of Journey to the Western part of the Province -18 Aug 1863', which comprises the narrative account, and 'R20592641 - CH287 - CP608a/PPC 23 - Session 20 - Papers and Returns - Map accompanying Report of Geological Survey - 18 Aug 1863', 'a very small hand-drawn map' (e-mail, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Archives New Zealand, <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>20 September 2021); the geological section is represented only by the cover sheet, at 'R20592640 - CH287 - CP608a/PPC 22 - Session 20 - Papers and Returns - Section accompanying Report of Geological Survey - 18 Aug 1863'. The title of the paper listed in the </seg>
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Journal of Proceedings</seg>
                     <seg style=""> of the Provincial Council, vol. 2, p. 207 is incorrect. H. von Haast (1948), p. 1089 lists this report with the incorrect date of the paper, and does not indicate that it was unpublished</seg>.</p>
               </note> By it you will see that I have endeavoured to honour the memory of your explorers, who succumbed whilst engaged in scientific researches, by naming two rivers the Burke and the Wills.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Both tributaries of what is now known as the Haast River, which drains the western watershed of the Haast Pass.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
