<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 July 1863. ¶ Revered Privy Councillor and President, ¶  ¶ It does not require my assurance, that the receipt of your kind communication of 29th of April ¶  filled me wit...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-07-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.07.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 July 1863. ¶ Revered Privy Councillor and President, ¶  ¶ It does not require my assurance, that the receipt of your kind communication of 29th of April ¶  filled me wit...</title>
               <date when="1863-07-25">1863-07-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-07-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Ruppia rostellata</term>
               <term>Ruppia maritime</term>
               <term>Ruppia spiralis</term>
               <term>Xanthorrhoea</term>
               <term>Leguminosae</term>
               <term>Myrtaceae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl von Martius</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 July 1863. ¶ Revered Privy Councillor and President, ¶  ¶ It does not require my assurance, that the receipt of your kind communication of 29th of April ¶  filled me wit...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.07.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl von Martius</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Martiusiana, II, A, 2, Handschriften-Abteilung, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also M to C. Martius, 12 August 1863, for a copy of this letter with a few minor changes in the text.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25 Juli 1863</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrter Herr Geheimrath u. Präsident!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es bedarf nicht meiner Versicherung, dass der Empfang Ihrer gütigen Zuschrift vom 29. April mich mit tiefer Freude erfüllte. Für mich liegt ein unendlich wonniges Gefühl in dem Bewusstsein der Zuneigung eines Gelehrten, der so würdig in der alten kaiserlichen Akademie deutscher Naturforscher den Vorsitz hält, den wir zu den Herren der Naturwissenschaft dieses Zeitalters zählen, und dessen geistreiche Schriften mich stets mit Enthusiasmus erfüllten und mit den Werken von Humboldt u wenigen andern strahlenden Gelehrten in meinem jugendlichen Gemüth so tiefe Eindrücke zurückliessen um meinem Lebensplane seine Richtung zu geben.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Dass mein begonnenes Werk über die Pflanzen dieser Colonie sich des Beifalls eines genialen Meisters wie Sie erfreut, ist eine von den freudigen Thatsachen, welche mich ermuntert der Weiterforschung in Australiens Pflanzenwelt auch fürder meine Kräfte zuzuwenden. Sie, ehrwürdiger Herr, der vor meinem Dasein schon in den herrlichen Tropenwäldern Brasiliens wirkte, werden immer, ich weiss es, mit Nachsicht die Unvollkommenheit derjenigen Arbeiten beurtheilen, die mit mangelhaften literarischen Apparat und noch dürftigen Gelegenheiten für critischen Vergleich entfernt von den grossen Stätten der Gelehrsamkeit hervorgehen. Unser jugendliches Land war ja vor wenigen Decennien noch eine unbekannte Wildniss, und massgebend sind daher unsere Wissenschafts-Institute noch nicht genug gereift, um unabhängigen Arbeiten hier denselben Aufschwung zu geben als daheim.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Empfangen Sie, Verehrter, auch den Ausdruck meines innigen Dankgefühls für die Güte, aus <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihrer</hi>
               </seg> Hand die mir freundlichst zugesandten Veröffentlichungen der <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name> u. <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name> zu erhalten. Letztere werden mir namentlich bei künftigen Untersuchungen über <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name> des tropischen Australien willkommen sein, weil jene auch bei uns weit hervorragende Pflanzenfamilie reich mit Äquinoctial-Typen erfüllt ist.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es bedarf nicht meiner Versicherung, dass ich bei der Vertheilung meiner überzähligen Pflanzen-Exemplare, bereitwillig für Ihre wichtige Sammlung Beiträge zurücklegen werde. Auch Ihre Wünsche auf Erlangung von australischen Arzneistoffen werde ich gern berücksichtigen. Ein schwankender Gesundheitszustand, wohl durch Entbehrungen auf meinen ausgedehnten australischen Reisen herbei geführt, hat es seit einiger Zeit für mich schwer gemacht, immer baldigst den Wünschen der Gelehrten zu entsprechen, welche von hier aus ihre Sammlungen zu vervollständigen wünschten. So ist denn auch eine Weile verstrichen, bis, wie es kürzlich geschah ich es vermochte Ihrem verehrten Bruder in Erlangen das balsamisch-duftende u an Benzonsäure so reiche <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name> Harz von hier zu senden, zumal da das Bäumchen in der Nähe unserer Hauptstadt nicht vorkommt. Jetzt erstarkend hoffe ich mich in Zukunft prompter zu zeigen. Unser gemeinsamer Freund Dr W. Sonder, wird mit seiner gewohnten Bereitwilligkeit gewiss die Weiterbeförderung meiner Sendungen vermitteln. Ich werde auch die Ehre haben, Ihnen die bisher erschienenen 3 Bände der Fragm. phytogr Austr. vorzulegen u. nicht verfehlen die Fortsetzung folgen zu lassen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Während eines kurzen Aufenthalts in Brasilien sammelte ich im Orgel-Gebirge. Nach meiner Übersiedling in Australien ging mir der brasilianische Theil meiner Sammlung, welche ich Ihnen zugedacht, durch das Niederbrennen eines Speichers in Adelaide verloren. Unter dem Gesammelten befand sich Ruppia maritima aus der Bucht von Rio de Janeiro. Ich erkannte selbige mit Sicherheit als identisch mit der von mir in Deutschland u. Dänemark beobachteten Art, welche auch in Australien vorkommt, u. welche die Scandinavier jetzt nach Linné's Vorlagen als <name key="Ruppia%20spiralis">Ruppia spiralis</name> bezeichnen. Selbige ist durch die sehr langen spiralen Fruchtstiele u. die grossen Antheren besser von <name key="Ruppia%20rostellata">Ruppia rostellata</name> unterschieden als durch die von Koch angebenen Merkmale, wenn ich überhaupt eine zarte Art mit sitzenden Fruchtdolden als R. rostellata richtig erkannte. Die brasilianische Pflanze zeichnet sich noch besonders durch etwas tuberculöse Früchte aus.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In diesen Tagen bat mich der Präsident der philosophischen Gesellschaft von Neu-Seeland, Hr Dr Julius Haast zu Christchurch, der als Regierungsgeologe sich bereits um die Geographie u. Naturkunde jener schönen Insel so verdient gemacht, ihn als einen Kandidaten der kaiserlichen Carol. Leop. Academie vorzuführen, was ich diesem gediegenen Gelehrten Ihrer Huld empfehlend, mit herzlicher Bereitwilligkeit thue, da ich weiss dass der Ehrensitz an einen dankbaren u. würdigen Mann vergeben würde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich möchte dies Schreiben nicht schliessen, ohne in kurzen Worten die Fehde über das Dasein von Species in der Natur zu berühren. Meine vieljährigen Beobachtungen im Felde haben mich stets das Unwandelbare der Species erkennen lassen. In Australien, wo die Übergänge von Glacier-Regionen zu Tropenwäldern u. dürren Einöden u. Wüsten vielleicht plötzlicher als meist anderswo sind, bot sich mir bessere Gelegenheit die Beugsamkeit der Pflanzenarten zu climatischen und zu geologischen Verhältnissen zu ermitteln als manchen andern Beobachtern. Immerfort aber drang sich mir die Überzeugung auf, dass die Natur Species schuf, dass aber der Formenkreis derselben häufig verkannt wurde, u. dass daher selbst von den leuchtendsten beschreibenden Pflanzenforschern unendlich viel Varietäten als wahre Arten angenommen wurden. Aus der Unmöglichkeit diese wankenden Gebilde zu begränzen entsprang der Irrwahn, wieder erregt in neuerer Zeit, von der Wandelbarkeit der Species. Doch aber überschreiten diese nie die Grenzen der Form, welche ihnen am Schöpfungstage aufgeprägt wurde, und unter den ewigen unwandelbaren Gesetzen der Natur werden diese Gestalten beständig bleiben bis unsere Schöpfungs-Epoche erlischt! Anders ist es mit der Begränzung der Gattungen u. Ordnungen, die unsern individuellen Ideen entwuchsen, und die in der Natur nicht begründet sind. Über diese werden daher unsere Meinungen endlos streiten, über jene sollten in späterer Zukunft sie es nicht! —</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Möge die schirmende Vorsehung Sie, ehrwürdiger Herr u. Meister, lange der Wissenschaft u Ihren Verehrern erhalten!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Mit tiefer Ehrerbietung der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ritt. v. Dannebr. u d. Ehrenlegion</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 July 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Revered Privy Councillor and President,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It does not require my assurance, that the receipt of your kind communication of 29th of April<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
               </note> filled me with deep joy. There is an infinitely blissful feeling for me in the awareness of possessing the favour of a savant, who presides so worthily over the old Imperial Academy of German Scientists,<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. Academia Caesarea Leopoldina-Carolina Germanica naturae curiosorum (Kaiserlich Leopoldinisch-Carolinische Akademie der Naturforscher). M was mistaken in thinking that Martius was President of the Academy; Carl Gustav Carus was President at this time. See also M to J. Haast, 12 March 1864.</p>
               </note> whom we count among the masters of the natural sciences of this age, and whose enlightened writings have always filled me with enthusiasm and, together with the works of Humboldt and a few other illustrious scientists,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Including Charles Darwin (see M to R. Owen, 24 August 1861), Carl von Hügel (see M to C. von Hügel, 29 January 1867) and Adolphe Brongniart (see M to A. Brongniart, 26 June 1862).</p>
               </note> left such deep impressions on my youthful mind as to give direction to the plans for my life.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>That the commencement of my work on the plants of this colony enjoys the applause of such a genial master as you is one of the happy events that encourage me to continue to expand my efforts on the research into Australia's vegetation.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A copy of M's <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Plants indigenous to the colony of Victoria</seg> had been sent to the botanic garden at Munich. See M to J. O'Shanassy, 31 March 1862.</p>
               </note> You, venerable Sir, who laboured in the wonderful tropical forests of Brazil already before my existence, will always, — I am sure of it, — judge with indulgence the imperfections of those works, which are carried out with inadequate literary reference works and still sparse opportunities for critical comparisons, and far from the great centres of learning. Only a few decades ago our young country was still an unknown wilderness, and our scientific institutes are therefore not yet sufficiently matured to give the same support to independent work as those at home.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Accept also the expression of my sincerest feelings of gratitude for your kindness, revered Sir, to have received from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> hand the publications on the <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name> and <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name> kindly sent to me.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>O. Berg (1857-9) and Bentham (1859-76). The copies of these works in the Library, Royal Botanic Gardens Melbourne, do not carry evidence of Martius's having sent them to M, although other issues of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Flora brasiliensis</seg> do. M had earlier asked Bentham for a copy of his contribution on the <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>; see M to G. Bentham, 20 February 1863.</p>
               </note> The latter in particular will be very welcome in future examinations of <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name> from tropical Australia, because here, too, they are a very prominent family of plants rich in equatorial types. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It does not need my assurance that, in the distribution of my spare duplicates, I shall willingly put aside contributions for your important collection. I am also happy to give consideration to your wishes to acquire Australian medicinal materials. A precarious state of health, probably brought about by privations during my extensive Australian travels, has made it difficult for me for some time always to meet quickly the wishes of scientists, who want to complement their collections from here. Thus some time had passed, before I was able, — as I have done recently, — to send the fragrantly aromatic <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
               </seg> resin so rich in benzoic acid to your esteemed brother in Erlangen,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>T. W. Martius.</p>
               </note> as the small tree is not found near our capital city.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Melbourne.</p>
               </note> Now recovering, I hope to be more prompt in future. Our mutual friend, Dr W. Sonder, will, I am sure, attend to the forwarding of my consignments with his usual willingness. I shall also have the honour to place before you the first three volumes published to date of my <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg>, and I shall not fail to follow up with their continuation.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>During my brief stay in Brazil I collected in the Organ Mountains.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Near Rio de Janeiro. On his way to Australia, while the ship 'Hermann von Beckerath' lay at anchor in Rio de Janeiro for two weeks in September 1847 to take on provisions, M collected plants in the surrounding country. For a list of species collected see M's notebook, 'Breviarium plantarum brasiliensium in vicinitate urbis Rio de Janeiro', RB MSS M43, Library, MEL.</p>
               </note> After my emigration to Australia I lost the Brazilian part of my collections, which I had intended for you, through a fire in a storeroom in Adelaide. The collection contained Ruppia maritima from the bay of Rio de Janeiro. I recognised it with certainty as identical with the species I had observed in Germany and Denmark, which occurs also in Australia, and which the Scandinavians now call <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Ruppia%20spiralis">Ruppia spiralis</name>
               </seg> after the specimens of Linnaeus. It is better distinguished from <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                  <name key="Ruppia%20rostellata">Ruppia rostellata</name>
               </seg> by its very long spiral fruit stalks<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>i.e. peduncles.</p>
               </note> and the large anthers, than by the characters given by Koch,<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>W. Koch (1843-5).</p>
               </note> that is, if I correctly identified a delicate species with sessile inflorescence as <seg style="font-style: italic; ">R. rostellata</seg>. The Brazilian plant was distinct particularly by somewhat tubercular fruit.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>A few days ago the President of the Philosophical Society of New Zealand, Dr Julius Haast at Christchurch, who has also gained great merit in the fields of geography and the natural sciences of that beautiful island in his position of Government Geologist, asked me to introduce him as a candidate for membership in the Imperial Leopoldine-Carolinian Academy,<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also M to J. Haast, 27 June 1863, and M to J. Haast, 28 July 1863.</p>
               </note> something I do with sincere willingness for this sound scientist, recommending him to your graciousness because I know that this place of honour would go to a grateful and worthy man.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not want to close this letter without touching in a few brief words on the controversy about the existence of species in nature. My observations in the field over many years have always led me to recognise the immutability of species. In Australia, where the transitions from glacier regions to tropical forests and barren wilderness and desert are perhaps more abrupt than elsewhere, I was offered greater opportunities to establish the adjustment of species of plants to climatic and geological conditions, than many other observers. But the conviction was constantly forced upon me, that nature created species, but that the range of their forms was frequently not recognised, and that therefore innumerable varieties were accepted as true species even by the most illustrious of describing botanists. From the impossibility of circumscribing the limits of these inconstant entities arose the delusion, once more resurrected in recent times, of the mutability of species. Yet these never trespass across the limits imposed on them on the day of creation, and these entities will remain constant according to the eternal never-changing laws of nature until this creation comes to an end. It is different with the limitation of genera and orders; these are the results of our individual ideas and are not founded on nature. About these, therefore, our opinions will differ endlessly, but about the first they should not in future times.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>May Providence long protect you and preserve you to science and to your admirers, venerable Sir and Master!</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">With deep respect your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Knight of the Dannebrog and of the Legion of Honour.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Myrtaceae">Myrtaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ruppia%20maritime">Ruppia maritime</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ruppia%20rostellata">Ruppia rostellata</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Ruppia%20spiralis">Ruppia spiralis</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Xanthorrhoea">Xanthorrhoea</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
