<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 May 1863. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I have to express my sincere gratitude for your kind lines of 10 March, ¶ Letter not found. ¶  ¶ which reached me with this month's mail i...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-05-24-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Kongelige Bibliotek, Copenhagen.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.05.24</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 May 1863. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I have to express my sincere gratitude for your kind lines of 10 March, ¶ Letter not found. ¶  ¶ which reached me with this month's mail i...</title>
               <date when="1863-05-24">1863-05-24</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-05-24-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl Rafn</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 24 May 1863. ¶ Noble friend, ¶  ¶ I have to express my sincere gratitude for your kind lines of 10 March, ¶ Letter not found. ¶  ¶ which reached me with this month's mail i...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.05.24</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl Rafn</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Kongelige Bibliotek, Copenhagen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne, im botanischen Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 24. Mai 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Edler Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich habe Ihnen meinen innigen Dank abzustatten für Ihre gütigen Zeilen, datirt vom 10. März, welche mich bei dieser Monatspost erreichten, inmitten der Vorbereitungen zu dem grossen Feste, in welchem wir hier die Vermählung des Prinzen von Wales mit der Prinzessin Alexandra feierten. So wie die Nachricht der Vermählung hier anlangte, wurden die grossartigsten Anstalten getroffen, um durch allgemeine Illuminationen, Errichtung von Ehrenpforten usw das allgemeinen Volksfest, in welchem die Loyalität unserer Kolonisten ihren Ausdruck fand, zu erhöhen. Möge denn die Huld der Vorsehung dies hehre königliche Paar beschützen und dem edlen Stamm ein hehres Geschlecht für das britische Reich erblühen. Ich selbst, als halb Skandinavier, habe mit besonderer Wonne die Schönheit dieses Festes gefühlt, mein botanisches Museumgebäude brillant erleuchtet gehabt, und in einem grossen Transparent die Bildnisse der königlichen Thronfolger Britaniens zu verherrlichen gesucht. Meine Verlobte, eine schottische Dame hochbegabt und geistreich, hatte die dänische Flagge, welche neben der britischen von meinem officiellen Gebäude wehte, selbst angefertigt, und diese werde ich als Kleinod zum Andenken an diese schöne u. seltne Feier ehrend aufbewahren. Sie wissen es wohl, dass ich Dänemark meine Erziehung schuldige und noch mit Pietät an diesem meinem zweiten Vaterlande hänge. Ich habe sogar vor einiger Zeit daran gedacht auf eine Weile heimzukehren, zumal da meine Gesundheit schwankte, habe aber einstweilen den Gedanken aufgeben müssen, da ich es zu schwer fand aus meiner grossen Anstalt auch nur auf ein Jahr auszutreten und die literarischen Obliegenheiten, welche ich hier und gegen den Präsidenten der Linneischen Gesellschaft in London habe, auch nur zeitweilig zu unterbrechen. Ich habe Mr Bentham beauftragt den ersten Band der Flora Australiens, von welchem er mir mit letzter Post eine Anzahl Probebögen sandte, an Sie, verehrter Herr, u. an Herrn Prof Lange in meinem Namen zu übersenden, u bitte ich Sie, ihn als ein geringes Zeichen meiner Ehrfurcht und Dankbarkeit und als eine Arbeit, die einen Theil der Untersuchungen eines noch jungen Gelehrten umfasst, gütigst annehmen zu wollen. Möge es mir gelingen Dänemark seinen grossen Wallich zu ersetzen!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Über die Gabe des Bildnisses Sr Majestät, des Königs habe ich mich überaus geehrt gefühlt und es mit Stolz in die Reihe der Bildnisse grosser Zeitgenossen aufgenommen, welche mir freiwillig ihre photographirte Karte sandten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch den Schwager Sr Excellenz des Gouverneurs Sir Henry Barkly habe ich die Ehre gehabt, der königl. Gesellschaft für nordische<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Alterthumskunde nahe 40 verschiedene aus Gold oder Gold u Kupfer (meist aus fast reinem Gold) geformte Zierrathen der alten Peruaner, aus den Zeiten der Inkas stammend, zu übersenden, hoffend dass Sr Majestät u die Mitglieder der Gesellschaft diese geringe Gabe, mit welcher ich eine frühere vervollständige, huldvoll entgegen nehmen mögen. Ein Drittel dieser Sammlung ist Geschenk des ursprünglichen Sammlers dieser Seltenheiten, des Herrn Pedro Nisser, eines gebornen Schweden, der lange in Peru lebte, und den ich als einen geistreichen Mann von ausgedehnten Kenntnissen und dem biedersten Herzen hochschätze. Da Mr Nissers Beitrag den eines Member-foundateurs übersteigt, wage ich die Bitte, diesen Herrn in Ihre Gesellschaft als Anerkennung aufnehmen zu wollen. Zwei Drittel der Sammlung ist als mein Beitrag anzusehen. Ich bat Capt. Timins (des Gouverneur's Schwager) das Kästchen mit diesen (ich kann's wohl sagen nun selten gewordenen) Kleinodien Sr. Excellenz dem dänischen Gesandten in London einzuhändigen, u. bat den Repräsentanten Ihres Hofes schriftlich, diese Beisteuer zu der Sammlung Ihres Vereins zeitigst weiter befördern zu wollen. So hoffe ich wird es diesmal wohl gelingen, diese Seltenheiten sicher in Ihre Hände zu liefern, denn es wäre doch wohl zu beklagen, wenn diese Gegenstände<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg>, an welchen der greise Nisser so viele Jahre sammelte, wie die von mir zuerst gesandten verloren gingen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Capt Timins reiste von hier mit dem "Great Britain" ab, u. wird vermuthlich Ende Juni in London eintreffen. Das Kästchen, welches die Goldsachen enthält, ist aus einheimischem Holz gearbeitet. Die Exemplare haben vielleicht noch dadurch etwas höhern Werth, dass es die Originale sind, nach welchen die Lithographien in den transact unserer Königl. Gesellschaft entworfen wurden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich hatte die Freude, Ihnen u. Hr Prof Lange (u ich denke auch Hr Prof Forchhammer) den 3 Band meiner Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae, an Ihren Konsul in London adressirt, zu übersenden. Verschmähen Sie die geringe Gabe eines früheren adoptiven Sohnes Ihres Reiches nicht. Jetzt bin ich in meinen Nebenstunden damit beschäftigt, die Materialien unserer (ich kann es wohl sagen) grossartigen Sammlungen für den 2 Band von Benthams Werk und den 2 Band meines eignen grössern Werkes über die Pflanzen Victorias u. des 4ten Bandes der Fragmenta zu bearbeiten. Liegt der königl. Bibliothek oder Ihrem verehrten Prof Oerstedt an dem Besitz dieser Bände, o bitte so lassen Sie es mich wissen, u. ich werde selbige freudig sofort übersenden. Ich glaube schon früher gesagt zu haben, dass ich stets innig bereit bin, Ihre wissenschaftlichen Anstalten, soweit ichs vermag, zu unterstützen. Daher gebieten Sie ohne Zögerung stets über mich. Der Kaiser von Russland u der Kaiser von Frankreich, auch der Kaiser von Österreich auch der König von Italien<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>haben es gnädig erlaubt, dass Beiträge für die wissenschaftlichen Anstalten jener Reiche, welche durch mich von hier versandt werden, von den Gesandten in London zur Weiterbeförderung adressirt werden dürfen. Sollte Ihr gnädiger<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Landesherr dieselben Vergünstigen<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vergünstigungen?</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>gewähren, so erleichert dies (bei dem Mangel an directer Verbindung) den Verkehr mit Ihnen und Ihren wissenschaftlichen Collegen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Bild Sr.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Excellenz des Gouverneurs Barkly folgt hierbei, mit einem kurzen Begleitschreiben, aus welchem Sie ersehen, dass Sr Excellenz in seiner Genealogie seine Abkunft von einem<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">dänischen</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Edelmanne herleitet,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die Einlage an Sr Excellenz, Sir John Young, habe ich ohne Aufenthalt befördert, auch um dessen Bild gebeten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Empfangen Sie noch, theuerer Herr Professor, den innigen Dank für den neuen Beitrag, welchen Sie für meine Bibliothek in Aussicht stellen</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir Charl. Nicholson, der unlängst von der Königin zum Baronet erhoben, befindet sich in London, u. werde ich die Notiz an selbigen Edelmann, mit dem ich in freundliche[m]<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg>.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Verkehr geblieben, sofort befördern.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Auch Sir Redm Barry bat ich um sein Bild für Sie, welches hiermit folgt.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bittend mich der Huld Sr Majestät empfehlen zu wollen, bleibe ich, edler Herr, verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS annotation by Rafn: 'modt[aget] 24 de Juli 1863' [received 24 July 1863].</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">24 May 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Noble friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have to express my sincere gratitude for your kind lines of 10 March,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>which reached me with this month's mail in the midst of preparations for the great festival in which we celebrated here the marriage of the Prince of Wales with Princess Alexandra.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The marriage took place on 10 March 1863.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>As soon as the news of the marriage was received here, enormous preparations were made to enhance the public holiday celebrations, in which the loyalty of our colonists found its expression with general illuminations, erection of triumphal arches, etc. May the graciousness of Providence protect this august royal couple, and may a great generation flourish from this noble tree for the British Empire. I personally, as half Scandinavian, have felt the beauty of the festival with particular joy; I had brilliantly illuminated my museum building and in a huge poster tried to glorify the pictures of the Royal successors to the throne of Britain. My fiancée, a greatly talented and enlightened Scottish lady,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Euphemia Henderson.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>had sewn with her own hands the Danish flag that fluttered from my official building next to the British flag, and I shall preserve it and hold it in honour as a treasure in commemoration of this beautiful and rare celebration. You are<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>well aware, that I owe my education to Denmark and am still piously attached to this my second fatherland. I even some time ago considered returning home for a while, especially as my health was in a precarious state, but had to give up this plan for the time being as I found it too difficult to leave my large institute even for one year, or to interrupt even temporarily my literary obligations here and to the president of the Linnean Society in London.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>George Bentham.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I have instructed Mr Bentham to send, in my name, the first volume of the Flora of Australia,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn7" n="8">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bentham (1863-78), vol. 1.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>of which he sent me a number of proof pages with the last mail, to you, revered Sir, and to Professor Lange, and I ask that you would kindly accept it as a small token of my respect and gratitude as a work that comprises a part of the examinations by a still young scientist. May I succeed in replacing the great Wallich for Denmark!<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn8" n="9">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>N. Wallich, born in Denmark, had a notable career as superintendent of the Calcutta Botanic Garden, 1817-46.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I felt exceedingly honoured by the gift of the picture of His Majesty the King<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn9" n="10">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Frederik VII, King of Denmark. Photograph not<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>identified at<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>MEL, but see M to J. Haast, 29 July 1862 (in this edition as 62-07-29b) and notes thereto<seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="color: #0070C0; ">.</seg>.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and have added it with pride to the series of pictures of great contemporaries who willingly sent me their photographs.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I had the honour to send to the Royal Society of Northern Antiquaries nearly 40 different ornaments made of gold or gold and copper (mostly of almost pure gold) of the ancient Peruvians from the time of the Incas, through the brother-in-law of His Excellency the Governor, Sir Henry Barkly,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn10" n="11">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Captain Octavius Timins.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and hope that His Majesty and the members of the Society may graciously accept this humble gift, by which I supplement an earlier collection.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn11" n="12">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See also M to J. Lange, 26 June 1863<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>(in this edition as 63-06-26a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>One-third of this collection is a gift from the original collector, Pedro Nisser, Swedish by birth, who lived in Peru for a long time, and whom I hold in high esteem as an enlightened man with extensive knowledge and an upright heart. As Mr Nisser's contribution exceeds that of a foundation fellow, I take the liberty to request that you would accept this gentleman into your Society in recognition.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn12" n="13">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nisser was included in the list of members of the Society published in<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Antiquarisk Tidsskrift</seg>, 1864.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Two-thirds of the collection is to be regarded as my contribution. I asked Captain Timins (the Governor's brother-in-law) to hand the casket with these (I might add, now rare) treasures to His Excellency, the Danish Consul in London, and asked the representative of your Court in writing,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn13" n="14">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>to forward this contribution to the collection of your Society as soon as possible. Thus I hope, that I will succeed this time to deliver these rarities safely into your hands, because it would really be lamentable, if<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>these objects, which the venerable old Nisser took so many years to collect, were to be lost like those I sent previously.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn14" n="15">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The earlier consignment was carried as far as Alexandria, in Egypt, by Ferdinand Hochstetter, where he delivered it to the Danish Consul for onward transmission; see Darragh (2001), p. 415. Contrary to M's fears, the collection of sixteen pieces was received in Copenhagen; see<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Antiquarisk Tidsskrift</seg>, 1861, p. 198. See also M to J. Lange, 26 September 1861.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Captain Timins departed from here in the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Great Britain</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and will probably arrive in London about the end of June. The casket containing the gold objects has been crafted from indigenous timber. The articles have perhaps an even greater value in that they are the originals, from which the lithographs in the transactions of our Royal Society were drawn.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn15" n="16">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nisser (1860).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I had the pleasure to send you and Professor Lange (and I think also Professor Forchhammer) the 3rd volume of my<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg>, addressed to your Consul in London. Do not disdain this small offering from a former adoptive son of your kingdom. During my spare hours I am currently engaged in working through the materials of our (I must say) magnificent collections for the 2nd volume of Bentham's work,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn16" n="17">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Bentham (1863-78),<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">vol</seg>. 2.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and the 2nd volume of my own larger work on the plants of Victoria,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn17" n="18">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The second volume of M's<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Plants indigenous to the colony of Victoria</seg>
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>was never published.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>The first five sheets were printed and sent at least to Bentham;<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>see<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>M to G. Bentham, 23 July 1863,<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>B63.13.06.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and for the 4th volume of the<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>. If the Royal Library or your revered Professor Oerstedt cares to own these volumes, please let me know and I shall be happy to send them at once. I believe I have said already earlier, that I am always happy to support your scientific institutions to the best of my ability. So do not hesitate to place me at your disposal at any time. The Emperor of Russia and the Emperor of France, also the Emperor of Austria, as well as the King of Italy have given their gracious permission, that contributions for the scientific institutions of these realms that are sent by me from here can be readdressed for forwarding by their representatives in London. Should your gracious ruler grant the same favour, with the lack of direct connections this would ease communications with you and your scientific colleagues.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The picture of His Excellency, Governor Barkly, is enclosed together with a short cover letter, from which you will see, that His Excellency traces his genealogy back to a<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Danish</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>nobleman.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn18" n="19">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Picture and letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I have forwarded the enclosure for His Excellency, Sir John Young, without delay,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn19" n="20">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and have also asked him for his photograph.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Receive also, dearest Professor, my sincere thanks for the contribution that you promised for my library.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir Charles Nicholson, who was recently elevated to a baronet by the Queen,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn20" n="21">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Nicholson was created a baronet in 1859. He returned permanently to England in 1862.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is in London, and I shall immediately forward the note to this nobleman, with whom I have remained in friendly contact.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I also asked Sir Redmond Barry for his photograph for you, which is herewith enclosed.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn21" n="22">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Photograph not found.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Asking that you will commend me to the graciousness of His Majesty, I remain, noble Sir,</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="margin-left: 1.75in; font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
