<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 26 June 1863. ¶ Esteemed friend, ¶  ¶ I sent a case of plants and a small collection of seeds for your kind acceptance by the ship Anglesey, which recently d...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-06-26a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Lange Papers, Botanisk Centralbibliotek, Copenhagen.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.06.26a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 26 June 1863. ¶ Esteemed friend, ¶  ¶ I sent a case of plants and a small collection of seeds for your kind acceptance by the ship Anglesey, which recently d...</title>
               <date when="1863-06-26">1863-06-26</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-06-26a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>DefaultParagraphFont</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>FootnoteReference</term>
               <term>FootnoteText</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="50">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="50">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Johan Lange</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden, ¶ 26 June 1863. ¶ Esteemed friend, ¶  ¶ I sent a case of plants and a small collection of seeds for your kind acceptance by the ship Anglesey, which recently d...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.06.26a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Johan Lange</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Lange Papers, Botanisk Centralbibliotek, Copenhagen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im bot. u. zool. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 26. Juni 63.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrter Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit dem Schiffe "Anglesey", welches unlängst unsern Hafen verliess, übersandte ich für Ihre gütige Entgegennahme eine Kiste Pflanzen u. eine kleine Sammlung Samen. Die Gabe ist freilich eine geringe, aber als Beginn meiner Beiträge für Ihr Herbarium doch wohl annehmbar. Hoffentlich werde ich während der Wintermonate Zeit gewinnen, eine grössere Sendung für Sie zusammenzubringen u. alljährlich denke ich dann, si fata voluit, das Gesandte zu supplementiren. In die Kiste sind einige Samenpackete für verschiedene europäische Gärten eingeschlossen. Sollten Sie keine directe Gelegenheit haben, um gütigst die Sendungen zu befördern, so würden Sie mich durch deren Übersendung an Hr. Dr Sonder verpflichten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Für die schöne Sendung spanischer Pflanzen u manche andere Beiträge sowohl zu meinem Herbarium, als zu dem hiesigen Garten u. zu meiner Bibliothek bin ich Ihnen zu herzlichem Danke verpflichtet.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In der Kiste befinden sich 2 Kästchen Insekten, (zum Theil neuer Arten) für das Copenhagener Museum. Die getrockneten Pflanzen sind meist dreifach gesandt, die Zahl der gesammten Exemplare = 1018. Etwas Harz von Xanthorrhoea Australis ist auch beigefügt, welches nachdem Sie gütigst das für Sie erwünschte abgenommen an Hr Dr. Sonder für Hr Prof. v. Martius befördert werden möchte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 12pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich erinnere nicht, ob ich schon bemerkte in einem frühern Briefe, dass Capt Timins, der Schwager unseres Gouverneurs, eine Sammlung peruanischer antiker Goldkleinodien für mich an Ihre archäologische Sammlung beförderte u. selbige an Se Excellenz den dänischen Gesandten zur Weiterbeförderung einhändigen wird. Capt. Timins schiffte sich im April mit der "Great Britain" ein. Der erste Band meines Werkes über die Pflanzen von Victoria wird Ihnen durch die gütige Vermittlung des Hr Dr Sonder zugegangen sein; er wurde im April v. J. per Suffolk verschifft. Der 2te Band ist jetzt im Drucke, u. wird Ihnen ebenfalls zugeschickt werden. Sollten meine Fragmenta von denen jetzt der 4te Band im Druck, nicht vollständig in Ihrer Bibliothek befindlich sein, so werde ich gern das Fehlende des Werkes liefern. — Und überhaupt, es soll<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Alles</hi>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>geschehen, was in meinen Kräften liegt um die Anstalten der Wissenschaft u. die Gelehrten eines Landes zu unterstützen, in dem ich meine Erziehung empfing, dem ich noch mit filialer Anhänglichkeit zugehöre und dem ich gern seinen grossen Wallich ersetzen möchte. Und namentlich jetzt, wo die Vermählung des Prinzen von Wales u der dänisch Prinzessin die Höfe Britaniens u. Dänemarks so eng verbunden hat, werde ich als Beamter der engl Regierung es mir zur besondern Ehre anrechnen meinem frühern adoptirten Vaterlande<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>dienstfertig zu bleiben. Es war meine Absicht für ein Jahr nach Europa zurückzukehren; indessen ist einstweilen auf unbestimmte vielleicht lange Zeit die Reise verschoben, da es nicht leicht ist, das grosse Departement, welches meiner Verwaltung anvertraut ist, auf längere [...]<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn0" n="1">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>MS comprises four pages on<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the two sides of a single sheet<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and ends in mid-sentence at the bottom of the page without valediction, suggesting that the letter continued on a second sheet, now lost.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic and Zoological Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">26 June 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I sent a case of plants and a small collection of seeds for your kind acceptance by the ship Anglesey, which recently departed our harbour.<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>It is true, the gift is only small, but as a beginning of my contributions to your Herbarium it may nonetheless be acceptable. I hope to find time during the winter months to put together a larger consignment for you and, if fate permits, intend to supplement this annually. A few packets of seeds for various European Gardens have been included in the case. Should you have no direct opportunity to forward these transmissions, you would oblige me by sending them on to Dr Sonder.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I am sincerely obliged to you for the beautiful consignment of Spanish plants<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn1" n="2">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to J. Lange, 8 June 1863 (in this edition as 63-06-08a).</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>and many other contributions to my Herbarium as well as to our Garden, and to my library.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In the case are two small boxes with insects (some of them new) for the Copenhagen Museum. The dried plants have been sent mostly in triplicate, the total number of specimens is 1018. Some resin of<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Xanthorrhoea australis</seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>has also been enclosed. After you have taken what you want for yourself, kindly send the rest to Dr Sonder for forwarding to Professor von Martius.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-size: 10pt; hyphenate: false; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not recall, whether I remarked in an earlier letter, that Captain Timins, brother-in-law of our Governor, conveyed a collection of antique Peruvian gold treasures from me to your archaeological Museum and will hand them to His Excellency the Danish Ambassador for forwarding.<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn2" n="3">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See M to C. Rafn, 24 May 1863.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Captain Timins embarked on the Great Britain in April. You should have received the first volume of my work on the plants of Victoria<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn3" n="4">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>B62.02.01.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>through the agency of Dr Sonder; it was dispatched in April by the Suffolk. The second volume<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn4" n="5">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The second volume was never completed, see B63.13.06.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>is currently in press and will also be sent to you. Should my<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               <seg rend="DefaultParagraphFont" style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg>, of which the 4th volume is now in press, not be complete in your library, I shall be happy to supply what is missing of the work. — And generally, everything shall be done as far as is within my power to support the scientific institutions and the scientists of a country, where I received my education, to which I am still attached in filial affection, and for which I would like to replace her great Wallich. And particularly now, when the marriage of the Prince of Wales and the Danish Princess has so closely united the Courts of Britain and Denmark,<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn5" n="6">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Britain’s<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Prince of Wales married Princess Alexandra of Denmark on 10 March 1863.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>I, as a public servant of the English<space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>Government, count it as a special honour to remain of service to my former adopted fatherland. It was my intention to return to Europe for a year; however in the meantime my voyage has been postponed for an indefinite period, perhaps a long time, as it is not easy […] the large department, that has been entrusted to my management, for a longer [...].<seg rend="FootnoteReference" style="font-size: 8pt; ">
                  <note type="footnote" xml:id="_ftn6" n="7">
                     <p rend="FootnoteText"
                        style="margin-left: 0.3333in; text-indent: -0.3333in; font-size: 9pt; hyphenate: false; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>See n. 1.</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
