<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne, 23 February 1863. ¶  ¶ I must acknowledge receipt of your very kind letters dated 7 December and 1 November 1862, ¶  the first by the last mail-boat, the latter having come during my absenc...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-02-23a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.02.23a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne, 23 February 1863. ¶  ¶ I must acknowledge receipt of your very kind letters dated 7 December and 1 November 1862, ¶  the first by the last mail-boat, the latter having come during my absenc...</title>
               <date when="1863-02-23">1863-02-23</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-02-23a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="51">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="49">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Achille Berg</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne, 23 February 1863. ¶  ¶ I must acknowledge receipt of your very kind letters dated 7 December and 1 November 1862, ¶  the first by the last mail-boat, the latter having come during my absenc...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.02.23a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Achille Berg</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin de la Société d’Acclimatation et d’Histoire Naturelle de l’Île de la Réunion</seg>, vol. 1 (1863), pp. 141-2 (B63.13.01). The printed heading to the letter reads, ‘LETTRE de M. le Dr. F. Mueller, Directeur du jardin d'acclimatation de Melbourne, Délégué de notre Société en Australie, à M. le Dr Berg, Secrétaire général’ [Letter from Dr F. Mueller, Director of the acclimatization garden of Melbourne, delegate of our Society in Australia, to Dr Berg, Secretary-General]. There is a footnote that reads, ‘Notre collègue M. le Docteur Legras, a bien voulu, traduire pour le bulletin cette lettre écrite en Anglaise’ [Our colleague Dr Legras has been good enough to translate for the bulletin this letter written in English].</p>
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>M was listed as one of the Sociey’s Délégués du Comité a l'Étranger [foreign delegates of the committee] in the information about the Society published in the first issue of its <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin</seg>. The date and circumstances of his election are unknown.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, 23 février 1863.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>J'ai à vous accuser réception de vos très bonnes lettres datées du 7 décembre et 1er novembre 1862, la première par la dernière malle, la dernière arrivée pendant mon absence dans les Alpes Australiennes. Acceptez, je vous prie, mes plus cordiales félicitations pour la formation de l'importante société qui, sous votre énergique secrétariat, est certaine de prospérer, eu égard au puissant et général intérêt qui existe dans votre île au sujet de l'acclimatation. Permettez-moi de vous adresser, ainsi qu'à vos honorables collègues, mes plus sincères remerciments pour le grand et inattendu honneur de me désigner pour faire partie de votre importante société. Je promets de faire tout ce que je pourrai justifier cette marque de confiance, en aidant vos nobles efforts.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mes collègues du conseil de la société de Melbourne ont éprouvé un véritable plaisir à ajouter votre nom au nombre très limité de nos <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Membres Honoraires</seg>, et j'espère que vous accepterez cette expression unamime de notre estime avec une effectueuse bienveillance et comme un signe de notre considération pour votre société en général.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Conformément à vos indications, je me suis mis en communcation avec M. Tuslasne, à Sydney, à l'effet de nous entrendre pour quelques envois. M. Tuslasne est en France, et son ami, M. Vial d'Aram m'a conseillé, commes les communications entre Sydney et votre île, sont extrêment rares, d'adresser nos envois à MM. Drouyn, Manès et Ce à Maurice, lesquels nous prèteront leur concours, sans aucun doute, pour la mise à bord de nos animaux, plantes, graines, etc, de Maurice à Bourbon. Je vais donc profiter du prochain navire qui sera expédié d'ici à Maurice, pour diriger le premier tribut de l'Australie à votre Société.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Quant aux Lamas et aux Alpacas, permettez-moi de remarquer que des premiers nous n'avons que 2 mâles pur-sang; des derniers, nous pouvons vous envoyer quelques uns. Mais comme l'espèce en est très inférieure, il serait probablement mieux d’attendre l’arrivée de 500 Alpacas purs, à la recherche desquels un marchand Péruvien, M. Duffield, est parti il y a quelques mois pour la côte Est de l'Amérique.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Recevez, etc.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. Mueller, Ph. Dr.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne, 23 February 1863.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I must acknowledge receipt of your very kind letters dated 7 December and 1 November 1862,<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note> the first by the last mail-boat, the latter having come during my absence in the Australian Alps. Please accept my most cordial congratulations on the formation of the important society which, under your energetic secretaryship, is certain to prosper in view of the strong and general interest in acclimatization that exists on your island. Allow me to offer you, and also your honourable colleagues, my most sincere thanks for the great and unexpected honour of nominating me to become part of your important society. I promise to do all that I can to justify this mark of confidence by helping your high-minded efforts.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>My colleagues on the council of the Melbourne society<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Acclimatisation Society of Victoria.</p>
               </note> have taken much pleasure in adding your name to the very limited number of our <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Honorary Members</seg>, and I hope you will accept this unanimous expression of our esteem with affectionate goodwill and as a sign of our regard for your society in general.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In accordance with your suggestions, I have been in contact with Mr Tuslasne in Sydney, in order to arrange some consignments. Mr Tuslasne is in France and his friend, Mr Vial d'Aram, has advised me, because communications between Sydney and your island are extremely infrequent, to address our shipments to Messrs Drouyn, Manès and Co. in Mauritius, who will no doubt co-operate in shipping our animals, plants, seeds, etc. from Mauritius to Bourbon. I shall thus take advantage of the next ship departing from here for Mauritius, to send the first tribute from Australia to your Society.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As for Llamas and Alpacas, I must first say that of the former we have only two pure-blood males; of the latter we can send you some. But since their breed is very inferior, it would probably be better to await the arrival of 500 pure Alpacas in search of which the Peruvian merchant, Mr Duffield, left the East coast of America some months ago.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Yours, etc.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>F. Mueller, Ph.D.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M's letter was read at a meeting of the Réunion Society on 1 May 1863; see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Bulletin de la Société d'Acclimatation et d'Histoire Naturelle de I'lle de la Réunion</seg>, vol. 1 (1863), p. 132.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
