<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TRANSLATION. ¶ Paris, Jan. 10,1863. ¶ Dear Sir and Colleague,- ¶  ¶ You are aware that the Angora goat was one of the first species of the  ¶ mammiferae ¶  that the Imperial Society of Acclimatisation...</title>
            <author>Edouard Drouyn de Lhuys</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-01-10a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.01.10a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Edouard Drouyn de Lhuys</author>
               <title>TRANSLATION. ¶ Paris, Jan. 10,1863. ¶ Dear Sir and Colleague,- ¶  ¶ You are aware that the Angora goat was one of the first species of the  ¶ mammiferae ¶  that the Imperial Society of Acclimatisation...</title>
               <date when="1863-01-10">1863-01-10</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-01-10a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva, Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="52">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="48">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Ferdinand von Mueller</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">TRANSLATION. ¶ Paris, Jan. 10,1863. ¶ Dear Sir and Colleague,- ¶  ¶ You are aware that the Angora goat was one of the first species of the  ¶ mammiferae ¶  that the Imperial Society of Acclimatisation...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.01.10a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">From Edouard Drouyn de Lhuys</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see the report of the Council of the Acclimatisation Society of Victoria held on 24 March 1863 (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 27 March 1863, p. 5). It was introduced by 'The following letter was read, from M. Drouyn de Lhuys.' The translation of the letter was copied into the minute book of the Acclimatisation Society, where an instruction to the Secretary that it be published was also recorded (Unit 1, VPRS 2223, Minute book of the Acclimatisation Society of Victoria, pp. 352-4, Public Record Office, Victoria).</p>
               </note>Paris, le 10 Janvier, 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Monsieur et Cher Collègue</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Vous savez que la chêvre d'Angora a été l'une des premières espèces de mammifères que la Société Impériale d'Acclimatation ait cherché a introduire en France. La richesse de la toison de cette espèce Asiatique ne pouvait, en effet, manquer d'uttirer<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>attirer?</p>
               </note> son attention. Grace a sa persévérance, et malgré les difficultés qui presentent toujours ces sortes d'expériences, son troupeau de chèvre d'Angora, c'est accru insensiblement sans rien perdre de ses qualités naturelles et son acclimatation en France peut actuellement être regardée comme tout a fait assurée. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Voulant donner à la Société de Melbourne, sa soeur ainée d'Australie, un temoinage de sa vive sympathie et de sa reconnaissance pour le genereux concours qu'elle n'a cesse d'apporter à l'oeuvre commune, notre société se fait un plaisir de lui offrir quelques uns de ces animaux qui trouverait certainment dans vos contrées privilegées les conditions convenables à leur nature, et s'y acclimaterant plus facilement encore que dans notre pays. J'ai, donc, l'honneur et la satisfaction de vous annoncer que notre Conseil d'Administration a décidé que deux boucs et quatre chèvres d'Angora, de race pure, et quatre chèvres metises seront envoyées il lu Soclétée d'Acclimatation de Melbourne. Des mesures ont été pris ca avec notre honorable collègue, Mr. Wilson pour que l'expedition de ces animaux ait lieu tres prochainement. Des deux boucs, l'un est né au printemps de 1859, l'autre à celui de 1862. Le premier est donc adulte, le second ne tardera pas à le d'evlnir.</seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                     <p rend="Footnote"
                        style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                        xml:lang="en">
                        <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                        <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>devenir?</p>
                  </note>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Sur les quatres chèvres de race pure, deux sont nées egalement en 1859, et les deux autres en 1862. Aux indívídus de race pure, nous avons voulu joindre quatres chèvres metises, dont deux de premier croisement sont nées en 1861, et les deux autres de deuxième croisement, plus rapprochées de la race pure, sont nées en 1862. </seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Le chèvre d'Angora offre cette particularité, qu'à l'état pur elle dégénère assez facilement il en resulté que les éleveurs à Angora même refont leur race en croisant les beliers pure avec des chèvres à laine longue mais sans valeur de leur pays, ils choissent ces chèvres communes. Parmi les plus noires les considerant comme d'un sang plus robuste. C'est par le même procéde que nous avons obtenir en France les metises dont nous avons envoyons quatres. Le premier croisement du bouc pur avec une chèvre commune bien constituée donne un produit qui se rapproche plus ou moins du typé pur. II faut, donc, choisir parmi les femelles obtenués de premier croisement celles qui se rapprochent le plus de typé pur pour les hoser au bouc pur; et en agissant ainsi successivement par selection, il est rare que la troisième generation ne donne pas des individus identiques à Ia race pure.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Vous trouverez, donc, comme nous, je pense, que ces quatres chèvres, metises, sur lesquelles vous pourrez remarquer deja, les progrès de l'infusion du sang pur ont leur valeur pour Ia multiplication de ce petit troupeau. La Société Impériale est heureux, je le répète, de pouvoir offrir ce don à sa soeur d'Australie, et elle espère que grace aux precautions prises, ces animaux lui parrlendront dans des bonnes conditions. Verrilley agreer,<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Veuillez agréer?</p>
               </note> Monsieur cher collègue, l'assurance de ma consideration la plus distinguée.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Le President de la Société Impériale d'Acclimatation.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>(Signed) <seg style="font-variant: small-caps; ">Drouin de L'Huys.</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Drouyn de Lhuys.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">A Monsieur le Docteur Fd. <seg style="">Mueller</seg>, Directeur du Jardin Botaniqué et Zoologique de Melbourne, Membre Honoraire de la Société Impériale d'Acclimatation. </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: center; "
               xml:lang="en">TRANSLATION.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The translation given here appeared in the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Paris, Jan. 10,1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Dear Sir and Colleague,-</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You are aware that the Angora goat was one of the first species of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">mammiferae</seg> that the Imperial Society of Acclimatisation sought to introduce into France. The richness of the fleece of this Asiatic species could not fail to attract the attention of this society. Thanks to its perseverance, and in spite of the difficulties always presented by this sort of experiment, its flock of Angora goats has increased without apparently losing any of its natural qualities, and its acclimatisation in France may really be looked upon as thoroughly certain.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Being desirous of giving to the society of Melbourne, its eldest Australian sister association, evidence of its lively sympathy and of its acknowledgement of the generous rivalry which the latter has unceasingly brought in furtherance of the work in common between them, our society has done itself the pleasure to offer to yours some of these animals, which will certainly find in your favoured climate those conditions agreeable to their nature; and they will acclimatise even more easily there than in our country. I have, then, the honour and satisfaction to announce to you that our council of administration has decided that two bucks and four she-goats of the pure Angora race, with four cross-bred she-goats, will be sent to the Acclimatisation Society of Melbourne. Measures have been taken by us. in conjunction with our hon. colleugue, Mr. Wilson,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Edward Wilson.</p>
               </note> so that these animals will be despatched at an early date. Of the two bucks, one was dropped in the spring of 1859, and the other in the spring of 1862. The first is, therefore, of full age, and the second will shortly be so. Of the four she goats of pure blood, two were dropped also in 1859, and the two others in 1862. To these animals of pure race we have thought well to add four cross bred she-goats, of which the two of the first cross were dropped in 1861, and the two others (which are of a second cross, and have thrown back nearer to the pure blood) were dropped in 1802.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <seg style="">
                  <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
               </seg>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The Angora goat offers this specialty, that in a pure state it is liable to degenerate, and the result is that the goat-breeders in Angora reinvigorate their blood by crossing their pure rams with the long-woolled but valueless she-goats of their country. They choose the latter from the most black, considering them of the most robust blood, and it is by the same process that we have obtained in France the cross-breds of which we send you four. The first cross of the pure buck with a common she-goat, of good constitution, gives a produce which recurs more or less to the pure type. It is then necessary to choose from among the females obtained in the first cross those which go back the nearest to the pure type, to put to the pure bucks, and in working thus successively by selection, it is rare that the third generation does not give some individuals identical with the pure race. You will find, then, as we do, I think, that these four cross-bred she-goats, in which you may already note the influence of the infusion of pure blood, have their value for the multiplication of this little flock. The Imperial Society is happy, I repeat, to be able to offer this gift to its Australian sister; and it hopes that, owing to the precautions taken, these animals will reach you in good condition.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/> Accept, my dear colleague, my assurances of the highest respect and regard, &amp;c.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The President of the Imperial Society of Acclimatisation, </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; line-height: 0.1945in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>(Signed) DROUYN DE L'HUYS.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; line-height: 0.1945in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">To Dr. <seg style="">Mueller</seg>, director of the Botanical and Zoological Gardens of Melbourne, and honorary member of the Imperial Society of Acclimatisation.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva, Geneva; margin-left: 0.3346in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3346in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The gift of the goats had been announced in a letter from Edward Wilson, read at the meeting of the Council of the Society held on 17 February (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>, 19 February 1863, p. 5); see M to E. Drouyn de Lhuys, 23 February 1863.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
