<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir,— ¶  ¶ The members of the Royal Society of Victoria beg to express to your Excellency at this, the last meeting which is honoured by your presence, those feelings of appreciation with which you wi...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-08-31-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.08.31</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Sir,— ¶  ¶ The members of the Royal Society of Victoria beg to express to your Excellency at this, the last meeting which is honoured by your presence, those feelings of appreciation with which you wi...</title>
               <date when="1863-08-31">1863-08-31</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-08-31-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="100">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Henry Barkly</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Sir,— ¶  ¶ The members of the Royal Society of Victoria beg to express to your Excellency at this, the last meeting which is honoured by your presence, those feelings of appreciation with which you wi...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="en">63.08.31</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="en">To Henry Barkly</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>
                     <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Letter not found. For the text given here, see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 1 September 1863, p. 6 (B63.14.02). As Honorary Secretary of the Royal Society of Victoria, M probably drafted this address, and he read it at the meeting of the Society on 31 August 1863 at which, ‘very beautifully engrossed and illuminated on parchment by Mr G. T. Smith of Wiiliamstown’, it was then presented to Barkly (see <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Age</seg>, 1 September 1863, p. 6). It was apparently only after this, however, that the address was mounted ‘in the morocco covers of a portfolio’ (<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Geelong advertiser</seg>, 23 September 1863, p. 3). At the ordinary meeting of the Royal Society on 21 September 1863, M exhibited ‘a beautifully mounted copy of the valedictory address of the society to Sir Henry Barkly’: ‘The address itself was engrossed on vellum, with an illuminated border, the design of which was wreaths of flowers, selected from the Australian <seg style="font-style: italic; ">flora</seg>, including a specimen of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Barkleia syringifolia</seg>, a plant originally found in Eastern Australia by Dr. Leichardt, but which remained unnamed for a long time after his death, and was now designated after the late Governor of Victoria…. It was arranged that the presentation of the address should devolve on the hon. secretary [i.e. M], who was left to choose a fitting occasion.’ [<seg style="font-style: italic; ">Argus</seg>, 22 September 1863, p. 6].</p>
               </note>Sir,—</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The members of the Royal Society of Victoria beg to express to your Excellency at this, the last meeting which is honoured by your presence, those feelings of appreciation with which you will ever be remembered in this society, and which are only the echo of sentiments entertained for you by our community.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Though surrounded by the multifarious duties your position as Her Majesty’s representative involved, you have never ceased to be animated by an ardent desire to promote scientific inquiries in this country, and have been prompted to accept for a series of years the presidency of this society, in order to direct its researches, and to foster, by your participation in our labours, all its objects and its usefulness.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The learned and graceful addresses delivered by you from the chair will not readily be obliterated from our memory, whilst the cordial reception given by you to distinguished men of science who visited our shores, remind us of the patronage which you have extended to all scientific inquiries, not only here, but also in those countries over which you previously ruled.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The committee charged with the direction of the expedition to explore the interior of Australia owe much to your counsels and unwearied attention; for although you shared not the responsibility of the Exploration Committee, you were ever ready, when needed, to afford your valuable advice and your prompt assistance.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>You will, not without pride, be conscious that whilst you held the office of our president the first pathway has been opened across the Australian continent by the heroic daring and perseverance of the leader of that expedition, and by the skilful aid of his lamented and faithful companion, an achievement materially promoted by your zealous interest in the advancement of Australian geography.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>We retain a pleasing recollection of the dignified courtesy with which you presided over the meetings of the society, and we are proud of your assurance that, though you may be far removed, we shall continue to enjoy your kind interest and sympathy, and that you will not cease to identify yourself with our labours and progress.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Hall of the Royal Society of Melbourne,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="en">August 31, 1863.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
