<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Revered dear Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ It is becoming difficult for me to find words with which to express my sentiments of deep gratitude for the new proof o...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-10-25-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Eduard Fenzl Nachlass, Archiv der Universität Wien, Vienna.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.10.25</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Revered dear Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ It is becoming difficult for me to find words with which to express my sentiments of deep gratitude for the new proof o...</title>
               <date when="1863-10-25">1863-10-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-10-25-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="plant-names">
               <bibl>plant names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#plant-names">
               <term>Argophyllum</term>
               <term>Leguminosae</term>
               <term>Saxifrageae</term>
               <term>Brexiaceae</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>underline</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>plant names</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="54">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="46">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Eduard Fenzl</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Revered dear Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ It is becoming difficult for me to find words with which to express my sentiments of deep gratitude for the new proof o...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.10.25</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Eduard Fenzl</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Eduard Fenzl Nachlass, Archiv der Universität Wien, Vienna.</seg>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im botanischen Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25. Oct 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Verehrter theuerer Herr u. Freund!</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es wird mir schwer Worte zu finden, um die Gefühle meines tiefen Dankes auszudrücken für den neuen Beweis Ihrer herzlichen Zuneigung, indem Sie Ihren mächtigen Einfluss geltend machten um mir eine Ehrenbezeugung von dem Herrscher Österreichs zu erwerben, welche ich um so höher schätzen muss als ich fühle selbige so wenig verdient zu haben. Und dazu gesellt sich noch zu dem Werth dieser Würde das erhabende Gefühl, dass ich dies Kleinod aus </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihren</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Händen erhalten sollte. Wenn mir nun auch diese Wonne nicht direct zu Theil wurde, so hoffe ich doch früher oder später den Tag zu erleben, wenn ich mit meinem Handdruck und von meinen Lippen Ihnen die Gefühle meiner freundschaftlichen Huldingung erneut darbringen kann. Also vorerst nur meinen brieflichen Dank für die zarte Weise u Herzlichkeit, mit welcher Sie meiner gedachten. Ihr Brief hatte noch für mich einen weiteren Reiz. Ich ersah zum ersten male daraus, dass Sie im Besitz einer Familie glücklich sind! Ich erhielt von Ihrem Gesandten durch die Vermittlung des Herzogs von Newcastle gleichzeitig mit Ihrem Briefe das prachtvolle Ordenskreuz, welches in Eleganz selbst dasjenige der Ehrenlegion und des Danebrogs überstrahlt. Durch unsern Gouverneur habe ich mit dieser Post meinen officiellen Dank an den österreichischen Minister in London ausgesprochen. Das Wenige, welches ich für die Novara Expedition gethan gab mir wahrlich keine Ansprüche auf die Anerkennung Ihres gnädigen Soverains, noch das Geringe was ich um die Förderung unserer Lieblingswissenschaft gethan. Die Gnade des Kaisers und </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Ihre</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Güte sollen mir aber eine Ermunterung sein den wissenschaftlichen Anstalten Österreichs u. namentlich der Ihrigen mehr nützlich zu sein als es bisher der Fall wahr. Ehrlich gestanden mein Wille war immer gut, aber es fehlte mir oft entweder an Zeit oder an Thatkraft energisch was ich wünschte durchzuführen. Meine Gesundheit war schwankend nach meiner Rückkehr von der anstrengenden anderthalbjährigen entbehrungsvollen Reise durch das tropische Australien. Kaum zurück gekehrt wurde mir die Verwaltung des wirklich grossen Departements, dem ich vorstehe, übertragen u ich war eine Reihe Jahre gezwungen über meine Kräfte zu arbeiten, denn mit uns in dem jungen Lande ist ja Alles Schaffen u Gründen. Nach 10 jähriger Dienstzeit giebt mir das Gesetz das Recht auf ein Jahr Urlaub u ich dachte im Beginn dieses Jahres an eine Erholungstour nach Europa. Selbstverstän[dlich]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — MS cut off.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> würde ich mich nicht der Freude beraubt haben, </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">Sie</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> zu besuchen u zu begrüssen Da es aber meine Absicht war im Allgemeinen ein Incognito zu bewahren, theils um Ruhe, der ich bedurfte, zu geniessen, theils um Studien ungestört nachzuhängen und nicht in unnöthige Correspondenz u Störungen gezogen zu werden, theilte ich bloss Sonder u Beckler meine Absicht des Kommens mit, zumal da ich noch nicht mit Gewissheit sagen konnte, ob ich wirklich mich aus meinen Berufspflichten auf eine so lange Zeit losreissen könne. Mancherlei Hindernisse vereitelten den Plan, u. ich bin nun auch noch nicht einmal gewiss, ob ich im Jahr 1864 die Reise unternehmen kann, indem dies von mancherlei Umständen abhängt, über welche ich jetzt noch keine Controlle habe. Unter Anderm ist es schwierig für mich, Bentham meine Hülfe so lange zu entziehen, bis die Arbeiten über die Pflanzenfamilien, welche R Br im prodromus unbearbeitet liess, unvollendet sind. Das Material welches ich hier (obgleich nur theilweis bearbeitet) für die Universalflora Australiens besitze, halte ich für bedeutender als Alles in England seit Sir Jos Banks' Zeiten Angehäufte zusammen genommen, u obgleich alle Species bestimmt sind, so ist doch von vielen keine genaue Beschreibung entworfen, durch welche Benthams Arbeiten so sehr erleichtert würden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist sogar möglich, dass ich ehe ich meinen Besuch nach Europa ausführe, noch eine längere Reise ins Innere Australiens unternehme, sollte ich dies unter günstigen u Erfolg versprechenden Verhältnissen ausführen können.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ihren Oreaden erscheine ich also als ein Alpenjäger! Als Australier habe ich auf diese stolze Benennung wohl einigen Anspruch, denn in nicht weniger als 7 verschiedenen Richtungen u zu 7 verschiedenen Zeiten habe ich diese majestätischen Ketten des Australlandes durchwandert, </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> hauptsächlichen Punkte meist zuerst erstiegen, manche der Berge zuerst ihre Namen u ihre geographische Position gegeben und </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alle</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> Alpenpflanzen kennengelernt. Auf einer dieser Touren war ich wochenlang mit den Pferden </seg>
               <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">allein</hi>
               </seg>
               <seg style=""> in diesen pfadlosen Gebirgen. Ich bedauere es fast, Ihnen mein Bildchen gesandt zu haben, da ich zur Zeit der Anfertigung recht leidend war. Ich muss Ihnen ein anderes senden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Da ich Bentham das sämmtliche Material für seinen 2 Band übersandt (gegen 150 starke fascicle, hauptsächlich Leguminosen) wird es mir möglich sein, si fata velint, Ihnen eine tüchtige Kiste voll Dubletten für Ihre schöne Anstalt zusammen zu suchen. Ich habe einen Sammler in den hohen Berggegenden Nordaustraliens, der manches Schöne, was auch für Vergleich mit der Vegetation Indiens oder den Inseln des stillen Weltmeeres Werth hat, bringen wird u wovon ich bereitwillig einen Theil zu Ihnen senden werde. So erhielt ich von ihm neulich ein <name key="Argophyllum">Argophyllum</name>, welches von den zwei von Labillardiere abgebildeten Arten Neu-[Cale]doniens</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — MS torn.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> verschieden [ist und]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — MS torn.</p>
               </note>
               <seg style=""> uns die Familie der Brexiaceen für die Flora Australiens giebt, wenn solche wirklich von den Saxifrageen im weiteren Sinne getrennt werden kann.</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">
                  <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herzlichen Dank für die Übersendung des Becklerschen Briefes</seg>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mit inniger Zuneigung u Verehrung, theuerer Herr Professor Fenzl, bleibe ich der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Mit dem Schiff "Monarch" sandte ich Anfangs September eine Kiste an Dr Sonder, welche für Sie die fehlenden Fragmenta, die vollständige Reihe der Bände unserer Royal Society u eine Samensammlung enthält, für Prof Haidinger eine Karte auf welcher der Haidinger Range angemerkt ist u für Dr Scherzer eine Anzahl statistischer Schriften u verschiedene von selbigem gewünschte Abhandlu[ngen.]</seg>
               <note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg> — MS torn.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 October 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Revered dear Sir and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is becoming difficult for me to find words with which to express my sentiments of deep gratitude for the new proof of your sincere affection, by having used your mighty influence to obtain for me an honour from the Austrian Monarch,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Fenzl proposed M for the Franz Joseph Order in E. Fenzl to the Lord High Chamberlain's Office, 10 June 1863 (in this edition as M63-06-10). M was appointed to the Order on 16 July 1863 (see Baron von Lichtenfels to M, 17 July 1863).</p>
               </note> which I appreciate all the more, as I feel so undeserving of it. Added to the value of this dignity is the exalted sentiment that I was meant to receive this jewel from <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> hands. Even though I did not experience this pleasure directly, I do hope I will live to see the day sooner or later, when I can render you once again my feelings of friendship and homage with my handshake and from my own lips. So for now just my written thanks for the sensitive manner and the sincerity with which you remembered me. Your letter held for me a further interest. For the first time I realised from it, that you are happy in possessing a family! Together with your letter, I received from your Minister through the agency of the Duke of Newcastle the magnificent cross of the Order, which surpasses in elegance even that of the Legion of Honour and of the Dannebrog Order.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was awarded the Knight's Cross of the Légion d'Honneur, 6 January 1863 (<seg style="">Ordre Imperial de la Lé</seg>
                     <seg style="">gion d’Honneur to M, 6 January 1863, in this edition as 63-01-06a)</seg>, and the Danebrog Order, 23 April 1863 (A. Moltke to M, 23 April 1863). </p>
               </note> By this mail I have expressed my official thanks to the Austrian Minister in London through our Governor.<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to C. Darling, 12 October 1863 (In this edition as 63-10-12a) and M to <seg style="">the Chancellery of the Franz Joseph Order, 10 October 1963 </seg>and notes to each. The letter of thanks to the Austrian Minister has not been found.</p>
               </note> The little I did for the Novara expedition<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Austrian scientific exploring expedition in the frigate <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Novara</seg>, 1857-9.</p>
               </note> hardly gave me any claims to recognition by your gracious Sovereign, nor the little I did for the promotion of our favourite science. The graciousness of your Emperor and <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">your</hi>
               </seg> kindness will, however, serve as an encouragement to me to be of more benefit to the scientific institutes of Austria, especially yours, than has been the case so far. To tell you the truth, my will has always been good, but I often lacked either the time or the energy to carry out with vigour what I wanted to do. My health was precarious after my return from the strenuous one and a half year journey, full of privations, through tropical Australia.<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">North Australian Exploring Expedition, 1855-6.</p>
               </note> Barely returned, the management of the really large Department over which I preside was assigned to me, and for a number of years I was forced to labour beyond my strength, for here in our young country it is all labouring and establishing. After 10 years in office the law entitles me to a year's leave, and at the beginning of this year I was thinking of a holiday voyage to Europe. It goes without saying, that I would not have denied myself the pleasure to visit and greet <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
               </seg>. As I had intended to remain generally incognito, partly to enjoy the rest I needed, partly to follow studies undisturbed and without becoming involved in unnecessary correspondence and disruptions, I had notified only Sonder and Beckler of my intended visit, especially as I could not say with any certainty, whether I would be able to tear myself away from my professional duties for such a long period. Various obstacles thwarted the plan, and now I am not even sure, whether I shall be able to undertake the voyage in 1864, as this depends on a variety of circumstances over which I have no control at present. Apart from other matters, it is difficult for me to withdraw my assistance from Bentham for so long until the work on the families of plants, which Robert Brown left untreated in his <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Prodromus</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">R. Brown (1810).</p>
               </note> has been completed. I consider the material (though only partly worked through) that I possess here for the universal Flora of Australia<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Bentham (1863-78).</p>
               </note> more significant than everything that has been accumulated in England since Sir Joseph Banks' time taken together, and although all the species are identified, no precise description has as yet been drawn up that would make Bentham's work so much easier.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is even possible that, before I carry out my visit to Europe, I might undertake a longer expedition into the interior of Australia, should it be possible to carry this out under favourable conditions that promise success.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>So I appear like an alpine huntsman to your Oreadae!<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">i.e. nymphs of the mountains.</p>
               </note> As an Australian I probably have some claim to this proud title, because I have wandered through these majestic mountain ranges of Australia in no less than 7 different directions and at 7 different times, have been mostly the first to climb <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> of the major peaks, have named many mountains and established their geographical positions, and have come to know <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
               </seg> the alpine plants. On one of these trips I was for weeks <seg style="">
                  <hi rend="underline">alone</hi>
               </seg> with the horses in these trackless mountain ranges.<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M explored the Australian Alps in 1853-5 and 1860. See Gillbank (1992), Albrecht (1996) and Home (2014).</p>
               </note> I almost regret, that I sent you my small photograph, as I was rather ill at the time it was taken. I must send you another one.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>As I have sent Bentham all of the material for his second volume (about 150 thick folders, mostly of <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>), it will be possible, if fate permits, to sort out for you a large case filled with duplicates for your fine institute. I have a collector in the high mountain areas of northern Australia,<note xml:id="ftn14" type="footnote" n="14">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">John Dallachy.</p>
               </note> who will bring back many beautiful things that will also be of value for comparison with the vegetation of India or the islands of the Pacific Ocean, and of which I shall be happy to send a portion to you. Thus I recently received from him an <name key="Argophyllum">Argophyllum</name>
               <note xml:id="ftn15" type="footnote" n="15">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">
                        <name key="Argophyllum">Argophyllum</name> lejourdanii</seg> (B63.10.01, p. 33). M acknowledged both Fitzalan and Dallachy as the collectors in his description. Dallachy's specimen, collected <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>4 August 1863, is at MEL 568352; Fitzalan's undated specimens, MEL 56834 and MEL 568353, have no collector's label but herbarium labels, each stating 'Mt Elliot | Fitzalan'. The specimen at K 739401 is attributed on M's label to Dallachy and Fitzalan jointly.</p>
               </note> that differs from the two species from New Caledonia illustrated by Labillardière, and gives us the family <name key="Brexiaceae">Brexiaceae</name> for the flora of Australia, if that can really be separated from the <name key="Saxifrageae">Saxifrageae</name> in a broader sense.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sincere thanks for forwarding Beckler's letter.<note xml:id="ftn16" type="footnote" n="16">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>With sincere affection and respect, dear Professor Fenzl, I remain your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">At the beginning of September I sent a case to Dr Sonder in the ship “Monarch” that contained the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta</seg> you were lacking, a complete series of the volumes of our Royal Society, and a collection of seeds for you, for Professor Haidinger a map on which the Haidinger Range<note xml:id="ftn17" type="footnote" n="17">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">A range named by M near the head of the Macalister River, Gippsland. The name does not appear on modern maps.</p>
               </note> has been marked, and for Dr Scherzer a number of statistical publications and various papers requested by him.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Argophyllum">Argophyllum</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Brexiaceae">Brexiaceae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Leguminosae">Leguminosae</name>
            </p>
            <p rend="plant%20names" xml:lang="en">
               <name key="Saxifrageae">Saxifrageae</name>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
