<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Venerable and dear Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ The last monthly mail brought me your friendly letter and also one from His Excellency, Minister Bille. ¶  From t...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-10-25e-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Kongelige Bibliotek, Copenhagen.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.10.25e</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Venerable and dear Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ The last monthly mail brought me your friendly letter and also one from His Excellency, Minister Bille. ¶  From t...</title>
               <date when="1863-10-25">1863-10-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-10-25e-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="53">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="47">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>Carl Rafn</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Venerable and dear Sir and friend, ¶  ¶ The last monthly mail brought me your friendly letter and also one from His Excellency, Minister Bille. ¶  From t...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.10.25e</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To Carl Rafn</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">Kongelige Bibliotek, Copenhagen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">Melbourne im bot. Garten</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">25/10/63</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ehrwürdiger u. theuerer Herr u Freund.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die letzte Monats-Post brachte mir Ihr herzliches Schreiben und auch eins von Sr Excellenz dem Minister Bille. Aus der Mittheilung des letzteren entnehme ich, dass die kleine Contribution peruanischer alterthümlicher Zierrathen in die Hand Ihres Gesandten gelangte, und so mit auch ehestens Sie erreichen werde. Möge Ihre schöne Gesellschaft die kleine Gabe freundlich annehmen. Ich werde über den Erwerb irgend anderer Gegenstände wachen, welche der königl archäologischen Gesellschaft willkommen sein möchten.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Durch die Güte Sr Excellenz Sir John Young erhielt ich die deutsche durch Professor Lucht veranstaltete Übersetzug der Abhandlung Sr. Majestät, wofür ich Ihnen meinen innigen Dank abstatte. Das Duplicat habe ich in Ihrer Gesellschaft Namen unserer königl Gesellschaft mitgetheilt. Die Photographie der herrlichen Prinzessin, welche Sie so freundlich sandten, ist ein wahrer Schatz, über den ich nach Ihrem Wunsche verfügte, u wofür ich den wärmsten Dank anstatte.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Von dem 2 Band meines Quarto Werkes über die Pflanzen Victorias ist ein Theil jetzt gedruckt, ebenso von dem 4. Band der Fragmenta phyt. Austr., in welchem einige höchst merkwürdige Pflanzen von Nordost-Australien neuerdings Ihre erste Beschreibung fanden.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich wagte es, Ihre gütige Aufmerksamkeit auf das Verdienst des Consuls Were zu lenken, der hier die Interessen Dänemarks sehr würdig vertritt. Es erschien mir, dass seine Ernennung zum Dannebrogsmanne ihm eine Ermunterung sein würde fortzuschreiten wie er es gethan. Indessen mag es vielleicht schwierig für Ihr Ministerium sein, einen Einzelnen Ihrer vielen Vertreter zu bevorzugen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist erfreulich wahrzunehmen, dass so manche ausgezeichnete Gelehrte die bleibenden Reihen der Mitglieder Ihres schönen Alterthums-Vereins stärken. Hoffentlich wird es in meiner Macht liegen, Ihnen vorschlagend einige Mitglieder aus Indien zuzuführen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In meinem letzten Schreiben sprach ich bereits meinen innigen Dank aus für die Gnadenbezeugung Sr Majestät, durch welche ich zum Range eines Dannebrogs Ritters erhoben wurde, eine Auszeichnung für welche ich Ihrem Land stets dankbar verpflichtet bleiben muss, und welche für mich als Beamter des englischen Staates nun bei dem innigen Verhältnis der Höfe Dänemarks u Englands eine doppelt hohe Bedeutung hat.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Stets, theuerer Herr Etatsrath, bleibe ich verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Ich darf es Ihnen doch nicht verhehlen, dass Sr. Maj. d. Kaiser von Österreich mich würdig fand, mir das Ritterkreuz des Franz Joseph Ordens zu verleihen. Alle diese Auszeichn'gn.<note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Auszeichnungen.</p>
               </note> betrachte ich dankbar als eine Ermunterung auf dem eingeschlagenen Wege vorwärts zu streben, nicht aber als eine verdiente Belohnung für das Wenige welches ich zur Förderung der Wissenschaften gethan.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir Henry Barkly befindet sich jetzt als Gouverneur in Mauritius, doch unterhalte ich stets eine regelmässige Verbindung mit demselben u. bin freudig bereit die Vermittlung von Übersendungen an denselben zu übernehmen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Herr Peter Nisser ist ein ausgezeichneter und treuherziger Mann, der in seinem Fache, dem Minenwesen, besseres Glück verdient hätte als seine rastlose Thätigkeit begleitete. Er ist ein Schwede, der lange in Südamerka lebte, aber noch eine grosse Vorliebe für sein nordisches Vaterland bewahrt. Augenblicklich befindet er sich in Neu Süd Wallis.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich hoffe meine durch Consul Were pr Post an den General Consul in London gesandten selbstständigen Werke werden wohl die königl Bibliothek erreicht haben u (darf ich es hoffen) gnädig aufgenommen sein. Ich habe seither meinen Freunde G. Bentham, den Präsidenten der Linneischen Gesellschaft gebeten, den unter meiner Mithülfe jüngst erschienene 1ste Band der Universal Flora Australiens, Ihnen[,]<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">
                     <seg style="font-style: italic; ">editorial addition</seg>.</p>
               </note> Hr Prof Forchhammer u Hr Prof Lange gleichfalls zuzusenden u es bedarf nicht der Versicherung, dass die folgenden Bände, von denen der 2te im Anfang des Jahres 1864 beendigt sein wird, Ihnen ebenfalls zu Gebot gestellt werden sollen.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 October 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Venerable and dear Sir and friend,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The last monthly mail brought me your friendly letter and also one from His Excellency, Minister Bille.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letters not found.</p>
               </note> From the communication of the latter I see, that the small contribution of ancient Peruvian ornaments has reached your ambassador and with that should have also reached you soon afterwards.<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to C. Rafn, 24 May 1863, and M to J. Lange, 26 June 1863 (in this edition as 63-06-26a).</p>
               </note> May the fine Society kindly accept the small gift. I shall watch out for the purchase of other articles that the Royal Archaeological Society might welcome. </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Through the kindness of His Excellency, Sir John Young, I received the German translation by Professor Lucht of His Majesty's essay, for which I express my sincere thanks. I have forwarded the duplicate copy to our Royal Society on behalf of your Society.<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">At the meeting of the Royal Society of Victoria on 2 November 1863, one of the contributions tabled was ‘”Ueber den Bau der Riesenbetten der Vorzeit [On the construction of the gigantic figures of ancient times],” by His Majesty King Frederick VII. Of Denmark—presented by the Royal Archaeological Society of Copenhagen’.</p>
               </note> The photograph of the glorious Princess,<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Princess Alexandra of Denmark, who had recently married England’s Prince of Wales.</p>
               </note>
               <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>so kindly sent by you, is a real treasure, of which I took care according to your wishes, and for which I give you my warmest thanks.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Part of the 2nd volume of my quarto work on the plants of Victoria is now printed,<note xml:id="ftn7" type="footnote" n="7">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">No further sheets were printed after sheet 5, and the volume was never published; see B63.13.06.</p>
               </note> Also of the 4th volume of the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Fragmenta phytographiae Australiae</seg>, in which a few most peculiar plants from North-East Australia were recently described.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I took the liberty to direct your gracious attention to the merits of Consul Were, who very worthily represents the interests of Denmark here. It seemed to me, that his appointment as a member of the Dannebrog Order would be an encouragement to carry on as he has done. However, it may perhaps be difficult for your ministry to give preference to one out of your many representatives.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It is pleasing to note, that so many excellent scholars strengthen the continuing group of members in your fine Archaeological Society.<note xml:id="ftn8" type="footnote" n="8">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Royal Society of Northern Antiquaries, Copenhagen [Koneglige Nordiske Oldskrift Selskab].</p>
               </note> I hope it will be in my power, to bring in some members by proposing a few from India.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>In my last letter<note xml:id="ftn9" type="footnote" n="9">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Letter not found.</p>
               </note> I already expressed my sincere gratitude for His Majesty's graciousness in elevating me to a Knight of the Dannnebrog,<note xml:id="ftn10" type="footnote" n="10">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See certificate, 23 April 1863.</p>
               </note> a distinction for which I must always remain under a grateful obligation to your country, and which for me as a public servant of the English State now has twice as much significance with the close ties between the Courts of Denmark and England.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I remain always, dear Councillor of State respectfully your</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I must not conceal from you, that His Majesty, the Emperor of Austria, found me worthy to confer on me the Knight's Cross of the Franz Joseph Order.<note xml:id="ftn11" type="footnote" n="11">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M was appointed to the Franz Joseph Order on 16 July 1863 (see Baron von Lichtenfels to M, 17 July 1863). See also M to E. Fenzl, 25 October 1863.</p>
               </note> I gratefully look on all these distinctions as an encouragement to strive ahead on my chosen path, but not as a merited reward for the little I have done to promote science.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Sir Henry Barkly is now Governor of Mauritius, but I always maintain regular contact with him and shall be happy to facilitate transmissions to him there.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Mr Peter Nisser<note xml:id="ftn12" type="footnote" n="12">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Nisser had collected the Incan gold ornaments that M had sent to Copenhagen; see M to C. Rafn, 24 May 1863.</p>
               </note> is an excellent and guileless man who has deserved better luck in his field of mining than what did accompany his restless labours. He is a Swede who lived for a long time in South America, but still retains great fondness for his Nordic fatherland. He is at present in New South Wales.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I hope my independent works, sent through Consul Were by mail to the Consul General in London,<note xml:id="ftn13" type="footnote" n="13">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">See M to C. Rafn, 24 May 1863.</p>
               </note> have safely reached the Royal Library, and (may I hope?) have been graciously received. Since then I have asked my friend, G. Bentham, the President of the Linnean Society, to send you, and also Professor Forchhammer and Professor Lange the first volume of the universal Flora of Australia, published with my assistance, and it does not require my assurance that the subsequent volumes will also be placed at your disposal; <space unit="chars" quantity="1"/>the 2nd of them should be completed early in 1864.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
