<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Esteemed Doctor, ¶  ¶ The intermittent significant news on the progress of the geographic exploration in Africa, which I receive thanks to your kindness,...</title>
            <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed into Microsoft Word</resp>
               <orgName>Correspondence of Ferdinand von Mueller Project</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Converted from Microsoft Word to TEI P5</resp>
               <persName>Conal Tuohy</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</authority>
            <idno type="filename">data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-10-25a-final.doc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <msName>Sammlung Perthes Archiv, SPA ARCH PGM 328, Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</msName>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>63.10.25a</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ferdinand von Mueller</author>
               <title>Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Esteemed Doctor, ¶  ¶ The intermittent significant news on the progress of the geographic exploration in Africa, which I receive thanks to your kindness,...</title>
               <date when="1863-10-25">1863-10-25</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p xml:lang="en">The file <idno>data/letters/1860-9/1863/63-10-25a-final.doc</idno> was converted from Microsoft Word format into TEI using an XProc pipeline.</p>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="status">
               <bibl>Status</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="typefaces">
               <bibl>typefaces</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="features">
               <bibl>features</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="styles">
               <bibl>styles</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="validity">
               <bibl>validity</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#status">
               <term>final</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#typefaces">
               <term>Geneva</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#features">
               <term>note</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#styles">
               <term>number</term>
               <term>correspondent</term>
               <term>location</term>
               <term>letter</term>
               <term>Footnote</term>
               <term>valediction</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#validity">
               <term>valid</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" usage="55">English</language>
            <language ident="de" usage="45">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sentTo">
               <name>August Petermann</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="main">
            <head type="incipit">
               <supplied reason="XTF-compatibility">Melbourne Botanic Garden, ¶ 25 October 1863. ¶ Esteemed Doctor, ¶  ¶ The intermittent significant news on the progress of the geographic exploration in Africa, which I receive thanks to your kindness,...</supplied>
            </head>
            <p rend="number" xml:lang="de">63.10.25a</p>
            <p rend="correspondent" xml:lang="de">To August Petermann</p>
            <p rend="location" xml:lang="de">
               <seg style="">Sammlung Perthes Archiv, </seg>
               <seg style="">SPA ARCH PGM 328</seg>
               <seg style="">, </seg>Forschungsbibliothek Gotha der Universität Erfurt.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <note xml:id="ftn1" type="footnote" n="1">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">MS annotation by Petermann: 'Erh. 20. Dez. 1863. | A. 27. April 1864' [Received 20 December 1863. Answered 27 April 1864]. See A. Petermann to M, 27 April 1864 (in this edition as 64-04-27a). For a published version of this letter, see Voigt (1996). pp. 48-9.</p>
               </note>Melbourne, im bot. Garten,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="de">am 25 Oct. 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">Hochverehrter Herr Doctor.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Die periodischen inhaltsreichen Nachrichten, welche ich Ihrer Freundlichkeit verdanke über den Fortschritt der geographischen Forschungen in Africa, sind mir stets ausserordentlich willkommen, u. veranlasse ich stets deren Weiterverbreitung in unsern Localblättern. Erlauben Sie mir bei dieser Gelegenheit wieder als einen Privatbeitrag von meiner Seite Ihnen den eingeschlossenen Wechsel zu überreichen u. nehmen Sie die Versicherung hin, dass ich auch fürder zu dem vom Gothaer Centralcommittee verwalteten Reisefond beitragen werde.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich halte es für eine Pflicht eines Jeden, der in der Erweiterung unserer geographischen Kenntnisse ein Interesse fühlt, für die edlen Zwecke der africanischen Reisenden zu wirken, und somit wenigstens ihre Mühen u. Gefahren zu vermindern, als es durch Subsidien geschehen kann. Wie glorreich wird es sein, wenn wir dereinst eine vollstände Karte des grossen afrikanischen Kontinentes besitzen, und wie viel glorreicher noch, wenn es uns gelingt Sitten u. Civilisation unter den barbarischen Urstämmen einzuführen u. damit die Geissel der Superstition der Tyrannei u. Mordsucht zu bannen.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Es ist doch entsetzlich wenn man bedenkt, welche Schrecknisse sich stets noch in Africa u. doch so nahe den grossen Ländern der Civilisation noch ereignen. Das entferntere Amerika ist doch in der Cultur ungleich weiter vorgeschritten. Es wird einer der ehrendsten u. glanzvollsten Punkte der Geschichte Gothas bleiben, dass Ihr erlauchter Fürst auf eine so aufopfernde Weise diese grossartigen afrikanischen Reiseunternehmungen unter seinen huldvollen Schutz nahm.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Was der Dr. Répin in diesem Jahre über die Gebräuche in Dahomey mittheilt, so wie ich es in dem Journal Le tour du Monde lese, ist doch wirklich entsetzlich.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Das Hamburger Schiff, mit dem Hr Dr Sonder die gütigst von Ihnen geschenkten Karten versandte ist noch immer nicht angelangt. So wie aber Ihre Sendung einläuft soll Ihrem Wunsch gemäss damit verfahren werden. In Adelaide sind weitere Karten für Sie unter Bearbeitung.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich erinnere nicht ob ich Ihnen je, wie ich es beabsichtigte, meine Carte de visite darbot. Nehmen Sie selbige gütig an u. lassen Sie mich Sie um die Ihrige als Gegengabe bitten, um selbige in die Reihe der mir befreundeten grossen Zeitgenossen aufzunehmen.</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">Stets verehrungsvoll der Ihre</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 12pt; "
               xml:lang="de">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ich glaube Ihnen bereits geschrieben zu haben, dass ich Ihnen am 7 Sept pr "Monarch" mehrere Karten Drucksachen u. Documente an Hr Dr Sonder für Sie absandte.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">Melbourne Botanic Garden,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; text-align: end; "
               xml:lang="en">25 October 1863.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Esteemed Doctor,</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The intermittent significant news on the progress of the geographic exploration in Africa, which I receive thanks to your kindness, is always extremely welcome, and I always see to their further dissemination through our local newspapers here.<note xml:id="ftn2" type="footnote" n="2">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">M sent Petermann's letter to the local German-language newspaper <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Germania</seg>. See M to editor of <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Germania</seg>, 27 January 1864 (B64.02.02).</p>
               </note> Permit me to use this opportunity to present you with the enclosed bill of exchange as a further private contribution on my part, and accept my assurance, that I shall continue to contribute also in future to the expedition fund administered by the Central Committee in Gotha.<note xml:id="ftn3" type="footnote" n="3">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">The 'Heuglin Fund' had been instituted by Petermann to collect funds for the German expedition in search of Eduard Vogel and for the exploration of unknown parts of Central Africa. M had previously contributed to the fund and had also collected contributions from the German community in Australia; see M to A. Petermann, 25 June 1861(in this edition as 61-06-25a) and M to A. Petermann, 24 August 1861 (in this edition as 61-08-24b).</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I consider it the duty of anyone, who is interested in the expansion of our geographical knowledge, to work for the noble purposes of the African travellers, thus at least to reduce their difficulties and dangers as far as can be achieved by subsidies. How glorious it will be, when one day we shall have a complete map of the large African continent, and how much more glorious still, if we succeed to introduce the barbaric indigenous tribes to morality and civilisation and so banish the scourges of superstition, tyranny and bloodthirsty murder.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>It really is terrible, when one considers, what horrors still occur in Africa, so close to the great civilized nations. The more distant America has made far greater cultural progress. It will remain one of the most honourable and resplendent moments in the history of Gotha, that your august Sovereign<note xml:id="ftn4" type="footnote" n="4">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Ernst II, Duke of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha.</p>
               </note> has taken these splendid African expeditions under his gracious patronage in such a devoted manner.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>What Dr Répin communicated this year about the customs in Dahomey, as I read in the journal <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Le tour du monde</seg>,<note xml:id="ftn5" type="footnote" n="5">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Répin (1863). Much of Répin's account portrays the people of Dahomey as kind and peaceful; but he then goes on to describe human sacrifices and public executions, and includes depictions of an Anglican missionary who was crucified, and of people wrestling over the heads of sacrificial victims.</p>
               </note> really is terrible.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>The ship from Hamburg, by which Dr Sonder dispatched your kind gift of the maps, still has not arrived. But as soon as your consignment arrives, I shall dispose of it according to your wishes.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Further maps are being prepared for you in Adelaide.</p>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>I do not recall, whether I have ever sent you my carte de visite, as I had intended. Please be so kind to accept it and allow me to ask you for yours in return, to be included in my collection of great contemporaries who are my friends.<note xml:id="ftn6" type="footnote" n="6">
                  <p rend="Footnote"
                     style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 0.3335in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: -0.3335in; font-size: 9pt; "
                     xml:lang="en">Photographs not found.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">Always respectfully yours</p>
            <p rend="valediction"
               style="font-family: Geneva; margin-left: 1.75in; margin-right: 0in; text-indent: 0in; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">
               <space dim="horizontal" extent="tab"/>Ferd. Mueller.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p rend="letter"
               style="font-family: Geneva; font-size: 10pt; "
               xml:lang="en">I believe I already wrote to you, that I dispatched to you on 7 September several maps, printed matter, and documents by the <seg style="font-style: italic; ">Monarch</seg>, addressed to Dr Sonder.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
